<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" "hansard.dtd">
<html>
 <body>
  <hansard chamber="Senate" date="18/08/1981" page="1" parliament.no="32" period.no="3" proof="No" session.no="1">
   <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
     <day.start date="18/08/1981">
      Tuesday, 18 August 1981
     </day.start>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA
      </para>
      <para>
       PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATE
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       HANSARD
      </para>
      <para>
       1981
      </para>
      <para>
       FIRST SESSION OF THE THIRTY-SECOND PARLIAMENT
      </para>
      <para>
       (THIRD PERIOD)
      </para>
      <para>
       The Senate, on 12 June 1981, adjourned to 18 August 1981, unless the President fixed an earlier day of meeting.
      </para>
      <para>
       Pursuant to the Resolution of the Senate passed on 12 June 1981, the Senate met on Tuesday, 18 August 1981, at 3 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Senate met at 3 p.m.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </business.start>
    <debate page="1" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      SWEARING-IN OF SENATORS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       His Excellency Sir Zelman Cowen, Governor-General of the Commonwealth of Australia, entered the chamber and, taking his seat on the dais, said:
      </para>
      <para>
       Honourable Senators:
      </para>
      <para>
       I am present to administer to senators elected to serve in the Senate from 1 July 1981 the oath or affirmation of allegiance as required by section 42 of the Constitution.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Clerk produced and laid on the table the certificates of election for the following senators elected, on 18 October 1980, to serve in the Senate for the respective States from 1 July 1981:
      </para>
      <para>
       New South Wales-Douglas McClelland; John Leslie Carrick; Bruce Kenneth Childs; Douglas Barr Scott; Kerry Walter Sibraa.
      </para>
      <para>
       Queensland-James Bernard Keeffe; Florence Isabel Bjelke-Petersen; Neville Thomas Bonner; Gerry Norman Jones; Michael John Macklin.
      </para>
      <para>
       South Australia-Donald Scott Jessop; Dominic John Foreman; Robert Hill; Nick Bolkus; Janine Haines.
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasmania-Peter Elliot Rae; Jean Margaret Hearn; Brian Harradine; Michael Townley; John Coates.
      </para>
      <para>
       Victoria-Cyril Graham Primmer; Margaret Georgina Constance Guilfoyle; Robert Francis Ray; Austin William Russell Lewis; John Royston Siddons.
      </para>
      <para>
       Western Australia-Reginald Greive Withers; Gordon Douglas McIntosh; Peter Drew Durack; Patricia Jessie Giles; Noel Ashley Crichton- Browne.
      </para>
      <para>
       The abovenamed senators made and subscribed the oath or affirmation of allegiance.
      </para>
      <para>
       His Excellency the Governor-General having retired-
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ELECTION OF PRESIDENT
     </title>
     <speech electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" nameid="2U4" page="1" party="LP" speaker="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2U4">
         Senator CARRICK
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr Bradshaw, I remind the Senate that the time has come when it is necessary for the Senate to choose one of its number to become President. I propose Senator Young, and I move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That Senator Young do take the chair of this Senate as President.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="MQ7" speaker="Senator Scott">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="MQ7">
          Senator Scott
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I second the motion.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="4F4" page="1" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I propose to the Senate, for its President, Senator Colston, and I move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That Senator Colston do take the chair of this Senate as President.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="9V4" speaker="Senator Grimes">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="9V4">
          Senator Grimes
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I second the motion.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The Clerk-Are there any further nominations? There being no further nominations, I invite the two candidates to address the Senate.
       </para>
      </interject>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="HV7" speaker="Senator Young">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="HV7">
          Senator Young
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I submit myself to the will of the Senate.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="PF4" speaker="Senator Colston">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="PF4">
          Senator Colston
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mindful of the consequences of doing so, I submit myself to the will of the Senate.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The Clerk-There being two nominations, in accordance with the Standing Orders a ballot will be taken. Before the Senate proceeds to ballot, the bells will be rung for three minutes.
       </para>
       <para>
        The bells having been rung-
       </para>
       <para>
        The Clerk-The Senate will now proceed to ballot. Ballot papers will be distributed to honourable senators, who are requested to write upon the paper the name of the candidate for whom they desire to vote. The Clerks will now distribute ballot papers to all honourable senators. The candidates are Senator Young and Senator Colston.
       </para>
       <para>
        A ballot having been taken -
       </para>
       <para>
        The Clerk-Honourable senators, the result of the ballot is as follows: Senator Young, 37 votes; and Senator Colston, 27 votes. Senator Young is therefore elected President of the Senate in accordance with the Standing Orders.
       </para>
       <para>
        Senator Young having been conducted to the dais-
       </para>
      </interject>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
         <name nameid="HV7">
          (Senator the Hon. Harold Young)
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Honourable senators, I feel very proud today because of the great honour you have bestowed upon me. In recognition of that honour I say that I am also very conscious of the responsibilities of the office of President. I assure this chamber that I will do my utmost in an earnest endeavour to conduct the affairs of this chamber with the same high standards as my predecessors. I trust that I will also do so, to the best of my ability, without bias to anybody within this chamber and with fairness to all.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" nameid="2U4" page="1" party="LP" speaker="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2U4">
         Senator CARRICK
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, I am delighted that I should have the privilege of first calling you Mr President. On behalf of my Government, and I am sure of all honourable senators, I acknowledge you as the President of this chamber. We assure you of our full support and loyalty. We know that you bring to the office qualities of character, dignity, experience and merit that will do further honour to the Chair. Mr President, this chamber has a long, honourable and magnificent tradition, and that tradition has been added to year by year by the Presidents of the past. Your predecessor, himself a South Australian, added further lustre, as did those before him.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       You have served long here. I have been proud to call you friend, as others have. I acknowledge also that I have been proud to know your wife, and she will bring to her high office with you a great dignity and charm. You have served in many capacities in senior roles-as Chairman of Committees, as Government Whip, and as Opposition Whip. You have a true sense of this chamber. You are, through your service in the past, a true parliamentarian. The highest tribute one can pay to a President in his objectivity is that he has a sense of parliament, and that he brings to his office that sense. You in your journey, with our full support and with our warmest congratulations, will add further strength to the tradition of this chamber. We wish you good fortune and success for the future.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="4F4" page="2" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, on behalf of the Opposition I would like to congratulate you on your success in the ballot just conducted. I suppose of all the things that can be regarded as success in politics, winning ballots is one of the highest. I must say that I have not studied you as closely as Senator Carrick, but I concur with all the nice things he said about you of which I have personal knowledge. On behalf of the Opposition I wish you every success in your role as President of this chamber. In our view and, I think, in the view of historians and your successors, your success or otherwise will be measured by the extent to which your deliberations and presidency of this chamber are touched by the wand of tolerance, firmness and complete impartiality. We hope that will be so and we wish you well.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="3V4" page="2" party="AD" speaker="Chipp Sen The Hon D.L.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="3V4">
         Senator CHIPP
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, on behalf of the Australian Democrats I warmly congratulate you on your success today in gaining the highest office in this Parliament. We congratulate you very sincerely. I am very pleased to say that I and all the members of my party voted for you.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Honourable senators interjecting-
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="3V4">
         Senator CHIPP
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Well, as far as I know all the members of my party voted for you. You are a friend of mine. You have been a friend of mine for, I think, 14 years, but that is not the reason I voted for you. Seriously, the reason we took the view that we should give you, a member of the Liberal Party, our support was in no way connected with the fact that you belong to a political party which happens to be in government. We feel very strongly that the Government is entirely separate from the presidency of this place. We believe that a member of the Liberal Party should be President because that party has the greatest number of members in this chamber. We will be adopting that same philosophy for the next ballot to be conducted in this chamber. I thought it would be fair to make that point at this stage.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       As I understand it this new Senate is unique in Australian politics. It is the first Senate in which the balance of power is held by an independent political party. It will not be easy for you, Mr President. Without naming anybody, a few of us here are known to be rather controversial people and a hung Senate or a tied Senate could bring you a number of problem days and problem nights. We sincerely hope, with respect, that you will be fair and impartial in your treatment of Ministers and ordinary senators and, above all, that you will always act as the defender of senators' rights against the Executive which, over the years, has tried to intrude its hand into this place. In that regard we can do no more than ask you to follow the magnificent example set by your predecessor, whom we both admire.
      </para>
      <para>
       At the risk of introducing a discordant note into these proceedings I want to say this to you: As a fair and a just man, you will be as disappointed as I am to learn that, for some incomprehensible reason, the Government has refused to grant any pair under any conditions to any senator belonging to the Australian Democrats or to Senator Harradine. Pairing is to be freely available to all senators of the Liberal Party, the National Country Party, which has fewer members in this place than the Australian Democrats, and the Australian Labor Party. Apart from being a rather quaint way to begin this session harmoniously and towards achieving an atmosphere in which consensus can be achieved, it is blatant discrimination against members of a party democratically elected to hold responsible office in this place. I mention it very briefly now, Mr President, in order to acquaint you with the difficult task that you have ahead; to acquaint you with some of the initial problems which many confront you in your new capacity as a result of decisions which have been made but which are not of your making. Apart from being unfair and discriminatory, the decision of the Government is against the spirit of democratic representation.
      </para>
      <para>
       I shall illustrate what I mean. Let us assume that the Government introduces a Bill, as it did three years ago, breaking an election promise of maintaining six-monthly indexation of pensions. Let us further assume that one of the five Australian Democrat senators is very ill or absent from the chamber on compassionate grounds. That Bill would be passed by this Senate because that Australian Democrat senator, absent through illness, would not make up the numbers to tie the vote. In that situation the Government would have deliberately refused to grant either him or her a pair.
      </para>
      <para>
       I make the point that that would be a gross and deliberate distortion of a vote in Her Majesty's Parliament. Every other honourable senator, except Senator Harradine and ourselves, would be granted a pair and leave of absence would be given for that vote. To complete the record, Mr President, when I discussed this matter with Senator Carrick this morning he stated that if I were prepared to limit our requests for a pair only to occasions when there is a death in one of our families or when one of us is ill, he would then consider taking that proposition to 'his people'. Mr President, you will understand in a flash why I flatly rejected that offer. All that Australian Democrat senators ask for is to have the same rights as other senators. We will not be regarded as people having second class rights in this place. I sincerely hope that the Government will look at this problem and present a reasonable solution to us by the end of this week. In conclusion, Mr President, we wish you well in the difficult task ahead of you.
      </para>
      <para>
       Government senators interjecting-
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="3V4">
         Senator CHIPP
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The recess has not helped the mental retards on the other side of the House. I offer to you and your wife our congratulations and good wishes.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="MQ7" page="3" party="NCP" speaker="Scott Sen The Hon D.B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="MQ7">
         Senator SCOTT
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the National Country Party in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        — Mr President, I add my personal congratulations and those of my party, the National Country Party. The warmth of our congratulations and feelings for you as you take up your important task is not to be measured by the brevity of what I am about to say. I endorse those very true things which have been said of you by previous speakers here this afternoon. I am sure that your long experience in this place, your knowledge of procedures and perhaps above all your fairness and unquestioned integrity will be of great value to this chamber and to the institution of Parliament. I endorse the things that have been said about you and warmly congratulate you. I am glad that you, a distinguished South Australian, are following another distinguished South Australian in the office of President. I am sure that your contribution to this chamber will be a constructive contribution and will enable this chamber to be the sort of constructive and dignified place that it should be. I offer my congratulations.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="PF4" page="3" party="ALP" speaker="Colston Sen M.A.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="PF4">
         Senator COLSTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, as your adversary in the ballot which has just occurred, I welcome the opportunity of congratulating you on your election as the sixteenth President of the Senate. From the floor of the Senate, the task of President often appears to be an easy one. But, having sat in the President's chair on a temporary basis on a number of occasions, I can assure honourable senators that the task is not easy. The task that you have will be quite demanding. We must also remember that you, as President, will have a number of administrative and ceremonial duties associated with your office of President, and because of that the demands upon you will be even greater. I certainly wish you well, and I hope that your term of office will be not only demanding but also rewarding.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Those of us who came into the Senate between December 1975 and early this year have served in the Senate under one President only; so to serve under a new President will be a new experience for many of us. As far as I can recall, the previous President called me to order only once. I dare say, Mr President, that you may have to do that in the future, although there will not be a deliberate effort on my part to get you to do so. But there is one part of your predecessor's example that you will not be able to follow, in that when he called me to order I was delivering my maiden speech. Again, Mr President, I offer my congratulations and my good wishes for your term of office.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="3" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, on behalf of myself I congratulate you on your election to the presidency. One of the most important functions of the Senate and of individual senators is the expressive or representative function. The right of any honourable senator to speak in this chamber should not be dependent upon the whims of the Whips, and I expect the President of the Senate to uphold that right of individual senators. I expect that there will be a difficult time ahead. I note that on your election to the position of President of this place you are also the Chairman of the Senate Standing Orders Committee. One of the matters that have been referred to that Committee is the question whether a seconder is appropriate for any motion before this Parliament, that is, whether any honourable senator should have the opportunity to represent the viewpoints of those persons who have elected him to this chamber.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       I have not been advised of the proposition relating to pairs, presumably because I have not yet asked for any; but I might just mention that the Legislative Council of Tasmania is composed mostly of independent members and there is no difficulty in arranging pairs. There are some very interesting ways in which members notify their intention of seeking a pair, but provided that that is made good within a certain time it is accepted by that Parliament.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr President, your duties will not be easy. They will depend on the good will of the Senate and the good will of individual senators. So far as I am concerned, you have my good will.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="1H4" page="4" party="AD" speaker="Haines Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="1H4">
         Senator HAINES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Senator Harradine, as I understand it, was born in Quorn, South Australia, but he is in fact a Tasmanian senator. Therefore, as a South Australian I would like to claim the privilege of welcoming the second South Australian President under whom I have had the privilege of being a member of this House and to say that I am sure that you, Mr President, will do at least as well as your distinguished predecessor. I add in passing that I had a few rather unpleasant moments around midday today when I thought perhaps something had come unstuck. When I returned to my office I discovered that a large box of envelopes which had been delivered to me was addressed to me and labelled 'President of the Senate'. I was not quite sure at that time whether someone was anticipating a coup or was having a trial run at prophecy. I can assure you, Mr President, that as far as I am concerned I hope it is the latter. I congratulate you. I am proud to work under you.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Honourable senators, I express my very sincere thanks to all of those honourable senators who have been so kind to me in their remarks today and who have also wished me well as President of this chamber. I again assure the Senate that I appreciate that things will not at all times be easy in this chamber, as they have not always been easy in the past. Having said that, I again want to emphasise that I will conduct myself, I hope, in an earnest endeavour not only to be fair but also to be seen to be fair to all people in this place. I trust that with the co-operation of the other chairmen who occupy the chair and honourable senators we can perform the duties of this place at the standard and in the manner in which they have been conducted in the past.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Honourable senators, again I thank you very much for your remarks and for your support, and also for the good wishes expressed to my wife, Margaret. I take this opportunity also to welcome from the chair all the new senators who have joined us today. I wish you well in your deliberations and your associations in this place. I trust that you will have a long, worthwhile and happy term as senators in this august chamber.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND ENERGY" nameid="2U4" page="4" party="LP" speaker="Carrick Sen The Hon J.L.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2U4">
         Senator CARRICK
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I wish to inform honourable senators that His Excellency the Governor-General will be pleased to receive the President and such honourable senators as desire to accompany him in the Senate Opposition Party Room forthwith.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Sitting suspended from 3.50 to 4.35 p.m.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="4" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      PRESENTATION TO GOVERNOR-GENERAL
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Honourable senators, I have to report that, accompanied by you this afternoon, I presented myself to His Excellency the Governor-General as the choice of the Senate as President and His Excellency was pleased to congratulate me upon my election.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The President read prayers.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="4" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      LEADERSHIP OF AUSTRALIAN DEMOCRATS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="3V4" page="4" party="AD" speaker="Chipp Sen The Hon D.L.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="3V4">
         Senator CHIPP
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I seek leave to make a statement concerning the leadership of the Australian Democrats and the allocation of responsibilities.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="3V4">
         Senator CHIPP
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I thank the Senate. I have the honour to inform the Senate that I have been re-elected by my party as parliamentary leader and my colleague, Senator Mason, has been re-elected as deputy parliamentary leader. The election was by form of a secret postal ballot in which all members of the Australian Democrats were allowed to participate. I have a list setting out how the areas of responsibility have been allocated. Copies are in the hands of the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Carrick) and the Leader of the Opposition (Senator Button). Unless it is the wish of the Senate that I read the list, I seek leave to have it incorporated in Hansard.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The document read as follows-
      </para>
      <para>
       FOR THE INFORMATION OF SENATORS AND THE MEDIA
      </para>
      <para>
       I am pleased to announce the allocation of the following areas of responsibility to the respective Australian Democrat Senators.
      </para>
      <para>
       I will be responsible for the: Department of the Prime Minister
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Attorney-General
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Trade and Resources
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Immigration and Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Transport
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Housing and Construction
      </para>
      <para>
       My Deputy, Senator Colin Mason, will be responsible for the: Department of National Development and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Foreign Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Science and Technology
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Environment
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Michael Macklin, will be responsible for the: Department of Primary Industry
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Education
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Aboriginal Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Administrative Services
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Veterans' Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of the Capital Territory
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Janine Haines, will be responsible for the: Department of Industry and Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Social Security
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Health
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Business and Consumer Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Home Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator John Siddons, will be responsible for the: Department of Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Treasury
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Finance
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Industrial Relations
      </para>
      <para>
       Department of Employment and Youth Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator the Hon. D. L. Chipp
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="3V4">
         Senator CHIPP
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I thank the Senate.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="5" type="Committee">
     <title>
      ELECTION OF CHAIRMAN OF COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Motion (by Senator Carrick) proposed:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the Senate do now proceed to elect a Chairman of Committees.
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="5" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
        <time.stamp>
         (4.38)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I move the following amendment to the motion moved by the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Carrick):
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave out all words after 'That', insert 'the appointment of a Chairman of Committees be made, prior to the dispatch of any other business, after the Senate has determined any motion for the appointment of a second Deputy-President, or after the Leader of the Government in the Senate has informed the Senate that he will not move such a motion'.
      </para>
      <para>
       I move that amendment by reason of the fact that, quite suddenly so far as I am concerned, there has emerged from the Government parties a proposition for the establishment of another position of Deputy President, that is, a Deputy President, Committees, as distinct from what, presumably, we are supposed to vote for in the motion moved by the Leader of the Government in the Senate, that of Deputy President, Procedures. At present nothing in the Standing Orders states that the office for which we are required to elect an occupant at this time is that of Deputy President, Procedures. There have been reports of horse trading between the senior coalition partner, the Liberal Party of Australia, and the National Country Party in regard to positions of Deputy President. I find it hard to believe that the National Country Party would be engaged in any such horse trading having regard to the statements made by Mr Nixon about horse meat traders, namely, that he would throw the book at them.
      </para>
      <para>
       I feel it is unfortunate that the Senate should be put in the position of having to decide who shall occupy one of the offices of Deputy President. In fact, the position of Deputy President or Chairman of Committees is not mentioned in the Constitution. Two objections are raised to my proposed amendment. The first is that the Senate should, and is bound to, elect a Deputy President or Chairman of Committees. The Constitution merely requires that we elect a President. Section 18 of the Constitution states that before or during any absence of the President, the Senate may choose a senator to perform his duties in his absence. That covers the situation where you, Mr President, are absent. Additionally, it is said by some that under the Standing Orders we must appoint a Deputy President. Standing Order 26 states that the Senate may appoint a Senator to be Chairman of Committees, who, unless otherwise determined, shall hold office until 30 June, and so on.
      </para>
      <para>
       The second major objection posed is that a question arises as to who would be the Chairman of Committees during the Committee stage of any Bill. Mr President, Standing Orders 28A and 31A provide that you, sir, shall appoint a panel of not less than two senators to act as Temporary Chairmen of Committees; also that you may call on either to relieve you in the chair. So, in fact, there is no requirement that the Senate elect today a Deputy President, or Chairman of Committees. Neither the Constitution nor the Standing Orders contain a requirement that that should occur. In fact, precedent shows that on 13 occasions the Senate has not elected a Deputy President on the first day of sitting. Indeed, on one occasion, it did not proceed to such an election until three weeks after the commencement of the session.
      </para>
      <para>
       In view of what I have outlined, it would be quite in order for the Senate to delay appointing a Deputy President who would, of course, be the Chairman of Committees. It must be understood by honourable senators that at present the Deputy President is paid an additional $6,500 and that, under the proposed 1981 review of remuneration, he will be paid almost an additional $8,000. I am not in a position to cast my vote for a Deputy President at this point unless I know how many Deputy Presidents we are to have and what are to be their functions. It is unfair of the Government to suggest that the Senate should now proceed to the election of a Deputy President without knowing how many such officers there are to be and what are to be their functions. Additionally, the Government will have to prove to the Senate that the proposed expenditure involved is warranted.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="C67" page="6" party="NCP" speaker="Collard Sen S.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="C67">
         Senator COLLARD
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
        <time.stamp>
         (4.45)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        — Mr President, I second the amendment moved by Senator Harradine. I have had a few discussions with him this afternoon and recognise his concern about the fact that two positions are being suggested at this stage. However, I can assure him that although we may sometimes use the quality of our representation to further a particular cause it is only on rather rare occasions that we do that, even though we are in the unique position of being able to do that. On this occasion I assure Senator Harradine that we plead not guilty to either horse trading or trading in horsemeat.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Amendment agreed to.
      </para>
      <para>
       Original question, as amended, agreed to.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="6" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      DEATH OF SIR THOMAS PLAYFORD, G.C.M.G.
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is with deep regret that I inform the Senate of the death on 16 June 1981 of the Honourable Sir Thomas Playford, G.C.M.G., a former Premier of South Australia. I invite all honourable senators to stand in silence as a mark of respect to the memory of the late Sir Thomas Playford.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Honourable senators having stood in their places-
       </para>
      </interject>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thank honourable senators.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <petition.grp page="6">
     <title>
      PETITIONS
     </title>
     <petition nameids="NJ4" page="6" presenters="TATE">
      <title>
       Tertiary Education
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="NJ4" page="6" party="unknown" speaker="TATE">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present the following petition from 864 citizens of Australia:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The petition of the undersigned respectfully showeth:
       </para>
       <para>
        That the present level of funding under the Tertiary Education Assistance Scheme is causing financial hardship to many Tasmanian families and jeopardizing the future tertiary studies of young Tasmanians.
       </para>
       <para>
        Your petitioners most humbly pray that the Senate, in Parliament assembled, should-call on the Federal Government,
       </para>
       <para>
        (i) to immediately increase the Tertiary Education Assistance Scheme to make more realistic provision for away-from-home tertiary studies of young Tasmanians and vary the threshold of parental income at which it diminishes.
       </para>
       <para>
        (ii) to abandon its proposal that a Loans Scheme be instituted whereby students and their families will be burdened by debt as they meet costs associated with new and further studies.
       </para>
       <para>
        (iii) to give a firm commitment that no tuition fees will be introduced for students undertaking their first degree, diploma or other courses at Tasmania's tertiary institutions.
       </para>
       <para>
        And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="8R7" page="6" presenters="SIDDONS">
      <title>
       Service Pensions
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="8R7" page="6" party="unknown" speaker="SIDDONS">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8R7">
          Senator SIDDONS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present the following petition from 23 citizens of Australia:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
       </para>
       <para>
        That the Ex-Servicemens' &amp; Womens' Pension Association is a body formed for the express purpose of obtaining a Service Pension for all Ex-Service Personnel at sixty years of age for men and fifty-five years of age for women regardless of where they served during the 1939-45 war.
       </para>
       <para>
        Your petitioners therefore humbly pray that the Senate, in Parliament assembled should give urgent consideration to a favourable decision to the granting of the Service Pension to all Ex-Service Personnel who served their country in time of need and who did not serve overseas through no fault of their own. The Service Pension is presently only granted to Returned Ex-Service Personnel.
       </para>
       <para>
        And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="5V4" page="6" presenters="COLEMAN">
      <title>
       Proposed Sinai Peacekeeping Force
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="5V4" page="6" party="unknown" speaker="COLEMAN">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5V4">
          Senator COLEMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present the following petition from 57 citizens of Australia:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
       </para>
       <para>
        (1) bipartisan concern exists in the Australian community over involvement of Australian military forces in the Middle East where those forces are not under United Nations auspices;
       </para>
       <para>
        (2) concern is also evident about Australia's military capacity to provide those forces without weakening Australia's defence;
       </para>
       <para>
        (3) Sinai is not an area within Australia's sphere of influence; and,
       </para>
       <para>
        (4) Australian agricultural export markets may be adversely affected by Australian military participation in Sinai.
       </para>
       <para>
        Your petitioners therefore humbly pray that the Australian Parliament does not ratify Australian military participation in the proposed Sinai peacekeeping force, unless that force is fully controlled by the United Nations.
       </para>
       <para>
        And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="8H7" page="7" presenters="KILGARIFF">
      <title>
       Housing Finance
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="8H7" page="7" party="unknown" speaker="KILGARIFF">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8H7">
          Senator KILGARIFF
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present the following petition from 108 citizens of Australia:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The petition of the undersigned citizens of the Northern Territory of Australia respectfully showeth:
       </para>
       <para>
        The level of home ownership in Australia is falling as increasing costs, particularly interest rates on housing loans, continue to rise. High interest rates and the increasing difficulties in obtaining housing loan finance have combined to jeopardise the prospects for home ownership of many Australians.
       </para>
       <para>
        Firm and positive action must be taken by the Federal Government to reduce interest rates on housing loans.
       </para>
       <para>
        Your petitioners therefore humbly pray that:
       </para>
       <para>
        The Federal Government will initiate policies to lower interest rates on home loans and promote greater availability of finance for housing.
       </para>
       <para>
        And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="5V4" page="7" presenters="COLEMAN">
      <title>
       Women's Centres
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="5V4" page="7" party="unknown" speaker="COLEMAN">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5V4">
          Senator COLEMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present the following petition from 235 citizens of Australia:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
       </para>
       <para>
        That many thousands of women and children in the Australian community who use the services of Women's Refuges, Women's Health Centres and Women's Rape Crisis Centres:
       </para>
       <para>
        (1) Express their concern at the decision of the Federal Government to pass to the States the responsibility of funding those essential services because of the poor record already demonstrated by some States;
       </para>
       <para>
        (2) Call on the Federal Government to reverse that decision;
       </para>
       <para>
        (3) Request that the Government ensure one Department to administer all funds for the above under the heading of Women's Services;
       </para>
       <para>
        (4) Propose that future funding should be on a guaranteed triennial basis taking into account inflation and indexation increases; and
       </para>
       <para>
        (5) Ask for a positive policy commitment for a substantial injection of funds to consolidate existing services and to develop new initiatives for women and children in the Australian community.
       </para>
       <para>
        And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="NJ4" page="7" presenters="TATE">
      <title>
       Pensioner Benefits
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="NJ4" page="7" party="unknown" speaker="TATE">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present the following petition from 312 citizens of Australia:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        To the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled the Petition of the undersigned citizens respectfully showeth:
       </para>
       <para>
        That it is clearly apparent that Australian society is becoming more polarised-that the rich at home and abroad are becoming richer profiting from Australia's mineral wealth, whilst pensioners and the disadvantaged, some three million people, are becoming a race apart.
       </para>
       <para>
        That, of necessity, the Federal Government take action that all Australians share the wealth of their country by the transfer of resources to income security, health care and housing, therefore your petitioners urge that:
       </para>
       <para>
        (1) All pensions and benefits be raised to at least 30 per cent of the National Average Weekly Male Earnings seasonally adjusted.
       </para>
       <para>
        (2) Removal of the means/income test on the Pensioner Health Benefit imposed by Federal legislation 1973. Reintroduction of Medibank in so doing restore all Australians to equality of citizenship.
       </para>
       <para>
        (3) To alleviate Australia's shortage of housing stock within the capacity of people to pay (rental and ownership) the Federal Government inject $200 million into State Housing Authorities, which will, in addition, alleviate unemployment.
       </para>
       <para>
        And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="GD5" page="7" presenters="RYAN">
      <title>
       Women's Centres
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="GD5" page="7" party="unknown" speaker="RYAN">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="GD5">
          Senator RYAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present the following petition from 20 citizens of Australia:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in the Parliament assembled. The humble petitions of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
       </para>
       <para>
        That many thousands of women and children in the Australian community who use the services of Women's Refuges, Rape Crisis Centres and Women's Health Centres:
       </para>
       <para>
        1. Express their concern at the decision of the Federal Government to pass to the States the responsibility of funding these essential services because of the poor record already demonstrated by some States;
       </para>
       <para>
        2. Call on the Federal Government to reverse that decision;
       </para>
       <para>
        3. Request that the Government ensure one department to administer all funds for the above under the heading of women's services;
       </para>
       <para>
        4. Professed that future funding should be on a guaranteed triennial basis taking into account inflation and indexation increases.
       </para>
       <para>
        5. Ask for a positive policy commitment for a substantial injection of funds to consolidate existing services and to develop new initiatives for women and children in the Australian community.
       </para>
       <para>
        And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="5V4" page="8" presenters="COLEMAN">
      <title>
       Trans Australia Airlines
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="5V4" page="8" party="unknown" speaker="COLEMAN">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5V4">
          Senator COLEMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present the following petition from 49 citizens of Australia:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in the Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
       </para>
       <para>
        Many Australians depend almost exclusively upon Trans Australia Airlines for the provision of essential air services.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Federal Liberal Party policy objective of selling Trans Australia Airlines within 4 years is contrary to the national interest.
       </para>
       <para>
        Sale of Trans Australia Airlines would inevitably result in-
       </para>
       <para>
        (i) the creation of a private monopoly of major airline services in Australia:
       </para>
       <para>
        (ii) higher domestic air fares.
       </para>
       <para>
        Your petitioners therefore humbly pray that the Senate will reject outright any proposal to sell Trans Australia Airlines.
       </para>
       <para>
        And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Clerk-Petitions have been lodged for presentation as follows:
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="8G4" page="8" presenters="DURACK">
      <title>
       Medical Records
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in the Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
      </para>
      <para>
       That we are gravely concerned by the invasion of privacy caused by Government agents seizing patients' medical records:
      </para>
      <para>
       Your petitioners most humbly pray that the Senate, in Parliament assembled should-Legislate to protect the private and confidential nature of medical records from scrutiny except on the express and informed consent of the patient or an order from a presiding judge.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="8G4">
         Senator Durack
        </name>
       </presenter>
       .
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="LF4" page="8" presenters="COATES">
      <title>
       Pensioner Benefits
      </title>
      <para>
       To the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled the petition of the undersigned citizens respectfully showeth:
      </para>
      <para>
       That it is clearly apparent that Australian society is becoming more polarised-that the rich at home and abroad are becoming richer profiting from Australia's mineral wealth, whilst pensioners and the disadvantaged, some three million people, are becoming a race apart.
      </para>
      <para>
       That, of necessity, the Federal Government take action that all Australians share the wealth of their country by the transfer of resources to income security, health care and housing, therefore your petitioners urge that:
      </para>
      <para>
       1. All pensions and benefits be raised to at least 30 per cent of the National Average Weekly Male Earnings seasonally adjusted.
      </para>
      <para>
       2. Removal of the means/income test on the Pensioner Health Benefit imposed by Federal legislation 1973. Re-introduction of Medibank in so doing restore all Australians to equality of citizenship.
      </para>
      <para>
       3. To alleviate Australia's shortage of housing stock within the capacity of people to pay (rental and ownership) the Federal Government inject $200 million into State Housing Authorities, which will, in addition, alleviate unemployment.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="LF4">
         Senator Coates
        </name>
       </presenter>
       .
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="8H7" page="8" presenters="KILGARIFF">
      <title>
       Pensioner Benefits
      </title>
      <para>
       To the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned showeth that your petitioners are gravely concerned that the Government is not fulfilling its responsibility in ensuring an adequate standard of living for all Australians, which is causing untold hardship on relief agencies' limited resources, and require the following steps to be taken as a matter of urgency:
      </para>
      <para>
       1. That the Commonwealth Government raise the level of all pensions and benefits at least to the poverty line.
      </para>
      <para>
       2. That the Commonwealth Government reconsider its recent decisions in relation to the health system and cuts to Commonwealth activity.
      </para>
      <para>
       Your petitioners, therefore, humbly request that Parliament take immediate and positive action to avert further poverty and suffering in our community by implementation of the above measures.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="8H7">
         Senator Kilgariff
        </name>
       </presenter>
       .
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <para>
      Petitions received.
     </para>
    </petition.grp>
    <debate page="8" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      NOTICES OF MOTION
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Before asking whether there are any notices of motion, I would like to make a statement to the Senate. It has been indicated to me that a number of honourable senators wish to give a considerable number of notices of motion. In order to avoid the necessity for honourable senators concerned to rise repeatedly and seek the call, I intend, with the concurrence of the Senate, to adopt a procedure which was used at the beginning of this Parliament; that is, I intend to allow honourable senators with more than one notice of motion to give their notices of motion together, and all of the notices of motion which are given will be arranged on the Notice Paper in the order in which the honourable senators would normally have been given the call. Is it the wish of the Senate that this procedure be adopted? As there is no objection, this course will be followed.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="9" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      BICENTENARY CELEBRATIONS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="9">
      <title>
       Notice of Motion
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="4F4" page="9" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Leader of the Opposition)
         </role>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate, noting that Australia celebrates its bicentenary on 26 January 1988, is of the opinion that measures should be taken by that date to amend or replace the Constitution in order to establish Australia as a legally independent and autonomous nation within the Commonwealth of Nations.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="9" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      ORDER OF BUSINESS ON THE NOTICE PAPER
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="3V4" page="9" party="AD" speaker="Chipp Sen The Hon D.L.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="3V4">
         Senator CHIPP
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give contingent notice that, contingent on the President proceeding to the placing of business on any day, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Chipp moving a motion relating to the order of business on the Notice Paper.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="9" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      PURCHASE OF AIRCRAFT CARRIER
     </title>
     <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="YJ7" page="9" party="AD" speaker="Mason Sen C.V.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YJ7">
         Senator MASON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That in the opinion of the Senate:
      </para>
      <para>
       The proposed purchase of a single, short-deck aircraft carrier for the Australian Navy is ill advised for the following reasons:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) That the estimated cost with aircraft, in the order of one thousand million dollars, is not justified by the capability and performance levels of such a vessel;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) That a single aircraft carrier, which must be out of service regularly for maintenance and refitting, cannot play any useful continuous role in Australia's defence;
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) That our present two squadrons of long-range maritime reconnaissance aircraft are better equipped for anti-submarine warfare than any helicopter type with which such a carrier could be equipped;
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) That the Harrier type jump jet aircraft proposed for the carrier are to specialised and lack the performance required to general operations in comparison with other modern aircraft; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (e) That the enormous cost of the carrier, equivalent to that of twelve modern hydrofoil attack ships which could be armed with as many as 96 Harpoon missiles, would dangerously limit Australia's options for naval purchasing of more modern practical ships especially of the missile attach-ship type.
      </para>
      <para>
       and that plans to proceed with the purchase of a short-deck carrier should be postponed pending a detailed public inquiry into the advantages of spending the same money on a fleet of fast, flexible, lightly-manned, inexpensive, stable and heavily armed missile-bearing platforms, preferably of the hydrofoil type.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="9" type="Bill">
     <title>
      HEALTH ACTS AMENDMENT BILL (No. 2) 1981
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Notice of Motion
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="1H4" page="9" party="AD" speaker="Haines Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="1H4">
         Senator HAINES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to amend certain Acts relating to sickness and hospital benefits to provide for a voluntary contribution scheme for health insurance.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="9" type="Bill">
     <title>
      BANKING AMENDMENT BILL 1981
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Notice of Motion
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="1H4" page="9" party="AD" speaker="Haines Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="1H4">
         Senator HAINES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to amend the Banking Act 1959 to provide for regulation of increases in interest rates.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="9" type="Bill">
     <title>
      INCOME TAX ASSESSMENT AMENDMENT BILL (No. 2) 1981
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Notice of Motion
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="1H4" page="9" party="AD" speaker="Haines Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="1H4">
         Senator HAINES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to amend the Income Tax Assessment Act 1936 to grant exemption from income tax of certain income from savings deposits.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="9" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      EFFECTS OF AGENT ORANGE ON VIETNAM VETERANS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="9">
      <title>
       Notice of Motion
      </title>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="9V4" page="9" party="ALP" speaker="Grimes Sen D.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="9V4">
          Senator GRIMES
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate calls for-
       </para>
       <para>
        (a) a review by the Administrative Review Council of all aspects of the administrative advice tendered to the Ministers for Veterans' Affairs, Defence and Health on the use of agent orange and other defoliants in Vietnam;
       </para>
       <para>
        (b) a clear and unequivocal assurance from the Government that servicemen thus affected will be fully compensated and that this compensation will include their wives and children; and
       </para>
       <para>
        (c) an independent judicial inquiry which shall ascertain-
       </para>
       <para>
        (i) the extent and range of disabilities incurred by Vietnam veterans and their dependants; and
       </para>
       <para>
        (ii) the effects of the continued use of these defoliants within Australia.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="9" type="Bill">
     <title>
      CUSTOMS AMENDMENT BILL (No. 2) 1981
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       Notice of Motion
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="2I4" page="9" party="AD" speaker="Macklin Sen M.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2I4">
         Senator MACKLIN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to amend the Customs Act 1901 to provide for approval by Parliament of the export of minerals extracted from sand.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="10" type="Bill">
     <title>
      REPATRIATION ACTS (TUBERCULOSIS PENSIONS) AMENDMENT BILL 1981
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       Notice of Motion
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="2I4" page="10" party="AD" speaker="Macklin Sen M.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2I4">
         Senator MACKLIN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act relating to repatriation pensions for pulmonary tuberculosis.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="10" type="Bill">
     <title>
      INDUSTRIAL DEMOCRACY BILL 1981
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       Notice of Motion
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="8R7" page="10" party="AD" speaker="Siddons Sen J.R.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="8R7">
         Senator SIDDONS
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to encourage the introduction of industrial democracy in Australian enterprises through reductions in company tax for enterprises classified as industrial democracy enterprises.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="10" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      GOVERNMENT CLOTHING FACTORY
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="10">
      <title>
       Notice of Motion
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="8R7" page="10" party="AD" speaker="Siddons Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8R7">
          Senator SIDDONS
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        (1) That the following matter be referred to the Senate Standing Committee on Finance and Government Operations: The Government's decision to sell the Government Clothing Factory at Coburg and the Ordnance Factory at Bendigo.
       </para>
       <para>
        (2) That in making its inquiry the Standing Committee consider a report by a Government committee of inquiry, known as the Allison-Brewster committee, which recommended continuation of the Government Clothing Factory.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="10" type="Bill">
     <title>
      WESTERN AUSTRALIAN ABORIGINALS (RIGHT TO ELECTORAL ENROLMENT) BILL 1981
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       Notice of Motion
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="TJ4" page="10" party="ALP" speaker="Walsh Sen P.A.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="TJ4">
         Senator WALSH
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Western Australian Aboriginals (Right to Electoral Enrolment) Bill be taken through all its remaining stages on or before Thursday, 10 September.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="10" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      COMMISSION TO ADMINISTER OATH
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I inform honourable senators that I have received from His Excellency the Governor-General a commission to administer to senators the oath or affirmation of allegiance.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Commission laid on the table and read by the Clerk.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="10" type="Bill">
     <title>
      ASSENT TO BILLS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Assent to the following Bills reported:
      </para>
      <para>
       Fish (Export Inspection Charge) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Fish (Export Inspection Charge) Collection Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Dried Fruit (Export Inspection Charge) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Dried Fruit (Export Inspection Charge) Collection Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statute Law Revision Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Commonwealth Legal Aid Commission Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wool Industry Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Excise Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Tariff (Anti-Dumping) Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Amendment (Securities) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Tariff Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Pay-roll Tax (Territories) Assessment Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Housing Assistance Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Conciliation and Arbitration Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Supply Bill (No. 1) 1981-82.
      </para>
      <para>
       Supply Bill (No. 2) 1981-82.
      </para>
      <para>
       Commonwealth Functions (Statutes Review) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Airlines Agreement Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Independent Air Fares Committee Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Airlines Equipment Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian National Airlines Repeal Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands-Miscellaneous Amendments) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) (Registration Fees) Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Minerals (Submerged Lands) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Minerals (Submerged Lands) (Royalty) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Minerals (Submerged Lands) (Exploration Permit Fees) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Minerals (Submerged Lands) (Production Licence Fees) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Minerals (Submerged Lands) (Works Authority Fees) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Minerals (Submerged Lands) (Registration Fees) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Tariff Validation Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Roads Grants Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies (Fees) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies (Transitional Provisions) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies (Miscellaneous Amendments) Bills 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Crown Debts (Priority) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies (Acquisition of Shares) Amendment Bill (No. 2) 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies (Acquisition of Shares-Fees) Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Securities Industry Amendment Bill (No. 2) 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Securities Industry (Fees) Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies and Securities (Interpretation and Miscellaneous Provisions) Amendment Bill No. 2) 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       States (Tax Sharing and Health Grants) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Local Government (Personal Income Tax Sharing) Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Environment Protection (Sea Dumping) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Bounty (Printed Fabrics) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Bounty (Textile Yarns) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Koongarra Project Area Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Lands Acquisition (Northern Territory Pastoral Leases) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian National University Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Christmas Island Agreement Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Income Tax Laws Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Income Tax (Assessment and Rates) Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Income Tax Laws Amendment Bill (No. 2) 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Income Tax Assessment Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Income Tax (Diverted Income) Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Broadcasting and Television Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Broadcasting Stations Licence Fees Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Overseas Telecommunications Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Capital Territory Gaming and Liquor Authority Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum Products Pricing Bill 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Health Acts Amendment Bill 1981.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="11" type="Committee">
     <title>
      JOINT COMMITTEE ON THE NEW PARLIAMENT HOUSE
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="11">
      <title>
       Sixth Report
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I present the sixth report of the Joint Standing Committee on the New Parliament House.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>
         Ordered that the report be printed.
        </para>
       </interject>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="11" type="Committee">
     <title>
      SELECT COMMITTEE ON PARLIAMENT'S APPROPRIATIONS AND STAFFING
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="11">
      <title>
       Report
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Pursuant to the resolution of the Senate on 11 June 1981 I lay on the table the report of the Senate Select Committee on Parliament's Appropriations and Staffing. I advise honourable senators that the printing and circulation of the report have been undertaken consistent with the terms of the resolution.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </proctext>
      <speech electorate="SA" gov="1" nameid="2G7" page="11" party="LP" speaker="Jessop Sen D.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="2G7">
          Senator JESSOP
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I table the transcript of evidence, and move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That consideration of the report in the Committee of the Whole be an order of the day for the next day of sitting.
       </para>
       <para>
        Question resolved in the affirmative.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="11" type="Committee">
     <title>
      SELECT COMMITTEE ON PASSENGER FARES AND SERVICES TO AND FROM TASMANIA
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Pursuant to the resolution of the Senate on 11 June 1981 I lay on the table the report of the Senate Select Committee on Passenger Fares and Services to and from Tasmania. In accordance with the terms of the resolution, the Clerk authorised the printing and circulation of the report.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="TAS" gov="1" nameid="0P7" page="11" party="LP" speaker="Rae Sen P.E.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="0P7">
         Senator PETER RAE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
        <time.stamp>
         (5.4)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-I table the transcript of evidence, and move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate take note of the report.
      </para>
      <para>
       When I moved to establish this inquiry, I said:
      </para>
      <para>
       I trust that the Senate will support the establishment of a small select committee, to use the select committee procedure, to enable Tasmanians to find out what is the majority view about what will best serve Tasmania's interest as a State of the Commonwealth in linking it with the remainder of the Commonwealth. The Committee should be able to present a report which can identify to government, to the ANL and to the airlines what questions have been brought out as a result of a public inquiry . . .
      </para>
      <para>
       The Committee had two fundamental aims in the inquiry: Firstly, to assemble information to produce and stimulate an informed debate in Tasmania and elsewhere on transport issues and, secondly, to examine those issues and make recommendations as appropriate.
      </para>
      <para>
       Widespread concern has been expressed in Tasmania in recent years about interstate passenger transport, especially the cost of travelling, but little information has been available to produce an informed and coherent debate on the subject. The various inquiries into Tasmanian transport up to 1980 concentrated on freight, with scant attention being paid to passenger services. The Committee has included much background information in the report to try to rectify this deficiency. The second aim was an examination of both air and sea passenger transport issues. This included consideration of the effects on Tasmania of the report of the Independent Public Inquiry into Domestic Air Fares-the Holcroft report-and the Commonwealth Government's response to it. It was the work of another Senate committee, the Senate Standing Committee on Primary and Secondary Industry and Trade, whose 1971 report on 'Freight Rates on Australian National Shipping Services to and from Tasmania' started the process which led to the introduction of the Tasmanian freight equalisation scheme. We hope that our report on passenger services will be the catalyst for an improved passenger transport service for Tasmania in the future.
      </para>
      <para>
       Many suggestions were put to the Committee for reducing the cost of air fares, including compensation or subsidy schemes. The most comprehensive of these was submitted by the Tasmanian Government. Essentially, the scheme would allow Tasmanian residents to receive a 40 per cent reduction on their return economy air fares between Tasmania and Melbourne for journeys originating in Tasmania. The Committee did not support that recommendation. The 40 per cent reduction was assessed as the difference between the cost of travel by air and land-based modes of transport on the mainland over similar distances. In principle, it is an extension of the Tasmanian freight equalisation scheme to cover passengers as well as freight. It was proposed that the benefits be limited to the residents of Tasmania.
      </para>
      <para>
       On 1 April 1981, in response to the Holcroft report, the Commonwealth Minister for Transport (Mr Hunt) announced changes to the national air fare formulae from which all Ansett Airlines of Australia and Trans Australia Airlines fares are calculated. The effect of this decision was to increase significantly fares on short-haul routes, such as those between Tasmania and Melbourne, and decrease fares on long-haul routes such as Melbourne to Perth. Cognisant of the effect which the full increase would have had on Tasmania, the Minister also announced that the Commonwealth would fund directly a 10 per cent subsidy on all routes operated by Ansett and TAA between Tasmania and Melbourne. The Government's decision very clearly acknowledged Tasmania's disadvantage in relation to interstate passenger travel.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Committee believes, however, that a subsidy is not necessarily the answer to Tasmania's passenger transport problems. There is no guarantee that its real value will be maintained or even that a future government will not reduce or remove it as the cost of maintaining it grows. In the case of Tasmania, the value of the subsidy could also be eroded by changes in the relativities between fares on short-haul and long-haul routes arising from further changes to the air fare formulae. In addition, a subsidy does nothing to overcome other shortcomings in air services identified during the inquiry. The Committee believes that compensation schemes or subsidies should only be used if no other methods of overcoming the problems are available. The Committee therefore considered alternative proposals for providing cheaper and better air services for Tasmania. The Holcroft report identified the high fixed costs which apply to a national airline network operator. Evidence to the Committee indicated-I stress this point-that a regional operator with adequate loadings could operate profitably with fares at 70 per cent to 80 per cent of the national airfare formula.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Committee therefore considered two alternative air service concepts for Hobart and Launceston. The first was the replacement of Ansett and TAA by a single regional operator. The second was the introduction on those routes of a regional operator in competition with Ansett and TAA. The information available to the Committee indicated that both concepts would result in cheaper and better services with a similar standard of jet aircraft to those proposed by Ansett and TAA. The Committee envisages the regional operator, being based in Tasmania, would provide the State with a significant new industry. Such an operator would also be in a position to take account of the needs of Tasmania without having to balance those needs with the needs of a national network.
      </para>
      <para>
       Neither concept is free from obstacles. The substitution of a single operator for Ansett and TAA would require their voluntary withdrawal from the routes. The Commonwealth Government does not have the power to deny licences for interstate routes except on safety grounds. Although the third operator concept does not face this difficulty, it runs into conflict with the Government's current two-airline policy. This restricts operators on routes such as those between Melbourne and Hobart and Launceston to Ansett and TAA.
      </para>
      <para>
       During the passage of the Airlines Agreement Bill through the Parliament earlier this year, the Government announced that it would establish an inquiry into deregulation of the airline industry to report within five years. If the Government accepts some form of deregulation, then there is the opportunity to introduce changes into the Tasmanian services. It would also be possible for Ansett, TAA and the Commonwealth Government to agree on changes to Tasmanian air services at any time if they so wished. The two concepts outlined by the Committee are therefore longer term, and not necessarily immediate, solutions to Tasmania's transport problems. In the meantime, the Committee believes that the Government should maintain the real value of the current 10 per cent subsidy on Tasmania to Melbourne routes. I emphasise that the Committee is saying that in the meantime, until some of its suggestions are taken forward, it recommends the maintenance of the existing subsidies.
      </para>
      <para>
       In the north-west there was the feeling that Ansett and TAA had provided an adequate service, but that an upgraded service, preferably a jet service, was desirable. There was also concern expressed about the future of the service, because the airlines had not made any commitments beyond the life of the F27s on those routes. In fact, TAA announced last Wednesday that it would be handing over its north-west Tasmania services to East-West Airlines Ltd. With regard to the upgrading of services to the north-west, the Committee noted that within three or four years a new generation of fast, pressurised turbo-prop aircraft will be available. These aircraft could upgrade the present F27 services. However, because of the expressed desire for jet services, the Committee examined the justification and feasibility of jet services for the north-west. The Committee concluded for reasons outlined in the report that there is justification for jet services for the north-west. However, there are a number of factors to be considered as to the feasibility of introducing jet services.
      </para>
      <para>
       Neither Devonport Airport nor Wynyard Airport is equipped to handle jet services at present. Both airports would need to be upgraded. To upgrade Devonport Airport to F28 standard would cost $2.9m and to DC9 or Boeing 737 standard, $5.5m. To bring Wynyard up to the standard for F28 aircraft would cost $4m and to the other standard, $6.5m. A prerequisite for the government upgrading of either airport would be its transfer from Commonwealth to local ownership under the Aerodrome Local Ownership Plan. To this end, the Marine Board of Devonport, in association with the transport company, IPEC, has been negotiating with the Department of Transport for more than three years on the transfer of the Devonport Airport to the Marine Board.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Wynyard Municipal Council and other councils in the north-west and west coast areas of the State served by Wynyard Airport have recently been giving consideration to entering into negotiation with the Department of Transport for the transfer of the ownership of Wynyard Airport to a sub-regional committee. Under the Aerodrome Local Ownership Plan, the Commonwealth Government will upgrade the airport to a standard to meet what it considers to be present and future needs. It will also meet half of the cost of upgrading terminal buildings. From an operational point of view, the information available to the Committee indicates that there is currently only enough traffic for jet services to operate to one north-west airport and maintain an acceptable frequency of flights. If jet services were to be operated to both airports, frequencies would have to be reduced or a triangular service adopted, or the north-west services would have to be carried out in tandem with one or more mainland services.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Committee believes that the introduction of jet services to the north-west is justified and feasible, subject to the aforementioned qualifications. The Committee supports their introduction. The Committee also examined the future of the north-west services. Last week TAA announced that it would relinquish its services to north-western Tasmania. This is in line with the gradual withdrawal by both Ansett and TAA from their F27 regional routes throughout Australia. I interpose for a moment to say that, if Press reports are to be accepted, there are indications that negotiations are taking place in relation to Queensland regional routes in respect of both TAA and Ansett, as well as arrangements for the transfer of some of the New South Wales routes.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="7V4" speaker="Senator Georges">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="7V4">
          Senator Georges
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Are you trying to start a debate?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="0P7">
         Senator PETER RAE
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —No, I was just referring, without comment, to Press reports. The Committee believes that the replacement of both Ansett and TAA on the north-west routes by a regional operator would be in the best interests of the region. Regional operators normally offer advance purchase excursion fares and stand-by fares which Ansett and TAA do not offer on the north-west routes. A regional operator would also promote the north-west as a gateway to Tasmania. Proposals to operate a regional service to the north-west were received by the Committee from both East-West Airlines Ltd and IPEC. The Committee discussed both proposals in the report to illustrate various objectives or characteristics which the Committee believes a regional operator should display. I emphasise that the Committee does not wish to support or oppose any proposal from a prospective applicant for a route licence. This is the responsibility of the Department of Transport and the Commonwealth Government.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The Committee examined air services to the Bass Strait islands. The Committee recommends a 20 per cent subsidy for air fares to and from Flinders Island and King Island to compensate residents of the Bass Strait islands for their total dependence on air travel. The shortfall in revenue to the airlines should be met by the Commonwealth. The Hobart-Christchurch air service, which began operating at the end of last year, was also examined by the Committee. Patronage of the service, up to April 1981, increased steadily. The number of forward bookings gave encouragement to the Committee about the future viability of the service. The Committee noted that it would be 12 months or more before the route would be included in overseas package tours and travel itineraries and so the ultimate success of the route would not be known for some time.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Committee examined the current sea service, the need for its continuation, demand for it, and various options for replacing the Empress of Australia, which is due to be retired from the Bass Strait service later in the decade. The Committee believes that the Bass Strait sea passenger service is essential for Tasmania. Without it Tasmania would be dependent solely on air transport, which in recent times has been subject to serious industrial disruption. Apart from the disadvantage of depending so heavily on air transport, there is the question of equity. On the mainland of Australia a range of modes of transport is available to choose from including a very heavily subsidised rail network. It would be inequitable for the Commonwealth Government to reduce further Tasmania's restricted transport options particulary in light of the huge subsidies spent on surface transport on the mainland. The sea service also presents other advantages for Tasmania and Victoria, and for travellers, which are enumerated in the report. The Committee considered the extent of latent demand for the service. After examining the number of passengers carried in the last two decades, the Bureau of Transport Economics estimates of demand based on its econometric calculations, and other factors, the Committee estimated that current demand, if capacity were available, would be about 135,000 passengers per annum, growing to about 145,000 passengers per annum once the service is operational and is promoted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Committee gave careful consideration to a service to replace the Empress of Australia later this decade. A number of options had already been rejected as impractical by both the Australian National Line and the Bureau of Transport Economics, such as the jetfoil, hydrofoil, hovercraft and semi-submersible catamaran. The Committee received no further evidence to suggest a contrary view. The Committee also evaluated the two service types which the Bureau of Transport Economics used in its 1980 report. The first equated the current service and the second was a two-ship service, each ship making a return crossing every 24 hours between Burnie and Westernpoint Bay, carrying passengers and cars by day and freight by night. This service was similar to the service recommended by Commissioner Nimmo in 1976. The Bureau of Transport Economics found the first service to be uneconomic. That is supported by the losses which the Australian National Lines has incurred in operating the Empress of Australia in recent years. However, the Bureau of Transport Economics found that some of the options of the second service would be economic. The Committee scrutinised the factors and assumptions used by the Bureau of Transport Economics in formulating its econometric model and concluded that the extent--
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="3V4" speaker="Senator Chipp">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="3V4">
          Senator Chipp
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —There is that word again.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="0P7">
         Senator PETER RAE
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I will try it again in a minute.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="7V4" speaker="Senator Georges">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="7V4">
          Senator Georges
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Why don't you incorporate your speech and be done with it?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="0P7">
         Senator PETER RAE
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I have only a couple of pages to go. The Committee scrutinised the factors and assumptions used by the Bureau of Transport Economics in formulating its econometric model and concluded that the extent to which they had to be qualified rendered the results unreliable. There was sufficient evidence to suggest that the second Bureau of Transport Economics service may be neither economic nor practical. After close questioning of representatives of both the Bureau of Transport Economics and the Australian National Line, the Committee concluded that limitations in the terms of reference given to the Bureau of Transport Economics, the truncated duration of its inquiry and the lack of sufficient Australian National Line input contributed to the shortcomings in the Bureau of Transport Economics report.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The ANL told the Committee it was looking at a ship similar in type to the Empress of Australia but with a five-fold increase in freight capacity. This would have the effect of providing enough freight capacity to meet the needs of one northern Tasmanian port while providing a similar passenger capacity to that of the present ship. The ANL considered that the total operation would be an economic proposition. Although the Committee was attracted to the combined freight and passenger concept, it believed that a much greater passenger capacity should be catered for. Rather than try to design and build one large ship, the Committee preferred to see the construction of two passenger-freight ships, one with a capacity of 450 passengers, cars and freight sailing between Melbourne and Devonport and the other with a capacity of 200 passengers, cars and freight sailing between Melbourne and Burnie.
      </para>
      <para>
       Because, in any event, between 1985 and 1990 the ANL has to replace the three Searoader freight ships which carry most of the freight between Northern Tasmania and the mainland, the Committee believes that there is logic in constructing two freight-passenger ships to meet the freight needs of the two northern Tasmanian ports, Burnie and Devonport, and to provide increased passenger capacity at the same time. A third ship at least would need to be constructed to meet the heavier freight requirements of Bell Bay which it is anticipated will maintain its position as the major freight port.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="9V4" speaker="Senator Grimes">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="9V4">
          Senator Grimes
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Hear, hear!
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="0P7">
         Senator PETER RAE
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Thank you, Senator Grimes. The Committee noted the long history of concern about transport between Tasmania and the mainland. The very first committee established by the Senate was a committee inquiring into passenger fares and transport across Bass Strait and that was in 1901. The Committee believes that a facility ought to be available for examining problems which inevitably will arise in the future. The Committee believes that the inter-State Commission, which is contained in the Inter-State Commission Act 1975, has the functions and the capacity necessary to carry out this task. This Act has not yet been proclaimed. The Committee recommends that the Interstate Committee be established and authorised to examine Tasmanian transport problems in the future.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Finally, I thank all the organisations and individuals who made a contribution to the inquiry. In particular, I thank the Tasmanian and Victorian Governments for their co-operation, and Ansett Airlines of Australia, Trans-Australia Airlines, ANL and the Commonwealth Department of Transport for supplying much additional information to the Committee, very often at short notice. I also thank my colleagues, Senator Grimes, Senator Tate, and Senator Townley, who I believe did what a number of people thought may not have been possible; that is, produced what I hope is a constructive, forward-looking report which is unanimous and which attempts to put forward a plan which can do away with subsidies and make the services suit the requirements of Victoria and Tasmania. In conclusion, I take the opportunity to thank the staff of the Senate Committee for their work in producing the report, notwithstanding some problems such as breakdowns of equipment of various sorts, including the word processor and the reproduction equipment, and a rolling strike in the office of the Government Printer. They did a very good job in getting out a report notwithstanding all those problems. I thank the Senate for the opportunity to refer in some detail to the report which I have had pleasure in placing before the Senate.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="NJ4" page="15" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen M.C.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="NJ4">
         Senator TATE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
        <time.stamp>
         (5.30)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —It gives me great pleasure to be associated with the presentation of the report of the Senate Select Committee on Passenger Fares and Services to and from Tasmania. May I emphasise firstly that the Committee was very ably chaired by Senator Peter Rae, who in this area is well informed, able and indeed indefatigable. He was very considerably helped by Senators Grimes and Townley. My part in the preparation of the report was indeed very small, but that does not preclude me from seeking to share some of the honours now that it is before the Senate.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The report deals with a most important matter. In the Australian federation Tasmania is unique. It is a State which is physically isolated from the mainland; yet it has very close social, economic, trading and commercial ties with it. Some 80,000 Tasmanians live on the mainland and wish to maintain their links with relatives and friends in Tasmania. I repeat: Our commercial and trading links are very largely with the mainland. My area of north-west Tasmania is oriented more to Melbourne than to the State capital of Hobart. But to reiterate the obvious, unless a person is one of the 111,000 sea passengers who cross to and fro between Tasmania and Melbourne every year on the Empress of Australia, to enjoy interstate travel he must take the most expensive form of transport in the Australian federation-air travel. More than a million passengers move to and fro between Tasmania and the mainland each year. When one considers that the population of Tasmania is only 400,000 or so, one is provided with some measure of the importance of this particular link. The situation is indeed unique and would allow one to mount a very sound argument for the Commonwealths voting moneys to help build an air and sea bridge between Tasmania and the mainland in the same way as it finances interstate land based links, whether by road or rail.
      </para>
      <para>
       Rather than seek to pursue that old approach, the Committee has been concerned to look for national policy frameworks which would allow to develop such appropriate services by aircraft and ships, and such transport policy, as would permit to emerge a fare structure which would require the payment, by people who wished to travel between Tasmania and the mainland, of fares that would be as modest as it would be possible to achieve.
      </para>
      <para>
       Thus, as Senator Peter Rae has pointed out, in relation to the main trunk routes, between Melbourne, Launceston and Hobart, the Committee proposes, as a preferred solution of the problem, that a regional operator based in Tasmania have the exclusive right to operate. By bringing in specialist aircraft and non-parallel scheduling and feeding efficiently into the national trunk-work on the mainland, one could provide a cheaper service-it has been estimated some 10 to 15 per cent cheaper-than is presently provided by the two major domestic airlines.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="0P7" speaker="Senator Peter Rae">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="0P7">
          Senator Peter Rae
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —On a subsidised basis.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="NJ4">
         Senator TATE
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Yes, even with the subsidy that is currently operating. With the current two-airline policy that is enshrined in legislation, and presuming that that policy is achieving overall national objectives which can lend themselves to Commonwealth support, there is an obligation on the Commonwealth-the possibility of the cheaper, more efficient regional operator solution having been debarred-to subsidise such air travel. It is only on the basis that the Commonwealth, for national reasons, is pursuing a less efficient policy in relation to Tasmanian air travel, that we say that the present 10 per cent subsidy is fair and equitable and seems to work very efficiently. But there is good reason for apprehension about the political will to sustain such subsidies. That is why the Committee has been concerned to move away from them.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That is demonstrated once again in the Committee's deliberations on a replacement for the Empress of Australia, which, I repeat, carries some 111,000 passengers each year between Melbourne and the great port of Devonport on the north-west coast of Tasmania. The Committee felt that there was good reason to suppose that there was a latent demand which was being suppressed because of an inefficient booking system and an inadequate capacity. Indeed, the Empress is at 84 per cent of its possible load factor throughout the year and at well over 95 per cent during the peak periods of travel. Also, we believe that with increased promotion sea travel would prove attractive to some 145,000 passengers travelling between Tasmania and the mainland each year.
      </para>
      <para>
       On that basis it has been suggested that to try once again to move away from subsidies which Tasmanians do not want we should construct as a replacement for the Empress of Australia two vessels, one plying between Melbourne and Devonport and carrying 450 passengers on top of an enhanced cargo freight operation-some five times greater than that operating at present-and a similar vessel carrying about 200 passengers on top of a cargo freight service operating into Burnie. These well-promoted services would run on a daily basis with a night-time crossing to and fro between Melbourne and north-west Tasmania. We can see this as an economically viable solution as the carriage of so much freight will make the ships economically viable and do away with the need for the $2.5m subsidy which is currently provided from the Commonwealth Treasury. This picks up the general theme of the Committee that, where possible, the most efficient, commercial solution will be found to be compatible with a modest structure of fares and ought to be pursued as expeditiously as possible. If some other national objective fails to commend that course to the Federal Government, then and only then should a subsidy be paid from the Commonwealth Treasury.
      </para>
      <para>
       Because of my interest in north-west Tasmania I will spend some moments on north-west air services. As to the upgrading of airports, it is the very strong recommendation of the Committee that both Devonport and Wynyard airports be upgraded to enable them to take jet services. This is not a mere unfounded assertion or claim by these regions. The Committee took pains to establish that by comparison with, for example, regional New South Wales where some eight airports are proposed to be upgraded to jet status and by looking at those airports in outback and regional Australia which already have such services, such as Mt Isa and so on, there is no doubt that the claims of Devonport and Wynyard are well-founded, each airport having well over 85,000 passenger movements a year, which is unique at such regional airports. The entrance of jet services to the north-west of Tasmania is well justified. Therefore, the upgrading of those airports, based on local ownership, is also justified. One looks forward with interest to tonight's Budget to see what appropriations will be made in that regard.
      </para>
      <para>
       The communities and the sub-regions of the north-west of Tasmania are prepared to take on local ownership, to undertake the expenditure involved and to give support through their local councils and marine boards to the management of such airports. It is up to the Commonwealth Government to complement that endeavour portrayed in those projects fostered in the north-west of Tasmania. In any such upgrading it is essential that Devonport airport terminal building be completely rebuilt at the total expense of the Commonwealth Government. No cost sharing should be undertaken. The present terminal is a disgrace. Indeed, it was a Royal Australian Air Force training shed somewhere in the Launceston area during the Second World War which was transpDevonport. We have had to put up with this very inadequate facility at the tourist gateway to Tasmania ever since. It needs to be upgraded immediately.
      </para>
      <para>
       We have been somewhat overtaken by events in the past week with Trans Australia Airlines announcing its withdrawal of Fokker Friendship services between the mainland and north-west Tasmania. The Committee took the view that unless TAA and Ansett Airlines of Australia upgraded their services they should be asked to withdraw in favour of a specialist regional operator such as that which is indeed replacing TAA, namely, East-West Airlines Ltd. There is no point lamenting the fact that TAA is going. One might express some disappointment at the manner in which it is leaving and the manner in which it dealt with some of its staff relations on the human level. Nevertheless, it is leaving. I believe that north-west Tasmania will want to make the best of the opportunity of having a specialist regional airline operating into Tasmania with appropriate aircraft, with therefore a lower flagfall because it would not be bearing national overheads, and with a real desire to promote north-west Tasmania as, as I have mentioned before, the tourist gateway to Tasmania. I do not intend to consume much more of the time of the Senate; its program is tightly organised this evening as we prepare for the presentation of the Budget. However, I wish to complete my remarks with a quotation from an editorial in the Advocate, which is Australia's leading regional daily.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="4L7" speaker="Senator McLaren">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4L7">
          Senator McLaren
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Who is the editor?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="NJ4">
         Senator TATE
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —A good friend of mine. I hope he will be a good friend after I make this quotation. Amongst other things, the editor stated:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       . . . the inquiry was carried out, and the report presented, by a non-partisan team of Tasmanian senators-four men qualified to assess and advise on Tasmania's needs. For this reason alone the Federal Government and others concerned for the transport and welfare needs of this state should not dismiss the report as just another mass of paper work, but give it their undivided attention.
      </para>
      <para>
       I hope that that exhortation is taken to heart by the Government.
      </para>
      <para>
       Debate (on motion by Senator Peter Baume) adjourned.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="17" type="Committee">
     <title>
      ESTIMATES COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="17">
      <title>
       Estimates Committee D
      </title>
      <speech electorate="NT" gov="1" nameid="8H7" page="17" party="LP" speaker="Kilgariff Sen B.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8H7">
          Senator KILGARIFF
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Northern Territory)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I table further additional information received by Estimates Committee D and seek leave for it to be incorporated in the Hansard record of the Committee's proceedings.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="17">
      <title>
       Estimates Committee G
      </title>
      <speech electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="0V4" page="17" party="LP" speaker="Bonner Sen N.T.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="0V4">
          Senator BONNER
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Queensland)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I table further additional information received by Estimates Committee G and seek leave for it to be incorporated in the Hansard record of the Committee's proceedings.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <para>
        Sitting suspended from 5.44 to 8 p.m.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="17" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      BUDGET 1981-82
     </title>
     <sso page="17">
      <title>
       Suspension of Standing Orders
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FINANCE" nameid="6D7" page="17" party="LP" speaker="Guilfoyle Sen The Hon Dame M.G.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6D7">
          Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Finance)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (8.0)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I take this opportunity to congratulate you on your election to this high office and to wish you well in the ensuing years. I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent the Minister for Finance speaking without limitation of time when moving that the Senate take note of the Budget Papers 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        Question resolved in the affirmative.
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6D7">
          Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —For the information of honourable senators I lay upon the table the following papers:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Budget Statements 1981-82
       </para>
       <para>
        Estimates of Receipts and Summary of Estimated Expenditure for the year ending 30 June 1982
       </para>
       <para>
        Civil Works Program 1981-82
       </para>
       <para>
        Government Securities on Issue at 30 June 1981
       </para>
       <para>
        Payments to or for the States, the Northern Territory and Local Government Authorities 1981-82
       </para>
       <para>
        Australia's Overseas Development Assistance Program 1981-82
       </para>
       <para>
        National Income and Expenditure 1980-81
       </para>
       <para>
        National Accounting Estimates of Receipts and Outlays of Commonwealth Government Authorities
       </para>
       <para>
        Income Tax Statistics
       </para>
       <para>
        Particulars of Proposed Expenditure for the service of the year ending 30 June 1982
       </para>
       <para>
        Particulars of Certain Proposed Expenditure in respect of the Year Ending 30 June 1982
       </para>
       <para>
        Mr President, I seek leave to move a motion.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6D7">
          Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate take note of the papers.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SG7" speaker="Senator Keeffe">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SG7">
           Senator Keeffe
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr President, I take a point of order. On every occasion since I have been a member of this place the condensed section of the Budget Papers has been available to every honourable senator. I do not propose to sit here if we are not to get a copy of it. In the past we were able to read this document while the Budget Speech was being delivered. As I said, this has never happened before. I know that party leaders have a copy of the Speech. However, we too are entitled to a copy of it. If this is another way of the Government keeping the Budget secret, it is pretty shallow.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="C67" speaker="Senator Collard">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="C67">
           Senator Collard
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Sit down.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SG7" speaker="Senator Keeffe">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SG7">
           Senator Keeffe
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —It is all right for honourable senators on the other side of the chamber because they cannot understand the Budget anyway. Mr President, we ought to be given a copy of it. I am asking that the debate be suspended until everyone has a copy.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6D7">
          Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I understand that the papers will be distributed on the commencement of my speech. The papers are ready to be put in the hands of honourable senators in the usual way.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SG7" speaker="Senator Keeffe">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SG7">
           Senator Keeffe
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr President, I again speak to the point of order. I ask you to suspend the sitting of the Senate until the Budget Papers are distributed. I ask that the Minister not be allowed to commence her speech until that is done.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I understand the papers are about to be distributed.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6D7">
          Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I would expect that the papers could now be distributed. I will then commence my speech.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SG7" speaker="Senator Keeffe">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SG7">
           Senator Keeffe
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I thank the Minister for her co-operation.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6D7">
          Senator Dame MARGARET GUILFOYLE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Tonight the Treasurer is delivering in another place his Budget Speech for 1981-82.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        It is my privilege to outline to the Senate the Budget proposals of the Government.
       </para>
       <para>
        1980-81 IN RETROSPECT
       </para>
       <para>
        1980-81 was a year of solid growth and achievement for the Australian economy.
       </para>
       <para>
        It was a year in which the benefits of this Government's economic policies not only became more apparent, but were widely enjoyed by the Australian people. Nothing illustrates this more than the fact that real wages rose by over 4 per cent in 1980-81-a gain that was shared by 140 000 extra people in employment.
       </para>
       <para>
        It was a year in which the fight against inflation was seen more clearly than ever before, not as an end in itself, but as a means of achieving greater investment, more jobs and higher living standards for all Australians.
       </para>
       <para>
        I say these things fully recognising that for those affected by the recent drought it was a year of adversity and, in many cases, real hardship.
       </para>
       <para>
        Economic success was achieved across a broad front.
       </para>
       <para>
        Production, employment, investment and consumer demand were not only stronger than a year earlier, but greater than thought likely at the time of the last Budget.
       </para>
       <para>
        Australia's international reputation as a strong, reliable country in which to invest, was further enhanced.
       </para>
       <para>
        Among the economic indicators, the area of greatest strength was undoubtedly business investment, which contributes so much to activity and employment and hence to rising living standards.
       </para>
       <para>
        Even last year's optimistic Budget forecast of strong growth in this area clearly under-estimated the upsurge then in prospect.
       </para>
       <para>
        During 1980-81, private business fixed investment grew by more than 20 per cent in real terms-the largest such growth for 30 years.
       </para>
       <para>
        There could be no clearer proof of the extent to which confidence in the economic future of this country has returned.
       </para>
       <para>
        Although the mining sector made a hefty contribution towards this investment growth, strong increases were recorded in manufacturing and other sectors.
       </para>
       <para>
        Private dwelling investment continued to grow firmly, with a real increase of about 11 per cent.
       </para>
       <para>
        There was also a strong lift in personal consumption expenditure of about 3 1/4 per cent in real terms.
       </para>
       <para>
        Over the year to June 1981, Australia's inflation rate as measured by the Consumer Price Index was 8.8 per cent-almost 2 per cent below the rate a year earlier.
       </para>
       <para>
        The outcome-again better than had been forecast in last year's Budget-was aided by a lower rate of increase in import prices flowing in part from the strong appreciation of the Australian dollar.
       </para>
       <para>
        Although the margin narrowed, Australia's inflation rate remained below the average of OECD countries.
       </para>
       <para>
        Business profits grew strongly last year but their further growth, so vital to continued investment and employment, is now being threatened by rising wage pressures.
       </para>
       <para>
        Overall, gross domestic product increased by almost 3 per cent in 1980-81, with growth of 4 per cent in the non-farm sector being offset by the fall in farm product associated with the drought.
       </para>
       <para>
        The sharp rise in non-farm activity was reflected in a strong rise in total employment, which increased by 2.6 per cent. This was enough to reduce overall unemployment to its lowest level for four years, well beyond our original expectations.
       </para>
       <para>
        This brief summary of the Australian economy over the past year presents a picture of considerable success and progress.
       </para>
       <para>
        It contrasts sharply with the general experience of other OECD countries where, in aggregate, there has been higher inflation and unemployment and slower growth.
       </para>
       <para>
        I would, however, be less than frank if I did not also point to some areas of concern to the Government and to certain challenges which, if not effectively tackled by this Budget and policies more generally, could undermine the progress and success to which I have referred.
       </para>
       <para>
        If a response to those challenges is put off to another day, they will be infinitely harder to resolve, the process of resolution more painful and the damage to our economic recovery all the greater.
       </para>
       <para>
        In his Budget Speech a year ago, the Treasurer spoke of the threat then posed by excessive wage demands and industrial disputes.
       </para>
       <para>
        Regrettably, the past year-and particularly the past few months-has seen the pressure for higher wages intensify.
       </para>
       <para>
        If unchecked, this will not only lead to higher inflation but reverse the falling trend in unemployment and put at risk both invesment and employment growth.
       </para>
       <para>
        It would be grossly unfair if excessive wage demands from those in employment were now to damage the prospects for further job creation just when we have begun to see real gains being made in reducing unemployment.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is important that the abandonment of the wage indexation principles not be seen as having left a vacuum in this area.
       </para>
       <para>
        In recent days Commonwealth and State Governments, as well as the ACTU and National Employers, have all pointed to the continued existence of workable conciliation and arbitration processes-which in some respects are more flexible than the indexation arrangements-to settle wage claims.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is essential that all parties co-operate to make these processes work effectively.
       </para>
       <para>
        Such an outcome would help to moderate excessive wage claims.
       </para>
       <para>
        INTEREST RATES
       </para>
       <para>
        No Government likes to see interest rates go up. This Government is acutely conscious of the effects of rising interest rates on all borrowers, especially home-buyers. We therefore regret the necessity for the further increases announced last week.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is important for all of us to understand why interest rates have increased and what needs to be done to reverse this trend.
       </para>
       <para>
        Interest rates have risen because the total demand for money in the community has exceeded its availability.
       </para>
       <para>
        In such circumstances interest rate rises are unavoidable unless the Government were prepared to print as much money as was demanded. This it will not do because of the inflationary consequences.
       </para>
       <para>
        It follows that if interest rates are to be brought down the growth in the total demand for money must be reduced.
       </para>
       <para>
        This demand comes from a number of sources, including businesses and prospective home- buyers.
       </para>
       <para>
        There are also demands from governments at all levels to finance their current activities and to refinance earlier deficits.
       </para>
       <para>
        In recent years government borrowing demands have been reduced, due entirely to reductions in the Commonwealth Budget deficit. However, with strong private sector demand, this fall has not been sufficient to prevent a significant increase in the total demand for funds.
       </para>
       <para>
        As a consequence, there has been upward pressure on interest rates.
       </para>
       <para>
        If this pressure is to be eased in a way that does not damage private sector activity or add to inflation-outcomes that would reduce job opportunities and retard economic growth-it is imperative that the borrowing demands of all levels of government be further reduced.
       </para>
       <para>
        The need for such action led to the Loan Council decisions in June to cut by about 4 per cent in real terms the total Commonwealth and State semi-government borrowing programs.
       </para>
       <para>
        Clearly, however, this Budget must make a further and substantial contribution towards reducing government borrowing demands if the upward pressure on interest rates is to be eased and indeed reversed. I can think of no cause more important to Australian families at present.
       </para>
       <para>
        We have therefore decided that this year we must go as far as possible towards eliminating the Commonwealth's Budget deficit.
       </para>
       <para>
        THE BUDGET OUTCOME FOR 1980-81
       </para>
       <para>
        Last year's Budget generated the first domestic surplus since 1973-74; in the outcome, both it and the overall deficit were about $400 million better than had been expected.
       </para>
       <para>
        Outlays were within 1 per cent of the Budget estimate. Receipts, however, were 2 per cent-$683 million-greater than estimated, mainly reflecting larger than expected income tax collections from both individuals and companies.
       </para>
       <para>
        Receipts from the crude oil levy were $35 million less than estimated, with the effects of industrial disputes on production from Bass Strait more than offsetting the higher import parity price from 1 January 1981.
       </para>
       <para>
        For two years in a row now, large reductions in the Commonwealth Budget deficit-$1,444 million in 1979-80 and $906 million in 1980-81-have been accompanied by strong growth in private sector economic activity.
       </para>
       <para>
        THE BUDGET STRATEGY
       </para>
       <para>
        In putting together this year's Budget the Government had to ensure that it would meet a possible resurgence of inflation head on.
       </para>
       <para>
        A less firm Budget, while easier to prepare, would carry with it a real risk of a fresh outbreak of inflation, thereby undermining the prospects for sustained economic growth in the years ahead.
       </para>
       <para>
        In particular, the uncertainty and loss of international competitiveness that would result from a new inflationary spiral would deter the production and investment essential to the creation of additional jobs and higher real incomes.
       </para>
       <para>
        We have therefore opted for a Budget which gives priority to containing and reducing inflation and sustaining private sector growth.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is a Budget which reduces the overall deficit by almost $1,000 million.
       </para>
       <para>
        This decisive move towards overall balance symbolises the Government's determination to play safe with the gains we have already made.
       </para>
       <para>
        OUTLAYS
       </para>
       <para>
        Total outlays are estimated to increase by 12.6 per cent in 1981-82, to $40,862 million. This represents an estimated increase in real terms of a little under 2 per cent.
       </para>
       <para>
        The growth in outlays in 1981-82 is affected by an additional payday for public servants and most social security benefit recipients. Adjusted for this special factor, outlays would increase by about 11 1/2 per cent in nominal terms or less than 1 per cent in real terms.
       </para>
       <para>
        Within total outlays, particular priority has been give to defence, pensions and other cash benefits and foreign aid.
       </para>
       <para>
        In total, provisions for these purposes are estimated to rise by 15.8 per cent in 1981- 82; the increase for all other purposes is 10.4 per cent.
       </para>
       <para>
        I turn now to some particular expenditure provisions; additional details are contained in the accompanying Budget documents, notably Statement No. 3. Relevant Ministers will be releasing further information as appropriate.
       </para>
       <para>
        DEFENCE
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government continues to give high priority to the strengthening of our national security.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Defence provision of $4,112 million represents an increase of 16.3 per cent in current prices or 5.3 per cent in real terms.
       </para>
       <para>
        This increase reflects the continuing implementation of the planned improvements in Australia's defence capability announced by the Prime Minister and the Minister for Defence in February 1980.
       </para>
       <para>
        The proportion of defence outlays to be spent on capital equipment is a little lower than had been planned because of contractual and other delays which have affected spending in this area, notably on the tactical fighter program.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Minister for Defence will advise the Parliament of further details later in the year.
       </para>
       <para>
        SOCIAL WELFARE
       </para>
       <para>
        Total expenditure on social security and welfare is estimated at $11,357m, an increase of 14.5 per cent. After allowing for the additional pension payday in 1981-82, the increase is about 12 per cent.
       </para>
       <para>
        This Budget provides for some new initiatives in areas of particular need whilst also demonstrating our continuing commitment in the family area.
       </para>
       <para>
        Family Allowances
       </para>
       <para>
        Prior to the last election the Government stated that any significant increase in oil revenue in 1980-81 over the Budget estimate would be returned to Australian families. In the event, receipts from this source last year were actually below the Budget estimate, as I have already indicated.
       </para>
       <para>
        Nevertheless, we have reviewed the levels of family allowances and decided to increase the rates of assistance for third and subsequent children by 50 per cent, with effect from 1 January 1982.
       </para>
       <para>
        This means that the rates for the third and fourth child will be increased from $26 a month to $39 a month. For the fifth and each subsequent child, the rate will increase from $30.35 to $45.55 a month. A family with 5 children will therefore gain by $41.20 a month.
       </para>
       <para>
        The rate for children in institutions will be increased from $21.70 a month to $39 a month.
       </para>
       <para>
        In total, some 540 000 families will benefit.
       </para>
       <para>
        These changes are estimated to cost $62m in 1981-82 and $124m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        Indexation of Pensions and Benefits
       </para>
       <para>
        Basic pension and benefit rates will continue to be adjusted in line with movements in the Consumer Price Index. In November the standard or single rate of social service pension, for example, will rise by $3.05 to $69.70 a week, while the combined married rate will increase by $5.10 to $116.20 a week.
       </para>
       <para>
        These new rates will represent increases of $5.60 and $9.40 respectively since November 1980.
       </para>
       <para>
        Supplementary Rental Assistance
       </para>
       <para>
        In recognition of the particular hardship suffered by many needy pensioners in rented accommodation, we have decided to increase and redirect the program of rental assistance to pensioners and long-term sickness beneficiaries so as to provide more support to those paying higher rents.
       </para>
       <para>
        From the first pension payday in February 1982 the maximum rate of assistance will be increased by $3 to $8 a week. At the same time the rate of rent subsidy will be reduced from $1 for each $1 of rent paid, to 50 cents for each $1 of rent in excess of $10 a week.
       </para>
       <para>
        The income test will be eased for single persons to provide a $1 for $2 rate of withdrawal in all cases.
       </para>
       <para>
        New public housing tenants will not be eligible for such assistance.
       </para>
       <para>
        Present rates and conditions for assistance will continue to apply for those current recipients who would otherwise be made worse off by these new arrangements.
       </para>
       <para>
        The changes are estimated to cost an additional $20m in 1981-82 and about $50m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        Unemployment Benefits
       </para>
       <para>
        The non-indexed rate of unemployment benefits for persons 18 years and over without dependants will be increased from $53.45 a week to $58.10 a week in November 1981.
       </para>
       <para>
        Assistance for the Handicapped
       </para>
       <para>
        This Government has provided substantial support for the mentally and physically handicapped since it came to office. The total provision of $1134m for handicapped people in 1981-82 represents an increase of $666m or 140 per cent over the comparable provision in 1975-76.
       </para>
       <para>
        New measures provided in this the International Year of Disabled Persons are:
       </para>
       <para>
        $1.5m as part of a $5m three year program to improve access and facilities in Commonwealth buildings for disabled persons;
       </para>
       <para>
        $690 000 to establish work preparation centres in Perth, Adelaide and Brisbane for mildly retarded young people;
       </para>
       <para>
        an increase from $5 to $8 a week in the incentive allowance payable to all sheltered employment allowees; and
       </para>
       <para>
        almost $1.4m to assist in the production of braille and audio books, the improvement of radio and TV services for the handicapped, and the provision of sport and recreation facilities for the disabled.
       </para>
       <para>
        Aged Persons' Accommodation and Crisis Accommodation
       </para>
       <para>
        Other welfare measures in 1981-82 include a $12m increase in expenditure on aged persons' accommodation to $58m, and the provision of $2m to commence a crisis accommodation program for families in distress.
       </para>
       <para>
        Assistance to Veterans
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget extends eligibility for repatriation benefits and service pensions and also provides for increases in a number of repatriation benefits.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Minister for Veterans' Affairs will announce details but the main points are:
       </para>
       <para>
        counselling centres for Vietnam veterans will be established in each State capital and Darwin;
       </para>
       <para>
        Australian mariners who served in a theatre of war during the Second World War will become eligible for service pensions from February 1982;
       </para>
       <para>
        for service pensioners, the amount of disability pension disregarded in the income test for pension and associated fringe benefits will be increased from 50 per cent to 60 per cent from January 1982; and
       </para>
       <para>
        the maximum rate or repatriation funeral benefit will be increased from $300 to $400.
       </para>
       <para>
        These measures are estimated to cost $6m in 1981-82 and $22m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        Assistance for Aboriginals
       </para>
       <para>
        In recognition of their special needs, this Budget provides $147m for Aboriginals, a 16 per cent increase on last year.
       </para>
       <para>
        This includes $8m as the first instalment of the Government's election commitment to provide $50m over five years for Aboriginal environmental health improvements.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Aboriginal Development Commission, which emphasises self-help for Aboriginals, will receive $47.8m in 1981-82, including a $9m addition to the Commission's accumulating capital investment fund.
       </para>
       <para>
        HEALTH
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government has already announced important changes to the funding of health services in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        Total outlays for health services in 1981-82 are estimated at $2872m.
       </para>
       <para>
        Additional payments totalling $1151m will also be made to the States and the Northern Territory as the health component of the financial assistance provided in the revised tax sharing arrangements.
       </para>
       <para>
        In all, these payments are $373m or 10.2 per cent higher than last year.
       </para>
       <para>
        Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government has decided to grant pharmaceutical manufacturers and wholesalers increases in PBS drug prices from 1 November 1981. The decision provides for an increase of 3.5 per cent on the price to chemists, plus 10 cents per benefit item.
       </para>
       <para>
        These increases are estimated to cost $9m in 1981-82 and $18m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        The decision by the Pharmaceutical Benefits Remuneration Tribunal to increase chemists' remuneration for dispensing prescriptions is estimated to add a further $33.4 million, including retrospective payments of $10.9 million, to the cost of the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        Given these cost increases the Government has decided to increase the current patient contribution by 45 cents to $3.20 for each benefit item prescribed, effective from 1 December 1981. Those presently exempt from paying contributions will remain exempt.
       </para>
       <para>
        This increase will offset the costs of the Scheme by $10 million in 1981-82 and $20 million in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        CULTURE AND RECREATION
       </para>
       <para>
        A total of $461 million has been provided for cultural and recreational activities in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        The National Broadcasting and Television Service will receive $273 million, an increase of $50 million. The Australian Broadcasting Commission will receive almost $234 million, including $12.1 million for the Commission as host broadcaster for the 1982 Commonwealth Games and $16 million to meet employer superannuation liabilities which fall on the ABC for the first time in 1981-82. An amount of $9.7 million is also provided to improve and extend the National Broadcasting and Television Service network, including facilities used for Radio Australia.
       </para>
       <para>
        Other expenditures include:
       </para>
       <para>
        $26 million to the Special Broadcasting Service for ethnic radio services and for the first full year of operations of multicultural television;
       </para>
       <para>
        $29 million for the Australia Council, including a special allocation for the Commonwealth Games Arts Festival;
       </para>
       <para>
        $25 million for the National Gallery, which is planned to open in October 1982; and
       </para>
       <para>
        $6.6 million for the development of international standard sporting facilities in co-operation with the States and the Territories.
       </para>
       <para>
        IMMIGRATION PROGRAMS
       </para>
       <para>
        Although the Assisted Migration Program is being discontinued, provision is being made for an expected migrant intake of up to 120 000 in 1981-82, compared with 111 000 last year.
       </para>
       <para>
        Funding for the programs established on the recommendations of the Galbally Committee is being maintained, pending the review during 1981-82 of programs reaching the end of the initial triennium. An amount of $31.3 million is provided to maintain the Adult Migrant Education Program at its present level.
       </para>
       <para>
        FOREIGN AID
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget provides for an increase of over $100 million or 18 per cent in foreign aid expenditure. This is estimated to raise the ration of official development assistance to GDP from 0.43 per cent in 1980-81 to 0.45 per cent in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        My colleague the Minister for Foreign Affairs will be making a full statement on this program later in the Parliament.
       </para>
       <para>
        EDUCATION
       </para>
       <para>
        Details of funding for the Commonwealth Tertiary Education and Schools Commission programs have already been announced.
       </para>
       <para>
        Total direct outlays on education are estimated to rise by 11.1 per cent in 1981-82 to $3,255 million.
       </para>
       <para>
        This provision continues the priority given to technical and further education and to vocational programs. It also includes a further $35 million under the Commonwealth's five year school to work transition program.
       </para>
       <para>
        Within the schools sector, increased priority will be given to particular areas of need, with migrant and special education receiving an additional $11 million and the country areas program an additional $1.2 million.
       </para>
       <para>
        The progressive implementation of the Government's 1980 election commitment to raise the subsidy levels applicable to non-government schools is estimated to cost almost $28 million in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        Student Assistance
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government is taking steps to adjust certain student assistance programs.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Secondary Allowances Scheme and the Adult Secondary Education Assistance Scheme will be made more accessible to refugees, migrants and other students whose special circumstances make it difficult for them to gain fully from these schemes.
       </para>
       <para>
        The allowance under the Secondary Allowances Scheme will be increased by 10 per cent from the beginning of 1982 and the income test requirements governing eligibility for tertiary and secondary allowances will be eased.
       </para>
       <para>
        EMPLOYMENT AND TRAINING PROGRAMS
       </para>
       <para>
        Expenditure on programs designed to expand the supply of skilled labour sought by industry and to assist young people in their search for employment is to be increased by 22 per cent to $203 million in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        This total includes $65 million-$24 million more than last year-to assist young unemployed people to obtain prior work experience and practical job skills or otherwise prepare them for employment.
       </para>
       <para>
        Some 100 000 apprentices, 5000 more than last year, will be assisted through the CRAFT and special apprentice training schemes in 1981-82 at a total cost of $76 million.
       </para>
       <para>
        Expenditure on school to work transition allowances will rise by $8 million to $13 million.
       </para>
       <para>
        A total of $20 million-an increase of 35 per cent-is being allocated for training in skills which are in short supply, including in the metal and electrical trades and in the construction industry.
       </para>
       <para>
        In the light of the increases in these programs, the Government has decided to terminate the Community Youth Support Scheme on 31 October 1981. This will allow available funds to be concentrated on programs more attuned to labour market conditions.
       </para>
       <para>
        ASSISTANCE TO INDUSTRY
       </para>
       <para>
        Rural Assistance
       </para>
       <para>
        Existing programs of budgetary assistance to rural industries are being maintained, at an estimated net cost of $226 million in 1981-82. This includes $19.2 million for rural research and $17.7 million for the Rural Adjustment Scheme.
       </para>
       <para>
        Export Incentives
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget includes $281 million for export expansion and export market development grants in 1981-82, an increase of $21 million which will permit a substantial reduction in the carry-over of outstanding claims.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government recently announced that grant rates under the Export Expansion Grants Scheme will be reduced by 50 per cent from 1 July 1982 and that both this Scheme and the Export Market Development Grants Scheme will be extended by one year to June 1983 pending their review by the Industries Assistance Commission.
       </para>
       <para>
        Research and Development
       </para>
       <para>
        As part of its response to the recommendations of the Committee of Inquiry into Technological Change in Australia, the Government initiated a further five year research and development program from 1 July this year.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget provides $50m for industrial research and development grants, broadly the same amount as in 1980-81.
       </para>
       <para>
        Energy Programs
       </para>
       <para>
        Energy research is to be given further impetus with a provision of $14.9m in 1981-82. Coupled with this will be an allocation of $1.6m for energy conservation and energy information programs.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget provides $2m to the Bureau of Mineral Resources for a geophysical study of the Bass Basin region. This work will complement private sector activity in the search for new hydrocarbon reserves.
       </para>
       <para>
        Other Assistance
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government will provide $129m in 1981-82 for the Petroleum Products Freight Subsidy Scheme, an increase of almost $9m over last year.
       </para>
       <para>
        Support will be provided for a further three year joint Commonwealth/Industry program for the development of the Interscan microwave landing system.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget also provides $49.8m for bounties for the textiles industry; these are being introduced as part of the revised assistance arrangements to apply to this industry from 1 January 1982.
       </para>
       <para>
        NATIONAL WATER RESOURCES PROGRAM
       </para>
       <para>
        A total of $35m has been allocated for the National Water Resources Program in 1981-82, an increase of 20 per cent on last year's allocation.
       </para>
       <para>
        TRANSPORT
       </para>
       <para>
        Air Transport
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government has decided to increase air navigation charges for domestic trunk airlines by 12.5 per cent, regional airlines by 25 per cent and the general aviation sector by 20 per cent. These increases are effective from 1 October 1981; overall, the level of cost recovery from these sectors is expected to decline slightly.
       </para>
       <para>
        To reduce the level of over-recovery of costs from international airlines, charges for that sector are to be lowered by 5 per cent with effect from 1 October 1981.
       </para>
       <para>
        These variations are expected to yield net additional recoveries of $3.5m in 1981-82 and $5.3m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        Roads
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget provides $685m for roads grants to the States and the Northern Territory in 1981-82, $57m more than last year. These grants form part of the Commonwealth's undertaking to provide a total of $3650m for roads over the five years to 1984-85.
       </para>
       <para>
        Shipping
       </para>
       <para>
        An amount of $32.7m is provided for the Tasmanian Freight Equalisation Scheme; the Government is currently reviewing this Scheme to assess its performance in relation to its intended objectives.
       </para>
       <para>
        Rail
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget includes $3m as part of a $10m program for the planning of the proposed Alice Springs to Darwin standard guage railway.
       </para>
       <para>
        HOUSING
       </para>
       <para>
        Total expenditure on housing programs is estimated to increase by 17 per cent, to $399m.
       </para>
       <para>
        Welfare Housing
       </para>
       <para>
        The Commonwealth has undertaken to provide the States and the Northern Territory with a base amount of $200m a year for welfare housing for each of the next five years.
       </para>
       <para>
        This year we are allocating $262m for welfare housing, including the transfer of $12m from the States Grants for Aboriginal Housing program.
       </para>
       <para>
        Of this total, $116m, including the whole of the $62m above the base amount, is in the form of non-repayable grants while $146m is allocated as repayable loans at the highly concessional interest rate of 4.5 per cent.
       </para>
       <para>
        Homes Savings Grants
       </para>
       <para>
        Following last year's initiative to increase substantially the maximum value limit for homes savings grants and to provide a family bonus, expenditure on this scheme is estimated to increase by over $29m to $74m in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        PAYMENTS TO THE STATES, NORTHERN TERRITORY AND LOCAL GOVERNMENT
       </para>
       <para>
        The major decisions affecting payments to the States have already been announced.
       </para>
       <para>
        Total net payments to the States, the Northern Territory and local government, including all specific purpose payments, are estimated to increase by $1059m or 8 per cent in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        STAFF CEILINGS
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government is continuing to maintain firm restraint over its own administrative costs.
       </para>
       <para>
        Provisional staff ceilings provide for a reduction of about 9000, or almost 3 per cent, in staff ceilings control during the course of 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        This is in line with the Government's decision to reduce, abolish or transfer certain Commonwealth functions and to aim for an additional 2 per cent cut in staff covered by ceilings over two years.
       </para>
       <para>
        CIVIL WORKS
       </para>
       <para>
        Public works expenditures also are being firmly restrained and the 1981-82 provision of $262m represents an increase of just over 5 per cent.
       </para>
       <para>
        This provision will allow a limited number of high priority new projects to commence, including further upgrading of airport facilities for the operation of wide-bodied domestic jet aircraft, upgrading of Adelaide Airport for international services and rebuilding and upgrading of Australia's Antarctic bases.
       </para>
       <para>
        COMMONWEALTH ENTERPRISES
       </para>
       <para>
        Australian Postal and Telecommunications Commissions
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government has decided to increase the interest rates payable on the capital advances by the Commonwealth which were taken over by the Postal and Telecommunications Commisssions on their inception in 1975. The average rates of interest on such advances will be increased from about 5.2 per cent and 6.9 per cent, respectively, to 10 per cent with effect from 1 January 1982. The resultant increase in revenue is estimated to be about $60m in 1981-82, and $120m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        In addition, the terms of the outstanding advances will be consolidated with a view to being progressively converted, over a ten-year cycle commencing in 1982-83, at the semi-government rate of interest prevailing on 1 January preceding the year of conversion.
       </para>
       <para>
        These measures will put the operations of Australia Post and Telecom on a more commercial footing.
       </para>
       <para>
        Australian Shipping Commission
       </para>
       <para>
        The Australian Shipping Commission has advised that it will make early repayment of interest bearing Budget advances totalling $30m in 1981-82 as a result of refinancing arrangements to be made on commercial considerations.
       </para>
       <para>
        RECEIPTS
       </para>
       <para>
        I turn now to the revenue proposals and estimates, details of which are presented in Statement No. 4.
       </para>
       <para>
        In line with our election undertaking, a half indexation adjustment was made to the personal income tax scale and dependant rebates with effect from 1 July 1981. That measure is estimated to cost $495m in 1981-82 and $525m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        In addition, legislation has already been passed to introduce a tax rebate for basic health insurance contributions. This measure, which will be reflected in tax refund cheques next year, is estimated to cost $600m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        This Budget also allows for a number of other recently announced taxation measures.
       </para>
       <para>
        Some of the new revenue proposals which the Treasurer will announce tonight will help to broaden the tax base and this, combined with measures in other areas, will enhance the potential for further personal income tax relief in future years.
       </para>
       <para>
        In addition to measures to contain expenditures and broaden the tax base, the Government is continuing its efforts to stamp out tax avoidance. I mention in particular the replacement of the old section 260 by the broader general anti-avoidance provisions, which have attracted wide suppport within the community.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Treasurer has also announced the Government's intention to tighten section 136, which is directed at tax avoidance in international business transactions.
       </para>
       <para>
        Sales Tax
       </para>
       <para>
        For reasons that were announced at the time, the Government decided earlier this year against a major restructuring of the tax system towards greater reliance on broadly based indirect taxes. That decision did not rule out later consideration of smaller adjustments within the present system.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is clear that there is advantage in some change in the mix of direct and indirect taxes to increase the potential for desirable reductions in direct taxes, and particularly personal income tax, as economic and budgetary conditions permit.
       </para>
       <para>
        To this end the Government has decided to increase by 2 1/2 per cent each of the existing rates of sales tax, effective in relation to goods passing the taxing point after tonight. The necessary legislation will be introduced in the House of Representatives this evening.
       </para>
       <para>
        This increase in rates is estimated to yield $314m in 1981-82 and $420m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        The legislation will also provide for the correction of a significant number of anomalies and inconsistencies in the sales tax law; the estimated net revenue gains are $107m in 1981-82 and $142m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        In addition, the Government will be bringing in legislation as soon as practicable to tax, at a rate of 2 per cent, a range of goods that are now exempt-such as clothing, footwear, drapery, soft furnishings, manchester; building materials; books, magazines and newspapers; packaging and wrapping materials; hand tools; and certain other goods but not including medicines, food or wine. To the extent that the goods in question are covered by other over-riding exemptions applicable to particular industries or organisations (including governments), they will retain their exempt status.
       </para>
       <para>
        This measure, which will have effect with respect to goods passing the taxing point on or after 1 January 1982, is estimated to raise $132m of additional revenue in 1981-82 and $330m in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        Further details will be given in the amending legislation.
       </para>
       <para>
        Excises
       </para>
       <para>
        I turn now to the question of excises.
       </para>
       <para>
        There have been no increases in the excise on refined petroleum products, beer or spirits or tobacco products for several years.
       </para>
       <para>
        There will be no increases in these excises in this Budget.
       </para>
       <para>
        Coal Export Duty
       </para>
       <para>
        At present, the coal export duty applies to exports of coking coal, at rates of either $3.50 per tonne or $1 per tonne depending on the quality of the coal and certain other features of the mining operation. There is no duty on steaming coal.
       </para>
       <para>
        The present rates are below those which applied when the Government came into office but it is no longer considered appropriate to phase out the duty, which was the intention some years ago.
       </para>
       <para>
        Rather, developments in the world market for energy resources and the consequential strengthening of export demand for steaming coal indicate that there is no longer any reason to differentiate between coking coal and steaming coal in the application of the duty.
       </para>
       <para>
        The $1 per tonne rate will therefore be extended to exports after 8 p.m. tonight of black coal not at present subject to duty.
       </para>
       <para>
        Deductions for Capital Expenditure of Mining Businesses
       </para>
       <para>
        Very generous income tax deductions are allowed for capital expenditure incurred in the development of a mining property or an oil or natural gas field. In 1976, when the mining industry was in the doldrums, deductions calculated by reference to a maximum statutory life of a mine or field of 5 years were introduced; this was increased to 6 years in the Review of Commonwealth Functions announced in April 1981.
       </para>
       <para>
        With the resources investment boom now proceeding apace, there is no longer justification for the continuation of this specially favourable tax regime for this sector of the economy. Accordingly, it has been decided to increase the maximum statutory life to 10 years.
       </para>
       <para>
        There will be no gain to revenue from this measure in 1981-82. The first full-year yield is estimated at $85m. The yield will be less than that in 1982-83, but is expected to build up gradually to $250m or more by about the mid-1980s.
       </para>
       <para>
        Depreciation Allowances on Plant used to
       </para>
       <para>
        produce Basic Iron and Steel
       </para>
       <para>
        In the light of the far reaching importance of the iron and steel industry in the Australian economy, the Government has decided to allow accelerated write-off for income tax purposes of capital expenditure on plant and equipment used exclusively to produce basic iron and steel.
       </para>
       <para>
        Eligible plant ordered under a contract entered into after today will be depreciable at a special rate of 20 per cent per annum where the current schedule life for taxation purposes is 5 years or more, and at 33 1/3 per cent where it is less than 5 years.
       </para>
       <para>
        These new provisions will apply until 1991. Full details will be provided with the legislation.
       </para>
       <para>
        Industry Assistance-IAC Reference
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government has decided to ask the Industries Assistance Commission to report on certain budgetary forms of assistance currently provided to industry and on possible changes or redirections which would be more cost-effective.
       </para>
       <para>
        At present, industry benefits from a wide range of measures-from direct grants and subsidies to taxation measures-which have significant budgetary implications.
       </para>
       <para>
        Consistent with its overall policy of fiscal restraint, and its desire to encourage the development of more efficient and internationally competitive industries, the Government wishes to ensure the maximum cost-effectiveness of these measures.
       </para>
       <para>
        Details of the reference will be announced shortly.
       </para>
       <para>
        Stamp Duties in the Australian Capital
       </para>
       <para>
        Territory
       </para>
       <para>
        At present, stamp duties in the Australian Capital Territory apply to a narrower range of instruments and transactions than those in the States. Moreover, most of the rates applying in the Territory have not been altered since they were introduced in 1than those in the States. Accordingly, we have decided to bring the range and levels of Australian Capital Territory stamp duties more into line with those of the States.
       </para>
       <para>
        The changes are estimated to yield $5 million in 1981-82 and $6 million in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        Departure Tax and Passport Fees
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government has decided to increase the rate of departure tax from $10 to $20 and to lower the taxable age from 18 years to 12 years. These changes will take effect from 1 October 1981 and are estimated to yield $15 million in 1981-82 and $20 million in a full year.
       </para>
       <para>
        Fees for passports are to rise by $5 to $30 with effect from tomorrow.
       </para>
       <para>
        Commercial Radio and Television Station Licence Fees
       </para>
       <para>
        A new structure for fees payable by commercial radio and television station licensees is to be introduced. This will raise revenue from this source to an estimated $31.5 million in 1981-82. The Minister for Communications will announce the details.
       </para>
       <para>
        Zone Allowance
       </para>
       <para>
        The Public Inquiry into Income Tax Zone Allowances, announced in the 1980-81 Budget Speech, has now reported and the Treasurer will be tabling the report tonight.
       </para>
       <para>
        In the main report, the Inquiry suggested that additional assistance be directed to taxpayers with families and to those living in especially isolated areas, and that certain other changes be made to the system.
       </para>
       <para>
        The recommendations of the main report have largely been accepted by the Government; the changes are to take effect from 1 November 1981.
       </para>
       <para>
        The full-year revenue cost is estimated at $10 million.
       </para>
       <para>
        Friendly Society Dispensaries
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government has decided to change the basis on which dispensaries conducted by friendly societies are subject to tax.
       </para>
       <para>
        Beginning with income derived in the 1982-83 income year, dispensaries will be taxed like other non-profit companies, at normal company rates on a net profits basis, inclusive of investment income but exclusive of profits arising from transactions with members. The revenue consequences of the change will be small.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Small Investor
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government attaches great importance to the part played in our economy by small investors; in this connection, we have been examining the present income tax treatment of persons with modest shareholdings.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Committee of Inquiry into the Australian Financial System is, however, expected to report soon in some depth on this matter, and we have therefore decided to defer any decisions until we have studied relevant sections of the Committee's Report.
       </para>
       <para>
        BUDGET OVERVIEW
       </para>
       <para>
        Total outlays in 1981-82 are estimated to increase by 12.6 per cent to $40,862 million.
       </para>
       <para>
        Total receipts, after allowance for the measures I have just outlined, are estimated to increase by 15.8 per cent to $40,716 million.
       </para>
       <para>
        The overall Budget deficit is therefore estimated at $146 million, a reduction of $981 million on the outcome for 1980-81. On present estimates the deficit expressed as a proportion of GDP will be a mere 0.1 per cent in 1981-82, compared with a peak of 4.9 per cent in 1975-76.
       </para>
       <para>
        After allowance for transactions abroad, there will be an estimated Budget domestic surplus of $1,542 million.
       </para>
       <para>
        ECONOMIC OUTLOOK
       </para>
       <para>
        As the figures I have just quoted show, this Budget represents a decisive response, in the area of fiscal policy, to mounting wage and cost pressures.
       </para>
       <para>
        By restraining the growth in total outlays the Budget will curb public sector demands on real resources at a time when those resources are being keenly sought by expanding businesses in the private sector.
       </para>
       <para>
        It will also significantly reduce the total public sector requirement for loanable funds in 1981-82 at a time when the corporate sector is likely to be seeking substantially larger borrowings to help finance its investment program.
       </para>
       <para>
        This will help to ease the pressures which, otherwise, that increase in private borrowings would produce.
       </para>
       <para>
        For a variety of reasons monetary conditions last year were more accommodating than had been intended; one illustration of this is that M3 increased by 12.7 per cent during the course of 1980-81 compared with the Budget projection of about 9 to 11 per cent.
       </para>
       <para>
        While there are many unpredictable influences on the money supply-including external developments in particular-it is fundamental to winding back inflation that growth in the monetary aggregates also be wound back.
       </para>
       <para>
        In particular, we are determined not to allow the money supply to expand so as to accommodate a new round of excessive wage increases.
       </para>
       <para>
        In these circumstances, it is clearly desirable that the rate of growth of the money supply be reduced.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government will therefore be seeking to restrain growth in the monetary aggregates to a degree consistent with growth in M3 of 10 to 11 per cent over the course of 1981-82. The sharply reduced Commonwealth Budget deficit will facilitate this task but an appropriate balance of other domestic and external policies will also be required.
       </para>
       <para>
        The increases in tap stock yield announced after last week's Loan Council meeting, taken together with this Budget, will make a major contribution towards reducing pressures on interest rates, settling capital markets and restraining monetary growth.
       </para>
       <para>
        As in recent years, arrangements will be made for the forthcoming wheat harvest to be financed in a manner consistent with monetary objectives.
       </para>
       <para>
        This tightening of fiscal and monetary policies is designed to prevent an acceleration in the underlying rate of inflation in 1981-82. Avoiding that acceleration is essential to restoring the conditions for a downward movement in 1982-83 and later years.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is to be hoped that current developments in the wages area will lead to more flexible and more orderly wage determination processes which pay proper regard to the economy's capacity to bear wage increases. I have already referred to the responsibilities on all parties in this regard.
       </para>
       <para>
        Given developments to date, however, it appears that average weekly earnings in 1981-82 could rise by about 13 1/2 per cent. This would be much the same as in 1980-81, when the rise in earnings was enlarged by the flow through of the so-called 'work value' round of wage increases which began in 1978.
       </para>
       <para>
        On that basis, the forecast rise in the Consumer Price Index in 1981-82 as a whole is about 10 3/4 per cent.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leaving aside the effects of the revenue measures mentioned in the Budget and the previously announced changes in health care arrangements, the rise would be a little under 9 1/2 per cent-an underlying rate of inflation much the same as that recorded in 1980-81.
       </para>
       <para>
        The tighter policy framework which is now essential for containing inflationary pressures does of course carry some implications in the short-term for activity and employment. Nevertheless, the non-farm sector of the economy should continue to grow strongly in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        Business fixed investment, in particular, seems certain to grow rapidly again this year. The rate of that expansion-especially in the building and construction sector-will depend importantly on the availability of materials and skilled labour, including the extent to which supplies of both can be augmented from overseas.
       </para>
       <para>
        Given continued strong growth in real household incomes, personal consumption expenditure could rise a little faster in 1981-82-perhaps by around 3 1/2 per cent.
       </para>
       <para>
        Private dwelling investment, however, is likely to decline somewhat in 1981-82 after rapid increases in each of the past two years. This will in part reflect a reduction in investment and speculative activity.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government continues to attach a high priority to maintaining a steady flow of private housing finance. The availability of such finance will be affected, of course, by the relative competitiveness of interest rates offered and hence the rates charged by housing finance institutions. As this Budget demonstrates, the Government has made major efforts to reduce public sector pressures on capital markets in the interests of limiting the competitive pressures on housing finance and interest rates.
       </para>
       <para>
        On present indications gross non-farm product could grow by between 3 and 3 1/2 per cent this year-below the 4 per cent rate estimated for 1980-81, but higher than the average rate of about 2 1/2 per cent in the second half of the 1970s.
       </para>
       <para>
        With farm production expected to recover in 1981-82, gross domestic product could rise by more than 3 1/2 per cent this year, compared with about 3 per cent last year.
       </para>
       <para>
        This outlook is considered to be consistent with employment growth of about 2 per cent in 1981-82. This would be below the increases of about 2 1/2 per cent recorded in each of the past two years but would still represent strong growth in employment, particularly by standards in other industrialised economies today.
       </para>
       <para>
        A further strong increase in imports is likely in 1981-82 but any recovery in the level of exports will be limited by the continued sluggishness in word trade-a fact which underlines the paramount need for Australia not to throw away the international competitiveness so hard won over recent years.
       </para>
       <para>
        Taken together with the prospect for invisibles, this means that the current account deficit may widen further in 1981-82 to around 4 1/2 per cent of GDP.
       </para>
       <para>
        Though the outlook for the balance of payments is as always subject to many uncertainties, it seems reasonable to expect this current account deficit to be covered by private capital inflow-provided that, as we are determined they shall be, wage demands and inflation are successfully contained. In those circumstances a surplus on private sector foreign exchange transactions of a similar order of magnitude to the $2,800m recorded last year could occur.
       </para>
       <para>
        CONCLUSION
       </para>
       <para>
        It is vital to the nation's interests that there be no acceleration in the rate of inflation in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        Such an outcome would have most adverse consequences for confidence-both here and abroad-in Australia's future and for the competitiveness of our industries.
       </para>
       <para>
        This is especially so given that most of the major industrialised countries, led by the United States, are now bent on firm anti-inflation policies.
       </para>
       <para>
        Australia has been doing better than many of these countries in containing inflationary pressures in recent years. Our aim is to keep it that way.
       </para>
       <para>
        This Budget is an essential part of the Government's strategy for containing wage and price inflation. It will also help in a major way to ease pressures on interest rates.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget is being supported-and will continue to be supported-by equally decisive action in monetary and other policy areas.
       </para>
       <para>
        Such action is necessary if we are not only to preserve the hard won gains of the past but also if we are to exploit the potential for even greater gains in the years ahead from the large investments now under way, particularly in resource projects.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget will also help to maintain further solid growth in private sector activity and to provide more jobs for Australians.
       </para>
       <para>
        I commend the Budget to the Senate.
       </para>
       <para>
        Debate (on motion by Senator Grimes) adjourned.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </sso>
    </debate>
    <debate page="27" type="Ministerial Statement">
     <title>
      SOCIAL SECURITY PROGRAMS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="27">
      <title>
       Ministerial Statement
      </title>
      <speech electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="SOCIAL SECURITY" nameid="EF4" page="27" party="LP" speaker="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="EF4">
          Senator CHANEY
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Social Security)
         </role>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-The Treasurer (Mr Howard) in his Budget Speech mentioned several changes in the social security area that will result from the 1981-82 Budget. I should now like to elaborate a little on what he has said and provide the Senate with some additional information. The Government has allocated $9865m in the Budget to pensions, benefits and other welfare payments and services provided through the Department of Social Security. This is $1265m more than was spent in 1980-81, representing an increase of 14.7 per cent. The main reason for this rise, apart from increases in the numbers of pensioners and beneficiaries, is the automatic indexation of the major pensions and benefits, introduced by the Government in 1976, to maintain the base rates of these payments. The annual cost of pension indexation is estimated to be $716m for increases that will be payable from November 1981 and May 1982 and the Budget allocation includes a sum of $281m to provide for these rises during the remainder of the 1981-82 financial year.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        These figures illustrate not only the cost but also the degree of the Government's commitment to its policy of protecting basic pensions against inflation. The Government regards automatic rises in the basic rate of pensions and benefits in line with consumer price index increases as a crucial element in ensuring social justice for people whose major or only source of income support is their pension. Since coming into office in 1975 the Government's application of its indexation policy has meant that the standard rate of pension has risen by $27.90, or over 70 per cent, in line with consumer price index movements. Sickness benefits for people 18 years and over and unemployment benefits for those with dependants have been adjusted in the same way. In the same period the upper limits at which people can receive some pension payment have risen by $55.80 to $153.30 a week for a single person and by $93.20 to $256.70 a week for a married couple.
       </para>
       <para>
        Under the pension indexation policy, the basic rate of social security pensions and benefits will rise by $3.05 a week for a single person and by $5.10 a week for a married couple from November. Some 1.9 million pensioners and beneficiaries will receive the increased payments. The new rates will be in line with the increase of 4.6 per cent in the consumer price index between the December quarter 1980 and the June quarter 1981. The standard rate of single pension or benefit will be $69.70 a week and the rate for a married couple will be $116.20 a week. In the case of age, invalid, wives' and widows' pensions and supporting parents benefits the new rates will operate from the first pay-day in November, that is, Thursday, 5 November. In the case of unemployment, sickness and special benefits the first payment of the new rates will be made on the individual beneficiaries first payday after 1 November 1981.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government has also decided to increase the rate of unemployment benefit paid to people aged 18 years and over who have no dependants. This rate will rise by $4.65 to $58.10 a week from the first benefits pay-day in November. In addition to the increased amounts necessary to cover rises in the numbers of pensioners and beneficiaries and the indexation commitment, the Budget allocations for the Department of Social Security include $244m for an extra pension pay-day this year. There will be 27 instead of the usual 26 pension pay-days in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        The other main elements in the Budget allocations to the Department of Social Security are to cover new government initiatives to assist large families by increasing family allowance rates for third and subsequent children, to increase and redirect supplementary assistance provisions towards those pensioners who are paying higher rents, and to increase the allocations to assist handicapped and aged people and for children's services. In the context of its commitment to the welfare of Australian families, the Government has decided to increase substantially assistance to families, with three or more children. In doing this, it is recognising the special needs of large families.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government is committed to enhancing the position of all families. Australian families bringing up children are perhaps the greatest beneficiaries of sound, responsible economic management. Such management requires continued restraint on outlays so that taxes and inflation can be kept as low as possible. Within this context, the Government decided this year to pay particular attention to larger families. Such families have been identified by many groups, including the Commission of Inquiry into Poverty, as being particularly vulnerable to economic hardship. Wage determination no longer involves consideration of the needs of families and wages are therefore less likely to cover the needs of large families than small families. From January 1982, the rates of family allowance for third and subsequent children will be increased by 50 per cent.
       </para>
       <para>
        I seek leave to incorporate in Hansard a table setting out the new rates of family allowance and the increases in monthly payments.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <para>
        The document read as follows-
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
        Family allowances (per child)
       </para>
       <para>
        Family allowances (per family)
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
        Number of children
       </para>
       <para>
        Current rate New rate Increase Current rate New rate Increase
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
        $ a month $ a month $ a month $ a month $ a month $ a month Children in Families-
       </para>
       <para>
        1  15.20 15.20 . . 15.20 15.20 . .  2  21.70 21.70 . . 36.90 36.90 . .  3 26.00 39.00 13.00 62.90 75.90 13.00  4  26.00 39.00 13.00 88.90 114.90 26.00 5 30.35 45.55 15.20 119.25 160.45 41.20  6  30.35 45.55 15.20 149.60 206.00 56.40  7 30.35 45.55 15.20 179.95 251.55 71.60  Each additional child  30.35 45.55 15.20 +30.35 +45.55 +15.20
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
        Children in Institutions-
       </para>
       <para>
        Each child  21.70 39.00 17.30 n.a. n.a. n.a.
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="EF4">
          Senator CHANEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The payment in respect of the 10,000 children being cared for in institutions will be increased from $21.70 to $39.00 a month. In total, some 540,000 families will benefit by these new arrangements. The cost of this initiative in the current financial year will be $62m, representing $124m in a full year. These new arrangements build upon our past initiatives to direct assistance to people bringing up children.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Last year the Government substantially increased assistance for children of pensioners and beneficiaries. Additional pension/benefit was increased by 33 per cent and mother's/guardian's allowance was also increased. In addition, the handicapped child's allowance and double orphan's pension were increased. Over the past five years the Government has also been very mindful of the difficulties facing single income families. As a result, the Government has regularly increased both the dependent spouse and sole parent tax rebates. These have been increased again in 1981-82, the dependent spouse rebate from $800 to $830 and the sole parent rebate from $559 to $580.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government has given particular attention in this Budget to helping other groups in special need and in this context has decided to change, from February 1982, the system of supplementary assistance or allowance payable to pensioners, including supporting parent beneficiaries, and sickness beneficiaries, who pay rent. The changes to be made will direct most assistance to those paying higher rents in the private rental market, will provide a higher maximum rate of assistance and will introduce a more gradual income test.
       </para>
       <para>
        The maximum rate of rental assistance will rise by $3 to $8 a week and, to ensure that assistance is concentrated on those pensioners and beneficiaries who have to pay higher rents, it will be paid only for rents in excess of $10 a week at the rate of 50 cents for each $1 of rent above this amount up to a maximum rate of $8 at rents of $26 or more. The income test for rental assistance will be changed so that the amount received will be reduced by a withdrawal rate of 50 per cent of the pensioner's assessable income. Tenants of State or Territory housing authorities will not be eligible for assistance under the new provisions because they are already, in effect, receiving an element of government subsidy.
       </para>
       <para>
        These new provisions, which will ensure that in future more assistance will be available to those pensioners and beneficiaries paying higher amounts of rent, will not operate to the disadvantage of any existing pensioners and beneficiaries. In cases where people would be made worse off by the changes they will continue to receive assistance on the basis of current rates and conditions. The related income-test-free incentive allowance for all people who receive a sheltered employment allowance will also be increased to $8 a week.
       </para>
       <para>
        Other means by which the concentration of assistance to those most in need will be pursued include: Strengthening the provisions in the Social Services Act against schemes contrived, through artificial reductions in income, to qualify people for pensions and pensioner concessions they do not really need; the development of a crisis accommodation program with special emphasis on the needs of families; and new arrangements about the circumstances in which people caring for refugee children may be eligible to receive an orphans pension.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government is concerned that, in the welfare area as well as in taxation, income rigging practices are circumventing the intent of the laws and throwing undue burdens on taxpayers generally. In turn such practices make it more difficult to help genuinely needy people. The Social Services Act already has provisions aimed at preventing people who are well able to maintain themselves from deliberately arranging their affairs so that they become eligible for higher rates of pension. These provisions, like the pension income test, are an essential part of the mechanisms for ensuring that available assistance is focused on those who are least protected and that the already large demands made by the welfare system on taxpayers are not further increased.
       </para>
       <para>
        It has become evident that there is a growing practice of avoiding income for pension purposes, or even more commonly for pensioner fringe benefits. There is no essential difference, so far as the general community effect is concerned, between this and tax avoidance. It is, quite simply, the welfare face of the income rigging coin. We shall therefore be moving during the Budget session of Parliament to tighten up the relevant legislation so as to prevent income avoidance for pension purposes by such devices as keeping large sums of capital in non-interest bearing accounts or by participation in other income avoidance schemes that are being promoted within the community. For example, there are schemes which produce no 'income' to pensioners but enable them to withdraw capital equal to the amount of income that would be payable under a normal investment arrangement. In other words, income is withdrawn in the guise of capital. The new provisions will not operate to penalise people if they liquidate income-producing assets for reasonable purposes, such as the purchase of a home, a car, or a holiday. Similarly, they will not operate to prevent people from keeping reasonable amounts of money in non-interest bearing current accounts.
       </para>
       <para>
        In the area of crisis accommodation, my colleague, the Minister for Housing and Construction (Mr McVeigh) and I will be taking up with the States the development of a special program of crisis accommodation for families for which $2m has been allocated by the Commonwealth in 1981-82. This will be in addition to the $6.3m allocated for the Homeless Persons Assistance Program which my Department administers.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Social Services Act will be amended during the year to bring certain refugee children within the definition of a 'double orphan'. At present, a person who has the care of a child both of whose parents are dead, or when one parent is dead and the whereabouts of the other is unknown, is entitled to a double orphan's pension of $55.70 a month. In the case of a refugee child, it is often a question of not knowing whether the parents are alive or dead or not knowing where they are. In some cases the parents are known to be overseas, but the parent and the child cannot be reunited and the parent cannot provide economic support. The circumstances of these children are similar to those of 'double orphans' so the Government proposes to pay a double orphan's pension to people who are caring for refugee children whose parents are not in Australia or whose whereabouts are unknown.
       </para>
       <para>
        To correct anomalies in the provisions governing eligibility for some pensions and benefits the Government has decided to amend the Social Services Act in relation to the granting of a wife's pension and the payment of unemployment benefit to the spouses of certain people. Recent legal advice to the Government has disclosed a weakness in the operation of the Social Services Act in relation to the administration of wives' pensions. This means that these pensions may currently be granted to women resident overseas even if they have never lived in Australia, while other pensions require the applicant to be resident in Australia. The proposed amendment will ensure uniformity of treatment for applicants for all types of pensions by bringing wives' pensions into line with the broad policy that if an Australian pension is to be payable abroad it must be in force when the pensioner leaves Australia.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is also proposed to amend the Act to prevent payment of unemployment benefit to the spouse of a person engaged in industrial action or the spouse of a person who in certain circumstances has been refused unemployment benefit, or has had the benefit cancelled or postponed. An example would be where a person's unemployment benefit is cancelled because an offer of a job has been refused without good reason. People whose benefit is refused, cancelled or postponed in these circumstances will also be ineligible for special benefit, although their spouses may qualify for such a payment in cases where extreme hardship would otherwise result.
       </para>
       <para>
        With the aim of providing a better service to clients in remote areas, my Department is to experiment with the use of paid agents as a point of contact for the receipt of pensions and benefits and for obtaining information about social security matters. In 1981-82 a pilot program, involving the appointment of 10 paid agents, will be conducted at a cost of $27,000. While the Department has undertaken in recent years an extensive decentralisation program involving the opening of many more local Social Security offices, there are still many remote areas where it is not practical for an office to be established. It is expected that the paid agents experiment will be of particular benefit to people in such areas, including remote Aboriginal communities.
       </para>
       <para>
        In this, the International Year of Disabled Persons, the Government has further consolidated and developed its support for programs to assist mentally and physically disabled people. Both the Handicapped Persons Assistance Scheme and the Commonwealth Rehabilitation Service administered by my Department have received increased allocations for the current financial year of $57.33m and $28.65m respectively.
       </para>
       <para>
        We have decided to expand further the successful work preparation program for training mildly intellectually retarded young people. The success of this program is illustrated by the fact that during 1979-80 the Granville Centre in Sydney placed some 75 per cent of its clients in gainful employment, and follow-up studies show that this high rate of employment is maintained. The Government has decided, in addition to the two new centres currently being established in Sydney and Melbourne, to establish a further three new work preparation centres, one each in Brisbane, Adelaide and Perth. A further $300,000 will be provided to upgrade the quality and effectiveness of existing services for the handicapped.
       </para>
       <para>
        In 1981-82 $300,000 will be provided for a new permanent scheme of assistance for the production and publication of braille and audio books for the print-handicapped. This is the first time that assistance in this area has been extended beyond braille. Taxation deductions will be provided for gifts made in 1981-82 to the Commonwealth and State committees for the International Year of Disabled Persons.
       </para>
       <para>
        We have also, as I have mentioned, raised the incentive allowance for those in sheltered employment. These measures are only a limited part of the Commonwealth's recognition of the needs of the disabled, which are regarded as having special significance in this international year. In other subsidy programs through which the Government directs assistance to groups with particular needs, allocations have been increased to $58m for aged and disabled persons accommodation and $80.1m for children's services, including pre-schools.
       </para>
       <para>
        In conclusion I would like to re-emphasise that the Government's attitude to the social security area in this Budget has been to maintain a steady course, introducing where possible worthwhile increases in provisions for those whose circumstances are such as to justify a special focus of assistance. Our approach reflects our concern to assist those in greatest need, against a background of overall expenditure restraint, and is the approach most likely to contribute to the overall welfare of all Australians.
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="9V4" page="31" party="ALP" speaker="Grimes Sen D.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="9V4">
          Senator GRIMES
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (9.15)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         - by leave-I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate take note of the statement.
       </para>
       <para>
        I do so, as I have for the past few years, to correct some of the imbalances in the statement of the Minister for Social Security (Senator Chaney), imbalances which result from its carefully selective nature. That is a practice which I suppose is understandable but one that is therefore also in need of balancing. It is worth while pointing out that initially the Minister correctly told the Senate that the main reason, almost the entire reason, for the increase in social security expenditure in the coming year is the automatic indexation of pensions and benefits-in cases in which they are in fact indexed. That action merely keeps them roughly in line with the level of inflation and with changes in the consumer price index, but extends no real benefit to such pensioners or beneficiaries. The second main reason is the increase that will occur next year in the number of pensioners and beneficiaries.
       </para>
       <para>
        I take up the point made by the Minister that the Government has introduced worth while increases in the provision for those whose circumstances are such as to justify a special focus of assistance. It is beholden upon me, as spokesman for the Opposition, to point out those areas which the Government did not consider worthy of a special focus of assistance and to discuss just what has happened in those areas. The first and most obvious is the area of family allowances, which are to be raised for families with three or more children-in other words, for the third, fourth and fifth child and so on. The 50 per cent increase in the benefit in respect of even those children will not make up for the increase in the level of inflation which has been experienced since 1976, when these allowances were introduced. Even these families, which certainly need assistance, will not receive a family allowance at the same real level as those which were introduced with such fanfare in this Parliament in 1976.
       </para>
       <para>
        Those who will benefit constitute only 26.4 per cent of all families with children. It is important to point out that they are not necessarily the poorest families in the community. Some one and a half million families or 73.6 per cent of all families with children, will receive no benefit at all from the proposed increase, and families on low incomes will be forced further below the poverty line. Pensioners, and families with an unemployed breadwinner and children, are all at the moment below the poverty line. Only 21 per cent of this group-those with more than two children-will obtain any benefit from this Budget. Some 163,000 or 79 per cent, of unemployed pensioner families will receive nothing.
       </para>
       <para>
        If family allowances had been indexed since their introduction, a family with one child would now be receiving an extra $9.30 per month, a family with two children an extra $22.37 a month, a family with three children an extra $25.07 a month, a family with four children an extra $27.77 a month, and a family with five children an extra $32.82 a month. If family allowances had not been allowed to erode in value the Government would be spending another $280m this year instead of the $124m additional that is proposed. When family allowances were introduced we were told that they represented the greatest reform in social security that had been seen in this country. However, until the present moment they have not since been increased. Their value has eroded and that situation will continue.
       </para>
       <para>
        Families on pensions and unemployment benefits and who are at the moment below the poverty line will remain below it and in most cases will go further and further below it. The proposed benefits will not go to the majority of families. They will go to large families, who badly need them of course, but not to small families-and the vast majority of poor families in this country have in fact one or two children. As a result of a scatter gun approach they will go across the board to the third, fourth and fifth children. Although we do not deny the need of those families there is a great group in this country which is in very difficult circumstances and is worthy of a special focus of assistance on the part of the Minister and of those government supporters who claim continually that they are concerned about the welfare of families in this country.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is worth while pointing out that the adjustment that is to be made to unemployment benefits for those who have no dependents is far less than is reasonable, when one considers that other pensions and benefits have been indexed. It is even more worth while pointing out that the unemployment benefit for those who under 18 years of age remains at $36, which is the same as it was in 1975. Those who have to leave high unemployment rural areas to seek work in the city will find their benefit eroded further and further. This will add more and more to the problem of homeless and poor youth in this community that has faced us in recent years.
       </para>
       <para>
        A particularly sad observation is the Minister's statement that the legislation is to be changed to prevent the spouses of those who are taking industrial action, or who for various reasons have been refused unemployment benefits, from receiving unemployment benefits even though at present they are eligible since they were in the work force and have qualified in the past.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="3V4" speaker="Senator Chipp">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="3V4">
           Senator Chipp
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Did you notice that that part was omitted from the Budget Speech?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="9V4">
          Senator GRIMES
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It was omitted from the Budget Speech but was included in Senator Chaney's statement. The Minister said in his statement that, in fact, these people will get special benefit in cases of dire need. Special benefit is available at the moment only to people in dire need. Heaven knows what the Minister means when he adds that in this statement. We do not know what is meant by the Minister in this statement by extreme hardship when, in fact, under the present circumstances special benefits are available only to people who, by anybody's description, could only be considered to be in extreme hardship.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The social services legislation of this country is designed and meant to assist those in need. This is using the social services legislation for industrial relations purposes. It is a misuse of the legislation. It is a further demonstration of the absolute absence of a sensible industrial relations policy by the present Government. To use this legislation in this way, to penalise the wives and children of people involved in industrial action or people who have been refused benefit under the extremely loose provisions of the Act because they have been unable to get a job is an absolute disgrace. It is no wonder that the Treasurer, Mr Howard, omitted to mention this at all in his Budget Speech but left it to the Minister for Social Security to sneak it in on page 11 of a statement made in this place. It is a disgrace and it is a further demonstration of the need for the Government to go away, really learn what is happening in the community, do something about industrial relations and stop misusing the social services legislation which is, in fact, designed to help people.
       </para>
       <para>
        In the area of aged persons housing we have a problem which has been recurring ever since this Government came to power. The Government promised that $225m was to be spent in a three-year housing program for the aged. This program, in fact, is $110m less in real terms than its predecessor which began as a three-year program and tapered off to be a five-year program with no additional money being spent. Last year $45.8m was spent, nearly $7m less than the allocation. This year $58m is allocated and even if it is spent it leaves another $120m to be spent in the last year of the program. As the Government has never spent more than $60m in a year in the time that it has been in power I suggest that this is an impossible target. It is a false target, as has been demonstrated in recent years. It is misleading those people and those members of organisations who are striving to assist with a very severe problem, a problem of accommodation for aged and disabled people in this community.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget comes down every year and the Opposition and others of course get very little chance to study the whole areas that are of concern to us. I have touched on only a couple of the areas mentioned in the statement of the Minister for Social Security but even those areas demonstrate that the Government's avowed aim of assisting families is nonsense when one looks at the facts and figures in the Budget. The Government's promise made during the last election campaign that it would protect not only families but particularly low income families and those in greatest need is absolute nonsense when one looks at the increases in family allowances, at the way in which the young unemployed are treated and at the way in which the unemployed with dependents are treated in this Budget.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Budget is dishonest in the one example to which I have drawn attention tonight when it claims that the Government is to maintain a high level of spending for aged accommodation, a claim it has made ever since it came into power. Outside the social security area, the increases in the cost of pharmaceuticals and the increases in the cost of health care for those people who fall just outside the disadvantaged status will mean that a vast number of people will be further disadvantaged, apart from those who do not receive their fair share of this country's wealth in this Budget. The statement again demonstrates how false and how callous are those people who wander around mouthing that they are concerned for the poor, the disadvantaged, the families, the children and the unemployed in this country. I dare say that as we study the documents further similar dishonest and misleading statements will be found. I seek leave to continue my remarks later.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leave granted; debate adjourned.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="33" type="Ministerial Statement">
     <title>
      VETERANS' AFFAIRS: BUDGET MATTERS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="VETERANS' AFFAIRS" nameid="9I4" page="33" party="LP" speaker="Messner Sen The Hon A.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="9I4">
         Senator MESSNER
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Minister for Veterans' Affairs)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-Mr President, I congratulate you on your appointment to the high office of President of the Senate and wish you a long and happy term. The Treasurer (Mr Howard) tonight announced certain measures affecting Australian veterans and their families. I would like to elaborate on his remarks for the benefit of honourable senators.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The Government, when reviewing the whole range of repatriation matters, had very much in mind the many representations made to it by the various ex-service organisations. Most of these requests were, no doubt, very worthy and if the Government had more money at its disposal it would have been able to increase a greater number of benefits or extend benefits to more categories of beneficiaries than it has. As it happens, we feel that we have been able to use such money as is available to give the greatest assistance to those most in need-that is, the more severely disabled veterans. This has been our main objective in each Budget over the last three years. Another objective has been gradually to extend eligibility for repatriation benefits, and so this year, with the funds at our disposal, the Government has been able to extend benefits to three new categories.
      </para>
      <para>
       The first of these is the provision of the service pension to Australian mariners who served in a theatre of war during the 1939-45 war. The service pension, which is similar to the Department of Social Security's age pension, is available to veterans who served in a theatre of war and have reached the age of 60 years in the case of males or 55 in the case of females, or have become permanently unemployable at any age. Subject to an income test, certain fringe benefits are attached to the service pension, including pensioner health benefits and I am sure this new measure, which will apply from 4 February next year, will be very welcome. Repatriation benefits are also to be extended to members of peacekeeping, observation and monitoring forces representing Australia under United Nations--
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="9V4" speaker="Senator Grimes">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="9V4">
          Senator Grimes
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Like Sinai.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="9I4">
         Senator MESSNER
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Not like Sinai-under United Nations or other recognised international arrangements. This will apply to persons who serve in such forces after 1 November this year. In addition, disability pensions are to be paid to former members of the Royal Papuan Constabulary and the New Guinea Police Force who served under the control of the Australian New Guinea Army Unit from 7 December 1941 to 31 December 1945, although these police were not members of the forces they were subject to Army discipline and control. Benefits will be paid from the date of assent to the amending legislation under the same conditions as apply to indigenous members of the Australian forces during the Pacific War.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Service pensioners are to be assisted in another respect. The maximum amount of supplementary assistance-also known as the rent allowance-payable to a service pensioner is to be increased from $5 to $8 a week from 4 February next year. Supplementary assistance is given if a pensioner pays rent or pays for lodging, or board and lodging, but, from 4 February next year, if rent exceeds $10 a week, it will be paid only at the rate of 50c for each $1 of rent over that amount. In an important move affecting many veterans and their dependants, the proportion of any repatriation disability pension disregarded when assessing eligibility for the service pension and fringe benefits is to be increased from the present 50 per cent to 60 per cent from 1 January 1982. The income test has disregarded 50 per cent of any disability pension for service pension eligibility for some years, but for fringe benefits this has applied only from 1 January this year. The main effect of the increased proportion will be to make more people eligible for the service pension and to enable those who became eligible for it and the fringe benefits this year to retain them. I am sure that this will be a very popular move.
      </para>
      <para>
       I said, Mr President, that the main thrust of the Government's concern for our veterans and their dependants has been to use what funds are available largely to improve benefits to the more severely disabled of our veterans. In this respect, I am pleased that we have been able to increase many of those allowances which were increased last year-for instance, additions to pensions for those suffering amputations or loss of vision are to be increased from 12 November by amounts ranging from 50 cents to $2.25, bringing the maximum addition for this purpose up to $28.05 weekly. From the same date there will be increases in the orphan's pension by $2.40 for orphans without parents, making a new pension of $30 a week, and by $1.20 to $15 a week for those with one parent. The attendant's allowance for the severely disabled will rise by $3.40 to $42.05 a week at the high rate and by $1.70 to $21.02 a week for the low rate. The recreation transport allowance will rise by $4.00 to 48.000 monthly at the high rate and by $2.00 to 24.00 monthly for the low rate. The gift car allowance will rise by $48 to $576 annually. The clothing allowance will also rise by 15c to bring the high rate to $1.80 a week, with proportional increases in the lower rates.
      </para>
      <para>
       Allowances under the Soldiers' Children Education Scheme are to be increased from 7 January next year. There are six rates depending upon age and whether the student is living at home or away from home. The increases range from 45c to $2.20 and the weekly rates will now range from $5.45 to $27.20.
      </para>
      <para>
       Two years ago, the Government was able to increase the maximum rate of funeral benefit in respect of the deaths of entitled veterans and some dependants from $100 to $300. This year we have been able to increase this benefit by a further $100 to a new maximum of $400. The Government has been concerned about the practice of some persons foregoing income in order to gain a Service pension, a higher rate of the Service pension or fringe benefits. The legislation is to be amended to allow the Repatriation Commission to deem such foregone income to be income for the purposes of the income test applying to Service pensions and fringe benefits. The period for which such income will be maintained as income will be determined by the Commission in accordance with the facts of each case.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr President, I am sure that the extension of eligibility and increases in benefits which have been announced tonight will be very welcome among those in the veteran community. In addition to these measures announced tonight, veterans and their dependants will benefit from the increases in the main repatriation pensions brought about by movements in the consumer price index over the six months to the end of June this year. These increases, which I announced on 30 July, will apply from the first payday in November.
      </para>
      <para>
       I might mention that there has been some anxiety expressed that, with the apparent ending of indexation of salaries and wages by the Arbitration Commission, the indexation of repatriation pensions might cease. I would like to make it clear that this measure introduced by the Government in 1976 will continue.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government has had before it a number of proposals for capital expenditure at the repatriation hospitals, one of which had been considered by the Parliamentary Public Works Committee. It is not possible to announce a decision on any of these proposals, which involve the expenditure of many millions of dollars. The Government will be giving further consideration to repatriation hospitals later this year.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government is not able this year to make any changes to benefits under the Defence Service Homes Scheme, but honourable senators will be aware that last year the Government made a very generous increase in the maximum loan obtainable under this scheme from $15,000 to $25,000 maximum and the waiting period for finance to assist with the purchase of a new home or a previously occupied home was reduced from 14 months to 10 months. Also, Mr President, the interest rates on DSH loans have not been changed, so that in view of the very high rates now being charged by commercial lenders, those eligible for DSH loans, at an average of about 7 per cent interest on the maximum amount, are placed in a very favourable position.
      </para>
      <para>
       Honourable senators will be aware of the Government's concern to assist veterans of the Vietnam war with their health and personal problems. To this end, I have already announced that an expanded counselling service will be established to help them at centres in each State capital city and in Darwin and, if necessary, to refer them to specialist services in the repatriation system or in the community. A sum of $625,000 has been approved to meet the operating expenses of this counselling service in the current financial year. I hope, Mr President, that these new measures which I have just outlined, will show the Government's genuine concern for those who have served their country in time of war.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="9V4" page="35" party="ALP" speaker="Grimes Sen D.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="9V4">
         Senator GRIMES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
        <time.stamp>
         (9.35)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-I move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate take note of the statement.
      </para>
      <para>
       I am in the same situation as I was in with regard to the statement by the Minister for Social Security (Senator Chaney) in that it is difficult for one with shadow responsibilities like mine to go through all the details of a statement. The interesting thing that will come out of the statement by the Minister for Veterans' Affairs (Senator Messner) is not that pensions and benefits in this area have been increased in line with inflation, therefore maintaining but not increasing their levels, as the Minister tried to imply in his statement. I refer to the statement which appears on page 2, which says:
      </para>
      <para>
       Repatriation benefits are also to be extended to members of peacekeeping, observation and monitoring forces representing Australia under United Nations or other recognised international arrangements. This will apply to persons who served in such forces after 1 November this year.
      </para>
      <para>
       Of course, I have no objection to that benefit being extended to those people. One wonders why it is done at this time. Quite clearly it is done in anticipation of the announcement of the decision, which has already been made by the Prime Minister (Mr Malcolm Fraser), to involve Australian troops in a peacekeeping force in the Sinai this year. It is a sop relating to the statement which will be made by the Prime Minister shortly that we are to be unnecessarily involved in this military operation overseas.
      </para>
      <para>
       I suggest it is absolutely typical of the Prime Minister of this country that, having wandered around making this promise to his friends across the Pacific and having made this known to his own colleagues in this country, he is unwilling to make a statement and to come clean with the Parliament and the people until he does a little preparatory work. The worst sort of preparatory work is to ask the junior Minister for Veterans' Affairs to wander into this place to slip into the middle of a statement on repatriation benefits this sop which obviously is aimed at what the Prime Minister intends to do. As a result of this statement the Prime Minister should present to both Houses of Parliament his plans on this matter. It is a pity that the Minister for Veterans' Affairs allowed himself to be used in this way and did not demand that the Prime Minister come clean with the people of this country, with this Parliament and even perhaps with the Minister himself.
      </para>
      <para>
       We will examine the rest of the benefits, and the lack of benefits, in the Veterans' Affairs area as we do each year and make a considered statement later. I believe it is important that we point out another example of deception by the gentleman who, unfortunately for this country, is the Prime Minister at the moment. I seek leave to continue my remarks later.
      </para>
      <para>
       Leave granted; debate adjourned.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senate adjourned at 9.39 p.m.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="35" type="Papers">
     <title>
      PAPERS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       The following Papers are presented, pursuant to statute:
      </para>
      <para>
       Air Force Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 132.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Capital Territory Supreme Court Act-Rules of Court-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 196.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Federal Police Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 161, 192.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Wine and Brandy Corporation Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 155, 156.
      </para>
      <para>
       BankingAct-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 210.
      </para>
      <para>
       Bounty (Agricultural Tractors) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 174.
      </para>
      <para>
       Coal Excise Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 150.
      </para>
      <para>
       Christmas Island Act- Ordinances 1981- No. 4-Census and Statistics (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-Industrial Relations (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 205.
      </para>
      <para>
       Cocos (Keeling) Islands Act-Ordinances 1981- No. 2-Census (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-Singapore Ordinances Application (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       Commonwealth Employees (Redeployment and Retirement) Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 182.
      </para>
      <para>
       Commonwealth Teaching Service Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 207.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies (Acquisition of Shares) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 125.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies (Acquisition of Shares-Fees) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 126.
      </para>
      <para>
       Conciliation and Arbitration Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 200, 201.
      </para>
      <para>
       Copyright Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 148.
      </para>
      <para>
       Currency Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 199.
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 149, 162, 176.
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Act and Commerce (Trade Descriptions) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 157, 169.
      </para>
      <para>
       Dairy Industry Stabilization Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 158.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Act- Determinations 1981- No. 19-Senior Chaplain's Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 20-Special Action Forces Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 21-Flying Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 22-Flying Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 23-Special Action Forces Allowance and Confined Spaces Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 24-Maternity Leave.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 25-Uniform Maintenance Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 26-District Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 27-Airconditioning Allowance and Post Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 28-Education Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 29-Insurance on Removal of Urgently Required Household Items.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 30-Insurance on Removal Overseas.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 31-Flying Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 32-District Allowance and Post Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 33-Sea-going Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 34-Antarctic Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 35-Uniform Maintenance Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 36-Recreation Leave, Leave for Members under Training and Leave for Special Purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 130, 152, 177, 193, 206.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Act, Naval Defence Act and Air Force Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 133.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Amendment Act-Interim Determinations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 144, 145, 146, 147, 185, 186, 187, 188, 189, 190, 191.
      </para>
      <para>
       Distillation Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 165, 173.
      </para>
      <para>
       Dried Fruit (Export Inspection Charge) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 178.
      </para>
      <para>
       Dried Fruit (Export Inspection Charge) Collection Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 179.
      </para>
      <para>
       Excise Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 163.
      </para>
      <para>
       Export Expansion Grants Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 137, 183.
      </para>
      <para>
       Fish (Export Inspection Charge) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 180.
      </para>
      <para>
       Fish (Export Inspection Charge) Collection Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 181.
      </para>
      <para>
       Health Insurance Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 198.
      </para>
      <para>
       Insurance Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 209.
      </para>
      <para>
       Lands Acquisition Act- Land, etc., acquired for Postal purposes- Dubbo, New South Wales.
      </para>
      <para>
       St Marys, Tasmania
      </para>
      <para>
       Statements (7) by the Minister, describing land acquired by agreement under sub-section 7 (1) of the Act, for specified public purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       Long Service Leave (Commonwealth Employees) Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 135.
      </para>
      <para>
       National Companies and Securities Commission Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 129.
      </para>
      <para>
       National Health Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 212.
      </para>
      <para>
       National Parks and Wildlife Conservation Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 197.
      </para>
      <para>
       Naval Defence Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 131.
      </para>
      <para>
       Navigation Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 170.
      </para>
      <para>
       Norfolk Island Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 153.
      </para>
      <para>
       Northern Territory Representation Act and Commonwealth Electoral Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 141.
      </para>
      <para>
       Overseas Telecommunications Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 172.
      </para>
      <para>
       Papua New Guinea (Members of the Forces Benefits) Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 211.
      </para>
      <para>
       Patents Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 202, 203.
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum Products Pricing Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 160.
      </para>
      <para>
       Phosphate Fertilizers Bounty Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 175.
      </para>
      <para>
       Pollution of the Sea by Oil (Shipping Levy) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 171.
      </para>
      <para>
       Postal Services Act- By-laws 1981-Postal (Amendment) No. 3.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 151.
      </para>
      <para>
       Public Service Act- Appointment-Department of Employment and Youth Affairs-E. C. Warrior.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 159, 194.
      </para>
      <para>
       Public Service Arbitration Act-Determinations by the Arbitrator, accompanied by statements regarding possible inconsistency with the law-
      </para>
      <para>
       1980- No. 426-Amalgamated Metal Workers' and Shipwrights Union and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       1981- No. 184-Association of Draughting Supervisory and Technical Employees.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 185-Professional Officers Association, Australian Public Service.
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 186 to 191-Australian Public Service Association (Fourth Division Officers).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 192-Amalgamated Metal Workers' and Shipwrights Union and another.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 193-Australian Public Service Artisans' Association and another.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 194-Professional Radio and Electronics Institute of Australasia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 195-Amalgamated Society of Carpenters and Joiners of Australia and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 196-Printing and Kindred Industries Union.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 197-Federated Miscellaneous Workers Union of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 198 to 200-Association of Officers of the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 202 and 203-Professional Radio and Electronics Institute of Australasia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 205-Australian Public Service Association (Fourth Division Officers).*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 206-Commonwealth Foremen's Association of Australia (Australian Public Service).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 207-Australian Public Service Artisans' Association and another.
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 208 to 210-Federated Liquor and Allied Industries Employees Union of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 211-Australian Public Service Association (Fourth Division Officers).
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 212 and 213-Amalgamated Metal Workers' and Shipwrights Union and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 214-Amalgamated Metal Workers' and Shipwrights Union and others.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 215-Amalgamated Metal Workers' and Shipwrights Union and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 216-Australian Workers' Union.*
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 217 and 218-Meat Inspectors Association, Commonwealth Public Service.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 219-Association of Draughting, Supervisory and Technical Employees.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 220-Federated Miscellaneous Workers Union of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 221-Commonwealth Works Supervisors Association.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 222-Vehicle Builders Employees Federation of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 223-Australian Journalists Association.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 224-Association of Draughting, Supervisory and Technical Employees.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 225-Federal Firefighters' Union.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 226-Hospital Employees Federation of Australia and another.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 227-Transport Workers' Union of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 228-Australian Broadcasting Commission Staff Association.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 229-Electrical Trades Union of Australia.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 230-Administrative and Clerical Officers' Association, Commonwealth Public Service and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 231-Australian Public Service Association (Fourth Division Officers).*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 232-Electrical Trades Union of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 233-Civil Air Operations Officers' Association of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 234-Australian Public Service Association (Fourth Division Officers).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 235-Australian Public Service Association (Fourth Division Officers).*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 236-Australian Broadcasting Commission Staff Association.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 237-Shop Distributive and Allied Employees Association.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 238-Merchant Service Guild of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 239-Professional Officers Association, Australian Public Service.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 240-Amalgamated Metal Workers' and Shipwrights Union and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 241-Amalgamated Metal Workers' and Shipwrights Union and others.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 242-Australian Building Construction Employees' and Builders Labourers' Federation.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 243-Australian Broadcasting Commission Staff Association.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 244-Transport Workers' Union of Australia and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 245-Administrative and Clerical Officers' Association, Commonwealth Public Service.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 246-Australian Journalists Association.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 247-Australian Public Service Association (Fourth Division Officers).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 248-Association of Professional Engineers, Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 249-Australian Public Service Association (Fourth Division Officers).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 251-Australian Journalists Association and another.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 252-Australian Journalists Association.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 253-Australian Broadcasting Commission Staff Association.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 254-Federated Liquor and Allied Industries Employees Union of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 255-Hospital Employees Federation of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 257-Association of Professional Engineers, Australia and another.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 258-Amalgamated Society of Carpenters and Joiners of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 259-Professional Radio and Electronics Institute of Australasia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 260-Professional Officers Association, Australian Public Service.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 261-Australian Public Service Artisans' Association.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 262-Association of Draughting, Supervisory and Technical Employees.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 263-Association of Draughting, Supervisory and Technical Employees and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 264 and 265-Administrative and Clerical Officers' Association, Commonwealth Public Service and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 266 and 267-Australian Public Service Association (Fourth Division Officers).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 268-Association of Professional Engineers, Australia.*
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 269 to 275-Australian Public Service Association (Fourth Division Officers).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 276-Administrative and Clerical Officers' Association, Commonwealth Public Service and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 277-Commonwealth Foremen's Association of Australia (Australian Public Service).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 278-Administrative and Clerical Officers' Association, Commonwealth Public Service and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 279-Amalgamated Metal Workers' and Shipwrights Union and others.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 280-Amalgamated Metal Workers' and Shipwrights Union and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 281-Federated Miscellaneous Workers Union of Australia.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 282-Administrative and Clerical Officers' Association, Commonwealth Public Service.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 283-Amalgamated Metal Workers' and Shipwrights Union and others.*
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 284 and 285-Hospital Employees Federation of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 286 to 288-Royal Australian Nursing Federation.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 289-Association of Draughting, Supervisory and Technical Employees.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 290-Amalgamated Society of Carpenters and Joiners of Australia and other.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 291-Association of Officers of the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization and another.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 292-Association of Professional Engineers, Australia and another.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 293-Australian Society of Engineers and another.*
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 294-Australian Theatrical and Amusement Employees Association.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 295-Professional Musicians Union of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 296-Australian Journalists Association.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 297-Administrative and Clerical Officers' Association, Commonwealth Public Service and others.*
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 298 and 299-Transport Workers' Union of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 300-Australian Public Service Artisans' Association and another.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 301-Merchant Service Guild of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       (*Not accompanied by statement. * Determinations resulting from decisions by the Australian Conciliation and Arbitration Commission, made on appeal, pursuant to section 15C of the Public Service Arbitration Act.)
      </para>
      <para>
       Quarantine Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 168, 215.
      </para>
      <para>
       Remuneration Tribunals Act- Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 124, 140.
      </para>
      <para>
       Remuneration Tribunal-Determinations 1981- No. 6-Remuneration payable to Chairman, Member and Medical Member, Social Security Appeals Tribunal, together with an explanatory statement, dated 7 May 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 7-Remuneration payable to Chairman and Member, Australian Wine and Brandy Corporation and others, together with an explanatory statement, dated 25 May 1981.
      </para>
      <para>
       Securities Industry Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 127.
      </para>
      <para>
       Securities Industry (Fees) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 128.
      </para>
      <para>
       Seat of Government (Administration) Act- Ordinances 1981- No. 14-Companies (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 15-Scaffolding and Lifts (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 16-Motor Traffic (Alcohol and Drugs) (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 17-Motor Omnibus Services (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 18-Police (Discipline and Administration) (Repeal).
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations 1981- No. 13-(Companies Ordinance).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 14-(Nurses Registration Ordinance).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 15-(Health Commission Ordinance).
      </para>
      <para>
       Senate (Representation of Territories) Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 142.
      </para>
      <para>
       Spirits Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 164.
      </para>
      <para>
       Superannuation Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 208, 213.
      </para>
      <para>
       Telecommunications Act- By-laws- Telecommunications (Charging Zones and Charging Districts) Amendments Nos 10, 11, 12.
      </para>
      <para>
       Telecommunications (Community Calls) Amendments Nos 8, 9, 10.
      </para>
      <para>
       Telecommunications (Staff) Amendment No. 34.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 138.
      </para>
      <para>
       Tertiary Education Commission Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 134.
      </para>
      <para>
       Trade Commissioners Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 136, 143, 204.
      </para>
      <para>
       Trade Practices Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 166, 167.
      </para>
      <para>
       Weights and Measures (National Standards) Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 195.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wireless Telegraphy Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 Nos 139, 184.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wool Industry Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1981 No. 154.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
   </chamber.xscript>
  </hansard>
 </body>
</html>
