<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" "hansard.dtd">
<html>
 <body>
  <hansard chamber="SENATE" date="18/09/96" page="3545" parliament.no="38" period.no="2" proof="NO" session.no="1">
   <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
     <day.start date="18/09/96">
      Wednesday, 18 September 1996
     </day.start>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         The PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. Margaret Reid)
        </emphasis>
        took the chair at 9.30 a.m., and read prayers.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </business.start>
    <qwn page="3545">
     <title>
      QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
     </title>
     <question.block page="3545">
      <title>
       Superannuation
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" gov="0" nameid="ZW4" page="3545" party="ALP" speaker="Sherry, Sen Nick">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZW4">
          Senator SHERRY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Assistant Treasurer in respect of the administrative complexities of the government's new 15 per cent superannuation tax. Are you aware of the trenchant criticisms of: Professor David Knox, former Liberal superannuation adviser and currently member of the government's actuarial advisory committee; Mr Bruce Cook, chairman of William M. Mercer; Mr Brian Bissacker of Bankers Trust; Mr Emery Feyzeny of KPMG and your own Liberal Senate colleague Senator John Watson on the superannuation tax? When will you acknowledge the broad community concerns on this issue? Will you support referral to the Senate committee on superannuation with a report back date by 30 November?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="DJ4" page="3545" party="LP" speaker="Short, Sen Jim">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The one thing that this question shows, quite clearly, is that the opposition is not prepared to join the government in seeking a fairer superannuation system for all Australians. That is the nub of what this question is all about. Is the Australian Labor Party really fair dinkum about supporting the surcharge that we have imposed in the budget? Mr Beazley says one thing and Senator Sherry says another thing. Someone says, `We will refer it to a committee.' Others say, `We do not need to do so—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="ZW4" speaker="SHERRY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="ZW4">
           Senator Sherry
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Madam President, on a point of order—
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —He can't take it. He has absolutely bogged himself down.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="ZW4" speaker="SHERRY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="ZW4">
           Senator Sherry
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —For the first time we would like an answer from Senator Short to a specific question. When will he answer this question?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="FAULKNER ">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator Faulkner
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Chance your arm, you hopeless individual.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
        </break>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="ALSTON">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Madam President, on a point of order: I simply draw attention to the fact that a fair degree of latitude is involved in points of order. But we have just had a naked example of a total disregard of the rules that had absolutely nothing to do with what preceded it. It was simply a cheap debating point. It can be made at any other time and it should not be made now—and you should not allow that sort of abuse of question time to continue.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Senator Short has spoken for less than one minute to this point and has the opportunity to develop an answer.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I preface my answer to Senator Sherry by asking the Labor Party, through you, whether it really does want greater fairness in the superannuation system in this country. If it does, then it would support the thrust of the policy decision.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="FAULKNER ">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator Faulkner
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You are obligated to answer the question. Answer the question.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —You don't like hearing the truth, Senator Faulkner, because truth is a word that is pretty out of your vocabulary and always has been.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Opposition senators interjecting
        </emphasis>
        —
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Senator Short, just wait, please. It is impossible to hear with so much noise in the chamber.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —If Labor took the same starting point as us in wanting greater fairness and, therefore, really supporting the surcharge that we have proposed in the budget—which Senator Sherry, I think, and Mr Beazley have said they do support—then it would be logical to wait until the legislation is introduced into the parliament after the extensive consultations that are going on at the moment.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <break soft-hyphen="1" type="COLUMN">
         Senator Sherry well knows that an actuarial advisory committee is looking at these issues in relation to defined benefit funds and unfunded schemes. He knows that the government has established a task force which comprises representatives of the ISC, the ATO, Treasury and industry to look at these issues. He knows that extensive consultations are going on, including the involvement of Professor David Knox, and we are very pleased that he is doing that; he is approach ing it in a very constructive way. Consultations are going on.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The logical, systematic, due process way to proceed with this would be to let those consultations proceed and, as a result, have the legislation drafted and presented to parliament. Then the parliament, through its committee systems, can have every opportunity to look at the legislation.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        But, quite frankly, it is absolutely ridiculous to say before that legislation is drafted, before the consultations have concluded—we are only halfway through the consultations—`Let's go and look at all the fine detail of this issue' before you have the detail to consider. It casts very grave doubts on the real motives of the Labor Party on this issue.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="TAS" gov="0" nameid="ZW4" page="3545" party="ALP" speaker="Sherry, Sen Nick">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZW4">
          Senator SHERRY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —A supplementary. Senator, you still refuse to acknowledge the broad community concerns.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="ALSTON">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Put your question through the chair.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZW4">
          Senator SHERRY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I take it from your answer that you do not want this matter referred to the Senate committee. Therefore, do you agree with Senator John Watson—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Senator Sherry, your question should be addressed through the chair.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZW4">
          Senator SHERRY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Do you agree with Senator John Watson's support on 11 September at a meeting of the Senate select committee in referring this matter to that committee?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="ALSTON">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Could I take a point of order, Madam President? It is very sad that Senator Sherry, who has now been here for some years—he is apparently the Deputy Leader of the Opposition in the Senate—still does not understand the requirement that questions should be addressed through the chair. Now what that—
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="ZW4" speaker="SHERRY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="ZW4">
           Senator Sherry
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I am doing that.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="ALSTON">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —But you don't! You were told three times that you ought to ask the question in the third person.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="ZW4" speaker="SHERRY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="ZW4">
           Senator Sherry
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You aren't addressing the chair!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="ALSTON">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I am making my remarks through the chair. I am making the point that
          <break page="3546" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
           Senator Sherry does not comprehend the difference between asking a question in the second person or the third person. That is what it is all about. He ought to know the distinction. Madam President, you should not allow him to continue in ignorance. If he is going to address questions through the chair, there is a proper form to be followed, and it is very unfortunate that after all these years he still has not got the vaguest idea.
          </break>
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Whenever the word `you' is used, it is apparent that the question or answer is not being directed through the chair. They should be. Have you completed your question, Senator Sherry?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="ZW4" speaker="SHERRY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="ZW4">
           Senator Sherry
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Yes, Madam President.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="DJ4" page="3546" party="LP" speaker="Short, Sen Jim">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Madam President, the government is not saying that the details of the implementation complexities should not be considered at all by a committee. What we are saying—and we are really prejudging the debate that is to come up a little later—is that until the consultations have taken place, until legislation has been drafted and brought into this parliament so one can see the details, then it is premature to refer such a matter of administration to a committee.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        What are you going to do when the legislation comes in—by the end of the year, hopefully? Are you going to do it again and again and again? It is quite deliberate time wasting on the part of the Labor Party in an attempt, I think, to thwart the introduction of a major change to the superannuation system that will make superannuation fairer and more equitable for all Australians.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3546">
      <title>
       Hindmarsh Island
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="9X5" page="3546" party="LP" speaker="Ellison, Sen Chris">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="9X5">
          Senator ELLISON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Thank you, Madam President. Through you, I ask the Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs, Senator Herron: Minister, in light of yesterday's announcement that the government plans to legislate to allow construction of the Hindmarsh Island bridge to proceed, can you outline the reasons why the government has taken this decision—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UI4" speaker="RAY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UI4">
           Senator Robert Ray
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Could I take a point of order, Madam President? Senator Ellison used the word `you' that you just ruled out—I
          <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
           think very foolishly, Madam President. Will you rule him out?
          </break>
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="9X5">
          Senator ELLISON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —On the point of order, Madam President, if Senator Ray had listened, I prefaced my comment by `Through you, Madam President'—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UI4" speaker="RAY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UI4">
           Senator Robert Ray
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I know. Silly ruling.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="9X5">
          Senator ELLISON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —and I believe that distinguishes what Madam President has said, Senator Ray.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —No, it does not. In fact it does not, and twice previously I have called government ministers when answering questions on this point. It is the way in which you refer also to other people.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UI4" speaker="RAY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UI4">
           Senator Robert Ray
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Madam President, on the point of order: I think Senator Ellison's question is totally in order. The use of the word `you' to a minister has been used here ever since this chamber started. It is, I guess, when the questioner is only just looking at the minister, never referring to you, then you could take action. But, if you think about that ruling you have made, it is just not practical.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —It was an observation I made about the use of the word `you', and it frequently refers to the fact that somebody is not directing their remarks through the chair and referring to people personally.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="9X5">
          Senator ELLISON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —In light of yesterday's announcement that the government plans to legislate to allow the construction of the Hindmarsh Island bridge to continue, can the minister outline the reasons why the government has taken this decision, and can he detail to the Senate the costs involved since the previous Labor government first took action to stop work on the Hindmarsh Island bridge?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs" nameid="VW4" page="3546" party="LP" speaker="Herron, Sen John">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Thank you, Senator Ellison, for that question. The government has taken the view that, after complete bungling and incompetence by the previous government, this matter has gone on for long enough. The sad fact is that we have had four state and federal inquiries costing in excess of $3 million, the latest by Justice Jane Mathews costing over $1 million. In addition, it is estimated that well over $1 million has been spent on associated legal appeals and actions
         <break page="3547" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
          in various courts. Of the four inquiries, three, Senator Ellison, have found that the bridge should go ahead, and the one that found the area should be protected was overturned on appeal.
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        When the previous government boxed themselves into a corner and proceeded, over 2&amp;half; years, to pour millions of dollars of taxpayers' money into efforts to justify their original decision to oppose the bridge, and after the High Court overturned the latest inquiry by Justice Jane Mathews, I was faced with the prospect of having to order yet another inquiry and, at the end of that, we could well face further legal appeals. The fiasco has gone on far enough. You have made yourselves—
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Senator Herron.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="FAULKNER ">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator Faulkner
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —A point of order!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —the laughing stock of the Australian public, and we are not going to do that.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Senator Herron.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="FAULKNER ">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator Faulkner
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Could I take a point of order, Madam President? My point of order is this: we have had a sanctimonious point of order from Senator Alston about comments being directed through the chair. I ask you to make a consistent ruling and rule that Senator Herron's comments then were out of order, and direct him to make his comments through the chair.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Of course. I had called him to order before you stood up, Senator Faulkner. I had called `order' before you stood up. I agree with you entirely, and the remarks should not be addressed in that fashion.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Madam President, this fiasco has gone on far enough.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="FAULKNER ">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator Faulkner
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —So don't repeat it!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will repeat it. The opposition have made themselves the laughing stock of the Australian public. We have inherited this mess from the Labor Party, and we plan to clean it up. We plan to do that by introducing legislation that will deal specifically and solely with Hindmarsh Island.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
        <para first-indent="16">
         The Labor Party has two choices—either accept that they made a mess of this and support our legislation to clean that mess up, or reject the legislation which will force a fifth inquiry, perhaps costing another million dollars of taxpayers' money. And, if they do reject it, Madam President, I suggest that the Labor Party should put up the money for the next inquiry because the Australian public is not prepared to do it. Madam President, I suggest the Labor Party should put up the money. Or do we put it on the Beazley Bankcard? We would have yet another fiasco if it goes onto the Beazley bankcard because that is where it will have to come from because the Australian public is not prepared to do that.
        </para>
        <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="FAULKNER ">
         <talk.start>
          <talker>
           <name nameid="5K4">
            Senator Faulkner
           </name>
          </talker>
          <para in-line="1">
           —Come on, eyes down.
          </para>
         </talk.start>
        </interject>
        <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
         <talk.start>
          <talker>
           <name nameid="10000">
            The PRESIDENT
           </name>
          </talker>
          <para in-line="1">
           —Order!
          </para>
         </talk.start>
        </interject>
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="VW4">
           Senator HERRON
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Do senators opposite—well, they don't want to do a U&amp;hyphen;turn—
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="FAULKNER ">
         <talk.start>
          <talker>
           <name nameid="5K4">
            Senator Faulkner
           </name>
          </talker>
          <para in-line="1">
           —On a point of order, Madam President: I don't think that Senator Herron has been listening to your ruling because he is straying again. He is not addressing his remarks through the chair.
          </para>
         </talk.start>
        </interject>
        <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
         <talk.start>
          <talker>
           <name nameid="10000">
            The PRESIDENT
           </name>
          </talker>
          <para in-line="1">
           —Senator Herron, you should direct your remarks through the chair and not directly to opposition senators.
          </para>
         </talk.start>
        </interject>
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="VW4">
           Senator HERRON
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Madam President, they are a bit touchy on the other side this morning because I think the facts are coming home to roost on them after years of dilly&amp;hyphen;dallying with this issue. Now they want the taxpayer to fork out more money in relation to the folly that has been pursued over a number of years by the previous government. They are between a rock and a hard place and they ought to wake up to that. If they want another inquiry, the ALP should put up the money for that inquiry, rather than the Australian taxpayer.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </break>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3547">
      <title>
       Minister for Small Business and Consumer Affairs
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" gov="0" nameid="RF4" page="3547" party="ALP" speaker="Cook, Sen Peter">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Madam President, through you, I address a question to Senator Parer representing the Minister for Small Business and Consumer Affairs. Could the minister please inform the Senate of the cost,
         <break page="3548" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
          purpose and benefits to the Australian community and small business of the recent trip to the Philippines by the Minister for Small Business and Consumer Affairs, Mr Prosser? Through you, Madam President, could the minister also comment on the reports that the Philippines government was so upset by Mr Prosser's repeated failure to attend working sessions of the APEC small and medium enterprises ministerial meeting that it considered lodging a diplomatic protest, and that such action was averted only by the professionalism of the officers accompanying him?
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Resources and Energy" nameid="KI4" page="3548" party="LP" speaker="Parer, Sen Warwick">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am aware of the fact that my colleague Minister Prosser did attend the APEC meeting in the Philippines. I have no idea of the cost. It was an APEC meeting. I have no idea of the comments that have been made by Senator Cook. I will refer them to the minister and come back to him.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="WA" gov="0" nameid="RF4" page="3548" party="ALP" speaker="Cook, Sen Peter">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Madam President, in view of that answer, as a supplementary, can the minister provide the Senate with full details of Minister Prosser's program, including details as to which conference sessions he actually attended and what other—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="FAULKNER ">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator Faulkner
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —If any—
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —If any; what other meetings, if any, he attended; what was discussed at them; and the details of the cost of this trip?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Resources and Energy" nameid="KI4" page="3548" party="LP" speaker="Parer, Sen Warwick">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Yes.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3548">
      <title>
       Telecommunications
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="LI4" page="3548" party="LP" speaker="Patterson, Sen Kay">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LI4">
          Senator PATTERSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Communications and the Arts. In view of the minister's statements that, industry wide, there will be many new jobs created in the telecommunications area despite the loss of jobs in Telstra over the next few years, can the minister provide concrete examples of job creation in this industry?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3548" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Yes, there are many examples. United Telecommunications, for example, which aims to be Australia's largest Telstra Mobilenet service provider, currently has a national operations centre with some 200 staff. They expect to increase that by 300 to 500 staff in the near future. The regional
         <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
          pay TV company, Austar—which has been rolling out a combined wireless satellite and cable television network across regional New South Wales, Queensland, Victoria, South Australia and the Northern Territory—has already established 23 wireless cable systems in larger regional centres and aims to expand that—
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="AW5" speaker="CARR">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="AW5">
           Senator Carr
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Twenty&amp;hyphen;three! Twenty&amp;hyphen;three out of 22,000!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Quite right. I am equally impressed by the fact that you are impressed too. It plans to expand that to 40 such systems by the end of next year. It has also introduced satellite TV coverage across regional New South Wales, Queensland, Victoria and South Australia. This has meant 600 new jobs throughout regional Australia, with another 200 people to be employed before the end of this year. In these two companies alone, we have more than 1,000 new jobs.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The high level of employment growth in the private telecommunications sector is reflected in the overall figures. The Telecommunications Industry Development Authority has published figures which show that the number of employees in the equipment suppliers and service provider sector of the industry alone has increased by just short of 20,000 in the two years from December 1993. That is up 30 per cent. Employment growth in the communications sector overall is phenomenal—35,000 new jobs since 1993. Of course, during that period Telstra was downsizing.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Telstra's own activities in cable roll&amp;hyphen;out and service expansion are also creating new jobs and new businesses across Australia. Some 1,200 jobs were created in Queensland alone during 1994&amp;hyphen;95. These examples are only a taste of what is to come. Paynet Telecommunications plans to roll out cable in Cairns and, hopefully, Townsville. Neighbourhood Cable plans to offer video on demand and other services to a regional community south&amp;hyphen;east of Melbourne. Northgate Communications proposes to install a network in the Ballarat area offering pay TV and other services. Austar is apparently interested in Tasmania, although at this time East Coast Television has the regional rights.
       </para>
       <break page="3549" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
        <para first-indent="16">
         These developments indicate the pattern of employment growth and technological advance across regional Australia which should lay to rest fears about unemployment and steam age technology in the less urbanised areas of Australia. All of this goes to confirm the words of the Managing Director of the Australian Telecommunications Users Group, Mr Allan Horsley, who told the Senate inquiry:
        </para>
        <para font-size="-=2">
         The industry is desperately short of people. We cannot find them. We put ads in the paper and our members are looking for people and cannot find them. Our experience has been that there is substantial demand for employment and, if as a result of any process this or just management changes in Telstra result in fewer employees, those employees will pick up work without a doubt outside. It is not overstating the case to say that demand is enormous.
        </para>
       </break>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="LI4" page="3549" party="LP" speaker="Patterson, Sen Kay">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LI4">
          Senator PATTERSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have a supplementary question, Madam President. Given that job losses have been occurring for some years in Telstra, can the minister explain why it has suddenly become an issue now?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3549" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is absolutely true—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="AW5" speaker="CARR">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="AW5">
           Senator Carr
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —It is not true.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is unfortunate that Senator Carr is so ignorant of the facts of this matter that he is not aware that, between 1991 and 1994, 25,000 jobs were lost inside Telstra.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="AW5" speaker="CARR">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="AW5">
           Senator Carr
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —What about last year?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Do not change the subject. I am just telling you the facts of the matter. I would have thought that you would understand that.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        This is a gross exercise in hypocritical double standards because, during that period of three years, unemployment was 10.3, 10.5, 11 per cent and 10.6. In other words, it was much higher than it is now. Something in the order of 850,000 to 950,000 people were unemployed, with not one squawk from the Labor Party, not one squawk from others about it, no industrial disruption.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Yet what do we have now? We have all this hypocritical hand wringing. We only have to look at the remarks of the telecommunications public sector union on this subject when they said:
       </para>
       <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
        <para font-size="-=2">
         It has only been after the election of a government committed to privatisation that speculation started.
        </para>
        <para>
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         </emphasis>
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </para>
       </break>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3549">
      <title>
       Papua New Guinea
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="0" nameid="SF4" page="3549" party="ALP" speaker="Cooney, Sen Barney">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="SF4">
          Senator COONEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Defence, Senator Newman. The question is: at the PNG ministerial forum, did the PNG defence minister indicate an implementation program for the Defence white paper published last year? Did the ministers agree that such implementation would alter the nature of the Australian Defence cooperation program with PNG? Did Australia accede to the PNG minister's public avowals that Australia's DCP should be reviewed? Who is to conduct such a review and when will the results be known?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="Social Security" nameid="BE4" page="3549" party="LP" speaker="Newman, Sen Jocelyn">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BE4">
          Senator NEWMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Of course, our relationship with Papua New Guinea has been a longstanding one and of great importance to both countries. The defence forces of both countries have had a very strong relationship over the years and many Papua New Guinea people have been trained by the Australian Defence Force. Last week officials from both countries met, as well as did the ministers. I will obtain the details of the answer to the senator's question.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="0" nameid="SF4" page="3549" party="ALP" speaker="Cooney, Sen Barney">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="SF4">
          Senator COONEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thank through you, Madam President, the minister for her answer to that. I wonder whether the minister would be able have answers available before program 5 in estimates, so we can follow it up there.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="Social Security" nameid="BE4" page="3549" party="LP" speaker="Newman, Sen Jocelyn">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BE4">
          Senator NEWMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As we had defence estimates for some hours yesterday, Senator, and we only got to the end of program 2, I am sure you have quite a while before you need your answer but, of course, I will get it for you.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3549">
      <title>
       Australia Post
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="0" nameid="1M6" page="3549" party="AD" speaker="Allison, Sen Lyn">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1M6">
          Senator ALLISON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Communications and the Arts, Senator Alston. According to reports in the media recently, the Productivity Commission has argued that Australia Post should be required to take on more debt because its current low level of debt suppos
         <break page="3550" soft-hyphen="1" type="PAGE">
          edly gives it an unfair advantage over the private sector.
          <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
           Does the government intend to privatise all or any section of Australia Post? Would the government be prepared to direct Australia Post to borrow money it does not need? Would the government agree to abolish the uniform letter right and allow the rate for postage to set according to the cost of delivery?
          </tab>
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3550" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —There is no intention to change the current arrangements, particularly in relation to the uniform service across Australia and, indeed, the standard postal delivery arrangements.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="XW4" speaker="KERNOT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="XW4">
           Senator Kernot
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Well done!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —But what is important to remember is this: on 15 November 1993, Mr Beddall, who was then the communications minister—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="XW4" speaker="KERNOT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="XW4">
           Senator Kernot
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Oh, here we go.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Come on, just a moment. Don't bury your heads in the sand and somehow pretend that everything is perfect.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="XW4" speaker="KERNOT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="XW4">
           Senator Kernot
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Oh, dear!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —All I am telling you is—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Senator Alston, direct your remarks through the chair.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UNKNOWN" speaker="Opposition senators">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UNKNOWN">
           Opposition senators
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          — Through the chair! Through the chair!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Madam President, I am simply at pains to point out that the previous administration committed themselves to a review and, on 28 June this year, the Treasurer similarly announced that we would be conducting a review of Australia Post during this financial year. Mr Crean himself welcomed that and said that, as long as it was a given in any such review that the level and quality of services were maintained and that people in regional and rural areas were properly looked after, there was a capacity to expose Australia Post to more competition. That is indeed what Mr Beddall had said when he made his original announcement.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        What ought to happen is that the fear card should not be played. You should not simply run around saying the sky is going to fall in
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
         if you have even a review to try to introduce more competition.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I understand Senator Allison's point about the levels of debt. I have not read any Productivity Commission report to that effect. It is certainly not something that is before us at the moment. If people want to make that sort of an argument, or indeed you want to make a counter&amp;hyphen;argument in the course of that review, then it will be perfectly open to you to do so. But I think your starting point ought to be that you should be interested in ensuring that services are not only maintained at the highest level but be delivered as efficiently as possible.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="XW4" speaker="KERNOT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="XW4">
           Senator Kernot
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —That is what you said about Telstra.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Indeed, indeed. It is just a pity that you will not join me in trying to achieve world's best practice instead of settling for mediocrity. It is very unfortunate that some people are prepared to accept second best in this game when you do have the capacity to achieve world's best practice, when you do have the capacity to ensure that you can maintain the quality of service, lower prices, better range of products—all of the things that consumers are entitled to, all of the things that can be protected in legislation—and at the same time ensure greater efficiencies.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        As you know, Australia Post has been downsizing also, has been becoming much more commercial in recent years. I think about 55 per cent of its total revenue now comes from competitive activities and it is continuing to undergo significant growth. It can therefore do that—
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="XW4" speaker="KERNOT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="XW4">
           Senator Kernot
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —In positive ownership.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —If anyone wants to put in a submission about any issues that might result in greater efficiency, you are welcome to do so. I am simply putting the proposition to you that you will have a review in due course. You will be able to explore all of those issues. In due course, Madam President, I hope that there will be an acknowledgment on all sides of the chamber, except for poor old Senator Schacht who simply wants to play the game of pure politics and clearly is not
         <break page="3551" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
          interested and proved that. He said it himself! He told the
          <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
           Australian
          </emphasis>
          . It is all there.
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="FAULKNER ">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator Faulkner
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Through the chair.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not need to say it through the chair. I am talking in the third person. He, Senator Schacht, made it very clear that he was not interested in policy outcomes; he was not interested in pure performance; he was not interested in the minutiae of administration, even though he never came within a bull's roar of it. He was simply interested in pure politics. Now I think, Madam President, that we can expect more of that from the Australian Democrats. I hope that in due course they will address the issues featured.
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="0" nameid="1M6" page="3551" party="AD" speaker="Allison, Sen Lyn">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1M6">
          Senator ALLISON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I ask a supplementary question, Madam President. If the outcome of that review that the minister has told us about is a recommendation to privatise part or the whole of Australia Post, will the government attempt to do so?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3551" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As you probably know, one of the things around this place is that hypothetical questions do not bear on government policy, so it is simply not a question to be answered at this time. But let me say this: the issue of greater competition should not be confused with the issue of privatisation in this instance. It may well be that there will be a decision to consider increased competition in the course of that review. There may well be submissions to that effect. That is a completely separate issue. I am not aware of any suggestions of privatisation of Australia Post. Senator Allison seems to think they are floating around, but I have not read them from anyone. It seems to me that is an entirely academic proposition at the present time. If what we are talking about is greater competition, greater efficiency and better results for consumers, then I hope that that is the sort of thing that the opposition and the Australian  Democrats will be supporting.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3551">
      <title>
       Ethanol
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" gov="0" nameid="8O6" page="3551" party="ALP" speaker="O'Brien, Sen Kerry">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8O6">
          Senator O'BRIEN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Resources and Energy. I refer to the government's decision announced in the 1996-97 budget to end the $25
         <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
          million ethanol bounty scheme. What was the basis of the minister's claim that the use and production of fuel ethanol was not cost&amp;hyphen;effective? Where exactly does the Bureau of Resource Sciences actually say, as the minister claims, that the scheme does nothing to improve the environment?
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Resources and Energy" nameid="KI4" page="3551" party="LP" speaker="Parer, Sen Warwick">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Let me give a bit of history for the new senator. The agreement to subsidise ethanol was a shady deal made by the Democrats and the former government to get their budget through in 1993. It was one of those decisions made without a lot of research being done—I can see former senior ministers nodding on the other side—that proved to be an abject failure. The idea was that, if we could subsidise ethanol, this would somehow replace other liquid fuels.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="4J4" speaker="SCHACHT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="4J4">
           Senator Schacht
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Make sure it doesn't contradict what Hilly said last night.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="BH4" speaker="HILL">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="BH4">
           Senator Hill
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I will listen carefully.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Order!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Madam President, it is very hard for me to answer with the rabble on the other side. This is a serious question and it deserves a serious answer. The idea was that if you subsidised the production of ethanol you would somehow replace liquid fuels. It goes along the theory of what happened in Brazil. In Brazil for many years, because of the absence of fossil fuels, the subsidies were given to ethanol and something like 98 per cent of all new motorcars were made to go on ethanol. Even that country found it could not continue that and the percentage of cars now made to run on ethanol in Brazil is two per cent.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Quote the BRS.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —`Quote the BRS,' Senator Bob Collins says. The people who took up the ethanol bounty were two companies. One was CSR, which had been making ethanol at Sarina, south of Mackay, since 1927. The other one was at Manildra, where ethanol is produced as a by-product from the production of gluten from wheat. The effect of this was that from all aspects—from an environmental perspective, from a cost perspective and from many other perspectives—it could not continue to be justified. Whether or
         <break page="3552" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
          not we had stringent budgetary measures, which we did have in this particular instance, no sensible person would continue that project.
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        What was the level of the subsidy? The cost of producing ethanol was 70c per litre. The cost of producing petrol is 23c per litre. The idea was that it was to be for a limited period, at which time the industry would stand on its own feet. It was clearly obvious that the industry could not stand on its own feet and the continuance of the bounty could not be justified under any circumstances. A study was done by the Bureau of Resource Sciences, ABARE and the department. The net outcome of that study was to not continue the ethanol bounty scheme.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Let me also say that this does not mean we have walked away from ethanol as being a potential substitute down the track, but we have a long way to go. We are continuing the research program. We have kept money in the budget for the woody waste or lignocellulosic plant, as it is called. I think it is $2 million. That must be matched by the New South Wales government and by industry. But by no means have we walked away from it. It was just a silly program. It was done overnight because of a deal made between the then Labor government and the Democrats to pass the budget. It was a matter of commonsense that we had no option but to drop the bounty.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3552">
      <title>
       Cape Murat
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" gov="0" nameid="DX5" page="3552" party="G(WA)" speaker="Margetts, Sen Dee">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DX5">
          Senator MARGETTS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister for the Environment. Is the minister aware of an application or expression of interest by Victoria Petroleum or any other company to carry out oil and gas exploration on Commonwealth owned land at Point Murat near Cape Range in the north-west of Western Australia in October or November of this year? Given the importance of the natural heritage values of the Cape Range National Park, the nearby Ningaloo Marine Park and the occurrence of unique underground stygofauna, or troglodytes, in the area, will the minister require an environmental impact assessment before any approval to carry out oil or gas exploration in this area is granted? If not, why not?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
       </break>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="Environment" nameid="BH4" page="3552" party="LP" speaker="Hill, Sen Robert">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BH4">
          Senator HILL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not personally know a lot about this matter. I gather that my department has some information on it at this preliminary stage. I think the facts are pretty much as Senator Margetts outlined. It has not been designated at this stage. But, now that you have brought it to my attention, I will make some inquiries and ensure that the appropriate course of action is followed.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3552">
      <title>
       Australia Television
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="0" nameid="7L6" page="3552" party="ALP" speaker="Hogg, Sen John">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="7L6">
          Senator HOGG
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question, through you, Madam President, is directed to the Minister for Communications and the Arts. I refer to the comments on Monday by the ABC Chairman, Mr Donald McDonald, supporting Australia Television International Pty Ltd, ATV. Minister, is it a fact that you recently wrote to the ABC board stating that ATV should be sold to commercial interests? Whose view on the ownership of ATV will prevail, yours or that of Mr McDonald's? Hasn't the statement of your views pre-empted the Mansfield inquiry process? What impact would the sale of ATV to commercial interests have on the provision of a television satellite service to the Asia-Pacific region?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3552" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —There has been a long history of difficulty with ATV in terms of raising sufficient funds from sponsorship. Indeed, we have been very supportive of it as a concept because it does make sense to try to ensure that we do have a voice in the region and I think ATV has a very important role to play, particularly where our news and current affairs are very well regarded. Nonetheless, you will recall that only towards the end of last year, I think, the then Labor government decided to allocate in the order of an additional $18 million for Australia Television over a three-year period in recognition of the fact that it still was not achieving its sponsorship target.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        There had been a series of internal reviews of the progress of ATV and I think a recognition that it was still going to experience difficulty in identifying sponsors. Indeed, one of the major problems is that sensible market research surveys simply cannot be conducted to determine the extent of an audience, because it is not a closed subscription system—it is open—and that means we really do not
        <break page="3553" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
         have any idea of who is watching. Against that background, it makes it very difficult for advertisers to sign up in any other than nominal amounts.
        </break>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Have you seen the survey results? I have got a copy.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —What we announced on 16 July was that the government would ask the ABC to explore the possibility of delivering more efficiently the services currently being provided by Australia Television. We also announced that we would discuss with the ABC board the scope for ensuring the maintenance of ABC program content on Australia Television, particularly news and current affairs, while tendering the operation of the service to the commercial sector.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Translated into English, that means you are going to get rid of it.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —If you do not understand English, I am afraid I cannot help you. I would have thought those words are perfectly plain. As a result of that, we will have further discussion with the ABC about how we can best progress what I think is a very sensible new approach to ensuring that we do not simply have the blinkered attitude that somehow the only way to assist a service of this nature is to simply pour more and more government dollars into it.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The Labor Party always took the view that funding should come from outside sources. Even though it is a charter activity, it was necessary for it to garner funds from other than the taxpayer. Indeed, even when those requests were being made for additional funds and you decided to provide I think $18.6 million, you made it clear that you expected the ABC to continue to rely on sponsorship and to do its very best to expand the market audience in that regard. That is still a continuing problem. It is still an approach that we think is worth pursuing. That is why we will be having discussions with the ABC to ensure we can achieve the best possible outcome.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="0" nameid="7L6" page="3553" party="ALP" speaker="Hogg, Sen John">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="7L6">
          Senator HOGG
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Madam President, I ask a supplementary question. So, Minister, why didn't you wait for the results of the Mansfield inquiry rather than pre-empt it?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
       </break>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3553" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It was not a term of reference of the Mansfield inquiry.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UI4" speaker="RAY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UI4">
           Senator Robert Ray
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Why not?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —We do not have to ask anyone who is conducting a review to look at everything that you might think might be a passing interest. We are able to make decisions in some areas. We are also able to require advice from other areas. We are also able to seek a review in other areas. We simply made the decision in relation to ATV—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="AW5" speaker="CARR">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="AW5">
           Senator Carr
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —What about political interference with the ABC?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —If we want to know all about political interference, there is only one party that we need to turn to in this chamber—the ultimate deal makers, the ultimate fixers, the ultimate heavies.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Opposition senators interjecting
        </emphasis>
        —
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —You ought to be ashamed of yourselves about the way that Keating used to carry on. Whenever he was dissatisfied with anything, he rang them up and thumped them, didn't he. He would always kick them to death. That was the political solution to your problems—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Opposition senators interjecting
        </emphasis>
        —
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —To intimidate.
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="7E4" speaker="VANSTONE">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="7E4">
           Senator Vanstone
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Madam President, I raise a point of order. I wish to draw to your attention that, whilst I am quite supportive of your apparent decision to try to enforce the standing orders to the extent that people speaking should address their remarks through the chair, I think if you are going to do that you will have to consider insisting that interjections follow the same procedure. It is possible, with a modicum of intellect—even the limited amount found on the other side—to interject through the chair. I took the opportunity during Senator Alston's answer to listen to Senator Carr, who on at least three occasions interjected by saying `you this' and `you that', Senator Bolkus, another senator whose name I was not quick enough to write down—
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <break page="3554" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
        </break>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UNKNOWN" speaker="Opposition senators">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UNKNOWN">
           Opposition senators
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Oh!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="ALSTON">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You have probably forgotten it.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </answer>
      <answer electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="Employment, Education, Training and Youth Affairs" nameid="7E4" page="3554" party="LP" speaker="Vanstone, Sen Amanda">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="7E4">
          Senator VANSTONE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Probably forgotten it—and Senator Bob Collins on a number of occasions. The point I am making to you is that it is simply unreasonable to expect both the question and the answer to go through the chair if at the same time you allow consistent interjections from the other side which invite a one-to-one response.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Interjections are disorderly in any event.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3554">
      <title>
       Ranger Uranium Mine
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" gov="1" nameid="5L6" page="3554" party="LP" speaker="Ferris, Sen Jeannie">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5L6">
          Senator FERRIS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister for Resources and Energy. Could the minister please advise the Senate of the level of background radiation at the Ranger uranium mine in the Northern Territory? Can the minister also please assure the Senate that workers at the Ranger mine and those tourists who visit the area are in no danger?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —And is it safe to get out of the bus? And, if you didn't get out of the bus, why did you go there?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Resources and Energy" nameid="KI4" page="3554" party="LP" speaker="Parer, Sen Warwick">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thank Senator Ferris for that question and also congratulate her on asking her first question in the chamber. Senators will be aware that Ranger is one of the two operating mines under Labor's foolish three&amp;hyphen;mine policy. From the Labor Party's point of view, the old, ridiculous story was that uranium from Ranger and Olympic Dam was good uranium but any other uranium was bad uranium. How stupid can you be?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Senators will be aware that background levels of radiation at Ranger are insignificant in comparison with radiation levels which we all encounter every day. The total radiation exposure of project workers is monitored to ensure that radiation exposure is within international agreed limits. These are about to change from 50 millisieverts to 20 millisieverts—
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Opposition senators interjecting
        </emphasis>
        —
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
        </break>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Obviously the Labor Party are not interested in this. The whole two&amp;hyphen;mine policy is embarrassing to them, but they should at least be interested in the radiation levels that apply to workers and to people who visit the mine. Currently the international level is 50 millisieverts, which is going to reduce to 20 over the next five years. The average level at Ranger is five millisieverts in open working areas and one millisievert in office areas. Caution, of course, must always be exercised with exit rays of radioactive materials. It is an area that I spent ten years of my working life in. Let me say that X&amp;hyphen;rays and radioactive materials have been a great benefit to the community at large. There are some 55 staff of the Office of the Supervising Scientist and 30 ERA staff involved in radiation and environmental monitoring at Ranger.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Visitors to Ranger face no potential hazard from radiation exposure. The total radiation exposure to members of the Senate select committee on uranium during their visit to Ranger was two to five microsieverts. Of the four members of the committee, all except one were briefed at the site. Where was Senator Margetts, the most vocal anti&amp;hyphen;uranium advocate in the Senate? She, with the rest of the committee flew all the way to Darwin, then from Darwin to Ranger and then all the way back again and would not get out of the bus. To use her own words, as reported in the
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Northern Territory News
        </emphasis>
        , she felt more comfortable in the vehicle. She is reported to have said, `If there is a problem with radiation, dust is not very healthy.'
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        If Senator Margetts intended to sit in the bus and if she has genuine concerns, a number of questions are raised. Why did she cost the taxpayers of Australia the return trips to Darwin and Darwin to Ranger? Why did she insist that taxpayers buy her a dose meter which she then did not trust and, of course, would have been of little use in the bus, anyway. If Senator Margetts is serious, she might like to know that on her weekly flights between Canberra and Perth she receives 13 microsieverts as compared with the two to three she would have received at Ranger. She could, of course, go by road between Perth
        <break page="3555" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
         and Canberra but to do so she would have to avoid bitumen roads and granite outcrops to avoid being exposed to radiation levels similar to or greater than she would have been exposed to at Ranger.
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </break>
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="SA" gov="1" nameid="5L6" page="3555" party="LP" speaker="Ferris, Sen Jeannie">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5L6">
          Senator FERRIS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Madam President, I ask a supplementary question. Could the Minister for Resources and Energy please inform the parliament whether any further expenditure was incurred by Senator Margetts during that visit?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Resources and Energy" nameid="KI4" page="3555" party="LP" speaker="Parer, Sen Warwick">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The only other information I have is that Senator Margetts did the same thing when she went to ANSTO at Lucas Heights. One wonders why she again put the taxpayer to the trouble of doing that. I have no particular problem with Senator Margetts stating her view on nuclear power. She is the one, of course, who initiated this Senate inquiry that is going on right now. That is her prerogative. But in this particular instance she either pulled a stunt, which was at great expense to the taxpayers of Australia, or she was serious about it, in which case there is some sort of paranoia there that I cannot help her with.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3555">
      <title>
       Unit Trusts
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="0" nameid="3L6" page="3555" party="ALP" speaker="Conroy, Sen Stephen">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="3L6">
          Senator CONROY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Assistant Treasurer. Has the Minister's attention been drawn to problems in investor protection for unit trusts? What is the government's view as to the most appropriate regulation of the interests of investors? Is the minister aware of the divergent views on this subject of those in the investment funds industry?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="DJ4" page="3555" party="LP" speaker="Short, Sen Jim">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have noted some of those reports, through you, Madam President, to Senator Conroy. We are having a look at them and I will come back to you with any response. It is a complicated and technical issue, as I think you are aware, but we will get you a response.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3555">
      <title>
       Ethanol
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" gov="0" nameid="8U4" page="3555" party="AD" speaker="Lees, Sen Meg">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8U4">
          Senator LEES
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister for Resources and Energy. It is a follow&amp;hyphen;up question on ethanol after a very, shall we say, selectively misleading answer to Senator O'Brien. Minister, is it not
         <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
          correct that on the issue of being competitive, robust and ecologically sustainable—and I refer you to this unsourced document you tabled in this place—is it not the fact that ABARE never conducted a current or future analysis of ethanol production; ABARE foreshadowed discussions on this type of company but never proceeded? As for robust, is it not the fact that the petroleum division of DPIE controlled the issue of production licences, not the industry, and never actively encouraged new producers outside New South Wales? As for ecologically sustainable, the evaluation at no time makes the claim that you just made that it was a complete failure. In misrepresenting the Australian production model, BRS incorrectly ascribes soil carbon flux to ethanol produced from industrial wastes from annual food crops.
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Resources and Energy" nameid="KI4" page="3555" party="LP" speaker="Parer, Sen Warwick">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It was very hard to hear the question being asked. I will do my best, Senator, but I can tell you that you are flogging a dead horse. You went down a loony—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="4J4" speaker="SCHACHT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="4J4">
           Senator Schacht
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Through the chair.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Lees is flogging a dead horse. A report was put out. You are talking about the costs of production and so on. Let me say to the Senate—if that suits you—that the ethanol industry, as does any other of these industries, still gets the benefit of no excise duty and no state excises on their production. That comes to in the order of about 40c a litre. So indirectly there is a subsidy already there for these alternative forms of fuel.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Might I also indicate that only within the last week I was approached by the Australian Conservation Foundation. Among a list of things they spoke about was the ethanol bounty. I offered them a copy of the report which they said they already had. I would have to say that they generally agreed, having reviewed the report—which is what I had at my disposal—there was no option but to go down that track of removing the bounty.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <break page="3556" soft-hyphen="1" type="PAGE">
         With regard to distribution, I think the ethanol contribution was 0.07 or 0.007. It was a very tiny amount, anyway, into the mix. It is a 90 per cent petrol, 10 per cent ethanol mix that occurs. Niche markets were devel oped by some independent suppliers, basically in New South Wales.
        </break>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="8U4" speaker="LEES">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="8U4">
           Senator Lees
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —But isn't it a fact that the oil industry would not cooperate?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Lees interjects that the oil industry would not cooperate. The oil industry had no play in this whatsoever, one way or the other; it did not interest them. Even where it has been used fairly extensively, with a lot of encouragement, on the west coast of the United States, I think the total contribution, after a lot of subsidy, was about 10 per cent. It should be borne in mind that that was very much driven by the need to reduce carbon monoxide. It is not a reduction of carbon dioxide through the ethanol process; it is a reduction of carbon monoxide.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        From an environmental point of view, as Senator Lees should know, because of the lead policies introduced in Australia, carbon monoxide levels have in fact reduced in this country. So carbon monoxide levels, from a pollutant point of view, are actually going down in Australia, not up.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The other area where it can be important if you have got high levels of carbon monoxide is in very cold climates. I think that climatic point of view is referred to in the report. I am not sure, but I know that is the advice that I have got.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="SA" gov="0" nameid="8U4" page="3556" party="AD" speaker="Lees, Sen Meg">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8U4">
          Senator LEES
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have a couple of follow&amp;hyphen;up questions, Madam President. Minister, this document has been refuted page by page by the industry. I ask: have you got a copy of that? I am particularly interested to know why this was unsourced, why you have not been able to include in the document you released the information on which you base this. As far as subsidies are concerned, is it not a fact that over $800 million is going to the diesel fuel rebate alone? This industry was never meant to be a competitive industry before the year 2000. Indeed, it was given seed funding and they were looking at the year 2000 before they would be able to go on their own. The final part of my question is: is it not a fact that they saw the year 2000 as being the time by which they would no longer need to have the bounty?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
       </break>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Resources and Energy" nameid="KI4" page="3556" party="LP" speaker="Parer, Sen Warwick">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My understanding is that the initial program was a three&amp;hyphen;year program. The industry certainly asked for it to be extended to the year 2000; that is quite correct. All the evaluations we have done were done quite independently—by BRS, ABARE and the department. To say that the department controlled it is an absolute nonsense.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Let me repeat: it does not mean we are turning our back on alternative fuels. I mentioned before that there is an amount of money still set aside in the budget for the lignocellulosics plant, which is woody waste. Also, the Energy Research and Development Corporation has an amount set aside for continuing research into this process. Finally, even in today's paper, which is what sparked off these questions, it is recognised that if you use crops to make ethanol, you are going to contribute to greenhouse gas emissions.
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         (Time expired)
        </emphasis>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3556">
      <title>
       Aviation: Emergency Locator Beacons
      </title>
      <question electorate="NT" gov="0" nameid="OF4" page="3556" party="ALP" speaker="Collins, Sen Bob">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator BOB COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Transport and Regional Development. After the minister gagged Aviation Safety Authority officials during the estimates hearings last night and prevented them from answering any questions relating to the unprecedented political direction of the minister for transport to overturn the decision of the authority to require the fitting of automatically activating emergency locator beacons, the minister said that the government had issued this direction on `the best advice'. He went on to say that `the government was conscious of the consequences of the decision'. Can the minister now advise the Senate what was, to quote him, `the best advice' that the minister for transport used to take this unprecedented action in overturning a safety authority decision on equipment to be installed in Australian aircraft? Can he make that best advice available to the Senate.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3556" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —In the course of last night's proceedings, after Senator Collins had made a fool of himself by suggesting that somehow you could ask officials about the level of morale in the department in relation to decisions, I was asked, with a preface, `I
         <break page="3557" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
          accept that you won't have any first&amp;hyphen;hand knowledge on this issue, but could you indicate the government's general approach'. I said that without knowing the merits of the decision, I would assume—
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —What?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Do you want the answer or not? I would assume that the government had access to the best advice, that it would have made the decision conscious of all the relevant factors, that it would not have been an arbitrary or capricious decision and that we therefore would have ensured that we had access to all the necessary information. All I am saying to you is that those are approaches that one would expect of good government. I am quite happy to ask Mr Sharp to provide you with as much as he possibly can in terms of the information that was taken into account in the making of that decision. But I am sure you understand now, as you understood then, that I did not have any personal knowledge of the issue. I therefore did not have access to the advice.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Oh, yes!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Of course. I was making it plain to you last night that all I could do was assume, as one would normally assume, and I think you were nodding vigorously at the end of that exchange, that that is indeed the best approach to adopt. You did not pursue the matter further for that reason. I say to you again that in making this decision—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Senator Alston, your answer should not be addressed directly to the questioner.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is surprising, Madam President, that the other side did not take a point of order. The fact is—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I was impeccable, Dick.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Well, you might have been impeccable to that extent but Senator Collins certainly was not impeccable in pursuing the matter last night. He did accept that there were principles of good government and good decision making that did involve having access to all the necessary facts and information. That includes the advice that is
         <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
          available to the minister. Naturally, I will invite the minister to respond in the most helpful way possible.
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="NT" gov="0" nameid="OF4" page="3557" party="ALP" speaker="Collins, Sen Bob">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator BOB COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Following that interesting answer from Senator Alston, is Senator Alston aware that his assumption that he has just told us about was sadly flawed and that the reason the minister for transport took what we were advised last night was an unprecedented action in politically directing the authority in respect of overturning a decision on safety equipment on aircraft was in fact a payment for some help that was given to the now government during the election campaign in some newsletters that were published, which I will canvass at a future time. Is the minister conscious of the fact that, on the evidence given to the committee last night, we are now the only country in the world that uses these beacons that allows manually activated beacons to be used?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3557" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am aware that Senator Collins did read into the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Hansard
         </emphasis>
         record before seeking to table or incorporate it a letter which I think was dated 5 May 1995—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —No, that has nothing to do with this question.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thought it had. Senator Collins I thought was suggesting that a decision was taken for reasons that were based on presentations made to the minister. If that is not so, of course I will disregard it. I simply say this, Madam President: whatever decision Mr Sharp made, he was not required to have access only to the advice that you think he should have taken into account.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —What!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —He was entitled to take into account all of the necessary areas of advice that are available to him, and he makes that judgment as best he can.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —About what equipment is fitted to aircraft?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —He does not have to take a decision based on what you think is the appropriate advice. He makes the decision on advice that appeals to him.
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <break page="3558" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
       </break>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3558">
      <title>
       Employees' Share Scheme
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="WH4" page="3558" party="NP" speaker="McGauran, Sen Julian">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="WH4">
          Senator McGAURAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is to Senator Short, the Assistant Treasurer. Minister, a recent article in the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Sydney Morning Herald
         </emphasis>
         reported that the Commonwealth Bank plans to give about $100 million of its shares to employees over the next three years under proposed changes to the share staff scheme announced in the federal budget. Therefore, can you outline how employees will benefit from the budget proposal for the taxation of employees' share plans.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="DJ4" page="3558" party="LP" speaker="Short, Sen Jim">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thank Senator McGauran for his question. It is a subject in which he has long had a keen interest.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UNKNOWN" speaker="Opposition senators">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UNKNOWN">
           Opposition senators
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Oh!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —He has. It is a bit different from the other side of politics. Yes, I did notice the article to which Senator McGauran referred. It was also contained in other papers.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        It is very pleasing to note that, not one month after the budget announcement, the business community is endorsing and acting on the government's policies to the possible benefit of many, many thousands of employees. I understand, as Senator McGauran has intimated, that the Commonwealth Bank is planning three employee share plans, one of which will be offered to most of the bank's 36,000 full&amp;hyphen;time and part-time staff. Those plans have to be approved, I understand, by shareholders at the annual general meeting next month.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The government announced in the budget its commitment to its election promise to provide more generous tax treatment for employees' share schemes, which was, of course, yet another promise delivered in full to the benefit of employees from the factory floor to the executive level. That is on top of the other election promises that were delivered in full and on time, of course: the family tax initiative, the private health insurance initiative, the capital gains tax rollover relief for small business, the reduction in provisional tax uplift factor and other things that will benefit small business and average Australians.
       </para>
       <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
        <para first-indent="16">
         Now, not more than a month after the budget, a major business house, we see, is announcing plans which are tailored to take advantage of our proposal. We want to see and to encourage further participation in employees' share schemes and to encourage greater voluntary saving. We want to see more employees owning shares in their employers' businesses through employees' share schemes because through those schemes we can promote greater industrial harmony and help break down the barriers between management and employees.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         Employees' share schemes have a very important and significant role in this case. That is why we announced in the budget that, from 1 July 1996, the value of shares or rights that may be tax exempt under qualifying employees' schemes will be doubled from $500 to $1,000 per employee per year. On top of that, from 1 July this year, the government will ease the employee participation conditions for qualifying employees' share schemes from 75 per cent of permanent employees to two-thirds of permanent employees for shares under the tax deferral concession and for shares and rights under the exemption concession. That will make it much easier for employees' share schemes to meet the participation conditions with the flow-on effect of concessional tax treatment.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         Legislation will be introduced into the parliament in the next few weeks to give effect to those proposals, which I must say are in quite stark contrast to the Labor Party's policies in relation to this area. The Senate will recall that in the 1994 budget Labor unveiled a plan to impose fringe benefits tax on those schemes. Labor's 1994 budget announcement would have thrown employees' share schemes pretty well out the window overnight and it was clear to everybody but the then Treasurer, Mr Willis, that the plan would spell the death knell of those schemes, in stark contrast to ours.
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </para>
        <interject chair="0" nameid="BH4" speaker="HILL">
         <talk.start>
          <talker>
           <name nameid="BH4">
            Senator Hill
           </name>
          </talker>
          <para in-line="1">
           —Madam President, after that excellent answer, I ask that further questions be placed on the
           <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
            Notice Paper
           </emphasis>
           .
          </para>
         </talk.start>
         <break page="3559" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
         </break>
        </interject>
       </break>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3559">
      <title>
       Minister for Small Business and Consumer Affairs
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Resources and Energy" nameid="KI4" page="3559" party="LP" speaker="Parer, Sen Warwick">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —During question time today Senator Cook asked me a question about the APEC small business meeting in the Philippines attended by Mr Prosser. I do have some responses to his question.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        First of all, the overall cost of the trip, as he would know, will be reported in due course, are as are all overseas trips, but the cost was kept to a minimum, as is the practice with this government. The benefits of the minister attending the APEC ministerial conference are generally those of being in touch with SME ministers in our region and the networking that results. I can understand the strange questions being asked from the other side, because this minister happens to be a real, genuine small business operator who started from scratch.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        As to the outrageous allegations of the minister's non&amp;hyphen;attendance, I have been advised by the minister that the sessions covered Thursday, 5 September and the morning of Friday, 6 September. The minister attended sessions at which he gave reports on the 1995 Adelaide APEC&amp;hyphen;SME ministerial conference and a report on the business matching and facilitation project. During some sessions the minister attended bilateral discussions with other ministers, which is not unusual, but at all times representatives of the delegation were present at the meeting.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The minister also advised me that, like two other members of the Australian delegation, he suffered an abdominal complaint that required his absence from some of the sessions. As to the full particulars of what was discussed at these sessions, these will be provided in a full report of the meeting that is in the process of being prepared in consultation with his department.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The minister did not attend the final press conference as the only flight available for him and a number of other delegates to leave Sabu was the 2.30 flight to Singapore. Otherwise he and his delegation would have had to remain in the Philippines for another night—at considerable cost to the Australian taxpayer.
       </para>
       <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
       </break>
      </question>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3559">
      <title>
       Telstra
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3559" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I wish to add to an answer that I gave to the Senate on Monday when I indicated that, in respect of suggestions of a $400 million windfall:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        If you look at the dividend figure of $1.368 billion, you find that is only about $74 million more than the implicit figure which we had budgeted for. In other words, there is a very minor increase.
       </para>
       <para>
        I did have discussions with the Treasurer yesterday morning, and he indicated that he was having work done in his office. This morning my attention has been drawn to the fact that yesterday, after question time in the House of Representatives, Mr Costello indicated that that work had demonstrated that the special dividend in respect of 1996&amp;hyphen;97 had not been taken into account by the Treasury in assessing the extent of the difference between the budget estimate and the actual announced dividend. Once that is taken into account, the dividend is running at about $26 million behind the budget estimate.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        What follows from that, of course, is that there is no windfall of anything of the dimensions of $400 million—not only as indicated by the Australian Democrats, but as supported by Kim Beazley. In fact, on those figures, there is indeed a shortfall.
       </para>
      </question>
     </question.block>
    </qwn>
    <debate page="3559" type="Personal Explanation">
     <title>
      PERSONAL EXPLANATIONS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="WA" gov="0" nameid="DX5" page="3559" party="G(WA)" speaker="Margetts, Sen Dee" time="10.40 a.m.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="DX5">
         Senator MARGETTS
        </name>
        <state>
         (Western Australia)
        </state>
        <time.stamp>
         (10.40 a.m.)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Madam President, I seek leave to make a personal explanation.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16">
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="DX5">
         Senator MARGETTS
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Thank you, Madam President. I rise to speak briefly on the issues that the Minister for Resources and Energy (Senator Parer) has mentioned on the personal level. I will also, probably like a number of senators, be rising on the substantive issue to deal with the issues of his answer to the question from Senator Ferris.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16">
       The first point I would like to make is that the minister has in effect misled the Senate. First of all, he has said that I insisted that the committee pay for a radiation dose meter. I do not know where the minister got that information, but it is incorrect, so he is in effect misleading the Senate.
      </para>
      <break page="3560" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
       <para first-indent="16">
        What in fact I did—and Senator Parer obviously did not talk about the internals of a private meeting—was ask for information to enable me to hire a dose meter for the trip to the Northern Territory. The outcome of the discussion with the committee was that I was advised that that would be organised.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="6E4" speaker="TAMBLING">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="6E4">
           Senator Tambling
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —The company would have given you one up there.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="HX5" speaker="WOODLEY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="HX5">
           Senator Woodley
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President, I rise on a point of order. I believe that when a personal explanation is being given it ought to be heard without interjection.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You are correct. Senator Margetts.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DX5">
          Senator MARGETTS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thank the Senate. In the end, the committee secretariat said that they were offered the use of two—as I was advised originally—dose meters. In fact, the Australian Radiation Laboratory offered to let us borrow two TLD monitor film badges. They were not dose meters.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The minister said I could have known that there was a high level of radiation because I did not trust the technology. Once again, Senator Parer has misled the Senate because a film badge will not give you a reading. It might change colour if you are in a very high level of radiation, but it does not give you a reading in a particular location; you have to have it analysed later.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        We were going to four different uranium mine sites. Out of curiosity, I thought I would wear the dose meter during the visits to the mine sites and have it analysed later.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The minister has used this place to defame me on the basis of taking the interest and the work that I have done—
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="N26" speaker="ABETZ">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="N26">
           Senator Abetz
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President, I rise on a point of order. Personal explanations—and, indeed, the opposition has made this point with me from time to time—are simply to set the record straight, and are not an opportunity to make allegations against other people, for example, by someone saying that a minister has defamed her.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! With personal explanations there can be no debate. I have been listening to Senator Margetts
          <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
           carefully. I do not think she has transgressed that area yet.
          </break>
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DX5">
          Senator MARGETTS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Let me point out another area where the minister has misled the Senate in this instance. The minister said that I did the same thing at Lucas Heights. When the committee went to Lucas Heights we were not offered dose meters. Other people on the staff had them. Most of them turned them off. Only one person, one staff member, had their dose meter on—it actually was one that gave readings. That person stayed back where I was when the committee was being shown radioactive waste repositories. So there was no instance where I was wearing a radioactive dose meter at Lucas Heights. They were not offered. However, we were not permitted by the Queensland government to go to the Esk facility unless we were wearing a radioactive dose meter.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I think that the minister certainly owes me an apology. The information that he has used was based on a Northern Territory newspaper article. I was contacted by the—
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! I think you are starting to debate the issue.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DX5">
          Senator MARGETTS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —No, I am sorry.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I am sorry, you are. You may continue, but do not debate the issue. You are making a personal explanation.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DX5">
          Senator MARGETTS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, during the debate the minister quoted from an article in the Northern Territory press. I am explaining what is also incorrect in that article. The journalist contacted me and said, `I hear you also didn't get out of the bus in your sightseeing at Kakadu.' He was fishing. The delegation did not do any sightseeing on that trip. Therefore, basically, the journalist was trying to find out whether or not I had got out at Kakadu.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        During his statement today the minister also made comments about what information is available on Ranger workers. That is more the substantive issue. I believe that I am owed an apology because the information is not correct. It is true that in the circumstances of a dusty mine environment at the Ranger uranium mine, I chose to stay in the bus because
        <break page="3561" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
         I felt more comfortable out of the dust of a uranium mine. I think that is a reasonable thing to do. There is a difference between ingested radiation and gamma radiation. I believe it is reasonable for me not to be forced to breathe in dust from a uranium mine on such an inquiry.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        There are very few people who do more work on the issue of radiation and radiation policy in this chamber than I do. So if there is any suggestion that I am wasting taxpayer's money, the minister ought to find out the facts. I will be seeking leave to take note of the substantive issues.
       </para>
      </break>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <qwn page="3561">
     <title>
      QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
     </title>
     <question.block page="3561">
      <title>
       Ethanol
      </title>
      <speech electorate="SA" gov="0" nameid="8U4" page="3561" party="AD" speaker="Lees, Sen Meg" time="10.49 a.m.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8U4">
          Senator LEES
         </name>
         <state>
          (South Australia—
         </state>
         <role>
          Deputy Leader of the Australian Democrats)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (10.49 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        That the Senate take note of the answers given by the Minister for Resources and Energy (Senator Parer), to questions without notice asked by Senator Lees and Senator O'Brien today, relating to the cessation of the ethanol bounty scheme.
       </para>
       <para>
        As the Minister for Resources and Energy said, the horse is dead. If it is, it is thanks to the minister who I presume has deliberately pursued a policy of removing what I think many in the oil industry see as a threat.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I will come back to the substantive matter and deal initially with the unsourced document that was tabled in this place a few weeks ago. I ask the minister: firstly, why is it unsourced? I think it is most unusual for a document to be put down in this place in this way. Perhaps the back page is missing. I have no bibliography, no attachments, to tell me what documentation you used to put this together. There is no indication of which scientific materials, what research papers, were used and which departments were involved. If you read through the body of it, you find that several departments are mentioned.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I begin by calling on the minister to please put before this chamber all the documents he used to put together this unsourced document. If we are not able to get them, shall we say, easily and, hopefully, happily minister, we will probably have to go through the process
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
         of a return to order to make sure that we can find our way through the maze to establish how on earth you came to many of the very strange conclusions.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I will just deal very briefly with a few of the conclusions. On the question of whether or not this industry is competitive, I would argue that it was never intended that the industry would be up and running in the two years that it has had the bounty scheme. Indeed it was given seed funding to enable it to begin to get going, to begin to prove that it was going to be in the longer term economically viable and that it could be competitive.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I can find no evidence that ABARE ever conducted a current or future analysis of ethanol production in Australia. ABARE foreshadowed discussions of this kind with Manildra, the company—in particular, with some financial personnel from the company—but never actually proceeded with this review. The model that it has used incorrectly relied on Brazilian data and, I believe, some United States data. So in conducting its overall analysis, ABARE further compounds its error by concentrating on Brazil and US models, which are not representative of ethanol production in Australia.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        We then come to the question of a robust industry. As I said in my question, the petroleum division of DPIE controlled the issue of production losses. There was no chance for the industry to build up to the point where we really could begin to talk about whether or not it was robust. It seems that outside of New South Wales there was no active encouragement for expansion.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The refusal of large foreign owned oil companies to distribute and market fuel ethanol initially imposed severe limits on the capacity of producers to take up the bounty allocation in these first two years of the scheme. Despite this policy of non-cooperation adopted by the major oil companies, ethanol producers succeeded in establishing a steadily expanding market in New South Wales—a steadily expanding market for fuel ethanol with the cooperation of the independent oil companies who were prepared to look at a new product and to take what
        <break page="3562" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
         they saw as a risk. But it turned out to be quite profitable for them. I have been reliably informed that, as fast as the ethanol could be produced, it was able to be marketed through independent oil companies.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Advice from one ethanol producer that their company would, with the benefit of the bounty, produce ethanol by 2000 without any further need for support was totally ignored. Indeed, nowhere in this document do you find that any real opportunity has been given for the companies, particularly Manildra, to put their point of view or to in any way refute some of the very questionable evidence that has been put before us.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        On the question of ecological sustainability, the evaluation that we have before us at no time actually makes the claim that the scheme was a complete failure, as the minister said on a couple of occasions. In misrepresenting the Australian production model, BRS incorrectly ascribes soil carbon flux to ethanol produced from industrial wastes from annual food crops. BRS acknowledged international research on the benefits of ethanol in relation to emissions of primary vehicle resource pollutants, but also identified complexities in determining the level of any evaporative emissions associated with ethanol fuel blends.
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         (Time expired)
        </emphasis>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="JI4" page="3562" party="LP" speaker="Panizza, Sen John" time="10.54 a.m.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="JI4">
          Senator PANIZZA
         </name>
         <state>
          (Western Australia)
         </state>
         <time.stamp>
          (10.54 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I would like to enter this ethanol debate for a very short period, because it is something that I have had experience with in the past. I have had experience of trying to set up a plant to produce ethanol on farm. In the United States from around 1965 to 1970 there was the big push for ethanol production with the so-called world oil crisis.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        However, you have to face realities. Ethanol production was first tried in Australia, somewhat successfully, during World War II because there was no other alternative. Cost was not a consideration because, if fuel was required, it had to be manufactured and it had to be got hold of somehow. It was tried with reasonable success. But we do not know for certain because that cost was not compared with other fuels. At the time gas producers seemed to have been far more efficient in
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
         producing for the average smaller vehicle, although gas producers were pretty useless when it came to heavy vehicles.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The next upsurge in the idea of producing ethanol as an alternative fuel came in about 1969 in Australia. It was tried at a time when the world overproduction of wheat was on and when Australia, for a very short time, had wheat quotas. There were a few experimental plants in Australia. But, even with wheat in those days of 1969-70 at around $50 a tonne, it was not viable to produce ethanol and use it successfully even with the rising world prices of oil.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        During that time I personally got quotes from the United States to get a plant out in order to erect on the farm and produce ethanol. But when you worked out that, with the average farm production unit the United States supplied at the time, it would take virtually two or three years to manufacture ethanol that you would use in one year; the cost factor was blown out as well as not being able to get enough production. Then, of course, wheat prices took a big jump in 1973-74 and ethanol was put on the backburner again.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        We have the case here, as has come out today, where, in order to get last year's budget through, some toing-and-froing went on with the Democrats and a certain amount was inserted into the budget to have a look at the ethanol situation again. Unfortunately, economics has proven that both ethanol and the cost of production of ethanol at the present moment cannot compete with other fuels. Furthermore, as Senator Margetts would know, the Metropolitan Transport Trust in Perth—Metrobus or whatever they call it—has had a couple of diesel buses converted to run on ethanol running around for quite some time. Although the operation has been rather successful, unfortunately, the economics has not. In this day of economic rationalism, which I support, ethanol has not reached the position where it can be economically manufactured. I mean, you can subsidise and you can subsidise, but there has been nothing new over the years. Until we come to a stage where it is somewhere near economically
        <break page="3563" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
         viable, I think it has to be left where it is now, and that is on the backburner.
        </break>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="QLD" gov="0" nameid="HX5" page="3563" party="AD" speaker="Woodley, Sen John" time="10.58 a.m.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="HX5">
          Senator WOODLEY
         </name>
         <state>
          (Queensland)
         </state>
         <time.stamp>
          (10.58 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I hope that the Minister for Resources and Energy (Senator Parer) is going to return to Manildra to listen to the people employed in this industry and what it means to them, which is one of the economic factors that needs to be looked into. It may be that he has not been there—I am presuming that he has—seeing he has made these pronouncements from a great height. But I am sure that he would want to face the people whose lives it will affect. However, he does not have to go as far as Manildra because ethanol is also produced from sugarcane. There is a plant at Rocky Point sugar mill just south of Brisbane that the minister could go to and get the same kind of information from.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —It is further than Manildra.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="HX5">
          Senator WOODLEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —He lives in Brisbane.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Fine!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="HX5">
          Senator WOODLEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That is right, Senator Collins. My geography is pretty good. I hope that that is one of the economic factors taken account of face&amp;hyphen;to&amp;hyphen;face by the minister. But one of the problems in this debate is that the coalition really does not understand the importance of regional development—one of the issues we are now debating—and the need to support new primary industries, especially those involved in value adding, which is the rhetoric that we hear from them all the time. But, when it comes to actual practical on&amp;hyphen;the&amp;hyphen;ground support for regional industry, we get what has happened today. The rhetoric is not backed up.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I am devastated that another regional industry has been cut off at the knees. I cannot understand why the coalition keeps targeting rural and regional industry for destruction. The coalition constantly says, `We represent those people.'
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        This unsourced document, which the minister keeps referring to, looks to me as though was written by somebody with a vested interest. If we do not have the source, we cannot tell, but in my mind there is the
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
         suspicion that the oil companies might have been behind it.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I feel sorry for the National Party of Australia, because I have lots of friends in the National Party. But, once again, they have been killed by the Liberal Party. Like Peter Pan on Captain Hook's pirate ship, the Nats are nice people but they are trying to live with very dangerous cutthroats.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YE4" speaker="BOSWELL">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YE4">
           Senator Boswell
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President—
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I did not give you the call, Senator Boswell.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YE4" speaker="BOSWELL">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YE4">
           Senator Boswell
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Have I got the call?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I wanted to know whether the minister needed the call.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="KI4" speaker="PARER">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="KI4">
           Senator Parer
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I am happy to defer to Senator Boswell. I think I should wait until the rest have spoken. Then I will be happy to respond to this so&amp;hyphen;called unsourced document.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You might be out of time.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="YE4" page="3563" party="NP" speaker="Boswell, Sen Ronald" time="11.03 a.m.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YE4">
          Senator BOSWELL
         </name>
         <state>
          (Queensland—
         </state>
         <role>
          Leader of the National Party of Australia in the Senate)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.03 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, Senator Woodley's contribution on behalf of the Australian Democrats was an absolutely disgraceful performance by a party that just wiped out 1,000 bush children qualifying for Austudy. Last week, the Australian Democrats voted with the Australian Labor Party and removed 1,000 rural students from Austudy. It was a disgraceful performance to then get up here and cry crocodile tears by saying, `We are friends of the bush.'
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Where do the Australian Democrats stand on kangaroo culling? You don't want it! Where do you stand on live sheep? You don't want it! Where do you stand on the diesel fuel rebate? Where do you stand on the increase in petrol fuel prices?
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Senator Boswell, would you direct your remarks through the chair, please.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YE4">
          Senator BOSWELL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The Democrats engage in an absolute facade by getting up here and saying that they are the farmers' friends. They are the farmers worst enemies. They are worse than the Labor Party. They
         <break page="3564" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
          have the most retrograde policies. And they get up here and cry crocodile tears!
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="XW4" speaker="KERNOT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="XW4">
           Senator Kernot
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President, on a point of order: we are debating ethanol. We have not heard the word `ethanol' used once.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YE4">
          Senator BOSWELL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will mention the word ethanol now. Anyone would recognise that Senator Panizza is one of Australia's most successful farmers. His family started with their backside out of their pants when they came from Italy and have developed into one of Australia's biggest and most successful farmers. He knows the cost of putting a product into the ground and growing it. He knows the cost of burning up all that energy on the tractor when you plant and harvest the product.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        It is financially impossible to grow and produce products cheaper with any product other than petrol. Senator Panizza knows that. Anyone with one iota of financial commonsense—I exclude the Democrats—would know that.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        You can go out there and subsidise farmers and so on. They do not want the sort of treatment that you are offering them, namely, trying to artificially produce a product that cannot be put on the market at a realistic price. So I say to the Democrats that producing ethanol this way has no financial future.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="XW4" speaker="KERNOT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="XW4">
           Senator Kernot
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Tell the canefarmers.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YE4">
          Senator BOSWELL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —You can tell the canefarmers but they know it. As for bringing up the plant at Rocky Point, the canefarmers produce ethanol but they have never been proud of this bounty system. They never wanted it and they never asked for it. They told me last week that they do not particularly want to be involved in this artificial scheme to produce ethanol.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The Democrats have no credibility in getting up here and arguing about ethanol or any other matter that relates either directly or indirectly to primary products.
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="SA" gov="0" nameid="3I6" page="3564" party="AD" speaker="Stott Despoja, Sen Natasha" time="11.07 a.m.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="3I6">
          Senator STOTT DESPOJA
         </name>
         <state>
          (South Australia)
         </state>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.07 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will discuss the ethanol rebate scheme after the clayton's ethanol debate that we just had from Senator Boswell, as much as I would love to get into the issue of the dependent spouse allowance on Aust
         <break soft-hyphen="1" type="COLUMN">
          udy, which Senator Boswell has misrepresented in this chamber today.
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        In this chamber today, Senator Parer in response to Senator Lees, said that the Australian Democrats were, in fact, flogging a dead horse. It is a horse that the Minister for Resources and Energy (Senator Parer) killed. Two years is all this scheme has had to establish itself. It is outrageous for this government to pull the props and assistance out from the rebate scheme—the one commitment by this nation to the development of alternative fuels and a sustainable industry.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Senator Panizza made the comment that ethanol was produced during World War II. That is true. But he claimed it was because there were no other alternatives. The reality that this chamber and this country has to wake up to is that after 2010 there will be no fuel alternatives, that in actual fact the exploitable reserves of oil in this country will run out. We do not have alternatives. It is about time we established and committed ourselves to renewable and sustainable industries.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        As for the report referred to, Senator Lees said in this chamber that in fact the report that has been peddled—not only in this parliament but in the press gallery—is an unsourced report. I wonder whether it is standard practice to table reports in this place that are unsourced and that have spurious recommendations and reach dubious conclusions? Senator Woodley referred to his suspicions as to who might have been responsible for the report. I would like to ask the minister, as did Senator Lees, for all documents pertaining to the conclusions he expressed in this chamber today to be tabled in this place.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Through you, Mr Deputy President, I would also like to ask the minister to address the issue of jobs. Senator Lees and others have been inundated. Farmers from rural New South Wales properties have been ringing and faxing us in despair over job losses through the removal of this rebate. We are talking farm jobs as well as jobs associated with particular production plants. And I repeat Senator Woodley's request. I hope the minister has visited Manildra. I have been there and I have met with people there,
        <break page="3565" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
         including Mr Gordon. I certainly hope the minister has visited Manildra and looked at the processes being developed there. They have put $28 million into research and the development of renewable industries. And what has this government done? It has just removed it. How many businesses and industries are expected to establish themselves in two years, especially an industry such as this with a long&amp;hyphen;term, sustainable objective? It is an absolute outrage.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I would also like to refer to the minister's comments today regarding a report in today's
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Australian
        </emphasis>
        . I believe the minister misrepresented that report when he talked about the environmental aspects and benefits of this particular scheme. The minister referred to comments by the ACF. I would like to hear directly from the ACF, with all due respect, because I think the ACF may have said something rather different from what was reported in this place. In fact, there is a fundamental difference between ethanol production in countries such as the United States and Brazil where crops are grown exclusively for the production of ethanol. Bob Gordon of Manildra pointed out that:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Unlike Brazil or the US, where crops are grown exclusively as feedstock for ethanol and where they could be net emitters of greenhouse gases—
       </para>
       <para>
        and that is acknowledged—
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        virtually all the country (Australia) could be supplied (with ethanol) as the bi&amp;hyphen;products from existing crops grown for other reasons, such as food.
       </para>
       <para>
        So the conclusions about net emissions are a furphy. Environmentally and economically we have not seen evidence that demonstrates that the rebate scheme is unsound, inefficient or unproductive.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I support the recommendations that have been put forward by the Fuel Ethanol Association of Australia which says that Australian interests will be best met by maintaining the bounty scheme without additional funding beyond which has already been allocated. They are not asking for more money; they are asking for the status quo, for maintenance, while closely monitoring its progress with the results of vital R&amp;D programs.
       </para>
       <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
       </break>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Resources and Energy" nameid="KI4" page="3565" party="LP" speaker="Parer, Sen Warwick" time="11.12 a.m.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
         <state>
          (Queensland—
         </state>
         <role>
          Minister for Resources and Energy)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.12 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I wish to respond to some of the remarks made by various speakers this morning. First of all, let us address the document, referred to as the unsourced document, which was waved around with great gusto by Senator Lees. It was also referred to by another senator. The Australian Democrats talked about producing all the documents, but let me say that all the documents have been produced.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="XW4" speaker="KERNOT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="XW4">
           Senator Kernot
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Which document is that one?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Let me finish, for goodness sake. You are the one who gets upset when people interject. That particular document happens to be, would you believe, my speech notes that I intended to use. They have not yet been approved; they are my own internal speech notes that ended up in the hands of Bob Gordon, and he gave them to the Democrats—surprise, surprise. There is nothing magical about them.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="COLLINS">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Bob Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —How did he get them?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will tell you later. What you did get, and what I tabled in this particular place, was the portfolio evaluation, a management response to the ethanol bounty scheme. It is the complete documentation; there is no other documentation.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I am not going to repeat all the things I said before, but from every aspect this thing was tried and it was a failure. There are tut&amp;hyphen;tuts coming from the Democrats over there. It was your idea so you have to promote it, but the question is whether it is ever going to be economic. The answer has to be no. You say, `Well, you have only given it two years; it was a three&amp;hyphen;year program.' The amount of uptake in the first two years was fairly minor, $3 million but, in taking a very sensible decision after an in&amp;hyphen;depth evaluation, we have saved the taxpayers of this country $20 million.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        But that is not the only reason. Other reasons have been outlined in the full report, and that is why I tabled it. If, having read the tabled document, you still have some dispute with it, by all means canvass it. But I would
        <break page="3566" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
         say that any reasonable person in this country, having read that document, could come to no other conclusion than to abandon the particular project.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        It is not as though we are walking away from alternative energies. We are totally supportive of alternative energies, provided the proposal is practical, not pixie stuff. This proposal fits into the pixie category, regrettably.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        We have assisted the Energy Research and Development Corporation's continuing research into ethanol. We have maintained the budget figure for the lignocellulosic pilot plant—the use of woody waste. Perhaps, with the passage of time, that technology will be able to produce liquid fuels which are competitive.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The issue of competitiveness was raised. I point out again that the cost of producing ethanol is in the order of 70c a litre, with no indication of that figure coming down. The estimate of 30c to 40c a litre does not bear scrutiny. The current production of liquid fuels from oil is about 23c a litre.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The bounty amounted to 18c a litre. All up, if you take into account the excise that applies to fossil fuels and the state excise levies, you are looking at all&amp;hyphen;up support for the industry of 60c a litre. Even with removal of the bounty, which saves the Australian taxpayer $20 million, there is still an amount of 40c a litre where the alternative fuel industry has a lead over fossil fuels. I would have thought that was fairly substantial.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        I come now to the crocodile tears shed by some senators. It was made very clear to me that ethanol is a by&amp;hyphen;product of CSR at Sarina and also the gluten manufacturer at Manildra. Certainly, they would have liked it to continue—anyone likes to keep the money coming in. But it was also made very clear to me that the work being done at Manildra and CSR will continue; it will not change. This talk of farmers ringing up is just nonsense—arrant nonsense.
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         (Time expired)
        </emphasis>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="WA" gov="0" nameid="DX5" page="3566" party="G(WA)" speaker="Margetts, Sen Dee" time="11.17 a.m.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DX5">
          Senator MARGETTS
         </name>
         <state>
          (Western Australia)
         </state>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.17 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I realise that my ability to speak on my question will be limited but I want to make some comments in relation to
         <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
          today's motion to take note of Senator Parer's answer on ethanol. The issues are many and various but it is significant that the government talks about why it is not possible to support a particular industry when it has not tabled a document recently produced by the Department of the Environment, Sport and Territories.
         </break>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        That document indicates that, even without mining, there is $5.7 billion annually of subsidy by state and federal government—money that could be spent in many productive ways. That $5.7 billion could go to fiscal assistance for resource extraction industries in Australia—and that is without the environmental subsidies of $8.5 billion per year.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        If what we are hearing is correct—Senator Parer probably knows that a number of people from his department were at Monday's seminar conducted by Brian Fleay—we will have to look for alternatives to petroleum. We are reaching the halfway point of the world's petroleum resources, so the price for petroleum will vary immensely.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        If Australia does not position itself for renewable, non&amp;hyphen;fossil fuel sources of energy, especially those that can be used for car and truck engines, we will be behind the eight ball. It makes no sense at all. I can see no forward thinking by the government in this regard. It is about time ministerial responsibilities were taken seriously and that ministers acted not just on behalf of fossil fuel producers and big corporations outside Australia.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Question resolved in the affirmative.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="3566">
      <title>
       Hospital Funding
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="Social Security" nameid="BE4" page="3566" party="LP" speaker="Newman, Sen Jocelyn">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BE4">
          Senator NEWMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Yesterday Senator Lees asked me a question and I undertook to get further particulars. I would like to incorporate the additional answer in
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Hansard
         </emphasis>
         .
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         The answer read as follows
        </emphasis>
        —
       </para>
       <para justification="CENTERJUST">
        QUESTION WITHOUT NOTICE SENATOR LEES—17 SEPTEMBER 1996
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para justification="CENTERJUST">
        Hospital Funding
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Health and Family Services. The cuts in the budget for public hospital funding, some $312 million across all States, are apparently
        <break page="3567" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
         there because the States have been cost shifting. Could you please explain what has been happening with regard to cost shifting? What have the States been doing? Which States have been doing what? How are you going to spread those $312 million in cuts over four years across the States? Finally, given the enormous problems facing our public hospital system, is your government prepared to reconsider this move and, in particular, are you prepared to consider allocating the one per cent increase in the Medicare levy for high income earners directly into the public hospital system?
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Minister, when you are seeking further details from the Minister for Health, could you please ask if he will again reconsider this move, considering the pressure that the public hospital system is under. Last June—you are quite right—all States agreed to stop cost shifting, but they are insisting that they have stopped cost shifting. So can you ask the Minister what evidence he has of where the cost shifting is occurring, and who is doing what? My final question is: could you please again check whether he is prepared to look at allocating the increase in the Medicare levy directly into the state public hospital system?
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Senator Lees asked several questions about the Budget measure addressing cost shifting under the Medicare program. I indicated that I would follow up on the details of this matter. I now have the relevant information.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        There has been no cut in the Budget to hospital funding. The Forward Estimates show that Hospital Financing Grants have been maintained in their entirety across the four years of the estimate.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        No efficiency dividend has been applied to Hospital Financing Grants, despite the significant improvements in efficiency in public hospitals in recent years. The Commonwealth would have been justified in asking the States for a share of these savings, but chose not to do so.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        The cost shifting measure is not a cut to hospital funding. This measure is an acknowledgment that the Commonwealth is recouping some of the money being taken out of the Medicare system by the States, contrary to the commitment given at the April 1995 meeting of Health Ministers. Given that the amount being cost-shifted is greater than the amount being recouped, it could be said that hospital funding has actually been increased.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Cost-shifting is still going on—for example, one Melbourne hospital has 62 privatised out-patient services, some of which have been established very recently.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        States cost-shift at different levels—at this point we do not have precise data. Estimates are based on Health Insurance Commission data, and the Department of Health is confident that over the coming months very exact figures can be devel
        <break soft-hyphen="1" type="COLUMN">
         oped. The cost-shifting measure recoups costs in proportion to the amounts by which States cost-shift.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        The Government has already recognised the problems of public hospitals by its decision not to apply an efficiency dividend to Hospital Financing Grants. Difficulties the hospitals experience are related to the decisions made by State Governments about their hospital funding.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        The Minister for Health has advised me that no State has stopped cost-shifting, and substantial evidence from medical practitioners who are being pressured to change the way they treat patients in casualty in public hospitals, and also to arrange pre- and post-operative work-ups away from hospitals gives a clear indication that the practice continues, in contravention of the Medicare Agreements.
       </para>
      </question>
     </question.block>
    </qwn>
    <petition.grp page="3567">
     <title>
      PETITIONS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="10001" speaker="CLERK">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10001">
          The Clerk
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Petitions have been lodged for presentation as follows:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <petition nameids="3I6, UNKNOWN" page="3567" presenters="Stott Despoja, Sen Natasha">
      <title>
       Higher Education Contribution Scheme
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in the Parliament assembled:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       The petition of the undersigned demand the Australian Government honour its commitment to the Higher Education sector as stated in the Liberal and National Parties' Higher Education Policy (February 1996).
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       We demand the Australian Government honour its promises to:
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        maintain Austudy and Abstudy with benefits at real levels
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        maintain levels of funding to universities in terms of operating grants
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        maintain the Higher Education Contribution Scheme (HECS)
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        ensure no compulsory up&amp;hyphen;front fees for undergraduate places
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        ensure no cuts in university places.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       Your petitioners ask that the Senate oppose any intention by an Australian Government to introduce student fees, increase HECS repayments, abolish Austudy or Abstudy, or cut funding for university places.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="3I6">
         Senator Stott Despoja
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 22 citizens)
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="3I6, UNKNOWN" page="3567" presenters="Stott Despoja, Sen Natasha">
      <title>
       Higher Education Contribution Scheme
      </title>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       The petition of the undersigned demand the Australian Government honour its commitment to the Higher Education sector as stated in the Liberal and National Parties' Higher Education Policy (February 1996).
       <break page="3568" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
       </break>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       We demand the Australian Government honour its promises to:
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        maintain Austudy and Abstudy with benefits at real levels
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        maintain levels of funding to universities in terms of operating grants
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        maintain the Higher Education Contribution Scheme (HECS)
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        ensure no compulsory up&amp;hyphen;front fees for undergraduate places
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        ensure no cuts in university places.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       Your petitioners ask that the Senate oppose any intention by an Australian Government to introduce student fees, increase HECS repayments, abolish Austudy or Abstudy, or cut funding for university places.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="3I6">
         Senator Stott Despoja
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 101 citizens)
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="HX5, UNKNOWN" page="3568" presenters="Woodley, Sen John">
      <title>
       Child Care
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in the Parliament assembled.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       The petition of the undersigned strongly oppose the cuts to Childcare Assistance available for holiday absences for families who use long day care centres.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       These cuts, which both the Liberal/National Coalition and the ALP support, reduce the amount of Childcare Assistance previously paid by the Government to parents for allowable holiday absences by half.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       Your Petitioners ask that the Senate reverse its support for these regressive changes to Childcare Assistance.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="HX5">
         Senator Woodley
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 532 citizens)
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="3I6, UNKNOWN" page="3568" presenters="Stott Despoja, Sen Natasha">
      <title>
       Non-conforming Petitions
      </title>
      <speech electorate="SA" gov="0" nameid="3I6" page="3568" party="AD" speaker="Stott Despoja, Sen Natasha">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="3I6">
          Senator Stott Despoja
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I seek leave to present two petitions which have been lodged with the Clerk under standing order 69 but which have not been certified because they are not in the proper form.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="JI4" speaker="PANIZZA">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator Panizza
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —These non&amp;hyphen;conforming petitions are given on a non&amp;hyphen;broadcast day. We are prepared to give leave on a non&amp;hyphen;broadcast day.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —That is the convention in this place. Does it create any problems for you?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
        </break>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="3I6" speaker="STOTT DESPOJA">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="3I6">
           Senator Stott Despoja
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Not at all, Mr Deputy President. I will do it tomorrow. I apologise.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SF4" speaker="COONEY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SF4">
           Senator Cooney
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I am in a similar position to that of Senator Stott Despoja. I will not try to persuade the Senate to take a different course. Through you, Mr Deputy President, would I have any hope?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I suppose I should ask you whether it creates any problems.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SF4" speaker="COONEY">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SF4">
           Senator Cooney
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —No. I will not press it.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <para first-indent="16">
      Petitions received.
     </para>
    </petition.grp>
    <debate page="3568" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      NOTICES OF MOTION
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="3568">
      <title>
       Federal Government Borrowings
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="LI4" page="3568" party="LP" speaker="Patterson, Sen Kay">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LI4">
          Senator PATTERSON
         </name>
         <state>
          (Victoria)
         </state>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        That the Senate—
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        (a)
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         notes that:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (i)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          during the 1995&amp;hyphen;96 financial year about $10 billion was spent paying interest payments on Federal Government borrowing,
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (ii)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          this $10 billion will be spent annually until the public debt is reduced, and so $10 billion each year cannot be put to economically and socially better uses, such as caring for the aged, health, the environment and education,
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (iii)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          the past 5 years of Government have seen the Australian Labor Party build up a dependency on debt and deficit, with general government debt increasing from $17 billion in 1990 to $96 billion, a staggering increase of $79 billion, and
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (iv)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          if the Coalition Government had not made the necessary adjustments in the 1996&amp;hyphen;97 Budget, general government debt would have increased to $120 billion by the year 2000, an increase of more than 600 per cent in just 10 years;
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        (b)
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         condemns the previous Labor Government for:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (i)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          mismanagement and neglect resulting in 7.5 per cent of gross domestic product, or $10 billion per year, being spent on interest payments rather than on improving Australia,
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (ii)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          placing a selfish imposition on future generations by making them pay for a government which spent more than it could earn, and
          <break page="3569" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
          </break>
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (iii)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          failing to enhance national savings by increasing government borrowing; and
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        (c)
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         supports the current Government in its plans to be economically responsible, reduce debt levels and get Australia back on track.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3569" type="Order of Business">
     <title>
      ORDER OF BUSINESS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="3569">
      <title>
       BHP Petroleum
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Motion (by
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Margetts
        </emphasis>
        ) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        That general business notice of motion No. 11 standing in the name of Senator Margetts for today, relating to a review of BHP Petroleum's offshore safety arrangements, be postponed till 8 October 1996.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="3569">
      <title>
       Rural and Regional Affairs and Transport References Committee
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Motion (by
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Woodley
        </emphasis>
        ) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        That business of the Senate notice of motion No. 1 standing in the name of Senator Woodley for today, relating to the reference of matters to the Rural and Regional Affairs and Transport References Committee, be postponed till 9 October 1996.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="3569">
      <title>
       Superannuation Committee
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Motion (by
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Foreman
        </emphasis>
        , at the request of
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Sherry
        </emphasis>
        ) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        That general business notice of motion No. 222 standing in the name of Senator Sherry for this day, relating to the reference of matters to the Select Committee on Superannuation, be postponed till the next day of sitting.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3569" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="3569">
      <title>
       Environment, Recreation, Communications and the Arts Legislation Committee
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="3569">
       <title>
        Extension of Time
       </title>
       <proctext>
        <para first-indent="16">
         Motion (by
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          Senator Patterson
         </emphasis>
         ) agreed to:
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
         That the time for the presentation of the report of the Environment, Recreation, Communications and the Arts Legislation Committee on the Natural Heritage Trust of Australia Bill 1996 be extended to 10 October 1996.
        </para>
       </proctext>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3569" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      DALAI LAMA
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       Motion (by
       <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
        Senator Bourne
       </emphasis>
       , at the request of
       <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
        Senator Kernot
       </emphasis>
       ) agreed to:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       That the Senate—
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (a)
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        welcomes the Dalai Lama to Canberra and to Parliament House; and
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (b)
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        wishes the Dalai Lama constructive outcomes in his meetings with members of
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
         Parliament and all representatives with whom he holds discussions.
        </break>
       </tab>
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3569" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="3569">
      <title>
       Legal and Constitutional Legislation Committee
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="3569">
       <title>
        Reference
       </title>
       <proctext>
        <para first-indent="16">
         Motion (by
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          Senator Panizza
         </emphasis>
         , on behalf of
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          Senator Ellison
         </emphasis>
         ) agreed to:
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
         That the following matters relating to the Administrative Review Council (ARC) be referred to the Legal and Constitutional Legislation Committee for inquiry and report by the last day in 1996:
        </para>
        <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
         The optimal role and function of the ARC and the relationship between the ARC and other relevant bodies including, but not limited to, the Attorney&amp;hyphen;General's Department, other Commonwealth departments, Commonwealth merits review tribunals, the Australian Law Reform Commission, tertiary institutions, the private sector, and territory and state agencies, with particular reference to:
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
         (a)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          the benefit of a separate and permanent administrative law advisory body;
         </tab>
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
         (b)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          the membership structure of the ARC;
         </tab>
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
         (c)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          the functions and powers of the ARC;
         </tab>
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
         (d)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          the effectiveness of the ARC in performing its functions and any obstacles to that effectiveness; and
         </tab>
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
         (e)
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          the need for any amendment to Part V of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act.
         </tab>
        </para>
       </proctext>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3569" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      TIBET
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       Motion (by
       <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
        Senator Bourne
       </emphasis>
       ) agreed to:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       That the Senate—
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (a)
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        recalls its resolution on Tibet passed on 6 December 1990; and
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (b)
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        notes:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (i)
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         the ongoing human rights abuses of the Tibetan people by the People's Republic of China on religious, political, educational, language and cultural grounds and calls for the cessation of any practice which would deprive the Tibetan people of their fundamental rights and freedoms,
        </tab>
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (ii)
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         the Dalai Lama's affirmation of a commitment to non&amp;hyphen;violence and negotiation to solve conflict, as exemplified in His Holiness' receipt of the Nobel Peace Prize in 1989,
        </tab>
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (iii)
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         that the People's Republic of China's appointment of a rival Panchen Lama (the second most holy position in the Tibetan religious order), in the place of the Tibet
         <break page="3570" soft-hyphen="1" type="PAGE">
          an&amp;hyphen;proclaimed reincarnation of the Panchen Lama, Gedhun Choekyi Nyima, is contrary to freedom of religious practice, as enshrined within the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and other human rights instruments,
         </break>
        </tab>
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (iv)
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         the concerns of Amnesty International for the safety, welfare and location of the Gedhun Choekyi Nyima and his family,
        </tab>
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (v)
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         the Dalai Lama's proposal at Strasbourg in 1989 to undertake dialogue with China, and the People's Republic of China's refusal to meet with the Dalai Lama, and
        </tab>
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (vi)
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         reports by Amnesty International that there are 650 Tibetan prisoners of conscience, some of whom are as young as 12, and that the torture and severe beatings of detainees are common.
        </tab>
       </tab>
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3570" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="3570">
      <title>
       Legal and Constitutional Legislation Committee
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="3570">
       <title>
        Report
       </title>
       <speech electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="JI4" page="3570" party="LP" speaker="Panizza, Sen John">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator PANIZZA
          </name>
          <state>
           (Western Australia)
          </state>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I present the second report of 1996 of the Legal and Constitutional Legislation Committee on the examination of annual reports.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para first-indent="16">
         Ordered that the report be printed.
        </para>
       </speech>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="3570">
      <title>
       Finance and Public Administration Legislation Committee
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="3570">
       <title>
        Report
       </title>
       <speech electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="YW4" page="3570" party="LP" speaker="Macdonald, Sen Ian">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YW4">
           Senator IAN MACDONALD
          </name>
          <state>
           (Queensland)
          </state>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I present the report of the Finance and Public Administration Legislation Committee on the examination of annual reports tabled January 1996 to June 1996.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para first-indent="16">
         Ordered that the report be printed.
        </para>
       </speech>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="3570">
      <title>
       Economics Legislation Committee
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="3570">
       <title>
        Report
       </title>
       <speech electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="JI4" page="3570" party="LP" speaker="Panizza, Sen John">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator PANIZZA
          </name>
          <state>
           (Western Australia)
          </state>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —On behalf of Senator Chapman, I present the second report of 1996 of the Economics Legislation Committee on the examination of annual reports.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para first-indent="16">
         Ordered that the report be printed.
        </para>
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
        </break>
       </speech>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="3570">
      <title>
       Legal and Constitutional Legislation Committee
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="3570">
       <title>
        Report
       </title>
       <speech electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="JI4" page="3570" party="LP" speaker="Panizza, Sen John">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator PANIZZA
          </name>
          <state>
           (Western Australia)
          </state>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —On behalf of Senator Ellison, I present the second report of 1996 of the Legal and Constitutional Legislation Committee on the examination of annual reports.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para first-indent="16">
         Ordered that the report be printed.
        </para>
       </speech>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3570" type="Bill">
     <title>
      PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY LEGISLATION AMENDMENT BILL (No. 2) 1996
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="3570">
      <title>
       First Reading
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Bill received from the House of Representatives.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Motion (by
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Herron
        </emphasis>
        ) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        That this bill may proceed without formalities and be now read a first time.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Bill read a first time.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="3570">
      <title>
       Second Reading
      </title>
      <speech electorate="QLD" gov="1" ministerial="Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs" nameid="VW4" page="3570" party="LP" speaker="Herron, Sen John" time="11.28 a.m.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
         <state>
          (Queensland—
         </state>
         <role>
          Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.28 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I table a revised explanatory memorandum and move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        That this bill be now read a second time.
       </para>
       <para>
        I seek leave to have the second reading speech incorporated in
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Hansard
        </emphasis>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         The speech read as follows—
        </emphasis>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The purpose of this bill is to introduce amendments to the Agricultural and Veterinary Chemicals (Administration) Act 1992, the Agricultural and Chemicals Code Act 1994, the Fisheries Management Act 1991, the Farm Household Support Act 1992, the Imported Food Control Act 1992 and the Quarantine Act 1908.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The bill further repeals the following inoperative acts:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Apple and Pear Export Underwriting Act 1981
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Beef Industry (Incentive Payments) Act 1977
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Coal Production (War&amp;hyphen;time) Act Repeal Act 1948
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Dairy Industry Stabilisation Act 1977
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Dairy Industry Stabilisation Levy Act 1977
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Drought Assistance (Primary Producers) Act 1982
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Fishing Industry Act 1956
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Fishing Industry Research Act 1969
        <break page="3571" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
        </break>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Fishing Industry Research and Development Act 1987
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        International Sugar Agreement act 1978
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Rural industries research act 1985
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Wheat Tax Act 1957
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Wheat Tax Act 1979
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Wheat Tax (Permit) Act 1984
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Wheat Tax (Permit) Collection Act 1984
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The proposed amendments to the Agricultural and Veterinary Chemicals (Administration) Act 1992 will ensure that the national registration authority for agricultural and veterinary chemicals (NRA) is required to comply with the policy directions of the Agricultural and Resource Management Council of Australia and New Zealand. This is in accordance with the principle of the Commonwealth, state, and territory governments being equal partners in setting the policy direction of the national registration scheme for agricultural and veterinary chemicals.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        A number of the other proposed amendments are collectively concerned with the department of primary industries and energy's management of chemicals subject to import and export restrictions under international obligations such as the prior informed consent procedures. The obtaining of information about chemical products from the NRA is a factor in that management. The proposed amendments will not place any additional reporting burden on the chemical industry as the necessary information is already required to be provided to the NRA.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Provision is also proposed for the NRA to be able to impose a fee for the issuing of certificates of export. Those certificates relate to requests from the chemical industry or importing countries to establish the bona fides of a particular chemical product following evaluation of the product by the NRA. Appeal provisions to the administrative appeals tribunal will be available to aggrieved applicants in the event of the NRA's refusal to issue a certificate.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The proposed amendments to the Agricultural and Veterinary Chemicals Code Act 1994 clarify the application of the compensation provisions under part 3 of the code. Those provisions apply when certain information is provided on request to the NRA as part of the review of existing agricultural and veterinary chemicals. The related transitional provisions have also been clarified.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        It is also proposed to introduce provisions to streamline the issuing of national notices under the agvet codes. This will enable the NRA to issue one national notice rather than separate notices for each jurisdiction, and represents improved efficiency for the NRA.
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
        </break>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The amendment to the Fisheries Management Act 1991 will provide that where there is an acquisition of property within the meaning of paragraph 31 of section 51 of the constitution, reasonable compensation or compensation as determined by the federal court, is payable.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The Farm Household Support Act 1992 is being amended to ensure that the drought relief payment is payable to eligible farmers only within the period specified on the drought exceptional circumstances certificate. This will ensure that drought relief payments are used by eligible farmers to meet their basic living expenses only during those periods of extreme drought.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The amendments to reinsert drought relief payment to section 43(1) are to correct previous consequential amendments which erroneously omitted drought relief payment from this section.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The Farm Household Support Act 1992 is also being amended to exempt from the drought relief payment income test any proceeds from the forced disposal of livestock.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The amendment will correct an anomaly in the existing legislation governing the payment of drought relief payment.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        At present, for the purposes of the drought relief payment, if a farmer is forced to dispose of livestock due to extreme drought, the proceeds from the forced sale are treated as income for the period in which they are received.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        This means the proceeds are assessed under the income test for the drought relief payment. The effect of this treatment is that the farmer may be excluded from assistance under the drought relief payment or have his or her entitlement reduced.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Following this amendment all proceeds from the forced disposal of livestock will be excluded from the income test for the purpose of the drought relief payment.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The purpose of the amendment to the Imported Food Control Act 1992 is to allow persons other than officers of the Australian Quarantine and Inspection Service (AQIS) to be appointed as authorised officers.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The amendment will allow quarantine officers of the various state and territory departments of agriculture to be involved in the inspection of food imported into Australia.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        AQIS anticipates a more effective and efficient service to clients as a consequence of the amendment as it minimises, where possible, the duplication of inspection activities.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The purpose of the amendment of the Quarantine Act 1908 is to provide for a system which allows for the issue of penalty notices, which are better known as on&amp;hyphen;the&amp;hyphen;spot fines, to persons alleged to have breached Australia's Quarantine Act or
        <break page="3572" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
         regulations by failing to declare, or intentionally incorrectly declaring, goods of quarantine concern when entering australia. Initially the system will be operated at all Australia's international airports.
        </break>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The system will allow the imposition of a penalty for relatively minor offences which, under existing arrangements, would not normally be able to be pursued through the courts.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The existence of the system will be widely advertised and is expected to increase compliance with Australia's quarantine requirements and thus minimise the risk to australia's agricultural industries.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        I commend the bill to honourable Senators.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Debate (on motion by
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Foreman
        </emphasis>
        ) adjourned.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3572" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ASSENT TO LAWS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       Message from His Excellency the Governor&amp;hyphen;General was reported informing the Senate that His Excellency had, in the name of Her Majesty, assented to the following law:
      </para>
      <para style="Bill">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commission Amendment Bill 1996
       </tab>
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3572" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="3572">
      <title>
       Membership
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        Motion (by
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Herron
        </emphasis>
        )—by leave—agreed to:
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        That senators be discharged from and appointed to committees as follows:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Economics Legislation Committee
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Participating member: Senator Boswell.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Employment Education and Training Legislation Committee
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Substitute member: Senator Evans to replace Senator Crowley on 18 September 1996.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Participating member: Senator Crowley for 18 September 1996.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Environment, Recreation, Communications and the Arts Legislation Committee
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Substitute members:
       </para>
       <para>
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Senator Campbell no longer to replace Senator Ian Macdonald from 18 September to 19 September 1996 but to replace Senator Ian Macdonald for the consideration of the provisions of the Natural Heritage Trust of Australia Bill 1996.
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
        </break>
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3572" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      BUDGET 1996-97
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="3572">
      <title>
       Consideration of Appropriation Bills by Legislation Committees
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="3572">
       <title>
        Meetings
       </title>
       <proctext>
        <interject chair="0" nameid="10000" speaker="DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
         <talk.start>
          <talker>
           <name nameid="10000">
            The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
           </name>
          </talker>
          <para in-line="1">
           —Before I call the minister to move the adjournment, I advise members of legislation committees that the Community Affairs, Economics, and Employment, Education and Training Committees will convene 15 minutes after the adjournment to examine proposed estimates of expenditure. Full details of the location for each hearing appear on page 4 of today's red. The bells will be rung for five minutes before the committees are due to meet. The Finance and Public Administration Committee will not meet until 12.20 p.m. and will convene in committee room 1R1.
          </para>
         </talk.start>
        </interject>
       </proctext>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3572" type="Adjournment">
     <title>
      ADJOURNMENT
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       Motion (by
       <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
        Senator Herron
       </emphasis>
       ) proposed:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       That the Senate do now adjourn.
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <debate.sub1 page="3572">
      <title>
       Ranger Uranium Mine
      </title>
      <speech electorate="WA" gov="0" nameid="DX5" page="3572" party="G(WA)" speaker="Margetts, Sen Dee" time="11.32 a.m.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DX5">
          Senator MARGETTS
         </name>
         <state>
          (Western Australia)
         </state>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.32 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —This is the first opportunity, apart from by way of personal explanation, I have had to deal with the issues that were brought up during question time today in relation to the answer from the Minister for Resources and Energy, Senator Parer, to the question by Senator Ferris. The issues that were raised by way of a question on the radiation levels at Ranger uranium mine were in fact an effort to have a cheap shot and a bit of a laugh at my expense. It is interesting. As I pointed out during my explanation, the minister does owe me apologies and I will be expecting to receive those apologies in relation to the incorrect information he has given to the Senate.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        But there is some further information that is necessary to add to this. The workers at Ranger uranium mine—it was Ranger that was mentioned—do not have an accurate record of how much radiation they receive. The method currently being used at Ranger tends to be an average method. There is equipment in various locations throughout the mine which measure radiation.
       </para>
       <break page="3573" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
        <para first-indent="16">
         But, for cost reasons, and this was given as evidence to the inquiry, the Ranger uranium mine no longer requires all its workers in the mine to wear even the film badges that I wore to the uranium mine during the recent hearings and visits. Only those people who are virtually constantly working in restricted areas are required to wear them. In areas that are constantly dusty there are other requirements, which include breathing apparatus, and I believe there are other hazardous areas within the mine and the mill which are not necessarily related only to radiation.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         But statements about the doses that individual workers are subject to are made now on averages only. This can mean that, if there is an average of five, some people may be getting eight or nine and some people may be getting two. Unfortunately most individual workers will not have an accurate record of the doses of radiation they have received while working in the mines.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         I do not think there are many people more aware than me of the fact that being a politician is an unhealthy lifestyle. I am also aware that various forms of radiation occur from granite buildings. I am aware of the fact that the natural environment is an area where there is naturally occurring radiation. I do not tend to spend hours and hours on top of granite outcrops, but I am working in a building which is made of various sorts of emitters of radiation; I am aware of that.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         I am also aware of the fact that flying in aircraft, which I do not particularly like doing, is not a particularly healthy thing to do. There are of course levels of radiation which occur from that. In fact, I was interested in finding out just how unhealthy this lifestyle is. My initial inquiries about a year ago were to find out whether or not I could wear a cumulative dose meter for the whole of the year and get it checked from time to time to find out how unhealthy this lifestyle is.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         Senator Parer, during the course of today's very badly informed answer to Senator Ferris, mentioned that I refused to get out of the bus. Yes; in the bottom of the pit of Ranger 1 ore body, where there was still workings going on, I did not actually get out of the bus, that
         <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
          is true. At other areas of the mine site and around the mill, including the artificial wetlands to try to leach out the radiation, it is true that I did not get out of the bus; I made a choice. We had had those issues explained. I had been with the rest of the committee members and taking copious notes during the briefings that we were given by the mine staff.
         </break>
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         I think a number of people would agree with me that I was taking what is known as basic radiological protection measures at the bottom of the pit. The protection measures were in relation to the possible inhalation or ingestion of small particles of dust. The minister seemed not to understand the difference between gamma rays and alpha emitters. I understand that the actual background radiation in some of those areas that may have been dusty may not necessarily have been high. But, in the vicinity of a uranium mine, of course you are going to get uranium dust. You also may get remnants of thorium&amp;hyphen;234, or thorium&amp;hyphen;230 or radium&amp;hyphen;226.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         There is a lot of dust around a mine, and I think it is eminently sensible for anybody not to deliberately breathe in that dust if they have a choice; that is, they can see what the bottom of the pit, the mine and the mill look like and they have had that explained to them, and they choose not to get out of the bus for three minutes at the bottom of the pit. I do not see why that was considered to be such an extraordinary thing.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         We also visited Rum Jungle. Perhaps I did a less sensible thing at Rum Jungle, where there is no dust from a current mine. Of course, this mine was used long ago but it is still in a disgraceful condition. Much of the radiation from almost any mine remains at the mine site in the form of waste. The thorium&amp;hyphen;234, thorium&amp;hyphen;230 and radium&amp;hyphen;226 are still there. Of course, when they mine for uranium they try to retrieve a large portion of the uranium, but the larger portion of the radiation remains at the mine site.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         It is also true that other areas within that region have high levels of recorded radiation. It is also true that water courses within that region have been contaminated. The fact that the level of contamination in the water may
         <break page="3574" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
          be similar to the level of radiation you might read from a granite outcrop does not necessarily accord. You do not drink granite outcrops, but people are expected to drink water. If the outcomes of mining or milling activities are that radiation gets into the water system, then comparing it, for instance, to background radiation of granite rock outcrops is immaterial.
         </break>
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         As I say, you do not drink large granite rocks in general, but people are being expected to drink water which may be contaminated. Whether it is ground water through artificial wetlands, in the end that water system will be contaminated by radiation. If you create artificial wetlands, then the soil itself is being deliberately contaminated by radiation by being some sort of filter to try to stop all of that radiation going through into the ground water system. We are talking about wetlands here.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         During our inquiries we did look at Nabarlek. Once again, at Nabarlek there is waste rock, there is waste in the pit, but the majority of radiation is still there. I think it is extremely important that people do have accurate information about the implications for workers. We are adjusting them down all the time.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         It is also important to understand that, during the inquiry in Darwin, the Northern Territory government said if only a very careful check of radiation at Ranger had have been done and that, if the check that was done had not been done, the average radiation levels would have been shown to be a lot lower. I thought that was interesting. Why would people coming to check the radiation levels have a much higher reading? I asked whether those people were wearing accurate dose meters all the time and the answer was yes, they were. So why did the people who came to check the mine end up with much higher readings? The answer given was, `Senator, that's because they must have been staying in restricted areas much longer than the average worker.' I find that amazing.
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         In visiting the four uranium mines, I thought it would be a useful piece of personal information to find out, even by staying in the bus, what level of exposure there was from
         <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
          walking on Nabarlek, talking at the mine site at Ranger—we only flew over the site for Jabiluka—and visiting the appalling mess of Rum Jungle and Rum Jungle South. During those activities, yes, I did have with me a film badge, although I would have liked to have had a dose meter that showed me readings.
          <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
           (Time expired)
          </emphasis>
         </break>
        </para>
       </break>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <adjournment page="3574" time="11.42 a.m.">
     <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
      Senate adjourned at 11.42 a.m.
     </emphasis>
    </adjournment>
    <debate page="3574" type="Documents">
     <title>
      DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="3574">
      <title>
       Tabling
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs (Senator Herron) tabled the following government documents:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Commonwealth Grants Commission—Report for 1995&amp;hyphen;96.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Defence Force Remuneration Tribunal—Report for 1995&amp;hyphen;96.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Native Title Act—Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Social Justice Commissioner—Report for 1995&amp;hyphen;96 on the operation and effect of the Act.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Natural Resources Management (Financial Assistance) Act—National Landcare Advisory Committee—Report for 1995&amp;hyphen;96.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Ombudsman Act—Commonwealth and Defence Ombudsman—Report for 1995&amp;hyphen;96, including report pursuant to the Complaints (Australian Federal Police) Act.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Remuneration Tribunal Act—Remuneration Tribunal—Report for 1995&amp;hyphen;96.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Social Security Act—Social Security Appeals Tribunal—Report for 1995&amp;hyphen;96.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="3574">
      <title>
       Indexed Lists of Files
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        The following documents were tabled pursuant to the order of the Senate of 30 May 1996:
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        Indexed lists of departmental and agency files for the period 1 January to 30 June 1996—
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commission.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Administrative Appeals Tribunal.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Attorney&amp;hyphen;General' Department.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australia Council.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australia Post.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Archives.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Broadcasting Authority.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Broadcasting Corporation.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Federal Police.
        <break page="3575" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
        </break>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Film Commission.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Film, Television and Radio School.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Heritage Commission.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Institute of Criminology.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Law Reform Commission.
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian National Maritime Museum.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Nature Conservation Agency.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Security Intelligence Organization.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Sports Commission.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Sports Drug Agency.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Telecommunications Authority (AUSTEL).
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Australian Transaction Reports and Analysis Centre.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Bureau of Meteorology.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Civil Aviation Safety Authority.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Commonwealth Director of Public Prosecutions.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Commonwealth Law Enforcement Board.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Department of Administrative Services and Portfolio agencies.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Department of Communications and the Arts.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Department of Health and Family Services.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Department of the Environment, Sport and Territories
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Department of the Environment, Sport and Territories—Antarctic Division.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Department of the Treasury.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Family Court of Australia.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Industrial Relations Court of Australia.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        International Air Services Commission.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        National Capital Authority.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        National Crime Authority.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        National Film and Sound Archive.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        National Gallery of Australia.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        National Library of Australia.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        National Museum of Australia.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        National Science and Technology Centre.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Office of Film and Literature Classification.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Office of Parliamentary Counsel.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Public Service and Merit Protection Commission.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Special Broadcasting Service Corporation.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Spectrum Management Agency.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Telstra.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Treasury Portfolio agencies.
        <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
        </break>
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
   </chamber.xscript>
   <answers.to.questions page="3575">
    <title>
     QUESTIONS ON NOTICE
    </title>
    <proctext>
     <para>
      The following answers to questions were circulated:
     </para>
    </proctext>
    <answer.to.qon page="3575">
     <title>
      Bullbars
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="92">
      (Question No. 92)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="QLD" gov="0" nameid="HX5" page="3575" party="AD" speaker="Woodley, Sen John">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="HX5">
         Senator Woodley
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Minister for Transport and Regional Development, upon notice, on 31 May 1996:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (1) Is it the case that the use of bullbars on cars and other vehicles is illegal under Federal Australian Design Rule 42.9.1.1, or any other regulation or legislation.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (2) Are the restrictions on the use of bullbars being enforced by the State Governments.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (3) How many fatalities in Australia are assessed as being predominantly due to the presence of bullbars.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (4) Are there any proposals currently under consideration to develop or enforce tighter restrictions on the use of bullbars.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3575" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LD4">
         Senator Alston
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Minister for Transport and Regional Development has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (1) Australian Design Rule 42 does not specifically proscribe bullbars, but clause 42.9.1.1 seeks to prohibit external and internal projections which are not technically essential to the vehicle. The issue of whether or not a bullbar is technically essential hinges on the consideration of the environment in which the vehicle operates. Country drivers argue strongly that a bullbar is essential for rural operations.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       A more recent issue is the effect that bullbars may have on the crash performance of vehicles required to comply with Australian Design Rule 69/00—Full Frontal Impact Occupant Protection. The fitting of bullbars to vehicles after they have been sold to the market could compromise compliance with this rule. Some vehicle manufacturers have developed bullbar designs which do not adversely affect the crash performance of vehicles.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       The Australian Design Rules apply to the design and construction of vehicles when first supplied to the market in Australia. Regulation of the use of vehicles and associated equipment when they are in service is the responsibility of the States and Territories. Generally they require on&amp;hyphen;going compliance with the Australian Design Rules which applied when the vehicle was manufactured, but can
       <break page="3576" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
        make exceptions as outlined in the answer to part 2 of this question.
       </break>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (2) The State Governments have permitted the use of bullbars, and in fact Clause 96(8) of the Victorian Road Safety Act 1986 reads `Regulations made under this Act must not (a) prohibit the fitting of bullbars to motor vehicles'.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (3) The Federal Office of Road Safety has reviewed the Fatality File for 1992 which shows that of the 350 pedestrian fatalities in that year, 38 crashes involved vehicles fitted with bullbars. Of these 38 crashes, there were 3 passenger cars, 12 off&amp;hyphen;road vehicles, 4 utilities and 19 trucks. 101 vehicles were not fitted with bullbars and there were 173 vehicles for which the accident report did not record the presence or absence of bullbars.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       It is not possible with the available data to determine whether the presence of bullbars in these crashes was the predominant cause of fatalities. Pedestrian fatalities are the result of a complex set of factors and the relative contribution of each is difficult to determine.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (4) A working group comprising Government authorities, industry representatives, road user groups and researchers, is working towards resolving the long standing debate over the effect of bullbars on pedestrians, and the more recent concerns over their effect on crash performance of modern vehicles.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       There are design issues which need to be addressed. Some bullbars are unduly aggressive to pedestrians, with sharp edges and small diameter tubing.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       The bullbar working group is considering a proposal to develop an Australian Standard for the design and mounting of bullbars. The aim is to ensure that bullbars will be designed to minimise injury to pedestrians by attending to details such as the shape and projection of the bullbar as well as incorporating energy absorbing padding and addressing concerns regarding any adverse effects of the crash performance of the vehicle.
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="3576">
     <title>
      Australian Broadcasting Corporation Publication
      <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
       24 Hours
      </emphasis>
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="172">
      (Question No. 172)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" gov="0" nameid="ZW4" page="3576" party="ALP" speaker="Sherry, Sen Nick">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="ZW4">
         Senator Sherry
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Communications and the Arts, upon notice, on 12 August 1996:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (1) What are the monthly sales figures for the Australian Broadcasting Corporation's publication
       <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
        24 Hours
       </emphasis>
       .
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (2) What was the total revenue and expenditure attributable to the publication for the 1995&amp;hyphen;96 financial year.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (3) What were the principle expenditure items attributable to the publication.
       <break soft-hyphen="0" type="COLUMN">
       </break>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (4) (a) Did the publication make a profit or a loss during the 1995&amp;hyphen;96 financial year, and (b) how much was the profit and loss.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="Communications and the Arts" nameid="LD4" page="3576" party="LP" speaker="Alston, Sen Richard">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LD4">
         Senator Alston
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (1) The monthly sales figures for
       <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
        24 Hours
       </emphasis>
       in the 1995&amp;hyphen;96 financial year were: July $37,000, August $116,000, September $95,000, October $94,000, November $67,000, December $70,000, January $86,000, February $95,000, March $113,000, April $86,000, May $99,000, June $74,000.
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (2)
      </para>
      <para>
       1995&amp;hyphen;96 Financial Year
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        ($,000)
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Revenue
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Sales Revenue
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        (1029.6)
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Misc Income
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        (3.0)
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Total Revenue
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        (1032.6)
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Cost of Goods Sold
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Printing
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        406.8
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Contributors
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        173.2
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Type setting and design
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        44.8
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Other
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        .7
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Total Cost of Sales
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        625.5
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Salaries and On Costs
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        193.5
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Other Expenses
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Advertising
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        22.7
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Selling and distribution
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        168.6
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Postage
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        27.1
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Other
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        19.1
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Total Other
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        237.5
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Internal Business Unit Charges
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        20.3
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Total Expenditure
       <tab leading="NONE" type="FLUSH-RIGHT">
        1076.8
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       Loss44.2
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (3) See above.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       (4) (a) and (b)
      </para>
      <para>
       <break page="3577" soft-hyphen="0" type="PAGE">
       </break>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       The publication made a loss of $44,200 for the 1995&amp;hyphen;96 financial year.
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="3577">
     <title>
      Defence Exports
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="173">
      (Question No. 173)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="WA" gov="0" nameid="DX5" page="3577" party="G(WA)" speaker="Margetts, Sen Dee">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="DX5">
         Senator Margetts
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Minister for Defence Industry, Science and Personnel, upon notice, on 14 August 1996:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       With reference to the department's Industry Involvement and Contracting Division's annual report Exports of Defence and Related and Dual&amp;hyphen;Use Goods from Australia for the 1992&amp;hyphen;93, 1993&amp;hyphen;94 and 1994&amp;hyphen;95 financial years:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (1) Why, for tables 1&amp;hyphen;16, have details of the nature of defence exports and related and dual&amp;hyphen;use exported goods not been included except for three broad categories under schedule 13.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (2) Can a brief description be provided of the nature of each defence export, related and dual&amp;hyphen;use exports and their end&amp;hyphen;use, per country, the number exported and approximate dollar value, as in table 1.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="Social Security" nameid="BE4" page="3577" party="LP" speaker="Newman, Sen Jocelyn">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BE4">
         Senator Newman
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Minister for Defence Industry, Science and Personnel has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (1) Expanding the Annual Report to include brief details of each export would require at least a single line to cover each shipment. Clearly such a report would provide sufficient detail to identify the individual exporters and thus would breach commercial confidentiality.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       (2) In this case, it is not possible to meet Senator Margetts' request without breaching commercial confidentiality. Thus no further details along the lines requested by Senator Margetts will be provided.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
   </answers.to.questions>
  </hansard>
 </body>
</html>
