<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" "hansard.dtd">
<html>
 <body>
  <hansard chamber="Senate" date="05/09/1991" page="1191" parliament.no="36" period.no="4" proof="No" session.no="1">
   <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
     <day.start date="05/09/1991">
      Thursday, 5 September 1991
     </day.start>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. Kerry Sibraa) took the chair at 10 a.m., and read prayers.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </business.start>
    <qwn page="1191">
     <title>
      QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
     </title>
     <question.block page="1191">
      <title>
       Disclosure of Political Donations
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="DU4" page="1191" party="LP" speaker="Olsen Sen J.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DU4">
          Senator OLSEN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I address my question to the Minister for Administrative Services. Given the evidence before the State Bank Royal Commission in South Australia that the Bannon Government donated $2m of taxpayers' funds to the bank to keep home loan interest rates down for the duration of the 1989 State election campaign on condition that the donation was not publicly disclosed through the bank's books, and given the Federal Government's supposed determination to stop political corruption through legislation to introduce disclosure of political donations, will the Minister agree that money deals, such as the Bannon Government's secret donation to its State Bank to procure votes, should be investigated in the context of the Political Advertising and Political Disclosures Bill 1991 and prohibited by legislation? Or does he believe that secret money deals by governments to influence election results are acceptable, while secret money deals by individuals and organisations are not?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" nameid="XE4" page="1191" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XE4">
          Senator BOLKUS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         — What is quite striking about the question from the failed former Opposition leader in South Australia is that it comes from that side of Parliament-from those who historically have been experts in pork barrelling. I can see that the National Party is quite embarrassed at the way in which Senator Olsen has asked this question. Senator Olsen raises matters that are clearly before the Royal Commission in South Australia and obviously they are matters for that Commission.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LE4" speaker="Senator Michael Baume">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LE4">
           Senator Michael Baume
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Go back to your telephone box; you are better there.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XE4">
          Senator BOLKUS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Here he rises from the bottom of the harbour. This is a melting pot society and in all melting pots the scum rises now and again, and there it is. The matters are before the Royal Commission; they should stay there and should be assessed there.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        In terms of whether these matters are in any way related to the Bill before the Parliament, this Bill does not seek to confuse the matters Senator Olsen raises with the basic principle that honourable senators should understand, which is that disclosure legislation should relate to and provide clearly and openly for full disclosure of donations to political organisations, whether they are political parties registered under the Act or third party organisations registered under the Act.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="WW4" speaker="Senator Kemp">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="WW4">
           Senator Kemp
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —That deal is all right.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XE4">
          Senator BOLKUS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Kemp says that that deal is all right. Allegations have been made, and he in his normal conservative way in this place comes in and asserts that those allegations are true. I will not accept that. I leave those allegations to be determined by the Royal Commission. I also say that we are concerned here to ensure that our disclosure legislation is as comprehensive as is possible under the Australian Constitution, so far as we can go federally, to ensure that donations to political forces in this country are disclosable to the public.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="DU4" page="1191" party="LP" speaker="Olsen Sen J.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DU4">
          Senator OLSEN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I ask the Minister to comment on the principle as to whether this is the type of deal he wants outlawed in future? Does the Minister want to ensure in legislation that governments are treated in the same way as individuals, third parties and organisations within the community, or does he want to have two sets of rules-one for incumbent governments and one for others within the community?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" nameid="XE4" page="1191" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XE4">
          Senator BOLKUS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I could understand then, and I can understand even more now, why Senator Olsen did not, despite his good judgment in terms of football teams, win government in South Australia. The basic thing about government activities-no-one should know it more than us at the moment-is that when governments make decisions they are open to parliamentary scrutiny. We are going through the exhaustive process right now of Senate Estimates committees, where every item of government expenditure is subject to scrutiny. In those circumstances if, in the hypothetical case that Senator Olsen raises, there is a particular problem, it can easily be disclosed and, in fact, can be dragged out.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        He is talking about the normal machinery of government. He is talking about normal government decision making. He is talking about the allocation of funds. Senator Olsen can understand quite clearly that, when we are talking about that, all those activities are subject to the scrutiny of the forums of both the Senate and the Estimates committees. Of course, if there were any problem it would come out. No matter what degree of obfuscating Senator Olsen might get into, the basic point is that at the end of this process he and his party, and the National Party which, in recent days, has emerging problems with this, will have to confront the basic issue: will they or will they not support full and adequate disclosure of donations to political organisations? I am sure that what they have been about from the start is to hide their secret backers. That will emerge as this process continues.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1192">
      <title>
       Interest Rates on Credit Cards
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="5K4" page="1192" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I ask the Minister for Justice and Consumer Affairs whether he saw Mr Hadyn Park of the National Australia Bank on the 7.30 Report last night defending the current rates of interest on credit cards made available by the major banks in Australia? If so, I ask whether he believes that credit card holders should get a reduction in interest rates in line with the fall in official interest rates.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="1192" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —There is no doubt that with the nine reductions in interest rates that have occurred since January 1990 there should be some flow-on of those reductions to the persons who hold credit cards in our community. Because we are a credit ridden society, most people-I have no doubt most honourable senators-hold a credit card of some sort from their bank or other financial institution. The fact is that over those 20 months or so when there have been nine reductions in official interest rates only a few banks reduced their interest rates by about one per cent last July. I think the Commonwealth Bank reduced its rate from 24.6 per cent to 23 per cent. There is still a huge gap between the official interest rates that are now available and the interest rates that are charged by the banks for the use of credit cards by their customers. That gap should be narrowed for the benefit of credit card holders. I believe that with the nine reductions in official interest rates over the last 20 months credit card holders deserve a much better deal from their banks.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        It is true that some credit card holders have the temerity to pay off their bankcard, or whatever it might be, within 30 days and therefore they do not pay the interest rates. That has to be acknowledged. But the fact is that, whilst the banks make much of that fact, it is also true that the shopkeeper, the retailer, the restaurateur and the hotelier all pay a fee to the bank for the privilege of being able to offer the goods or services and having them paid for on that credit card arrangement. In fact, the banks do get a payment from all those providers of the goods and services when a credit card is accepted.
       </para>
       <para>
        I saw yesterday in the Sydney Morning Herald the first admission ever from Westpac's Assistant Chief Manager of Retail Banking, Mr Don Easter, that the bank's credit card operations had broken even over the past four or five years. The line from the Australian Bankers Association has been that this has been an unprofitable area of activity. I believe that consumers out in the marketplace who hold credit cards ought to get the benefit of the reduction in interest rates. There should be some reflection from that particular reduction in interest rates seen in their credit card rates. I hope that consumers use their power out in the marketplace to switch to those financial institutions which offer a lower rate of interest on their credit arrangements.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1192">
      <title>
       Medicare Levy
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="VW4" page="1192" party="LP" speaker="Herron Sen J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Prime Minister. Did the Prime Minister promise during the last election campaign that the Medicare levy would not be increased? Do the Prime Minister and the Government intend to keep that promise?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="1192" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The answer to that question is yes. The Prime Minister said so yesterday. I do not know why Senator Herron wants me to repeat it.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1193">
      <title>
       Middle East
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="SF4" page="1193" party="ALP" speaker="Cooney Sen B.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="SF4">
          Senator COONEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade. What is Australia's present position in respect of the carrying out of United Nations resolutions 194, 242 and 338?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="1193" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —United Nations General Assembly resolution 194 was adopted back on 11 December 1948. It was one of the early attempts to resolve the Arab-Israeli and Palestinian issues. Among other things, it established the United Nations Conciliation Commission to assume the functions of the UN mediator on Palestine-Count Bernadotte-who was murdered in Jerusalem on 17 September of that year. It resolved that Jerusalem should be placed under a permanent international regime under United Nations control. It also resolved that refugees wishing to return to their homes after the 1948 Arab-Israeli war and live in peace with their neighbours should be allowed to do so and that compensation should be paid for the property of those choosing not to return and for loss of or damage to property. Australia voted in favour of that resolution. Among states which voted against were, regrettably, Egypt, Iraq, Lebanon, Saudi Arabia, Syria and Yemen.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Since that resolution was adopted almost 43 years ago, there have been dramatic further developments in the region, including three major wars between Israel and its neighbours. Australia's current attitude to that resolution is that the broad issues it canvasses should be discussed in the context of a peace conference between all the parties involved.
       </para>
       <para>
        UN Security Council resolutions 242 and 338 were adopted after the 1967 and 1973 Arab-Israeli wars respectively. They call for Israel's withdrawal from territories occupied during the 1967 war and respect for and acknowledgment of the sovereignty of every state in the region and their right to live in peace within secure and recognised boundaries.
       </para>
       <para>
        As Australia was not a member of the Security Council in 1967, we were not entitled to vote on resolution 242. We were on the Security Council in 1973 and we did vote in favour of resolution 338. As I have made clear on several occasions, including through a news release as recently as last month, on 3 August, Australia has for many years supported a comprehensive solution to the Middle East dispute based on these Security Council resolutions and the principle of land for peace.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1193">
      <title>
       Social Security Leaflets
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="8U4" page="1193" party="AD" speaker="Lees Sen M.H.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8U4">
          Senator LEES
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister for Social Security to a meeting held with welfare groups in Adelaide in October last year in which he committed his Department to several measures, including the provision in every Department of Social Security office of information regarding the legal rights of DSS clients. I also refer the Minister to his response to my question of 21 June this year regarding the whereabouts of these leaflets when he undertook to make the leaflets available in CES offices also. Firstly, what steps has the Minister taken to ensure that the leaflets are available in CES offices? Secondly, why have field officers and mobile review teams not been handing out the leaflets to DSS clients as promised by the Minister? Finally, why have the leaflets on legal and appeal rights been printed but still not made publicly available in all social security and CES offices as promised by him in October last year and again in June this year?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="SOCIAL SECURITY" nameid="4E4" page="1193" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —After the last question Senator Lees asked on this matter I, naturally enough, consulted the Department to find out why the leaflets did not have the wide distribution I had promised. There had simply been an error and many of those pamphlets had been left sitting in an office. As a result of that discovery, my understanding is that they were very quickly pushed out, not only to the offices of my Department but also to CES offices and certainly to mobile review teams. In fact, from the inquiries I made originally I am quite certain that at least some mobile review teams were handing them out. I will have to check further to see whether the information I received probably about two months ago was correct.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="8U4" page="1193" party="AD" speaker="Lees Sen M.H.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8U4">
          Senator LEES
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. Information received by my office as late as Friday of last week indicates that no offices-either CES or DSS-in South Australia have these leaflets available. It seems from information I have received this week that they are also not available in New South Wales. Can the Minister please give us some date when these leaflets will be available?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="SOCIAL SECURITY" nameid="4E4" page="1193" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —All I can say is that, according to the information I had before, the honourable senator is not correct about their not being available in any offices in South Australia and New South Wales. I will have to check whether or not that is true and, if the honourable senator is right, I will give her a date when they will be available.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1194">
      <title>
       Industrial Disputes in Victoria
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="IF4" page="1194" party="ALP" speaker="Childs  Sen B.K.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="IF4">
          Senator CHILDS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Industrial Relations. Is the Minister aware of an advertising campaign being conducted by the Victorian Trades Hall Council into alleged media bias against trade unions in Victoria? If so, is the Secretary of the Victorian Trades Hall Council correct in his assertion that the number of working days lost through industrial disputation in Victoria is half the level in New South Wales and is falling far below industrial disputation figures of 10 years ago? Does the Minister agree with the reports of statements from Mr Des Moore of the Institute of Public Affairs that Department of Industrial Relations figures show the real picture that nearly half of all disputes were in Victoria during May?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="1194" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am aware of the campaign publicly announced by the Victorian Trades Hall Council against what it calls media bias. I make no judgment as to whether or not it is appropriate to conduct such a campaign and, therefore, I make no judgment as to whether the grounds exist for one. However, I make the observation about media bias that, in my experience, resort to the Australian Press Council or the Australian Journalists Association Ethics Committee concentrates the minds of editors wonderfully. Nothing brings them up quicker than to have to print a retraction in their newspapers after an adverse finding by either of those bodies.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I have been asked a question in two parts by Senator Childs concerning the level of strike activity and the comments made recently by Des Moore of the Institute of Public Affairs. The answers to those two parts, in sequential order, are yes and no. To the first part of the question about what are the strike statistics in Victoria, the Victorian Trades Hall Council is dead accurate when it asserts that disputes in Victoria are half the level of those in New South Wales. The Australian Bureau of Statistics figures for May show that the number of working days lost per 1,000 employees in the year to May 1991 was 147 in Victoria. This was 52 per cent below the rate of industrial disputation in New South Wales, which had 306 working days lost per 1,000 employees; and 37 per cent below the Australian average of 202 working days lost per 1,000 employees.
       </para>
       <para>
        Since the Hawke Labor Government came to power the rate of industrial disputation in Victoria has dropped by 72 per cent compared with that of the Fraser years. Held against a national average of a fall of 62 per cent, it can be clearly said that the rate of disputation in Victoria has fallen further than in other States. I have made statements about this, and I note, too, that those statements have not been reported. There seems to be an obsession with ignoring the facts and going to the spectacular in terms of reporting incidents of disputes rather than getting any sense of proportion.
       </para>
       <para>
        I now turn to Mr Moore. Mr Moore says that the real picture is shown in the publication on disputes produced by my Department. My Department's figures mainly show the number of disputes rather than address the index of working days lost per thousand. Therefore, the figures comment on incidents; they are rapidly accumulated. They are figures which my Department does not pretend to be the final word at all. We respect the ABS as the independent statistician in this case. Its figures come later, they are collected over time and are a more reliable index.
       </para>
       <para>
        The figures my Department collects hope to show changes and our immediate response to what is happening in the environment. To pretend that the ABS figures are not to be regarded as authoritative, in view of the survey results that my Department produces, is of course entirely inaccurate.
       </para>
       <para>
        I conclude by saying that one of the most outstanding features during the Hawke Labor Government's period of office, in terms of industrial disputes, is that the cause of disputes, as registered by the statistician, has changed. The cause of disputes in this country is no longer substantially over wages and working conditions. The cause of disputes is, as the statistician describes it, over managerial policy.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1195">
      <title>
       Work Bans at Military Outposts
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="BE4" page="1195" party="LP" speaker="Newman Sen J.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BE4">
          Senator NEWMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister for Defence-maybe these figures do not appear in Senator Cook's statistics either-to the six-week long nationwide work ban by Public Sector Union personnel working in military outposts in response to the Government's plan to rationalise and decentralise stores holding and handling accounts in the Department of Defence. I also refer to the fact that the PSU objections are based on the requirement for union members to be managed by military personnel. Has the Minister seen reports that the union is now prepared to agree to the devolution of power of civilian management at outposts but that the question of military management should be deferred? Will the Minister inform the Senate whether he will agree to this proposal or is he committed to the Government's rationalisation and decentralisation reforms? If so, what action will he take over the work bans?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE" nameid="UI4" page="1195" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UI4">
          Senator ROBERT RAY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As in most initial industrial disputes, Ministers do not take a direct involvement but require the various people to get together. The main industrial dispute is, of course, at Zetland in Sydney. We have had bans applied by the Public Sector Union because of the defence regional support review. The dispute is basically about the various recommendations concerning the devolution of civilian personnel administration delegations.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        There was an agreement reached with the PSU in settlement of this current dispute. However, the most recent meeting in September failed to conclude that agreement. That was of some surprise to me. I thought that the basic grounds for agreement were there.
       </para>
       <para>
        Following a further meeting between management and the PSU on 4 September, in which the Naval Support Commander agreed to defer implementation of the restructuring procedures until December, the PSU was going to recommend to its members that all bans be lifted. I think that the PSU is meeting with its members tomorrow to that end.
       </para>
       <para>
        The dispute, in the principal area, is still not resolved. We have not indicated that we would revoke our previous position. The position now is that a final decision will be made in December.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="BE4" page="1195" party="LP" speaker="Newman Sen J.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BE4">
          Senator NEWMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I asked the Minister whether he is committed to his rationalisation and decentralisation reforms and what action he was going to take over work bans. Is he prepared to allow this to drag on until December? He said that it was primarily at Zetland. It is, however, in fact causing work bans right around the country. Is he prepared to allow the union to dictate the tune on defence reforms?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE" nameid="UI4" page="1195" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UI4">
          Senator ROBERT RAY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That question, of course, is put in such a way as to already prejudge any answer that I will give. Of course I am committed to those reforms, of course I am not going to allow the unions to dominate absolutely this discussion, nor am I going to exclude the union from the discussion. It is representing people who have worked in the defence area for a long while. It is entitled to put a point of view. It is entitled to negotiate. I am entitled to consider its position. Whether, in the long run, I agree with its position will be a matter for those sorts of discussions to continue. On the basic principle, yes, I am committed to those sorts of reforms. I believe that, with proper consultation and proper discussion, the work force will come to agree with that position.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1196">
      <title>
       Reforms to Depreciation System
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="1X4" page="1196" party="ALP" speaker="West Sen S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1X4">
          Senator WEST
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I address my question to the Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce and refer to comments in the press in recent days that suggest that the reforms to the depreciation system announced in the March industry statement have become bogged down in discussions between business and government officials. Can the Minister clarify the situation on these important matters?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="1196" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is true that the depreciation changes announced in the March statement were to be subject to discussion between officials of the Australian Taxation Office and business. There have been a number of disagreements over the interpretation of the depreciation reform announced in the March statement. The Treasurer said yesterday during Question Time that discussions with the business community are still under way on implementing the depreciation changes announced in that statement. The sticking point is the question of the definition of effective life for plant and equipment, and that has been a point of dissension during the discussions to date.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I agree with the Treasurer that the outcome of these discussions will lead to a more sensible depreciation system. That was the objective of the changes announced in March. I said at the time of the March statement that the changes announced by the then Treasurer would have a far-reaching impact on firms and lead to a more competitive taxation environment for investment. In particular, I said at that time that the definition of effective life should help ensure that asset lives afforded for tax purposes accurately reflect the actual period an asset can be expected to contribute to the income earning process.
       </para>
       <para>
        I understand that business groups have argued strongly with Treasury and the Tax Office that the legislation should accurately reflect these words. I therefore welcome the Treasurer's comments yesterday that the Government would need to be more accommodating in further discussions with business.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1196">
      <title>
       Unemployment
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="TH4" page="1196" party="LP" speaker="Knowles Sen S.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="TH4">
          Senator KNOWLES
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister for Social Security to statements of his former ministerial colleague Stewart West that the failure of the Budget to deal with the unemployment facing hundreds of thousands of Australians was `a triumph of the ideologues and a slaughter of the innocents'. How many more innocents will have to suffer as the Minister and his colleagues allow the ALP leadership struggle to paralyse the Government?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="SOCIAL SECURITY" nameid="4E4" page="1196" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am not as aware as Senator Knowles of Mr West's comments. I have not seen them, so I would not wish to comment on them. In terms of her more general point about the number of innocents, et cetera, the Minister for Finance in one report I read this morning suggested that 100,000 new jobs would be created in the second half of this financial year as the economy recovered. If that is the case, one would imagine that there would be many innocents gaining a job in the very near future.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1196">
      <title>
       Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" gov="1" nameid="4J4" page="1196" party="ALP" speaker="Schacht Sen C.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Can the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade give details on the progress being made on whether China, Taiwan and Hong Kong will participate in APEC? Can the Minister also indicate whether countries such as Mexico, Chile and other Latin American countries will be able to participate in APEC in the near future?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="1196" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am pleased to be able to advise Senator Schacht and the Senate that it is now our understanding that the way is clear for China, Hong Kong and Taiwan to participate in APEC. The APEC senior officials meeting, which took place in the Republic of Korea just a few days ago, from 27 to 29 August, decided to recommend to Ministers that the People's Republic of China, Hong Kong and Taiwan be invited to participate at the November ministerial level meeting of APEC. That followed a long course of discussion and negotiation about the basis on which that should take place to the satisfaction of all parties concerned.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        This, of course, fulfils one of Australia's major objectives for the development of APEC. Their participation will very much strengthen the organisation, and they too will benefit from the process of consultation on regional economic cooperation.
       </para>
       <para>
        The terms under which they will participate were decided upon during a process of consultation conducted by Korea as the current chair of APEC. We understand that Taiwan will participate under the name Chinese Taipei as it does in the International Olympic Committee and the Asian Development Bank. We welcome the flexibility which has been shown by all parties which has enabled them to reach agreement. In particular, we congratulate Korea on its conduct of the negotiations.
       </para>
       <para>
        In terms of the possible further expansion of APEC to extend to Mexico or other countries on the Latin American rim, no doubt that will be the subject of further discussion and consideration, but I would not imagine that any such additions to the membership should be regarded as imminent.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1197">
      <title>
       Land Council in Arnhem Land
      </title>
      <question electorate="NT" nameid="6E4" page="1197" party="CLP" speaker="Tambling Sen G.E.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6E4">
          Senator TAMBLING
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Northern Australia and Minister representing the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs. I refer to the Federal Government's hypocritical and patronising rejection of a new mainland land council in south-east Arnhem Land to which Senator Collins has previously given specific obligations and support. Can the Minister explain why the wishes of the Aboriginal people were ignored and certainly not reconciled; why their 67 per cent Yes vote in last year's Government initiated plebiscite was dismissed by the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs as not representing a majority; why the mainland Aborigines are treated differently compared with the Aborigines of Groote Eylandt; and whether the Australian Electoral Commission, which conducted the plebiscite, has been undermined as a result of this decision?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="1197" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Once again on these issues Senator Tambling is up a tree. The facts are that there was not a 67 per cent vote in the communities that were excluded from the boundaries. The reason why the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs came to the sensible decision that he did in respect of-I am pleased to say-establishing this new land council, which I have consistently supported personally for a decade, is because of Aboriginal representations. Senator Tambling should be aware of that.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The figure that Senator Tambling quoted was an aggregate figure for the outcome of the entire plebiscite which, of course, includes the majority of the population in the area-that of Groote Eylandt, where there was a very strong vote indeed in favour of the land council.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="6E4" speaker="Senator Tambling">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="6E4">
           Senator Tambling
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —It was the same on the mainland and at Groote Eylandt, and you know it.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Regrettably for Senator Tambling's assertions, that is not the case. The difficulty was-and Senator Tambling, personally, has to take a considerable amount of the blame for this-that the progression of this land council became so hopelessly politicised by Country-Liberal Party politicians in the Northern Territory, that there was an extremely strong reaction from the Aboriginal leadership of Groote Eylandt expressed not just to the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs but also to me about the inclusion of Ngukurr.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Unfortunately, the public relations campaign for the separate land council at Ngukurr was hijacked from the Aboriginal community by the person acting as its consultant, who is now the Country-Liberal Party candidate for the House of Representatives seat in the Northern Territory, Arthur Palmer. That is a matter of fact. I might add that he got himself a very substantial little consultancy out of the whole deal, too, and feathered his nest at the same time.
       </para>
       <para>
        Representations were first made to me as the local member for Arnhem Land for a separate land council for Groote Eylandt in 1977. I have been directly involved in representations to the Federal Government since 1977 to establish that land council. Unfortunately, the divisions between the Groote Eylandt Aboriginal people and the people at Ngukurr became so intense and personal that there was legitimate concern that those divisions were going to cause very serious conflict between the two communities.
       </para>
       <para>
        In those circumstances, the Minister responded positively to direct representations from the Groote Eylandt community that at this point in time Ngukurr not be included in the land council. Frankly, with that advice given to him by the Groote Eylandt leadership, the Minister was not in a position to do anything other than take the decision that he took.
       </para>
       <para>
        It does Senator Tambling no credit to run this pathetic partisan CLP campaign on this issue which is of deep concern to the Aboriginal community in that area. There is nothing to prevent the boundaries of that new land council being amended to include those areas at a future time when negotiations between the Aboriginal people at Ngukurr and the Aboriginal people at Groote Eylandt are successfully completed-as I am sure they will be-without the involvement of any politicians. There is no reason why at a future time those areas cannot be included in a new land council. In conclusion, I commend the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs, firstly, for establishing the land council and, secondly, for responding as positively as he did to the representations from Aboriginal people in the area.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="NT" nameid="6E4" page="1197" party="CLP" speaker="Tambling Sen G.E.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6E4">
          Senator TAMBLING
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. Once again the Minister has shown that he is deliberately playing favourites between particular communities-in this instance the Groote Eylandt community. I ask the Minister to clarify his statement that the mainland communities of Numbulwar and Ngukurr did not record a 67 per cent pro vote in a plebiscite on boundaries determined by the Government, for which the turnout was greater than for Federal, State or ATSIC elections. Why does the Government now determine to play favourites in this particular area for its own political advantage and not take into account the wish of the Aboriginal people in those communities?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="1197" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I hate to confuse this political nonsense with a little fact, but I will do so. I would be interested to know how Senator Tambling can assert that there was a 67 per cent vote at the community of Ngukurr when the votes from Ngukurr were not counted individually but pooled with other ballot boxes in the area. It would be a very interesting trick. Maybe Senator Tambling had somebody looking over the shoulders of the voters at the plebiscite there.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I reiterate that the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs, firstly, is to be commended for establishing the land council after a 10-year struggle to get one and, secondly, for acting as sensitively as he did in responding to direct representations from Aboriginal people and ignoring the Country-Liberal Party and establishing the council on the boundaries that he did.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1198">
      <title>
       Air Links with Taiwan
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="PF4" page="1198" party="ALP" speaker="Colston Sen M.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="PF4">
          Senator COLSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade. The Minister will recall that on Tuesday I asked a question about Australian visa stamps placed on the passports of Taiwanese tourists and the consequence that this could have on the opening of direct air links between Taiwan and Australia. Could the Minister advise whether there have been any developments in relation to those air links since he answered my question on Tuesday.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="1198" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am very pleased to be able to tell the Senate that last night in Taipei the technical annex to the airline services understanding between Australian and Taiwanese commercial interests was signed, thus enabling airlines from both sides to now lodge applications for operating approvals, the last stage of the process of establishing air links. Those remaining technical procedures could take a few weeks and I will make a formal announcement when a precise date for the commencement of services is known.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        As I told the Senate on 3 September, two days ago, the Taiwan side did not insist that a visa disclaimer be dropped as a condition for the commencement of direct air services. The review of the disclaimer, which I also indicated that I had embarked upon when I spoke in the Senate two days ago, is a matter entirely separate from the air links issue and I shall make my decision, as always, on the merits of that case and in my own time.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1199">
      <title>
       Taxation of Swaps
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="VJ4" page="1199" party="LP" speaker="Watson Sen J.O.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VJ4">
          Senator WATSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Treasurer. Given the weight of accounting and tax evidence in Australia and overseas against the cash basis for swaps and the clear threat that the cash basis poses for the Australian financial system, why is the Australian Taxation Office insisting on this approach to the taxation of swaps?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="1199" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That is a question that I will have to ask the Treasurer to direct to the Australian Taxation Office.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="Senator Alston">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You wouldn't have a clue.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The answer is that I would not have a clue because the Taxation Office is an independent authority, as Senator Alston might learn one day. The answer is that, of course, I would not have a clue. While the Tax Office is responsible to the Treasurer, it is in its day to day negotiations and dealings an independent authority. I will get the Treasurer to direct Senator Watson's question to the Taxation Office and obtain an answer for him as soon as possible.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="VJ4" page="1199" party="LP" speaker="Watson Sen J.O.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VJ4">
          Senator WATSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. Is the Minister aware that in 1990 the Australian Taxation Office issued a draft ruling on interest in which it recommended that financial institutions tax account for interest on a daily accruals basis? Given that interest swap payments are effectively substitutes for interest payments or are analogous to interest payments, how does the Australian Taxation Office explain the inconsistency between its view on swaps in 1991 and its view on interest payments in 1990?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="1199" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The answer to the first part of the question is that because I have a great respect for Senator Watson's integrity, I am now aware of the facts which he has put to me. As to why the Taxation Office changed its view, I provide the same answer as I did to the original question: I will find out for him and will provide him with an answer as soon as possible.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1199">
      <title>
       East Timor
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" nameid="TW4" page="1199" party="AD" speaker="Bourne Sen V.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="TW4">
          Senator BOURNE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade. Is the Minister aware of recent reports from Amnesty International of an accelerating pattern of short term detentions, torture and ill-treatment of suspected political opponents of the Indonesian Government in East Timor, including at least 30 apparent extra-judicial executions by Indonesian security forces? What steps have been taken by Australia to attempt to improve the human rights of the East Timorese? Will Australia support Portugal's requests to the United Nations for a parliamentary delegation to visit East Timor?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="1199" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am, of course, aware of the Amnesty report which contains the allegations referred to by Senator Bourne. The important thing to appreciate about that report is that it covers the whole of the three years since 1988. It was submitted to the UN in August and forms part of Amnesty's regular submissions to the UN on human rights in East Timor.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I certainly agree that there have been significant human rights problems in East Timor over the past three years and in particular, as I have acknowledged before in the Senate, in the period of September, October and November last year when the Indonesian authorities were responding to what they perceived to be an increase in security problems. Our embassy's assessment, based on a visit to the province again in June this year, is that the human rights situation is now significantly better. I do not think it is fair to characterise the overall situation as one of accelerating human rights abuse, as Senator Bourne suggested.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Australian Government has attempted to improve the human rights situation of the East Timorese by, first of all, making it clear on many occasions to the Indonesian Government that we support the universal observance of fundamental human rights in all countries. We have done that very clearly and very consistently, both at the bilateral level and in multilateral forums, such as the UN Commission on Human Rights. Secondly, by making representations to the Indonesian authorities whenever we have received credible, specific reports of human rights abuse, I and my ambassador in Jakarta have regularly registered concerns at those reports with Indonesian Ministers.
       </para>
       <para>
        The remaining point that was raised by Senator Bourne was about the parliamentary delegation from Portugal. Let me say simply that the Australian Government supports the idea of a visit to East Timor by a Portuguese parliamentary delegation and we do hope that such a visit will help Portugal and Indonesia overcome their remaining differences over East Timor.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1200">
      <title>
       Conduct of Federal Court Judges
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="EU4" page="1200" party="NP" speaker="O'Chee Sen W.G.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="EU4">
          Senator O'CHEE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister for Justice and Consumer Affairs. I seek advice from the Minister as to what is considered appropriate conduct for Federal Court judges. Where a Federal Court judge hears a matter in which one of the parties is a corporation of which he is the chairman, would the Minister expect that judge to disqualify himself from the hearing of the matter further and would a serious conflict of interest exist if the judge were to continue with the matter and make a finding in favour of the corporation of which he is the chairman?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="1200" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I regard it as unfortunate that Senator O'Chee should raise this matter in such a general way because I think it could be taken as an attack on any number of members of that bench of the Federal Court, under parliamentary privilege and without any real evidence. I am not asking that in a supplementary question evidence be offered of the particular case. I believe Senator O'Chee ought to make available to me in specific form any misgivings or concerns he has and I will ensure that the Attorney-General gives consideration to such evidence as he might bring forward.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="EU4" page="1200" party="NP" speaker="O'Chee Sen W.G.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="EU4">
          Senator O'CHEE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I am asking for an indication of the Government's attitude on what is the accepted and expected conduct of Federal Court judges. I hope the Minister will be able to answer that question now.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="1200" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I believe that judges on the Federal Court Bench have a good understanding of their responsibilities in relation to the hearing of cases, as is generally the case with those on the benches of all superior courts. As I said, I will not answer a question in such general terms, but if Senator O'Chee has anything specific he wants to put before the Attorney-General, which I then would take to be transmittable to the Chief Judge of the Federal Court, I will facilitate the transmission of such misgivings or evidence.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1200">
      <title>
       Unionism at Robe River
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" gov="1" nameid="ZF4" page="1200" party="ALP" speaker="Crowley Sen R.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZF4">
          Senator CROWLEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister for Industrial Relations. Is it a fact that Robe River Mining is seeking to prohibit union membership among certain members of its staff under section 118 of the Industrial Relations Act? Is this, in effect, a case of the company seeking compulsory non-unionism? Can the Minister advise what the Government's attitude is to this use of section 118 by Robe River? Can the Minister also advise how many individual legal actions the company has initiated against the unions which represent its employees since 1986, when it began its industrial campaign? Can he advise what the financial cost has been to unions and their members by the company's apparent policy of constantly tying unions up in legal actions or threats of legal action?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="1200" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The answers to the questions are yes, yes, and it is an inappropriate use of section 118. If I can now turn to the other questions, I have to say that Robe River is the self-proclaimed leader of the New Right in Australia. It is certainly militant and it has set about systematically trying to deny the rights of its employees by the use of dismissals and stand-downs. It has a record of defying orders made by the Australian Industrial Relations Commission. It is indeed a vexatious litigant, appealing even the most unremarkable decisions of the Industrial Relations Commission-one imagines in order to act out the New Right theory that one should excessively resort to the law.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SE4" speaker="Senator Bishop">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SE4">
           Senator Bishop
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr President, on a point of order: I wonder whether you would ask the Minister to tell the Senate whether he is speaking as a Minister of the Crown or as a paid-up trade union official?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —There is no point of order.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The most recent issues concern actions regarding the Australian Seamen's Union and Cape Lambert Services, which is a wholly owned subsidiary of Robe River and supplies the tugs for the towing of the bulk carriers to the wharf. Since 1989, in cases involving the Seamen's Union there have been some eight appeals by Robe River to the Industrial Relations Commission's Full Bench and two appeals to the High Court. The actions have all been about whether or not the same conditions that apply at all other ports in Australia should apply at this particular port, Cape Lambert.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        In essence, the outcome of these appeals has been for the Seamen's Union to be upheld in all cases. Now that the appeals system has been exhausted and Robe has had nowhere to go, on Friday, 28 August, Cape Lambert Services went into voluntary liquidation. A new company, Westug, was formed immediately to take over the role of Cape Lambert Services. It now appears the case that the Seamen's Union is going to be proceeded against by the new company in the same way as it was by Cape Lambert. The outcome of all the appeals and the wins they have recorded are set at naught and so the process begins from scratch.
       </para>
       <para>
        The conditions are that the Seamen's Union wishes simply that the same conditions that apply in all other ports in Australia apply here. I think that it is reasonable in the circumstances to observe, and I do so, that this is a contrivance, and a false contrivance, when at the end of an appeal outcome in which a company is then expected to abide by a decision, it goes into voluntary liquidation and another company is contrived to take its place and the process commences again. It is not unreasonable either to speculate that should the same processes be replicated with this company, as one would expect they would be, when the outcome is arrived at again and the final appeal source is exhausted, the existing company will go into voluntary liquidation and a new company will start.
       </para>
       <para>
        In all those circumstances one has to say that this is behaviour within the law, but the law is an ass if it permits behaviour of this sort. These are the actions of an employer version of the BLF. In the circumstances I understand that the Seamen's Union is contemplating a nationwide strike. I earnestly counsel the Seamen's Union not to proceed to do that. It is not in the national interest, nor is it in the union's interest, irrespective of how one can feel that it has been provoked in these circumstances. But it means that some examination of this type of behaviour has to be undertaken so that it can be ended.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1201">
      <title>
       Strike by Meat Inspectors
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="UW4" page="1201" party="LP" speaker="Crane Sen W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UW4">
          Senator CRANE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister for Industrial Relations to the meat inspectors strike at Wodonga Meats on Friday, 30 August.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="Senator Faulkner">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator Faulkner
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Ah!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UW4">
          Senator CRANE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The honourable senator can say `Ah' as much as he likes. This was a strike that was in direct defiance of award conditions which stipulate when rostered days off will be taken. First, will the inspectors who defied the award provision be disciplined? Secondly, will the Government, in its capacity as the employer, take action available to it under the Industrial Relations Act against the Public Sector Union for breach of award?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="1201" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President--
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="WW4" speaker="Senator Kemp">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="WW4">
           Senator Kemp
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Try to be consistent on this one in view of your previous answer.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order, Senator Kemp!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The Government is consistent in all these affairs. If there are breaches of the award, there are remedies available to the offended against parties, and those remedies can be resorted to, and should be, if there is any concern in the minds of those parties. In industrial disputation it is often far more sensible to consider what is the issue in dispute and come to terms that will settle that particular issue than immediately, and without consideration of what the justification of the initial grievance might be, resort to the heavy handed actions of penalties. Nonetheless, penalties exist and if there is behaviour by an organisation which offends against the law, then that action should be taken.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="UW4" page="1201" party="LP" speaker="Crane Sen W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UW4">
          Senator CRANE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         — I ask a supplementary question. Will the Minister advise what action will be taken, as the Government is the employer, to reimburse abattoirs and meat workers that suffered commercial damage or wage losses due to the strike, given that the Meat Inspection Service is legislatively compulsory and something for which the abattoirs pay full cost recovery of $67,000 per inspector per year?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="1201" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —In these circumstances, I believe that there is no obligation on the Commonwealth to reimburse anyone in this particular case. I will have a look at the matter but, as I have said, on my understanding of this issue I do not think there is any obligation. It is not appropriate in a case like this that there be any compensation paid.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1202">
      <title>
       Permanent Building Society, Western Australia
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="NE4" page="1202" party="ALP" speaker="Beahan Sen M.E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NE4">
          Senator BEAHAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I ask the Minister for Social Security whether his attention has been drawn to claims made through the media by Adrian Nizzola, former manager of the Permanent Building Society in Western Australia, that the Department of Social Security had early warning of the freezing of the Society's funds. Did the Department of Social Security try to stop payments to the Society on Thursday before it became public knowledge that the Society's funds had been frozen? What arrangements have now been made for pensioners and beneficiaries to access their last fortnight's payment?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="SOCIAL SECURITY" nameid="4E4" page="1202" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I answered a question on this yesterday morning. Later in the day, despite a denial, Mr Nizzola, the former managing director of the Society, in some radio interviews made the specific allegation that an attempt had been made to stop payments on Thursday. I can repeat only what I said in the Senate before, that the Department did not have knowledge and that no attempt was made to stop payments on Thursday. In fact, had the Department had knowledge on Thursday, one wonders why a Reserve Bank cheque should have gone to Westpac for the Society for the payment of JSA and Newstart benefits on Friday. We had been unable to stop that because we did not find out about it until after the close of business on Friday when there were media reports in Perth about the fate of the Society's funds. Obviously, it is normal for the Department to try to get cheques into any building society of this kind on a working day prior to when our beneficiaries would begin to withdraw money. In fact, we were successful only in stopping payments that would otherwise have been able to be claimed on the Tuesday.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Having said that, in answer to the final part of Senator Beahan's question, my Department has had discussions with the administrator and my office has had discussions with the Attorney-General in Western Australia. I can now announce that the administrator has agreed that social security payments credited to the Permanent Building Society during the week ended 30 August can be withdrawn in full. That can be done after the production of a letter from the Department, which is going out today to every pensioner and beneficiary so affected.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="JI4" speaker="Senator Panizza">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator Panizza
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —What about the other old people with money in there?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That will mean that the last payment received can be accessed in full by all the beneficiaries. If beneficiaries are concerned about the balance of their accounts, in accordance with the administrator's normal rules, they will have to satisfy the hardship provisions. But the administrator has accepted, in answer to Senator Panizza's interjection, that pensioners and beneficiaries-not being the wealthy people in our society but people who do draw out the great bulk of their payments every week-would be in great hardship were they not able to access their last payment. That is why the administrator has agreed with exactly what was said.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1203">
      <title>
       Yugoslavia
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="1203" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BH4">
          Senator HILL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to the appalling situation in Yugoslavia and, in particular, to reports overnight that the Yugoslav armed forces have effectively cut Croatia in half. I remind the Minister of the statement over a week ago by the Prime Minister, Mr Hawke, that he had discussed with President Bush the option of United Nations involvement to try to bring to an end this tragedy. Now that it appears that the European efforts are failing, what has the Government done to pursue the option discussed by the Prime Minister and Mr Bush?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="1203" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Although I agree with Senator Hill that the situation in Yugoslavia at the moment is very distressing in the sense that the cease-fires manifestly have not held and heavy fighting continues, it is nonetheless premature to say that the European peace process has come to a conclusion. A few days ago, on 2 September, the European Community, along with the Yugoslav Federal Government and the six republican governments, signed a cease-fire agreement calling for a halt to the use of force and the separation of the warring forces. Compliance with the cease-fire agreement is not the subject at the moment of any monitoring arrangement, but it is proposed to be observed by an international monitoring group.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        According to the EC plan, the next steps are the holding of a peace conference in The Hague with all the parties, starting on 7 September-this weekend-and chaired by Lord Carrington, together with the establishment of an arbitration commission to examine the differences of the parties in Yugoslavia. The EC plan rejects any changes to borders brought about by force. There are unspecified threatened additional measures, no doubt involving, among other things, economic sanctions, should one of the parties not agree to these conditions.
       </para>
       <para>
        Our position has been to warmly endorse this exercise by the EC and the Yugoslav parties concerned and to urge all parties to respect the terms of the cease-fire agreement and to get around a table and try to resolve the issue. I think it is still possible for the issue to be resolved in this way. The option of United Nations involvement, which was canvassed by the Prime Minister with President Bush, is still a rather difficult option to implement and operationalise to the extent that we are still talking about an internal situation within traditional Yugoslav borders not yet spilling out elsewhere. Although there have been recent precedents of a kind in international affairs in the context of the Gulf, the Kurds, and so on, which suggests an evolving disposition on the part of the UN to be willing in extreme circumstances, through the Security Council and other organs, to look at these issues, it is universally acknowledged that at the moment this is a very difficult issue on which to get agreement.
       </para>
       <para>
        So although it remains an option which we will of course take further in the event that the European peace process breaks down, we and the United States both want to give priority to the European peace efforts. We certainly would not be minded to try to pre-empt those efforts while they still have any life in them. I repeat that it is premature to make the judgment that they do not have any life in them.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="1203" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BH4">
          Senator HILL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I put it to the Minister in the form of a supplementary question that it is very difficult to maintain that the European proposals have not broken down when the cease-fire has obviously been flagrantly abused by the Yugoslav armed forces. Acknowledging that the Minister has said that the UN proposal is a difficult one, would it not have been useful to use this time available to pursue that option and to look at ways of overcoming the obvious difficulties because the alternative may be too late?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="1203" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I understand what Senator Hill is saying. Obviously, what our policy response should be is under continuing and very close review. I repeat that for the moment we do want to see how the European process works. It is a very hands-on one involving not only the European Community but indeed the whole CSCE apparatus, with the EC operating as the delegate of the CSCE. It is manifestly an apparatus without any of the constitutional or charter constraints that afflict the UN. On the face of it, it does seem likely to be a more productive route for reaching a resolution of this, given the constraints that exist with the UN.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Obviously the UN option is very much alive, but I think it is premature to try to take it any further at this stage. However, I repeat that we will obviously be keeping the situation under close review.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="4F4" speaker="Senator Button">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="4F4">
           Senator Button
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr President, I ask that further questions be placed on the Notice Paper.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1204">
      <title>
       Income Tax Simplification Unit
      </title>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="1204" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —On 16 August Senator Watson asked me, as Minister representing the Treasurer, a question about tax simplification. I recall the question because he made the charitable suggestion that the departure of Treasurer Keating was a loss to the country. I concur with that view. The departure from the front bench of any Minister in this Government is a loss. The answer the Treasurer has provided is somewhat complicated, so I seek leave to have it incorporated in Hansard.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <para>
        The answer read as follows-
       </para>
       <para>
        The income tax simplification project was a joint review by officers from the Australian Taxation Office and the Treasury. The work of the review team was completed (not abandoned) in August 1990 with a submission to Government.
       </para>
       <para>
        After due consideration of the submission, the Treasurer through a Press Release issued on 13 December 1990, announced the first tranche of simplification measures including self-assessment and foreign source employment income and indicated that into the future, simplification proposals for change would be implemented incrementally.
       </para>
       <para>
        Rather than an abandonment of simplification, the Government has therefore foreshadowed its ongoing evolution. Subsequent measures have included a review of depreciation as announced in the March Industry Statement, 1991.
       </para>
       <para>
        Moreover, it should be noted that issues of simplification are intrinsic to the manner in which legislative and administrative proposals are formulated within the Australian Taxation Office which seeks to bring forward proposals which minimise costs of administration and of compliance to the community.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1204">
      <title>
       Minister for Aboriginal Affairs
      </title>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="1204" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Yesterday Senator Crichton-Browne asked me a question as to whether a Mr Ken Colbung had been `thrown out' of the office of the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs. The Minister for Aboriginal Affairs has advised me that the answer to the honourable senator's question is no.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1204">
      <title>
       Minister for Aboriginal Affairs
      </title>
      <speech electorate="WA" nameid="XF4" page="1204" party="LP" speaker="Crichton-Browne Sen N.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XF4">
          Senator CRICHTON-BROWNE
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate take note of the Minister's answer.
       </para>
       <para>
        This will take just a couple of minutes. Information was given to me by a very senior Aboriginal who came directly to my office from the Minister's office. He is a longstanding Chairman of the Institute--
       </para>
       <para>
        Government senators interjecting-
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="BH4" speaker="Senator Hill">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="BH4">
           Senator Hill
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr President, I raise a point of order. I ask you to ask Senator Faulkner to withdraw that remark.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Senator Faulkner, I ask you to withdraw the comment you made.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="Senator Faulkner">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator Faulkner
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr President, I cannot withdraw any comment because all I did was laugh. I made no comment.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! I did not hear the interjection. I thought it was Senator Faulkner, but obviously it was not.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XF4">
          Senator CRICHTON-BROWNE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The facts have been given directly to me by Mr Colbung. He has an impeccable reputation in terms of the job that he does and the role that he has played in the Aboriginal community not only in Western Australia but Australia-wide. In particular, the Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies, of which Mr Colbung is Chairman, and its Principal are having a great deal of difficulty making any contact with the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs (Mr Tickner). They had asked the Minister to open their day for Aboriginal Week at the Institute. My understanding is that he had accepted but then declined. He was asked to visit the Institute some time during the day, but he could not manage that. Mr Colbung asked whether he could see the Minister, and the Minister could not even do that.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        So Mr Colbung presented himself at Parliament House. This caused some consternation in the Minister's office. The Minister then agreed to see him. He spoke to Mr Colbung for 10 minutes and then in the midst of the conversation, in a very unpleasant and angry way, he got up, slammed his book shut and said, `If you're not leaving I am'. He then walked out. Mr Tickner's staff then told Mr Colbung in a very unsavoury way that he had to get out, too. He left and came to my office. What Mr Colbung does not know is that the staff in my office were contacted by the Minister's staff and told that, if Mr Colbung caused any trouble for me in my office, they would come and rescue me because they were responsible for him as they had signed him in.
       </para>
       <para>
        Government senators interjecting-
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="4J4" speaker="Senator Schacht">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="4J4">
           Senator Schacht
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Ha, ha!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XF4">
          Senator CRICHTON-BROWNE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I note that it is very amusing for the Government. Government senators can have a lot of laughs; but there is more to come. I did not see them, but I understand from my staff that some time later two of Mr Tickner's staff arrived at my office door to inform my staff that Mr Colbung was unable to move around the building because he had a pass which required that he be accompanied and that they had come to get him. I did not tell Mr Colbung about that either, because I thought it was a bit humiliating. Senator Schacht must think that is very funny.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="4J4" speaker="Senator Schacht">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="4J4">
           Senator Schacht
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You have never had any interest at all in Aboriginal affairs.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XF4">
          Senator CRICHTON-BROWNE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That shows the ignorance in which Senator Schacht basks. Mr Colbung came to my office because of my reputation in Western Australia for care and interest in Aboriginal affairs. I assume he also came because I am a past member of the Australian Institute of Aboriginal Studies.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="Senator Collins">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —This was going to be a couple of minutes-to quote you, senator.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XF4">
          Senator CRICHTON-BROWNE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I did not expect the response that we have received from the Government. Ultimately, when my office was able to assure Mr Tickner's office that I was quite safe and that Mr Colbung could be moved around the building without the able assistance of Mr Tickner's staff, Mr Colbung was accompanied by one of my staff to Mr Chaney's office.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        If I were to speculate, I would have to say that the Minister realised how disgracefully both Mr Colbung and his wife had been treated. When Mrs Colbung dared to make a comment during the conversation, one of the staff said, `What would you know about Aboriginal affairs? You are not even Aboriginal'. I suspect that the Minister's office was highly embarrassed. On sober reflection, they thought that if they could extricate themselves and get Mr Colbung out of my office before he told me the sad sorry story, they would relieve themselves of some embarrassment.
       </para>
       <para>
        I put it to Senator Collins, with respect, that if he is suggesting that Mr Colbung was not thrown out of Mr Tickner's office, he is misleading the Senate and has been misled by Mr Tickner. If Senator Collins would care to ring Mr Colbung personally, I am sure that he would reinforce everything I have thus far told the Senate and that which he told the ABC this morning.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1206">
      <title>
       Minister for Aboriginal Affairs
      </title>
      <speech electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="1206" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Northern Territory-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.11 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will be brief, but a response is required. I am sorry to hear, I must say, so soon after commending the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs (Mr Tickner) in Question Time, that any offer to rescue Senator Crichton-Browne was made by the Minister's office. I will take that matter up with his office.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The reason I am responding to this is that I have known Mr Ken Colbung personally for a very long time. I not only respect him but also like him; I have a lot of time for him. I am sorry to hear that he was involved in any kind of difficulty in Parliament House. I can assure you, Mr President, that on a personal level I will contact Ken Colbung, whom I know well.
       </para>
       <para>
        I reiterate that I put to the Minister's office yesterday Senator Crichton-Browne's question, which was that Ken Colbung was thrown out of the Minister's office. The advice I received from the Minister was that that was not correct.
       </para>
       <para>
        Question resolved in the affirmative.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1206">
      <title>
       Strike by Meat Inspectors
      </title>
      <speech electorate="WA" nameid="UW4" page="1206" party="LP" speaker="Crane Sen W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UW4">
          Senator CRANE
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I seek leave to move a motion that the Senate take note of the answer given by the Minister for Industrial Relations (Senator Cook) to my question and to make a few brief remarks.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5I4" speaker="Senator McMullan">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5I4">
           Senator McMullan
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —How brief?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UW4">
          Senator CRANE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —A couple of minutes.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5I4" speaker="Senator McMullan">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5I4">
           Senator McMullan
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —The same two minutes that Senator Crichton-Browne used?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UW4">
          Senator CRANE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Come on!
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Is leave granted?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5I4" speaker="Senator McMullan">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5I4">
           Senator McMullan
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Of course leave is granted. I would appreciate it if Senator Crane does not abuse the leave as much as Senator Crichton-Browne did.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>
         Leave granted.
        </para>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UW4">
          Senator CRANE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate take note of the answer.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="NG4" speaker="Senator Lewis">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="NG4">
           Senator Lewis
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I rise on a point of order, Mr President. On behalf of Senator Crichton-Browne, I take strong exception to Senator McMullan's comment. Senator Schacht was continually interjecting throughout the course of Senator Crichton-Browne's remarks. Senator Faulkner, Senator Jones and Senator Walsh were laughing. The point of order is--
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Resume your seat. Senator Lewis knows that he has no right to speak. Leave was granted. Senator Lewis-I am--
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! You did not seek leave at all.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="NG4" speaker="Senator Lewis">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="NG4">
           Senator Lewis
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I am not seeking leave. I am asking that the Parliamentary Secretary be required to withdraw the allegation against Senator Crichton-Browne. It was a disgraceful allegation. All of the performance was on the other side of the chamber throughout a very sensible and rational speech by Senator Crichton-Browne.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! It was a debating point. There is no point of order.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UW4">
          Senator CRANE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —In speaking briefly to this point, I want to pose some questions. Following the Minister's answer, the first one is how long do we have to put up with the anarchy in the meat industry, particularly in relation to AQIS inspectors, before some direct action is taken? Secondly, in his answer to my supplementary question on reimbursement to the abattoirs and the meat workers, he indicated that, as far as he was concerned, the Government had no responsibility.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I believe it was in 1987 in the case of Mudginberri that the Judicial Appeals Tribunal found against the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy, Mr Kerin, for not supplying the inspectors for a compulsory service paid for by the industry through the levies from the abattoir amounting to $67,000 per inspector. A damages case is being lodged against the Department of Primary Industries and Energy and, because of that and the lack of action by the Government, which is the employer in this case, taxpayers' funds once again are being put at risk. In the case of Mudginberri, it cost the taxpayers of this country $68,000. How long is the Minister going to allow the anarchy in the meat industry, which is now being aided and abetted by the Government, by Wally Curran and the inspectors, to continue?
       </para>
       <para>
        Question resolved in the affirmative.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </question.block>
    </qwn>
    <petition.grp page="1207">
     <title>
      PETITIONS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10001" speaker="The Clerk">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10001">
          The Clerk
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Petitions have been lodged for presentation as follows:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <petition nameids="TW4; IG4" page="1207" presenters="BOURNE">
      <title>
       Smokefree International Flights
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled:
      </para>
      <para>
       We, the undersigned,
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) are alarmed at the health and safety hazards that arise from the smoking of cigarettes and other tobacco products on international airlines, a dangerous practice banned within Australia;
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) call for the International Civil Aviation Organisation (ICAO) of which Australia is a member to set a standard for smokefree international flights; standards set by ICAO must be agreed to by its 162 member nations.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="TW4">
         Senator Bourne
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 100 citizens) and
        </from>
       </presenter>
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator Vallentine
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 120 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="IG4; FE4" page="1207" presenters="VALLENTINE; ZAKHAROV">
      <title>
       Uranium: Mining and Export
      </title>
      <para>
       To the honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
      </para>
      <para>
       That your petitioners request that the Australian Government take steps immediately to stop the mining and export of uranium
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator Vallentine
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 80 citizens) and
        </from>
       </presenter>
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="FE4">
         Senator Zakharov
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 110 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="LD4" page="1207" presenters="ALSTON">
      <title>
       Tobacco Advertising
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled: the humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
      </para>
      <para>
       That we the undersigned call for urgent action by our Federal Parliament and all government agencies concerned with Health and Sport to impose an immediate ban on the incidental advertising of tobacco products on television and provide for alternative funding to replace tobacco sponsorship. That tobacco sponsorship of sporting events and participants openly flouts the 1976 Federal law prohibiting tobacco advertising on TV and radio. That our Parliament immediately end this association between healthy sports and the deaths of 18,300 people in Australia each year from tobacco-related diseases.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners in duty bound will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="LD4">
         Senator Alston
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 25 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="SF4" page="1207" presenters="COONEY">
      <title>
       Consumption Tax
      </title>
      <para>
       To the honourable the President and members of the Senate assembled in Parliament:
      </para>
      <para>
       The petition of certain citizens of Australia draws to the attention of the Senate proposals to introduce a 15% consumption tax on bread, milk, eggs, meat, fruit, vegetables and clothing which will increase food costs for those who have low incomes and have to spend most of their income on food, heating and clothing.
      </para>
      <para>
       Your petitioners therefore pray that the Senate will not agree to such a tax.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="SF4">
         Senator Cooney
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 72 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="BE4" page="1207" presenters="NEWMAN">
      <title>
       Telecom: 0055 Services
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth that:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) Telecom is selling 0055 telephone networks to private contractors who provide offensive and sexually explicit recorded messages to the public.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) The providers of these services are advertising in the pages of Australian newspapers in a manner which is designed to titillate and attract calls from the whole community and thus play on the curiosity of children.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) These services degrade and humiliate women and portray them as sex objects, and they destroy the innocence of children.
      </para>
      <para>
       Your petitioners request that the Senate, in Parliament assembled, immediately call on Telecom to so regulate the conditions under which these services are made available, that women are no longer portrayed as sex objects, degraded or humiliated and that the innocence of children is protected.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="BE4">
         Senator Newman
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 512 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="KI4" page="1208" presenters="PARER">
      <title>
       Electoral Advertising
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled; the petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
      </para>
      <para>
       That we call upon Honourable Senators to reject legislation denying Australians the right to advertise electoral material on radio and television, believing such bans amount to a denial of free speech, an unfair advantage to an incumbent government, and a denial of information to print-handicapped and other Australians.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="KI4">
         Senator Parer
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 251 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="XI4" page="1208" presenters="REYNOLDS">
      <title>
       Aidex Exhibition
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable Speaker and members of the House of Representatives assembled:
      </para>
      <para>
       The petition of the undersigned shows the very deep concern of people in the community against the proposed AIDEX exhibition of weapons of war in our country. We firmly believe that it is not in Australia's interest to become dealers in death and destruction. Particularly at this time when our planet's environment is in a parlous condition and demands statesmanlike leadership to the world on its rehabilitation. We therefore ask that:
      </para>
      <para>
       The Exhibition to take place be one which shows instead the ways in which we aim to overcome the dangers to our world from poisoned soil, air and water by high-lighting the need for tree-planting, solar-powered homes, electric cars, etc. as a means of attacking the global warming and other hazards to our fragile environment.
      </para>
      <para>
       And we, your humble petitioners will as in duty bound, ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="XI4">
         Senator Reynolds
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 20 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="IG4" page="1208" presenters="VALLENTINE">
      <title>
       Arms Trade
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in the Parliament assembled:
      </para>
      <para>
       We the undersigned petitioners draw to the attention of the Senate the central role played by the arms trade in creating an environment in which armed conflict such as the Gulf War can occur.
      </para>
      <para>
       Your petitioners request that the Senate, in Parliament assembled, should demand that the Australian Government:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) outlaw sales of armaments and arms-related technology to overseas organisations: government and private.
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) lobby internationally, including at the United Nations, for the banning of sales of armaments and arms-related technology.
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) cancel the AIDEX 91 arms bazaar.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator Vallentine
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 141 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="IG4" page="1208" presenters="VALLENTINE">
      <title>
       Aidex Exhibition
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled:
      </para>
      <para>
       We the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully call on the Government to withdraw its endorsement from the arms bazaar, AIDEX `91, scheduled to be held in Canberra, 26-28 November, 1991, and to ensure that no government department or company takes part in the aforementioned event.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator Vallentine
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 373 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="IG4" page="1208" presenters="VALLENTINE">
      <title>
       Nuclear-powered Warships
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President of the Senate and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled: The petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth that:
      </para>
      <para>
       We are concerned about the dangers posed to the people and environment of Western Australia by the entry of nuclear-armed and nuclearpowered warships to our ports.
      </para>
      <para>
       Your petitioners therefore humbly pray;
      </para>
      <para>
       That you ban nuclear-armed and nuclear-powered warships from entering Australian ports.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator Vallentine
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 30 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="PF4" page="1208" presenters="COLSTON">
      <title>
       Croatia and Slovenia
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="PF4" page="1208" party="unknown" speaker="COLSTON">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="PF4">
          Senator COLSTON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Queensland)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I present to the Senate the following petition, from 386 petitioners, which is not in conformity with the Standing Orders as it is not in the correct form:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        To the Honourable Speaker and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled.
       </para>
       <para>
        The petition of the undersigned respectfully shows:
       </para>
       <para>
        That 92% of Croatians who voted in a referendum on 25 April 1991, supervised by the Constitutional Court of the Republic of Croatia, declared their support for Croatia as a sovereign and independent State and their opposition to Croatia remaining in the Yugoslav Federation;
       </para>
       <para>
        That 88% of Slovenians who voted in a referendum democratically expressed their support for Slovenia as an autonomous and independent State;
       </para>
       <para>
        That both Slovenia and Croatia have declared themselves to be independent Republics and that each Republic is prepared to defend its territorial integrity.
       </para>
       <para>
        Your petitioners therefore pray that the House of Representatives, in Parliament assembled, should request the Australian Government to:
       </para>
       <para>
        Establish diplomatic relations with the legitimate representatives of each Republic and of any currently subjugated country whose residents by a democratically expressed popular vote have declared their wish to be independent; and
       </para>
       <para>
        Established trade relations with the Croatian and Slovenian Republics, to take advantage of the very favourable attitude which exists between the people of these Republics and the Australian people.
       </para>
       <para>
        And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="ZW4" page="1209" presenters="SHERRY">
      <title>
       Port Sorell Post Office
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="ZW4" page="1209" party="unknown" speaker="SHERRY">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZW4">
          Senator SHERRY
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I present to the Senate the following petition, from 316 petitioners, which is not in conformity with the Standing Orders as it is not in the correct form:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        We the undersigned ratepayers and residents of Port Sorell, strongly object to the Port Sorell post office being re-located.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <para>
      Petitions received.
     </para>
    </petition.grp>
    <debate page="1209" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      NOTICES OF MOTION
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1209">
      <title>
       Parliamentary Privileges Amendment (Effect of Other Laws) Bill 1991
      </title>
      <speech electorate="WA" nameid="XF4" page="1209" party="LP" speaker="Crichton-Browne Sen N.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XF4">
          Senator CRICHTON-BROWNE
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the following bill be introduced: A Bill for an Act to amend the Parliamentary Privileges Act 1987 in relation to the effect of other laws on the powers, privileges and immunities of each House of Parliament and of the members and committees of each House.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1209">
      <title>
       Social Security Benefits
      </title>
      <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="LE4" page="1209" party="LP" speaker="Baume Sen M.E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LE4">
          Senator MICHAEL BAUME
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (New South Wales)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate-
       </para>
       <para>
        (a) notes that the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button) presented to the Senate on 20 August 1991, Budget Paper No. 3, which included a series of totally incorrect figures relating to the vital matter of social security benefits available to the unemployed, particularly to the record proportion of youth unemployed, and that these figures had to be corrected in a corrigenda tabled in this chamber on 4 September 1991, more than a fortnight later;
       </para>
       <para>
        (b) regrets that important official Government documents on such vital issues cannot be trusted, and that its statement that budgeted outlays on Job Search Allowance were not available was wrong, with the correct figure being $5.2 billion, that Newstart allowances should have been $1.8 billion and that staff years involved in providing income security for families with children really totals 3506.6 instead of the 1205.7 that Senator Button wrongly presented to the Senate; and
       </para>
       <para>
        (c) calls for a better performance from the Government in ensuring the accuracy of documents containing figures in respect of social security.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1209">
      <title>
       Nuclear Waste
      </title>
      <speech electorate="WA" nameid="IG4" page="1209" party="IND" speaker="Vallentine Sen J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="IG4">
          Senator VALLENTINE
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate-
       </para>
       <para>
        (a) notes that CRA, Western Mining Corporation, BHP and Energy Resources of Australia, with the Australian National University and the Australian Nuclear Science and Technology Organisation, are considering a proposal to import nuclear waste for reprocessing in Australia;
       </para>
       <para>
        (b) further notes that the mining companies hope that their plan will win the support of a coalition government, given the current Government's ban on the import of nuclear waste;
       </para>
       <para>
        (c) calls on the current Government to maintain its ban on the import of nuclear waste into Australia;
       </para>
       <para>
        (d) further calls on the Government to launch a campaign to explain to the Australian people why this country should not become a nuclear dustbin for the rest of the world, and to promote the development in Australia of what the United States energy expert (Amory Lovins) has called the Soft Energy path; and
       </para>
       <para>
        (e) recommends that the research teams involved in the plan for reprocessing nuclear waste instead use their talents to research and promote energy conservation and renewable forms of energy, which Australia can develop for domestic purposes and for an export market.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1210">
      <title>
       Consumption Tax Revenues
      </title>
      <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="LE4" page="1210" party="LP" speaker="Baume Sen M.E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LE4">
          Senator MICHAEL BAUME
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (New South Wales)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate-
       </para>
       <para>
        (a) notes the false claim by the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button) in Parliament on 4 September 1991 that a correction to the coalition's weekend press release on the size of the Hawke Government's hidden consumption tax revenues only took place `as a result of an intervention by the Tax Office pointing out an error to the Leader of the Opposition's (Dr Hewson) office;
       </para>
       <para>
        (b) notes that if Senator Button's knowledge of such contact by the Tax Office came from the Tax Office, he should also have known that when the Tax Office made contact with Dr Hewson's office on the afternoon of 2 September 1991 it was advised that a correction had been made earlier that day (with the correct figures appearing in the Australian on 3 September 1991), and that the correction would immediately be faxed to the Tax Office for its information, with the transmission time shown as 4.55 pm; and
       </para>
       <para>
        (c) expresses its concern that either Senator Button was not properly advised by the Tax Office that a correction had been made on the coalition's own initiative, or else that he chose to mislead the Senate.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1210" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1210">
      <title>
       Standing Committee on Community Affairs
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="FE4" page="1210" party="ALP" speaker="Zakharov Sen A.O.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FE4">
          Senator ZAKHAROV
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the time for presentation of the report of the Standing Committee on Community Affairs on annual reports be extended to 12 September 1991.
       </para>
       <para>
        I seek leave to make a very brief statement.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FE4">
          Senator ZAKHAROV
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The Standing Committee on Community Affairs requires further time to complete consideration of its report on annual reports. The Committee has a very heavy workload on legislation as well as its own references and Committee members and staff are involved this week in Estimates consideration.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1210">
      <title>
       Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
        Motion (by Senator Schacht) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para>
        That the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade have leave to meet during the sittings of the Senate on 17 October 1991 from 3.30 p.m. till 6.30 p.m., for the purpose of taking evidence from witnesses visiting from overseas.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1210" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      TABLING OF DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="ACT" gov="1" nameid="5I4" page="1210" party="ALP" speaker="McMullan Sen R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5I4">
         Senator McMULLAN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Australian Capital Territory-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Manager of Government Business in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Papers are tabled in accordance with the list circulated to honourable senators. With the concurrence of the Senate I ask that the list be incorporated in Hansard.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The list read as follows-
      </para>
      <para>
       1. UNITED NATIONS GENERAL ASSEMBLY-Report of the Australian Delegation-Forty-fifth Session 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       2. OFFICIAL ESTABLISHMENTS TRUST-Annual Report 1990-91.
      </para>
      <para>
       3. OFFICE OF THE OFFICIAL SECRETARY TO THE GOVERNOR-GENERAL-Annual Report 1990-91-section 19 of the Governor-General Act 1974.
      </para>
      <para>
       4. NATIONAL BOARD OF EMPLOYMENT, EDUCATION AND TRAINING AND ITS HIGHER EDUCATION COUNCIL-Report-Postgraduate Course Fee Guidelines-section 30 of the Employment, Education and Training Act 1988.
      </para>
      <para>
       5. PUBLISHED NURSING HOME STANDARDS MONITORING REPORTS 1 MAY 1991-31 JULY 1991-PUBLISHED HOSTEL STANDARDS MONITORING REPORTS 16 MAY 1991-31 JULY 1991-Minister for Aged, Family and Health Services.
      </para>
      <para>
       6. GOVERNMENT HOUSE CANBERRA-STRATEGIC PLAN.
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As the Senate will be adjourning early today to enable Estimates committees to meet, there will not be an opportunity to consider the Government documents just tabled. The documents will be listed on the Notice Paper and senators will have the opportunity to consider them during General Business on Thursday, 10 October 1991.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="SE4" page="1210" party="LP" speaker="Bishop Sen B.K.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="SE4">
         Senator BISHOP
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-I want to speak specifically on items numbered 2, 3 and 6 on the red business sheet, that is, the Official Establishments Trust annual report, the Office of the Official Secretary to the Governor-General annual report and the Government House, Canberra-strategic plan. Those documents are all relevant to the hearings for Estimates Committee A. Estimates Committee A began its sittings yesterday. As a matter for the Committee to determine, we determined amongst ourselves in what order we would deal with business. To have those documents tabled today, after that hearing was scheduled, is not acceptable.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Furthermore, I asked for these reports when I first came into the chamber, bearing in mind that we rise at 12 o'clock and bearing in mind that we know that the Estimates hearings start at 2 o'clock and that we have a two-hour rule for so many of these reports whereby it is eminently sensible that we are permitted to have reports two hours prior to tabling, irrespective of whether they are scheduled on the red for consideration. I feel that some action is needed so that honourable senators are better informed and able to deal with the material.
      </para>
      <para>
       As far as the Estimates hearings are concerned, I think it is outrageous that these documents are being made available only now. They should have been made available some time ago. I have checked with the secretariat of the Committee to ensure that draft reports were not made available as is the practice with other departments or agencies. I see no reason why we should allow this action by the Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet to go uncommented upon. Indeed, I should say, as it reflects on the Governor-General and on the official establishments, including Government House, that there should be absolute scrupulous attention to ensure that these reports are received in due and proper time. As we are discussing the titular head of this nation, that office ought to behave in a way that is better than most. Again, I would ask that we look at that rule about honourable senators being able to have reports two hours in advance of tabling, irrespective of whether they are listed for consideration.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="ACT" gov="1" nameid="5I4" page="1211" party="ALP" speaker="McMullan Sen R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5I4">
         Senator McMULLAN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Australian Capital Territory-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Manager of Government Business in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-Yesterday a number of issues were raised concerning the tabling of government documents. Senator Patterson raised one matter, which, had the facts been exactly as I was then afraid they might be, would have been a very serious cause of concern. I undertook to make a report on that matter and I am about to do so.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       There are difficulties for all of us in the managing of the Senate program because of the impact of Estimates. They are impacting on the legislation program and on the time available for some Opposition preferred business. I understand that. We have tried to manage those changes in a cooperative way. I appreciate the cooperation that, in general, has been provided with regard to that.
      </para>
      <para>
       I want to make some specific points about the matter that was raised yesterday. The documents tabled yesterday were provided to the Senate in accordance with the normal practice; that is, as soon as the necessary clearances were obtained. As most honourable senators would know, there are guidelines for presentation of ministerial statements and reports to Parliament. Those guidelines in relation to the House of Representatives state that reports and papers will normally be presented in the House on the sitting day following receipt of the report by the tabling officer, although programming considerations, especially where a statement accompanies tabling, may create delays. This week all of the documents presented to the Parliament have been tabled one sitting day or less after becoming available.
      </para>
      <para>
       The guidelines also state, with regard to the Senate, that in most cases reports presented to the Senate will have already been presented to the House, usually on the previous day. Exceptions to this general rule are where the report is the responsibility of a Senate Minister, where there is a particular requirement for simultaneous tabling or--
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="SE4" speaker="Senator Bishop">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="SE4">
          Senator Bishop
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Why not simultaneously?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5I4">
         Senator McMULLAN
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —There has been a longstanding practice and that is the point that I am explaining. That was the point of Senator Patterson's proper concern yesterday. Let us get this point on the record and we can subsequently talk about this sequencing arrangement which, as I understand it from honourable senators who have been here longer than I, was originally introduced to facilitate the Opposition-not this Opposition now-but that does not mean that it has to be set in concrete.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       I want to get the facts from yesterday correct first. The report is usually tabled first in the House in which the Minister sits and subsequently in the other House. When it is a Senate Minister-as was the case with two of the reports yesterday-the reports are tabled first in the Senate and subsequently in the House of Representatives. That also happened with regard to the documents that were tabled yesterday. When it is a House of Representatives Minister, the documents are tabled first in that House and subsequently in here. That is why that circumstance-the matter which Senator Patterson raised-occurred yesterday. It was news to her and to me, but it has in fact been the practice for a very long time. There was no departure yesterday from the standard practice with regard to that matter. Had there been, Senator Patterson is right: that would have been a profound cause of concern. But it was in accordance with that standard practice.
      </para>
      <para>
       I reiterate that we endeavoured yesterday to proceed in as cooperative a manner as possible. We had negotiated with the Opposition about the manner of presentation of those matters. I will come to Senator Bishop's point in a moment. What I have said does not go to more general questions of concern about whether reports should be tabled in both Houses simultaneously.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="VJ4" speaker="Senator Watson">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VJ4">
          Senator Watson
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I hope you don't use that precedent for the Budget Papers.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5I4">
         Senator McMULLAN
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —That is not really one of Senator Watson's more profound interjections. There was no special arrangement yesterday, the potential of which had alarmed some honourable senators, including me.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="SE4" speaker="Senator Bishop">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="SE4">
          Senator Bishop
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Does that mean that these have been tabled in the House of Representatives?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5I4">
         Senator McMULLAN
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —No, they have all been tabled simultaneously today, for reasons which I will come to in a moment. Had they been tabled in the House of Representatives, they would have been available in advance, because they would then have been tabled in accordance with normal practice. That is why we always have a large number of reports on the list, most of which are available in advance and some of which are not, either because they are being tabled for the first time by Senate Ministers or they are being simultaneously tabled for some particular and specific reason. That was the case yesterday, on every other day, and it is the case today.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="SE4" speaker="Senator Bishop">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="SE4">
          Senator Bishop
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —To cover the two-hour rule.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5I4">
         Senator McMULLAN
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I will come to Senator Bishop's point in a moment. I ask her to restrain her enthusiasm just for a moment. If honourable senators want to discuss whether the guidelines should be changed, I am quite happy to listen to those discussions. It does not strike me as one of the world's greatest issues, but there is no barrier to having some discussions about it if people have a particular view.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The change may not be totally in the interests of the Senate; the sequencing often makes it easier for people to debate documents. Most reports, because of this procedure, are tabled in the House of Representatives one day and tabled here the next day. That gives us more time to discuss them later that day because they have been received from the House of Representatives. The procedure usually works in our interest, but I am not averse to having discussions about changing it. There is no particular government interest in whether they are all tabled simultaneously or otherwise. That is not a matter of any consequence.
      </para>
      <para>
       With regard to these particular reports-and some of those yesterday about which Senator Baume spoke more broadly as to whether they should have been in earlier from the departments-irrespective of which House they were tabled in on which day, I do not intend to stand up here and defend every agency and their timetable of presentation. I do not know the details of all those reports tabled yesterday or these tabled today. In my view, some reports come to the Senate outrageously late. Some come late for good reasons; some come late for no reason at all. I have no quibble with the right of senators to express concern about that. Whether they are right on every occasion is a matter of judgment, but they are entitled to raise that as a proper concern, because departments do have a responsibility to report. I do not challenge that point.
      </para>
      <para>
       We have set out to be cooperative, including in the tabling of the various documents today relating to Estimates committees. It may be that they should have been tabled two weeks ago. I do not know when they could conceivably have been available; they are not reports with which I am familiar. I do know that the reason they have been simultaneously tabled is to facilitate the earlier consideration of them by senators because they will be required for Estimates and because we knew, as the Notice Paper has made clear for some time, that consideration of the Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet is scheduled for next Monday.
      </para>
      <para>
       We wanted to make sure that the reports were tabled today so that they were available before Monday. It is true that facilitating their being tabled today would not have helped the Estimates Committee yesterday, but I assure honourable senators that it will help them for Monday. That is why we made an exceptional arrangement today to facilitate both Opposition and Government senators in the consideration of these reports at Estimates.
      </para>
      <para>
       I cannot debate whether they should have been available a fortnight ago; I have no information about that. But we have set out, in the knowledge that the Estimates Committee is scheduling Prime Minister and Cabinet for Monday, to make these reports available in a slightly unusual manner so that honourable senators have them prior to Estimates Committee consideration.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Deputy President, that was a slightly longer statement than intended but there were two matters to be dealt with rather than the one on which I originally intended to report.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1213" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1213">
      <title>
       Standing Committee on Employment, Education and Training
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="1213">
       <title>
        Report
       </title>
       <speech electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="LH4" page="1213" party="ALP" speaker="Jones Sen G.N.">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LH4">
           Senator JONES
          </name>
          <electorate>
           (Queensland)
          </electorate>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —On behalf of Senator Aulich, I present the report of the Standing Committee on Employment, Education and Training on the examination of annual reports.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>
         Ordered that the report be printed.
        </para>
       </speech>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1213">
      <title>
       Joint Standing Committee on Migration Regulations
      </title>
      <speech electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="LH4" page="1213" party="ALP" speaker="Jones Sen G.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LH4">
          Senator JONES
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Queensland)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —On behalf of Senator Cooney, I present the first special report of the Joint Standing Committee on Migration Regulations, entitled Recommendations to the Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs, and seek leave to move a motion in relation to the report.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LH4">
          Senator JONES
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate take note of the report.
       </para>
       <para>
        I seek leave to incorporate the tabling statement in Hansard.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <para>
        The statement read as follows-
       </para>
       <para>
        1 This special report to Parliament essentially comprises two letters written to the Hon Gerry Hand MP, Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs.
       </para>
       <para>
        2 The Joint Standing Committee on Migration Regulations, as part of its terms of reference, has determined that where necessary and appropriate, it will provide advice to the Minister on matters where for reasons of urgency or otherwise it is not practicable to await the tabling of a report to Parliament.
       </para>
       <para>
        3 Often issues of concern to the Committee arise during the course of an inquiry. However, sometimes issues not the subject of specific inquiry are considered and if it is decided that further consideration is warranted by the Minister and his Department, and possible amendment required, the Committee has agreed that it will notify the Minister accordingly. The Committee has further determined that any such letters of advice will be tabled in Parliament at the earliest opportunity.
       </para>
       <para>
        4 Prior to July 1991, only one such letter had been transmitted to the Minister. That was included in the Report to Parliament called Change of Status, tabled in May of this year. That letter included a number of recommendations relating to the Committee's inquiry into change of status on marriage or de facto grounds, recommendations which the Committee was concerned to put to the Minister prior to a deadline of 30 November 1990 and before it was possible to finalise its report on the issue.
       </para>
       <para>
        5 This ``Special Report'' includes two letters of advice to the Minister, one on the current refugee/humanitarian arrangements and one relating to a number of other issues.
       </para>
       <para>
        6 The former arose out of the Committee's current inquiry into refugee/humanitarian arrangements and the latter was prompted by correspondence to the Committee, direct references from the Minister's office and a consideration of issues arising from decisions of the Immigration Review Tribunal.
       </para>
       <para>
        7 The major issues dealt with in the second of the two letters include:
       </para>
       <para>
        7.1 the section 121 aggregation procedure;
       </para>
       <para>
        7.2 the balance of family test;
       </para>
       <para>
        7.3 certain requirements relating to the Family Extended Eligibility Temporary Entry Permit;
       </para>
       <para>
        7.4 special need relative;
       </para>
       <para>
        7.5 the complexity of the immigration legal scheme.
       </para>
       <para>
        8 On this last point I must emphasise the continuing difficulties experienced by everyone who comes into contact with the immigration process as a result of the very complex nature of the scheme. The Committee is of the view that this problem must be rectified before the regulatory process is properly workable.
       </para>
       <para>
        9 I commend the report to honourable senators.
       </para>
       <para>
        Debate (on motion by Senator Bjelke-Petersen) adjourned.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1214" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      TABLING OF DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1214">
      <title>
       Program Performance Statements
      </title>
      <speech electorate="ACT" gov="1" nameid="5I4" page="1214" party="ALP" speaker="McMullan Sen R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5I4">
          Senator McMULLAN
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Australian Capital Territory-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasurer)
         </role>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I table the corrigenda to the program performance statements of the Administrative Services portfolio.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1214" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1214">
      <title>
       Procedure Committee
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="1214">
       <title>
        Membership
       </title>
       <proctext>
        <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
         <talk.start>
          <talker>
           <name nameid="10000">
            The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
           </name>
          </talker>
          <para in-line="1">
           —The President has received a letter from the Acting Leader of the Australian Democrats nominating a senator to be a member of the Procedure Committee.
          </para>
         </talk.start>
         <para>
          Motion (by Senator Robert Ray)-by leave-agreed to:
         </para>
         <para>
          That, having been duly nominated in accordance with standing order 17, Senator Bourne be appointed a member of the Procedure Committee.
         </para>
        </interject>
       </proctext>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1214" type="Bill">
     <title>
      NATIONAL MEASUREMENT (STANDARD TIME) AMENDMENT BILL 1991
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1214">
      <title>
       First Reading
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
        Bill received from the House of Representatives.
       </para>
       <para>
        Motion (by Senator Robert Ray) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para>
        That this Bill may proceed without formalities and be now read a first time.
       </para>
       <para>
        Bill read a first time.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1214">
      <title>
       Second Reading
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE" nameid="UI4" page="1214" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UI4">
          Senator ROBERT RAY
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Defence)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.38 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That this Bill be now read a second time.
       </para>
       <para>
        I seek leave to have the second reading speech incorporated in Hansard.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <para>
        The speech read as follows-
       </para>
       <para>
        This Bill was presented to the House of Representatives on 18 April this year as a Private Members Bill by Mr Ron Edwards, the member for Stirling, and the Bill passed through all stages in the House on 21 June.
       </para>
       <para>
        Whilst Mr Edwards' motivation in introducing the Bill was to overcome an impasse in the introduction of summer time in Western Australia, the Bill has a broader impact by clarifying the Commonwealth's responsibility for civil time in Australia and its external territories. Because time is such an important component of the National Measurement System the Bill has been adopted by the Government and it is on this basis that I introduce the Bill to the Senate.
       </para>
       <para>
        The current legislative responsibility for civil time is divided between the National Measurement Act 1960 and Time Acts of the State Governments. These latter Acts were enacted in 1894 as a result of an International Meridian Conference in 1884 that recommended the establishment of a global system of time zones based on the Greenwich Meridian of longitude with zones based on one hour difference for each 15 degrees of longitude. It is under these pre-Federation State Time Acts that some State Governments have set their summer time.
       </para>
       <para>
        With Federation in 1901 the Commonwealth was given responsibility under Section 51 (xv) to establish a National Measurement System. In accordance with this responsibility the Commonwealth in 1947 acceded to the Convention of the Metre and in 1959 to the International Convention on Legal Metrology. In 1948 the Commonwealth enacted legislation, now the National Measurement Act 1960, defining the legal units of measurement in Australia including the measurement of time.
       </para>
       <para>
        However no provision has yet been made in the Commonwealth legislation for defining civil time. In 1975 the Fifteenth General Conference of Weights and Measures recommended that Co-ordinated Universal Time based on atomic clocks replace the solar based Greenwich Mean Time as the basis for legal and civil time. Australia is now one of the few, if not the only, modern industrial nation to have not enacted national legislation defining civil time.
       </para>
       <para>
        The passage of this Bill will clarify the Commonwealth Government's responsibility for civil time and will remove any legal anomalies in the definition of civil time with respect to Co-ordinated Universal Time.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Time Zones defined in the Schedule to the Bill have been defined with respect to Co-ordinated Universal Time but are consistent with the zones defined in the existing State Time Acts. In addition time zones have been defined for Australia's external territories, consistent with their geographic position.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Bill also makes provision for setting of summer time by regulation following consultation with the Premier or Chief Ministers of the States or Territories.
       </para>
       <para>
        Summer time was first introduced in Australia in peace time by the Tasmanian Government during a severe drought in 1967. The aim was to save water in the hydro-electric systems and the success of the experiment has resulted in its continuance in Tasmania and adoption of summer time by all the States and Territories except Western Australia and the Northern Territory.
       </para>
       <para>
        Whilst summer time has a high degree of acceptance in Australia, a Morgan Gallop Poll in March this year indicated some 74 per cent of the population in support, there has been great difficulty in obtaining uniformity of summer time with the result that the three standard time zones can be expanded in summer to up to seven zones creating major difficulties for transport and communication utilities.
       </para>
       <para>
        Summer time has been adopted in all industrialised countries except Japan and most middle income countries. However each summer in Australia it still generates a high degree of passionate public debate. There is in Australia a deal of current debate about the moves by European community to establish a single market in goods and service; what is less well recognised is the extent to which continental Europe has established uniform standard and summer time. This Bill will provide the opportunity to introduce a summer time regime that is appropriate for our climate, geography and economic welfare and in addition will allow for a review of the existing time zones to ensure that they meet current business and community needs.
       </para>
       <para>
        I commend the Bill to the Senate.
       </para>
       <para>
        Debate (on motion by Senator Bjelke-Petersen) adjourned.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1215" type="Bill">
     <title>
      HONEY LEVY (No. 1) AMENDMENT BILL 1991
      <break type="LINE">
       HONEY LEVY (NO. 2) AMENDMENT BILL 1991
       <break type="LINE">
        HONEY EXPORT CHARGE AMENDMENT BILL 1991
       </break>
      </break>
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1215">
      <title>
       First Reading
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
        Bills received from the House of Representatives.
       </para>
       <para>
        Motion (by Senator Robert Ray) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para>
        That these Bills may proceed without formalities and be now read a first time.
       </para>
       <para>
        Bills read a first time.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1215">
      <title>
       Second Readings
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE" nameid="UI4" page="1215" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UI4">
          Senator ROBERT RAY
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Defence)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.40 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That these Bills be now read a second time.
       </para>
       <para>
        I seek leave to have the second reading speeches incorporated in Hansard.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <para>
        The speeches read as follows-
       </para>
       <para>
        HONEY LEVY (NO 1) AMENDMENT BILL 1991
       </para>
       <para>
        This Bill provides for amendment to increase the maximum allowable Honey Levy on honey produced and sold in Australia. The Bill is one of three similar Bills, each dealing with a different way of selling honey, which provide for an increase in the maximum allowable levies or export charge on honey to 0.75 cent per kilogram. The levies and export charge are imposed to provide the basis for funding the Honeybee Research and Development Council.
       </para>
       <para>
        Under the present legislation the maximum allowable levy for research and development is 0.50 cent per kilogram, which is the same as the current operative rate. The operative rate is determined by Regulation on advice of the Federal Council of Australian Apiarists' Associations, which is the national representative beekeeper organisation, or the Honeybee Research and Development Council.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Federal Council of Australian Apiarists' Associations has advised that it wishes to increase the operative rate to 0.52 cent per kilogram from 1 January 1992 as part of its program of progressively increasing the producer contribution to research and development.
       </para>
       <para>
        To allow for this increase and any further increases, the Federal Council of Australian Apiarists' Associations has requested the raising of the maximum rate to 0.75 cent per kilogram. Increasing the maximum rate by 50 per cent will give industry the flexibility to increase its contributions to research and development over an extended period without the need for frequent amendments to the legislation.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government commends the industry's foresight and support of the need for increased research and development. The Australian honey industry is currently contributing about 0.4 per cent of its gross value of production to research and development.
       </para>
       <para>
        Research and development is a major factor underlying this country's future growth. The Government is committed to continued matching of industry levies for funding of research and development up to 0.5 per cent of gross value of production. This has continued to encourage rural industries to increase their contributions to research and clearly the honey industry recognises the advantage of this commitment in moving towards the 0.5 per cent target.
       </para>
       <para>
        No additional budgetary outlays will result from the amendment itself. However, this amendment would enable the Government to agree to an industry request for an operative rate increase above the current maximum, which would then generate additional matching budgetary outlays.
       </para>
       <para>
        I commend the Bill to Honourable Senators and I present the Explanatory Memorandum to this Bill.
       </para>
       <para>
        HONEY LEVY (NO 2) AMENDMENT BILL 1991
       </para>
       <para>
        This Bill provides for amendment to increase the maximum allowable Honey Levy on honey produced in Australia and used in the production of other goods. The Bill provides for an increase in the maximum allowable levy to 0.75 cent per kilogram. The levy is imposed to provide the basis for funding the Honeybee Research and Development Council.
       </para>
       <para>
        I have already outlined the background to this amendment in my Second Reading Speech on the Honey Levy (No 1) Amendment Bill 1991.
       </para>
       <para>
        No additional budgetary outlays will result from the amendment itself. However, this amendment would enable the Government to agree to an industry request for an operative rate increase above the current maximum, which would then generate additional matching budgetary outlays.
       </para>
       <para>
        I commend the Bill to Honourable Senators and I present the Explanatory Memorandum to this Bill.
       </para>
       <para>
        HONEY EXPORT CHARGE AMENDMENT BILL 1991
       </para>
       <para>
        This Bill provides for amendment to increase the maximum allowable Honey Export Charge on honey exported, but not levied under other legislation. The Bill provides for an increase in the maximum allowable export charge to 0.75 cent per kilogram of honey. The export charge is imposed to provide the basis for funding the Honeybee Research and Development Council.
       </para>
       <para>
        I have already outlined the background to this amendment in my Second Reading Speech on the Honey Levy (No 1) Amendment Bill.
       </para>
       <para>
        No additional budgetary outlays will result from the amendment itself. However, this amendment would enable the Government to agree to an industry request for an operative rate increase above the current maximum, which would then generate additional matching budgetary outlays.
       </para>
       <para>
        I commend the Bill to Honourable Senators and I present the Explanatory Memorandum to this Bill.
       </para>
       <para>
        Debate (on motion by Senator Bjelke-Petersen) adjourned.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1216" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1216">
      <title>
       Joint Standing Committee on Migration Regulations
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —The following message has been received from the House of Representatives:
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>
         The House of Representatives having considered message No. 290 of the Senate, acquaints the Senate that the House does not concur in the Senate's modification of the resolution relating to the amended resolution of appointment of the Joint Standing Committee on Migration Regulations. The House of Representatives desires the reconsideration by the Senate of the resolution in respect of the said modification. (Leo McLeay, Speaker)
        </para>
        <para>
         Motion (by Senator Robert Ray) agreed to:
        </para>
        <para>
         That the Senate does not insist on the modification with which the House of Representatives has disagreed, and that the Senate's resolution be communicated to the House of Representatives by message.
        </para>
       </interject>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1217" type="Bill">
     <title>
      SOCIAL SECURITY (DISABILITY AND SICKNESS SUPPORT) AMENDMENT BILL 1991
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1217">
      <title>
       Second Reading
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
        Debate resumed from 4 September, on motion by Senator Collins:
       </para>
       <para>
        That this Bill be now read a second time.
       </para>
       <para>
        upon which Senator Alston had moved by way of amendment:
       </para>
       <para>
        At end of motion, add ``, but the Senate:
       </para>
       <para>
        (a) condemns the Government for failing to extend the proposed reforms to Australia's current unacceptably large invalid pensioner population, with the inevitable result that there will be two classes of pensioners, poor targeting and a reduced capacity to assist the most disabled.
       </para>
       <para>
        (b) expresses its concerns at the Government's totally inadequate consultation with medical practitioners, health professionals, welfare groups and representatives of people with disabilities and their carers, resulting in serious uncertainties about the reliability and validity of the proposed Impairment Tables as well as over 100 proposed amendments since the bill was guillotined through the House of Representatives.''.
       </para>
      </proctext>
      <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="LI4" page="1217" party="LP" speaker="Patterson Sen K.C.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LI4">
          Senator PATTERSON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.41 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The passage of the Social Security (Disability and Sickness Support) Amendment Bill 1991 is about as tedious as the negotiations on this legislation have been since it passed through the House of Representatives. I remind honourable senators that this Bill went through the House of Representatives with no amendments. It came into the Senate and went to a committee, and now today we have on the table 111 amendments and five or six requests. We have seen a Bill which was passed through the House of Representatives in a shoddy and disgraceful form, mainly because of lack of consultation and which now, because of consideration of Estimates in the Senate, which is no excuse, the Bill is taking quite a while to get through the Senate as well.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        It is irrefutable that over the past 20 years there has been a massive rise in the number of invalid pensioners and sickness beneficiaries, far exceeding any increase in the Australian population. Let me reiterate a few of the figures which I find rather startling, as I am sure will some members of the public, especially the few of us who are left who are taxpayers. The number of invalid pensioners has risen from 134,000 in 1970 to 229,000 in 1980, to 316,000 in 1990. This is an increase of 136 per cent in just 20 years, and in that time the population has risen by only 36 per cent. In 1990 one in every 56 Australians was on the invalid pension compared with one in 93 two decades earlier. If we take carer's pension and other related benefits into account, we find that over 422,000, or one in 40 Australians, were receiving long term disability assistance in June 1990-one in 40 Australians!
       </para>
       <para>
        The number of sickness beneficiaries has risen from 10,000 in 1971 to 39,000 in 1980 and to 70,000 in 1990. This is a massive 654 per cent increase in 19 years. In that time the population has risen by only 31 per cent. In 1990 one in every 230 Australians was receiving sickness benefit compared with one in every 1,240 in 1971. This means that one in 34 Australians was receiving some sort of short or long term disability related assistance from the Department of Social Security in 1990-I repeat, one in 34. As two-thirds of our population are at working age, this equates to one in 22 of working age Australians in receipt of some form of benefit.
       </para>
       <para>
        These figures beg the question: has there been a massive increase in the number of permanently and temporarily disabled working age Australians over the past 20 years, or has there merely been a massive increase in the proportion of working age Australians with disabilities who rely on social security benefits?
       </para>
       <para>
        Demographer Dr Graham Hugo estimates that there has been a 16 per cent increase in the number of people with disabilities over the past decade, and that by the turn of the century one in 12 Australians will have some form of disability. While there is little doubt that the overall incidence of disability in Australian society is rising, the overwhelming reason for this increase is the larger number of old people who have chronic conditions. Medical breakthroughs now mean that elderly people who suffer from diseases which would have killed them 20 or 30 years ago are now able to continue living, although often in a severely incapacitated state of health. The combination of an ageing population and life prolonging medicines indicate that the number of very old people with disabilities will continue to rise at a faster rate than the overall population.
       </para>
       <para>
        I have found no studies that indicate that the rate of incapacity in the working age population is rising at anywhere near the rate of increase in the number of invalid pensioners and sickness beneficiaries over the past two decades. Conversely, it is quite valid to suggest that the number of people with permanent disabilities or temporary incapacities keeping them out of the work force should have fallen during the past 20 years.
       </para>
       <para>
        Medical breakthroughs mean that many temporary illnesses can be cured more quickly and many permanent disabilities have a less debilitating effect on a person's lifestyle. There has been a marked improvement in the knowledge, expertise and rehabilitative skills of allied health professionals such as occupational therapists, physiotherapists, speech therapists, psychologists and a range of other allied health professionals, including orthoptists, orthotists and prosthetists. I could go on at length about the level of skills of those people who have contributed to enabling people with disabilities to have a better quality of life than they would have earlier.
       </para>
       <para>
        Equal employment opportunity and affirmative action laws have been enacted. The Federal Government's commitment to policies that promote mainstream community involvement by people with disabilities is embodied in the Disability Services Act. A wider and more diverse choice of employment and education opportunities has opened up new careers for people with disabilities. There have been marked improvements in the networks of community support available to people with disabilities. Workplaces are more accessible and material aid supports have become more technologically advanced. The development of comprehensive and generous State run workers compensation schemes-and I could spend half an hour discussing Workcare in Victoria, though not very positively-and privately funded injury and accident insurance schemes also should have reduced the reliance on social security based disability welfare.
       </para>
       <para>
        Despite these innovations, the number of invalid pensioners has increased at four times the population rate, while the number of sickness beneficiaries has risen at 20 times the population rate since the early 1970s. Some but not all of this increase could be credited to the greater recognition and higher incidence of psychiatric, social and environmentally related diseases and impairments. However, I contend that significant advances in medicine, law, employment, education and community support which have helped alleviate the handicaps associated with disabilities far outweigh any deleterious factors over the past two decades.
       </para>
       <para>
        So why do we have this massive increase in disability related welfare dependence over the last 20 years? One reason that cannot be overlooked is the difference in community attitudes between now and then. Twenty years ago people were far less aware of how the social security system worked. As well, there was a social stigma attached to the receipt of welfare, which was seen to represent a loss of independence and financial self-sufficiency. If one were sick, one often coped with the help of family and friends. Sadly, many of the disabled were institutionalised. However, if the disability was not considered severe the person concerned was encouraged to overcome, forget or even hide that disability and cope to the best of his or her ability. A large number of people with disabilities did just that, with the help of family and friends as well, I contend in a more compassionate and understanding society than exists today.
       </para>
       <para>
        Neither social security take-up rates nor questionable claims that we live in a sicker, more disabled society explain this surge in disability welfare dependence. One of the basic reasons for this surge is that it has been far too easy to get onto these benefits and too easy to stay on them indefinitely. There has been little incentive offered or assistance provided to help people move off these benefits. In relation to the invalid pension, the Minister stated in his second reading speech:
       </para>
       <para>
        We reached the stage where a person could suffer from a mild medical condition but, because of a combination of age, education, lack of skills in English, work history and worker's compensation, could end up receiving invalid pension . . . At the same time, there were a small but significant percentage of cases where relatively young people, even people in their twenties who were not manifestly impaired but were being awarded invalid pension with the expectation that they would continue to receive it on an indefinite basis.
       </para>
       <para>
        That is not a very good record. The Minister has to admit that we have a system which is encouraging young people in their twenties to remain on this sort of support benefit for very lengthy periods, sometimes even their whole lives. In relation to the sickness benefit, the Minister stated:
       </para>
       <para>
        The end result of these problems has been that there have been many cases where clients with impairments too insignificant to warrant grant of invalid pension have continued on sickness benefit for several years-
       </para>
       <para>
        I interpolate here to say that in many cases it is more than several years; I have been alerted to some cases lasting for 15 or 16 years, extensive periods-
       </para>
       <para>
        in a manner which is inappropriate to the intentions of the payment.
       </para>
       <para>
        I would not disagree with that. In the 1989-90 financial year, the invalid pension and related benefit cost $2.8 billion compared with $0.8 billion a decade earlier. Sickness benefits cost $600m a year compared with $126m a decade earlier. By 1990-91, income support for people with disabilities and the sick had risen to more than $4 billion.
       </para>
       <para>
        If the Government is to stem this growth in outlays it must ensure that only those people who are genuinely sick or incapacitated can access the benefits. Just as important, the Government must also ensure that all benefit recipients have a realistic opportunity to rid themselves of the shackles of welfare dependency. I emphasise that this should be all benefit recipients. I believe that that is not the case under the current legislative arrangements; there are some people who will not be encouraged as much as others. I refer to those people currently on invalid pensions.
       </para>
       <para>
        I doubt whether this legislation will fulfil either objective. The Department shares my doubts. When asked twice by Senator Herron during the hearings of the Senate Standing Committee on Community Affairs about the envisaged change in the number of invalid pensioners resulting from this legislation, the departmental officer stated:
       </para>
       <para>
        We still see it increasing but these measures would act to curb the rate of increase a little, particularly by helping people off the payment back into work.
       </para>
       <para>
        The officer continued:
       </para>
       <para>
        Yes, we would expect the number of claims at the margin to ease off, just as they go up when employment goes up.
       </para>
       <para>
        These two telling remarks sum up the effect that this Bill will have on the burgeoning invalid pension and sickness benefit populations. It will result in a slight improvement at the margins. I have already referred to the enormous burgeoning of those figures. But, according to the Department, we will see a slight improvement at the margin. For example, new eligibility criteria will make it slightly harder to access the disability support pension, with 5,000 or 12 per cent fewer successful claimants annually. It will be slightly easier to access rehabilitation and training, with 4,250 and 6,500 extra places respectively by the end of 1993-94. One in three new pensioners, representing one in 25 pensioners overall, will be asked to draw up activity plans to facilitate their eventual placement in mainstream employment. Some 20 per cent of those pensioners who successfully complete activity plans will get full time work; 30 per cent will get part time work.
       </para>
       <para>
        Entitlement for the supposedly temporary sickness allowance will be shortened to two years maximum duration. Some 8,000 or 5 per cent of sickness allowees will benefit annually from rehabilitation. Over the three years to the end of 1993-94, net savings from a program that costs the taxpayer over $4 billion a year will be $25.3m.
       </para>
       <para>
        In judging these reforms, one must consider not only how they will impact on new recipients but also the benefits that will be derived by the 300,000-plus current invalid pensioners, their families and carers. The Government has stated that these reforms build upon the work of Bettina Cass in her Social Security Review Issues Paper No. 5 entitled Towards Enabling Policies: Income Support for People with Disabilities. On reading this paper by Cass, it is obvious that she favours the extension of these reforms to existing invalid pensioners. Two of the five objectives that she considered central to a successful income support program for people with disabilities were: first, the development of employment potential through incentives and opportunities; and, secondly, the introduction of a greater degree of flexibility to accommodate different degrees of employability. She expressed concern that the existing arrangements have actually created additional barriers to employment and entrenched labour force marginality. She concluded:
       </para>
       <para>
        . . . a fundamental objective must be the establishment of enabling policies, those which encourage and support participation and the enhancement of capabilities rather than the entrenchment of marginality.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Government has been very non-committal about whether existing pensioners will be given access to activity plans, panel assessment, rehabilitation and training programs. In the Government's 1990 Budget Related Paper entitled New Opportunities for People with Disabilities, the only reference to the effect of these reforms on existing pensioners was:
       </para>
       <para>
        It will be open to such invalid pensioners to seek rehabilitation or other assistance voluntarily.
       </para>
       <para>
        In the draft guidelines outlining the conduct of these reforms, it was stated:
       </para>
       <para>
        . . . former invalid pensioners can volunteer to participate in an activity program but would not be subject to formal activity plans . . . as this would reduce the incentive to volunteer.
       </para>
       <para>
        Neither of these references indicates a full-blown commitment to the enabling policies referred to by Cass. When I put this question to departmental officials during a briefing last June I was told that the emphasis would be on early intervention and hence that the concentration would be on new claimants. I was told that after 12 months it would be decided whether to extend the program to existing invalid pensioners. I was given the distinct impression that the voluntary option would not be promoted within the current pensioner population. That concerns me.
       </para>
       <para>
        The hesitancy of the Department of Social Security in extending these reforms to current invalid pensioners was clear during the hearings of the Committee on Community Affairs when Senator Knowles requested an estimate of the number of current pensioners who would volunteer for assistance and the burden that they would place on training programs. Despite the fact that it had been claimed that pensioners could volunteer for assistance, the Department had not even estimated the number of pensioners it believed would take advantage of the offer.
       </para>
       <para>
        It seems to me that it would have been fairly simple to take a random sample of pensioners and to ask them whether, if these programs were available, they would avail themselves of the opportunity. A reasonable sample would have given us some information about, firstly, whether people would participate in these programs and, secondly, what the demand would be on the programs. We may see a rush of people. I know of one person on an invalid pension who has developed some computer skills. If those skills were honed and refined, that person most probably would be able to make his computer operation viable in a business sense. But he needs some training. He said to me, `If I could get the opportunity to get off the invalid pension I would'. I am sure that story could be repeated around the country.
       </para>
       <para>
        I condemn the Department for not doing such a survey, for not seeking to find out how many invalid pensioners believe they might benefit from these programs and for not giving such pensioners the opportunity to be included in a much more active way than that of merely volunteering. They should be actively encouraged to participate rather than being left somehow to find out that the program may be available to them.
       </para>
       <para>
        It was claimed by the Department that the emphasis should be on early intervention because, generally, the experience is that the longer people stay on income support the greater their chance of staying there forever. It was claimed that the majority of current invalid pensioners were over 50 years of age and that the focus should be on new entrants, particularly young people. As I have said, I have concerns about this. I am also disappointed that such spurious grounds are being used to justify effectively scrap-heaping so many invalid pensioners. Given the time, I think that this is an appropriate place for me to stop. I seek leave to continue my remarks later.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leave granted; debate adjourned.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1221" type="Adjournment">
     <title>
      ADJOURNMENT
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       Motion (by Senator Robert Ray) proposed:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the Senate do now adjourn.
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Before we go any further, I advise honourable senators that, after the Senate adjourns, Estimates Committee D will meet in committee room 2S3 and Estimates Committee E will meet in committee room 2S1 at 1.30 p.m. Estimates Committee F will meet in the main committee room at 2 p.m. Estimates Committee E will be televised on channel 2 and Estimates Committee F will be televised on channel 22.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <debate.sub1 page="1221">
      <title>
       Immigration
      </title>
      <speech electorate="SA" nameid="FF4" page="1221" party="LP" speaker="Chapman Sen H.G.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (12.01 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —We all know that immigration can be a traumatic event in a person's life, particularly when for some reason or another an applicant finds that his or her application for migration has been refused on grounds that may be regarded as unjust or inappropriate. We also know of other cases where blatant action by a newly arrived migrant has abused the very system used to gain entry as a permanent resident.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I well recall the case of an Australian citizen who married a woman from the Philippines. After arrival, she immediately deserted the husband and chose to live apart. The incensed husband sought to have the woman's visa cancelled, only to be told by the Department of Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs that it had no power to do so. It should be the concern of every honourable senator when inconsistencies within the regulations and the attitude of the Department of Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs in the execution of its duties are apparent.
       </para>
       <para>
        My attention has been drawn to a particular case where the irresponsible actions of an Australian citizen, combined with the harsh application of government regulations, have, without compassion or feeling, literally dumped an English migration applicant. I am advised that the Department's compliance section has resorted to heavy-handed tactics to scare and threaten a person who has been described by the Immigration Review Tribunal in the following terms:
       </para>
       <para>
        Her genuineness cannot be impugned . . . We are prepared to accept implicitly her genuineness.
       </para>
       <para>
        I will briefly describe this case. An English lady came to visit her sister living in South Australia. During the visit, the visitor met and fell in love with a separated Australian citizen. Following a courtship, a relationship developed and at the end of the stay the lady returned to England.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Australian sought and was granted a divorce from his wife. He continued to court the English lady and persuaded her to return to Australia and to consider marriage. The English lady, wanting to be sure of her feelings and the genuineness of the Australian, returned on a visitors visa on 28 September 1989 for a stay of up to six months.
       </para>
       <para>
        In December 1989, the couple talked of marriage and inquired of the Department as to her status and whether they could marry in Australia. They were told of various changes to the regulations that were introduced that month. The following month, the couple asked the Department for advice. They explained that they had originally decided to get married in South Australia and then fly to England for a honeymoon and, whilst there, apply for a permanent residence visa under the spouse category so that they could fly back together and start their life as Australian residents together.
       </para>
       <para>
        The problem was, however, that the man's employer could not let him remain away for too long, and thus they wanted to know how long a visa would take to be issued in England and whether it could be done quickly. The departmental officer pointed out that in the new regulations it was indeed possible to seek a change of status in Australia and apply for a temporary residence permit and then graduate to a permanent entry permit after entry. They were advised that they should go ahead with the marriage and then apply in Adelaide instead of London because it would be both safer and faster. This they did but, as it turned out, it was neither faster nor safer. An application was subsequently lodged. Incidentally, the form used-No. 690-recommended that applicants read carefully four particular covering booklets. When asking for these the applicant was told, `They have not been printed yet'.
       </para>
       <para>
        Several weeks later and totally unexpectedly, the Australian deserted his new wife, leaving her alone and devastated. Before leaving the new wife, I understand, he had been subject to some external manipulative pressure. Several weeks later, being honest and reputable, the lady notified the Department of her changed circumstances as was required of her by regulation. The Department requested written advice with which she complied, but she received neither acknowledgment nor instruction as to her status. After subsequently being subjected to an impersonal interview at the counter of the Department in Adelaide, she was later advised in writing that her residency application had been rejected and that she had 28 days in which to depart Australia or take the opportunity to appeal against the decision through the Migration Internal Review Office. We should remember that she was still married to an Australian citizen who had walked out on her.
       </para>
       <para>
        She instituted an appeal through the Migration Internal Review Office on 20 August 1990, attaching the reasons as to why she was appealing. The Migration Internal Review Office eventually rejected this appeal and reaffirmed the original refusal. It also gave notice of her right to appeal through the Independent Migration Review Tribunal, provided this was done within the remaining days of grace left of the original 28 days given for her departure under the original decision. She lodged the appeal on 14 January 1991. At that time she also sought legal aid, bearing in mind that she was legally married to an Australian who had left her in the lurch with no money. She also sought social security assistance for a special benefit.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Tribunal heard the case on 1 March 1991 and subsequently handed down its determination on 5 August. This was all procedurally correct. The case put forward by the applicant to the Tribunal was logical and straightforward. It contained various arguments on the legality of the interpretation of several sections of the regulations. The Tribunal accepted these arguments and upheld the lady's point of view on these important issues, but it stopped short of approval. The question of the applicant's eligibility had been finally reduced to only one point of contention, namely, whether the marriage was really genuine in that it was intended to be a lasting union. It is a question that may well be asked of all marriages. In the view of the marriage celebrant, the bride, the bridegroom, the guests at the wedding and, indeed, many friends in the country town of Moonta in South Australia it was. But in the view of the Tribunal it was not. I remind the Senate that this was an opinion given some 18 months after the marriage and after the Tribunal talked to the husband in Darwin.
       </para>
       <para>
        For this interview with the husband, during the questioning one Tribunal member was present in person, the other listening on a conference phone hook-up from Canberra. I quote from the report of the Tribunal at page 15:
       </para>
       <para>
        Whilst therefore the Tribunal is prepared to accept that the husband felt love and desire for the applicant and indeed was probably very happy in the relationship as it progressed towards marriage and immediately thereafter, it is not prepared to accept that his commitment to the marriage with the applicant was such as to exclude the possibility of him sharing a life with his former wife at some stage in the future.
       </para>
       <para>
        Although, therefore, the parties in this instance may be said to have had a mutual commitment to the marriage, unfortunately for the applicant, this commitment was not one that her husband shared with her `to the exclusion of others'.
       </para>
       <para>
        Suddenly our Tribunal members have become expert psychologists, knowing what was in another person's mind at an event 18 months earlier. In the penultimate paragraph of the Tribunal's summary, it also states that it has every sympathy with the applicant and that the irresponsible behaviour of an Australian citizen has placed her in a position where she must face leaving the country. It also stated that it unfortunately cannot grant applications merely on the basis of strong compassionate circumstances. It concludes by saying that the law must be applied and applied correctly.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Tribunal said that unfortunately the application failed to satisfy the criteria in subregulation 135(B) inasmuch as the Tribunal could not accept that the relationship between the applicant and her husband was a genuine one at the relevant time for the above reasons. She was therefore refused entry under the spouse class.
       </para>
       <para>
        The lady remains legally married but has now been told by the Tribunal that, on her wedding day and after, her husband had a notion, hidden away in his mind somewhere, that one day somewhere in the future he was going to live with his first wife. Such an interpretation must raise in the minds of all reasonable senators questions about the Migration Act and the supporting regulations for which we as legislators have the final responsibility.
       </para>
       <para>
        Was it, and indeed should it ever be, the intention of this chamber to place within such legislation, or even accept, that applicants under a spouse category should be subject to a psychological examination at the time of a marriage to determine whether or not each party has, or harbours, any hidden notion or idea that at some stage in the future-whenever that might be-they may go off and live with a former friend or spouse? I believe we would all say, `Don't be stupid, how could anyone legislate on such a boundless matter?'.
       </para>
       <para>
        Yet here we have a decision which seeks to interpret the law and the regulations in just such a way. How on earth can anyone postulate or presume to know what another person has in his or her mind at any given time, other than guessing-particularly after a period of 18 months has elapsed? How can anyone postulate or even guess whether one person is going to remain faithful to another and for what period of time? There are flaws in the interpretative section of the Act and the regulations which do not enunciate clearly the intent of the Act and the words it uses. For this reason people are suffering injustices and being denied natural justice.
       </para>
       <para>
        The lady approached two Labor senators from South Australia and also wrote directly to the Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (Mr Hand). The Minister's office actually responded in 48 hours. This is interesting in itself because on occasions I have waited six months for a response to a migration query. But her appeals were to no avail. It seems that compassion and justice are not on the agenda of this Government and its representatives, despite Labor's claims to a monopoly on compassion.
       </para>
       <para>
        After receiving the Tribunal decision, the lady contacted the Department's compliance branch to advise it that she was thinking of lodging an appeal in the Federal Court of Australia, particularly in light of the interpretation of the Tribunal members as to what constituted her relationship. I am troubled to be advised that, in response, the Department's compliance section used suggestive comments more appropriate to police states or dictatorships, such as:
       </para>
       <para>
        We will starve you out . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        . . . . . . . . . . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        I know the Federal Court system, you won't win. So why don't you save us all of the expense and go quietly under our planned departure strategy . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        . . . . . . . . . . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        When we deport you, you will become a prisoner in your own country . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        You are classified as an illegal entrant. You are not entitled to any compassion or help from social services, so you will have to pay all the benefits back, unless you leave quietly . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        . . . . . . . . . . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        If you go quietly under your own means, you will not suffer a long penalty of being unable to re-apply for another visa, whereas if we deport you, you must wait five years . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        . . . . . . . . . . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        I will ensure that any payments are stopped tomorrow.
       </para>
       <para>
        It should be noted that when the applicant lodged her forms the Department took possession of her passport with the visitor's visa stamped in it. It has never been returned. As no-one from the Department had written to her to explain that it had actually cancelled her temporary resident visa in August 1990, how could anyone expect the applicant to know her status? It was not until 19 August 1991 that she was informed by the compliance section that she had been an illegal migrant for 12 months. After all, had she not used the correct administrative process to appeal, as she had been invited to? Had she not acted in a proper and correct manner?
       </para>
       <para>
        If we allow, through the legal process, an applicant access to an appeal mechanism, then should we not also ensure that during the period of time of the appeal special status is given to the applicant? Do we really intend that an innocent person be pilloried because of a seemingly wayward interpretation of the intent of the Act? Surely the provisions being applied in this case were included to ensure that people whose intentions were not honourable were flushed out by the requirement to establish the existence of a `genuine and lasting relationship'.
       </para>
       <para>
        In this case, the applicant was urged to come to Australia, was wooed, courted and married by an Australian citizen and she committed herself to the marriage. She has been adjudged by the Tribunal as being genuine and honest. Yet she is now subjected to treatment as though she were an undesirable-an unwanted person. The town of Moonta feels so strongly about this person that the people are running functions to establish a fighting fund for her. She has developed an affinity with that community.
       </para>
       <para>
        At the start of my remarks I mentioned, by comparison, the case of a Filipino lady who thwarted the Act and an Australian citizen and yet is allowed to remain in Australia legally. Here we have an applicant who has been thwarted by an Australian citizen and adverse departmental rulings and who now faces deportation. Surely none of us in this chamber would deliberately intend such an interpretation of the Act. I therefore call on the Minister and the Government to amend the regulations and to incorporate adequate interpretative meanings to the phrase `genuine and lasting relationship'.
       </para>
       <para>
        May I add that I have been approached by three other parties, all of whom are being questioned on applications under this spouse area where the precise argument is in proving what constitutes a `genuine and lasting relationship'. They have also been asked to prove that they do cohabit with their partners. Despite the fact that one lady is pregnant and one has just had a child and has already had three others by the resident Australian-as is testified upon each child's birth certificate-each applicant has been told that such an event is hardly proof of genuine cohabitation or even of a genuine relationship! But if they can show a joint gas bill or a joint bank account then, they are told, the Department would be satisfied. What proof does the Department want, or is it hopeful of using the appeal mechanism as a fund-raiser?
       </para>
       <para>
        Action on the interpretive clauses is a matter of urgency. In the meantime, the Department should be instructed to delay any further action on these cases until the Parliament accepts the subordinate legislation of the regulations supporting the Migration Act. It makes me extremely angry that regulations designed to prevent rorts and abuses of the system-but which so often fail to do this-are now being used to intimidate and exclude a genuine case.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1225">
      <title>
       Soviet Union
      </title>
      <speech electorate="SA" gov="1" nameid="ZF4" page="1225" party="ALP" speaker="Crowley Sen R.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZF4">
          Senator CROWLEY
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (12.16 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I rise to speak on a different matter altogether from the case presented by Senator Chapman. I hope that what he has said is not exactly the case, but if it is I do not think there will be many people in this place who do not sympathise with what the honourable senator has said-except that bit about compassion.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I was involved in an event which I found so interesting and pleasing that I want to share it with the Senate-particularly in light of the consequences. On, I think, Tuesday 20 August-I am not quite sure whether that is the right date-in the middle of the Russian coup, I tried to ring Moscow. To my amazement, I was able to get through at the height of the coup and I was able to speak to a member of the Soviet Women's Committee, Vera Soboleva, head of the international department. From speaking to the Soviet women, I noted some curious, interesting, very moving and different interpretations of what life is like in a city experiencing a coup of that sort.
       </para>
       <para>
        One of the women said to me, `It is very unpleasant to come to work and find a tank outside the window'. That probably rates as one of the understatements of the century-particularly when one knows that those tanks have a history of use. These are not monuments standing for effect; they are not there to remind people of war; these tanks have been used. It was one way that this woman was able to convey to me the great fear that the women in the Soviet Union were experiencing.
       </para>
       <para>
        Another woman said, `It is not very quiet'. The way they use their capacity with English-which I might say is fantastic and is certainly greatly superior to my capacity with Russian-has its own impact. That woman said, `It is not very quiet in the city. There are military and troops everywhere. We are waiting for a decision'. That sense of a city in waiting came through to us. Another woman said, `We are very concerned. We do not want civil war. We want normal conditions under which we can live'.
       </para>
       <para>
        Then, as I suppose is often the case, with wry Soviet humour another woman said, `This morning I came to work on the public transport system. People were reading their papers or their books. The trains were running. The TV is working, the radio is working, the shops are opening and we can queue for the same absence of food'. It is that last statement in particular which reminds us that, yes, everything is the same; it is very tough indeed living in Moscow.
       </para>
       <para>
        The women went on to say that it was the school holidays. In all of the newspaper articles that I read about the coup in the Soviet Union I do not think anyone reminded me that it was the school holidays or explored the concept of how to baby-sit or care for children in a city experiencing a coup d'etat.
       </para>
       <para>
        That is something that many of us have not had the opportunity to think about; it would have been very frightening. Would we, for example, want to leave our children in a child-care centre on one side of a city and cross the city-passing the tanks, the people gathering and so on-to go to our workplace? I imagine that very many people in Moscow decided not to go to work or not to be separated from family. I have no idea of the numbers. It is an interesting point that came home to me from the use of the words by the Soviet women: `It is the school holidays'.
       </para>
       <para>
        Further, the Soviet women said, `Like last year, the universities will not be returning until October because the university students will be required to assist with the harvest'. When I was in the Soviet Union with some of my colleagues from the Senate and the House of Representatives in October 1990 we learnt that the students, as well as the military, had been deployed to assist with the harvest. We learnt, and we are again reminded, of the huge wastage of food in the Soviet Union. The food is lost, wasted and destroyed in transport and destroyed because it cannot be harvested or picked off the ground in time; it just rots.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Soviet Union has huge problems confronting it. Not only are there problems with the food-although we understand that much more food is produced than is actually delivered to the cities-but also there are transport infrastructure problems and so on. According to the women, the tough conditions of life in the Soviet Union, particularly in downtown Moscow, are not too different from when we were there-perhaps marginally worse. It is a very tough time. The words the women used when I was speaking to them gave me a dimension of the coup that, I think, we have not been reading about in the papers; a side to the coup that is really very perturbing and very moving. I was delighted to speak to the Soviet women and say that we in Australia were very concerned.
       </para>
       <para>
        I am also delighted to say that I have received a cable from the embassy of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, forwarding a message from the Soviet Women's Committee. The cable states:
       </para>
       <para>
        Dear Senator,
       </para>
       <para>
        The Soviet Women's Committee extends its gratitude to you and other women members of the Australian Parliament for the support at the very difficult times. In its statement the SWC has demanded that an urgent extraordinary meeting of the Congress of Peoples Deputies of the USSR be called and that the constitutional order in the country be restored. The Committee has also stressed upon that it stands for further development of the reforms in our country, against any suppression, for observation of all civil rights and freedoms.
       </para>
       <para>
        With deep respect,
       </para>
       <para>
        The Soviet Women's Committee
       </para>
       <para>
        August 24 1991
       </para>
       <para>
        The cable was sent to me by Mr V. Kuznetsov, Charge d'Affaires at the USSR embassy. It is interesting to report to the Senate the impact that the phone call had on me. The women were very frightened, very concerned, guarded in what they had to say, and very anxious that the threat of civil war could be lifted. In particular, they were very moved that Australia should know about them and worry about them.
       </para>
       <para>
        From talking to them, I was reminded of the impression that we got when we were in the Soviet Union: one knows more about the Soviet Union if one lives outside of it than if one lives in it. They were amazed that somehow we knew about the situation, that somehow the world might be concerned. They were moved by that and they were moved that we should be bothered to contact them and tell them that. They seemed to have less detail of what was happening in their own city than I had from watching Australian television. That was certainly the impression we had when we were in the Soviet Union. We now know the story of how the incident at Chernobyl was suppressed and not advised to the Soviet citizens. It is not restricted to Chernobyl. Other matters seem to take a long time to pass through the media networks to the Soviet citizens.
       </para>
       <para>
        The impression that I had was of their isolation, their terrible anxiety and their huge fear. As one of the women said, `As wives and mothers, we certainly do not want any war and we do not want a civil war'. I am pleased to say that I have received this cable addressed to the women of the Australian Parliament thanking us for thinking of them at that time. I am moved and delighted that they now know that we do think of them.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1226">
      <title>
       Minister for Aboriginal Affairs
      </title>
      <speech electorate="WA" nameid="XF4" page="1226" party="LP" speaker="Crichton-Browne Sen N.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XF4">
          Senator CRICHTON-BROWNE
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (12.24 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I rise briefly to touch on a matter on which I spoke following Question Time today. I refer to the matter of Mr Colbung, the Chairman of the Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies, being thrown out of the office of the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and the Minister Assisting the Prime Minister in Aboriginal Reconciliation (Mr Tickner).
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I was appalled at the response at Question Time to my question about whether or not Mr Colbung had been thrown out, which was simply `No'. Clearly, Senator Collins was doing no more than reflecting precisely the response he had received from the Minister's office. The fact that there appeared to be no contrition, no apology or explanation in itself is, in many ways, an indictment.
       </para>
       <para>
        What horrified me more than anything else was the response of the Government senators when I rose to speak for a few moments to present the facts as they had been given to me moments after the incident took place by Mr Colbung and his wife. My comments created much laughter and much mirth for a number of Government senators, Senator Schacht being one such senator. Senator Walsh was highly amused by it all. He was interjecting to the attraction of the Deputy Whip, Senator Faulkner. They thought it was all terribly funny. In fact, when a point of order was taken against Senator Faulkner he claimed proudly that he need not withdraw anything because all he had done was laugh during my speech.
       </para>
       <para>
        This comes from a government which purports to have care and compassion for the Aboriginal community. In fact, the Government would have the Aboriginal community and the wider community believe that it has a mortgage on sensitivity, consideration and compassion for the Aboriginal community. It is a government that believes that only it has an empathy, an interest or an understanding. In the process, it is wringing out every last vote that can be had from the Aboriginal community and those who genuinely do have a care, an interest, an empathy and a belief in the Aboriginal community. In the broad sweep of the Government's politics, it picks up not only the Aboriginal race in the ballot boxes but also everybody else who seriously takes up their cause.
       </para>
       <para>
        We have a living example in Ken Colbung-a 60-year old man whose sin apparently has been to serve his people for the better part of his life. He is a man who fought on behalf of his country in the Korean War. He has served his State of Western Australia on a number of occasions on boards, committees and in many other ways. He has served as Chairman over many years of the Institute of Aboriginal Studies, as it then was-now the Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies. If I remember correctly, he has been honoured by the Queen.
       </para>
       <para>
        When Mr Ken Colbung and his wife went to see the Minister-it seems that their only sin was to go to the Minister to plead for better access to and better communication with the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs-Mr Colbung was thrown out of the Minister's office. If that was not humiliating enough, when he then turned to somebody else in the Parliament whom he knew, someone with whom he had previously had dealings, it was a source of much mirth, guffaws, laughter, interjections, jokes and snide remarks by the Government.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is bad enough that Mr Colbung is humiliated by the Minister and the Minister's staff but the final act was the conduct of the Government members in this place. I say to the credit of the Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support, Senator Collins, who was responding on behalf of the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs, that there was a look of thunder on his face for two reasons: firstly, I suspect he really cares; and, secondly, he would be horrified at the politicking of his back bench and one or two others sitting on the front bench at the time. Perhaps it says something about the wilderness in which this Government has now lost itself; it cannot even have the sensitivity to recognise the stupidity of its own conduct, putting aside any genuine belief and any genuine care.
       </para>
       <para>
        Now is not the moment to go into the matters which caused Mr Colbung to go to the Minister's office in the first place. When I responded to the Minister immediately following Question Time, I did not want then to have to give the history of what went on in Mr Tickner's office and what was going on in the background when he was in my office, when my office was getting phone calls asking, `Is this man giving you trouble? If he is, let us know and we will help you remove him' or words to that effect. Then two of Mr Tickner's staff were at my door on the alleged spurious ground that he had a pass that required him to be accompanied in the building. They certainly did not accompany him to my office but, upon sober and cooled reflection, they realised the difficulties they had got themselves into. It was what you might call, I suspect, a rescue operation.
       </para>
       <para>
        I had not told Mr Colbung that this was all going on in my outer office; Mr Colbung was unaware of it. While he was very cool and objective, he was clearly angry and upset at the treatment he got. I was not about to inflame his passion or to cause him or, in fact, the Minister any more embarrassment. Today, I asked a simple question expecting a sensitive and reasonable answer. I could not extract that even from the Government. If the Government's best response is this facade of reconciliation, this public claim to care about ensuring that there is a better understanding and living relationship between the two races, if it genuinely believed in it rather than in putting up this facade of legislation, it would conduct itself privately behind the scenes and publicly in this Parliament in a different way.
       </para>
       <para>
        As I said when I asked the question yesterday, if this is living proof, a technicolour demonstration of reconciliation, an understanding between two races, an acknowledgment of a need to be sensitive to each other's lifestyles, attitudes, beliefs and feelings-if there were a genuine belief in that-it was not demonstrated this morning after Question Time and it was not demonstrated the night before last in Mr Tickner's office.
       </para>
       <para>
        I conclude by saying that it is nothing short of an indictment of this Government and, more particularly, it is a sober revelation of the genuine commitment of this Government and individuals in it towards the Aboriginal community. If I were a cynic, I would say that the Government sees it as a good political issue to be exploited and a whole bunch of votes to be got-nothing more and nothing less.
       </para>
       <para>
        Question resolved in the affirmative.
       </para>
       <para>
        Senate adjourned at 12.34 p.m.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1228" type="Documents">
     <title>
      DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The following documents were tabled:
      </para>
      <para>
       Civil Aviation Act-Civil Aviation Orders-Parts-
      </para>
      <para>
       105, Amendments, dated 23 July, 29 July, 8 August (2) and 16 August (2) 1991.
      </para>
      <para>
       106, Amendment, dated 29 July 1991.
      </para>
      <para>
       107, Amendment, dated 29 July 1991.
      </para>
      <para>
       Lands Acquisition Act-Statement describing lands acquired by agreement under subsection 40(1) of the Act for specified public purposes.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
   </chamber.xscript>
   <answers.to.questions page="1229">
    <title>
     ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS
    </title>
    <proctext>
     <para>
      The following answers to questions were circulated:
     </para>
    </proctext>
    <answer.to.qon page="1229">
     <title>
      Administrative Services: Newspapers and Magazines
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="741">
      (Question No. 741)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="5F4" page="1229" party="LP" speaker="Calvert Sen P.H.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5F4">
         Senator Calvert
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Administrative Services, upon notice, on 14 May 1991:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Are officers of the Minister's department regularly supplied with newspapers or magazines; if so (a) which officer classifications are entitled to this facility; (b) what is each officer's entitlement; (c) which newspapers and magazines are supplied; (d) what was the cost of providing this facility in: (i) 1986-87, (ii) 1987-88, (iii) 1988-89, and (iv) 1989- 90; (e) who supplies the newspapers and magazines to the department; (f) if tenders were called for the supply of the newspapers and magazines, how was the successful tenderer selected; and (g) if tenders were not called for, why not.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="XE4" page="1229" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="XE4">
         Senator Bolkus
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —-I am advised that the answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (a) and (b) No officer has a specific entitlement to newspapers or magazines. Various newspapers and magazines are purchased for Departmental libraries as well as for circulation throughout the Department to particular officers as required.
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) All major daily newspapers and a large variety of magazines which reflect the diverse nature of the Department's operations.
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) (i) The Department of Administrative Services was not formed until July 1987; figures for 1986-87 are not available.
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) $58,650 (approx) *#
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) $58,550 (approx) *#
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) $64,165 *
      </para>
      <para>
       * Figures do not include the cost of journals which were included in an answer of 17 August 1989   to an earlier similar question (Q 1913) in the House of Representatives.
      </para>
      <para>
       # These figures are approximate since extraction of precise figures in respect of some areas would be an unjustifiably costly manual process.
      </para>
      <para>
       (e) Various newsagents and publishers in all States and Territories.
      </para>
      <para>
       (f) Tenders were not called.
      </para>
      <para>
       (g) The individual amounts involved were below the tender threshold.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1229">
     <title>
      Immigration: Mr Jamie Brown
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="983">
      (Question No. 983)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="5F4" page="1229" party="LP" speaker="Calvert Sen P.H.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5F4">
         Senator Calvert
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister Representing the Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs, upon notice, on 21 June 1991:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) What is the current visa/immigration status of Mr Jamie Brown, a British national who entered Australia in 1989 and who currently resides in Evans Head, NSW.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Under what circumstances are British citizens allowed to obtain employment whilst in Australia.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="XE4" page="1229" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="XE4">
         Senator Bolkus
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —-The Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) In deference to privacy concerns, it is inappropriate to comment on the immigration status of a named individual.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) There are no circumstances unique to British nationals governing right to obtain employment in Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       All persons approved for permanent residence and certain temporary residents and their dependants have work rights in Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       Persons entering Australia on visitor visas are not permitted to work, without the written permission of the Secretary to the Department or his delegate.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1229">
     <title>
      Invalid Pension
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1049">
      (Question No. 1049)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="VIC" nameid="LD4" page="1229" party="LP" speaker="Alston Sen R.K.R.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LD4">
         Senator Alston
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Social Security, upon notice, on 23 July 1991:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       What proportion of invalid pensioners granted the invalid pension in 1989-90 and 1990-91 had an assessed medical impairment of 50 per cent or less, 60 per cent or less and 70 per cent or less and who had spouses who have so far been granted a wives' pension.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="VIC" nameid="4E4" page="1229" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4E4">
         Senator Richardson
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —-The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The table below shows the proportion of all persons granted invalid pension in each of the years 1989-90 and 1990-91 whose impairment rating was 50 per cent or less, 60 per cent or less, 70 per cent or less and who had a spouse receiving wife pension at 22 June 1990 and 21 June l991, respectively:
      </para>
      <para>
       Impairment
      </para>
      <para>
       Rating  1989-90  1990-91
      </para>
      <para>
       %  %
      </para>
      <para>
       50 per cent or less  29.2  28.0
      </para>
      <para>
       60 per cent or less  31.6  29.7
      </para>
      <para>
       70 per cent or less  32.6  30.4
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1230">
     <title>
      Transport and Communications Consultancy
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1066">
      (Question No. 1066)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="5F4" page="1230" party="LP" speaker="Calvert Sen P.H.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5F4">
         Senator Calvert
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Administrative Services, upon notice, on 26 July 1991:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) What termination payments, if any, were made to Mr C M Parks upon the termination of his consultancy with the Minister.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) What were the contractual provisions under which these payments were made.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="XE4" page="1230" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="XE4">
         Senator Bolkus
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —-I am advised that the answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) No termination payments were paid to Mr Parks.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Parks resigned from his position as a consultant to the Minister for Transport and Communications to take up a position on the staff of the Prime Minister. He was therefore not eligible for termination benefits.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Not applicable.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1230">
     <title>
      Treasury Consultancy
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1067">
      (Question No. 1067)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="5F4" page="1230" party="LP" speaker="Calvert Sen P.H.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5F4">
         Senator Calvert
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Administrative Services, upon notice, on 26 July 1991:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) What termination payments, if any, were made to Dr K R Henry, Mr I J K Ross and Dr J Edwards upon the termination of their consultancies with the Treasurer.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) What were the contractual provisions under which these payments were made.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="XE4" page="1230" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="XE4">
         Senator Bolkus
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —-I have been advised that the answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) Details of termination payments are as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       Dr K R Henry  Nil payment.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr I J K Ross  $1,377.16
      </para>
      <para>
       Dr J Edwards  $54,969.05
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) The Members of Parliament (Staff) Act 1984 provides that terms and conditions for each consultant are determined by the Department of Industrial Relations.
      </para>
      <para>
       As part of the Determinations the following termination provisions were:
      </para>
      <para>
       Dr K R Henry  No Provision
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr I K J Ross  One month's salary
      </para>
      <para>
       Dr J Edwards  Two month's salary for each six months or part thereof service foregone with a minimum payment of four months salary and a maximum of twelve month's salary.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1230">
     <title>
      Holsworthy Housing Development
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1109">
      (Question No. 1109)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="QLD" nameid="YH4" page="1230" party="LP" speaker="MacGibbon Sen D.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YH4">
         Senator MacGibbon
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Minister for Defence Science and Personnel, upon notice, on 6 August 1991:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       With reference to the new DHA housing development at Holsworthy called `Wattle Grove':
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) Is there a requirement under NSW legislation that an environmental impact study must be done on the proposed subdivision.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Was an environmental impact statement study done before this land was subdivided and development commenced.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Is an impact study now being done, and when was it commenced.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) When was the development application submitted to the local council.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) At what stage was the development project before the environmental impact study was commenced.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) If an environmental impact study is now being done on this land, what is the current status of the development and is there any financial impact from the hold up from the DHA's point of view.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="QLD" nameid="UI4" page="1230" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="UI4">
         Senator Robert Ray
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —-The Minister for Defence Science and Personnel has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) No.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) No, although the Defence Housing Authority had Kinhill Engineers conduct an environmental study as part of its submission to the Joint Parliamentary Committee of Public Works examination of the project in October 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) No.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) To date development applications have been submitted to Liverpool City Council as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       Stage 1B subdivision  6 June 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Stage ic subdivision  12 October 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Stage 2A subdivision  13 September 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Stage 2B subdivision  7 December 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Stage 2C subdivision  8 January 1991
      </para>
      <para>
       Stage 4A subdivision  9 November 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Stage 4B subdivision  9 November 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Stage 6A/6B subdivision  15 May 1991
      </para>
      <para>
       Stage 10A subdivision  31 May 1991
      </para>
      <para>
       Shopping Centre  4 July 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Drainage Retention Basin  4 December 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) See (2) and (3).
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) See (3).
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1231">
     <title>
      Special Benefit
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1166">
      (Question No. 1166)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="SA" nameid="8U4" page="1231" party="AD" speaker="Lees Sen M.H.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="8U4">
         Senator Lees
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Social Security, upon notice, on 16 August 1991:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       For the periods 1 January 1990 to 30 June 1990; 1 July 1990 to 31 December 1990 and 1 January 1991 to 30 June 1991: (a) how many applications were made to the Department of Social Security for the payment of special benefit; (b) how many such applications for special benefit were rejected; and (c) what is the percentage breakdown of the reasons for such rejections.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="SA" nameid="4E4" page="1231" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4E4">
         Senator Richardson
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —-The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (a) and (b) The following information is available from Departmental statistical records:
      </para>
      <para>
       Special Benefit Claims
      </para>
      <para>
       Number  Number
      </para>
      <para>
       Lodged  Rejected
      </para>
      <para>
       6 weeks to end Dec 90  26,200  3,300
      </para>
      <para>
       26 weeks to end June 91  80,800  16,200
      </para>
      <para>
       The numbers of claims lodged and claims rejected for the earlier periods are not available. ADP Statistical Systems to collect this sort of information have been in place only for the period mentioned.
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) Time series data on reasons for rejections are not yet available. However, an analysis of a fortnight's data ending 28 June 1991 shows that the main reasons for rejection of special benefit claims were, in order of importance:
      </para>
      <para>
       Under 16 and does not meet the guidelines for special benefit
      </para>
      <para>
       Incorrect information on record
      </para>
      <para>
       Own request
      </para>
      <para>
       Did not attend interview
      </para>
      <para>
       Income precludes entitlement
      </para>
      <para>
       Did not reply to correspondence
      </para>
      <para>
       In receipt of pension
      </para>
      <para>
       Not residentially qualified
      </para>
      <para>
       Spouse income precludes entitlement
      </para>
      <para>
       Assets exceed allowable limits
      </para>
      <para>
       Failed to produce proof of identity
      </para>
      <para>
       Tax file number not provided
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1231">
     <title>
      Pawpaw Ringspot
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1172">
      (Question No. 1172)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="LH4" page="1231" party="ALP" speaker="Jones Sen G.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LH4">
         Senator Jones
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Minister for Resources, upon notice, on 16 August 1991:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       With reference to the outbreak in south-east Queensland of the exotic plant disease `pawpaw ringspot', one of the most devastating diseases of pawpaw known, and never previously detected in Australia and which can affect pumpkins, melons, zucchinis and cucumbers and the origin of which is unknown:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) What precautions, if any, is the Government taking to prevent such diseases from entering this country.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) How does the Commonwealth Government assess the biological risks associated with the importation of fruit, including pawpaw into Australia.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="RF4" page="1231" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="RF4">
         Senator Cook
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —-The Minister for Resources has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) The Australian Quarantine and Inspection Service (AQIS) has been charged with the responsibility to ensure that adequate quarantine measures are in place to prevent introduction into Australia of serious exotic diseases, including pawpaw ringspot. Plant species known to harbour such diseases have been targeted and vegetative propagable materials are permitted entry into Australia only after they have been screened for disease in a quarantine glasshouse and found free of diseases of quarantine concern. Restrictions on importation of fruit and seeds are applied, if, they have a potential to provide an avenue for introduction of unwanted pests and diseases.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Assessment of biological risks with various fruit imports, including pawpaw, is complex and requires consideration of scientific and technical aspects pertinent to a particular fruit.
      </para>
      <para>
       In short, diseases of quarantine concern are identified and management options to minimise the risk of their introduction into Australia are investigated. Quarantine measures are determined accordingly. These may range from unrestricted entry to total prohibition or importation subject to a satisfactory treatment or sourcing from an area free from specified pests and diseases.
      </para>
      <para>
       Fruits and seeds are not known to spread pawpaw ringspot. Therefore, AQIS has not exercised any measures, for fruit and seed imports, against pawpaw ringspot virus.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
   </answers.to.questions>
  </hansard>
 </body>
</html>
