<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" "hansard.dtd">
<html>
 <body>
  <hansard chamber="Senate" date="21/06/1994" page="1775" parliament.no="37" period.no="4" proof="No" session.no="1">
   <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
     <day.start date="21/06/1994">
      Tuesday, 21 June 1994
     </day.start>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         The DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Crichton-Browne)
        </emphasis>
        took the chair at 9.30 a.m., and read prayers.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </business.start>
    <debate page="1775" type="Ministerial Arrangements">
     <title>
      MINISTERIAL ARRANGEMENTS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1775" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="VD4">
         Senator GARETH EVANS
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave—I inform the Senate that the Minister for Family Services, Senator Crowley, is attending a health and community services ministerial council meeting in Sydney and will be absent from question time today. During Senator Crowley's absence, Senator Cook will take questions relating to human services and health, including family services, Senator Schacht will take questions on social security and I will take questions relating to the status of women.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <qwn page="1775">
     <title>
      QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
     </title>
     <question.block page="1775">
      <title>
       Interest Rates
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="1775" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BH4">
          Senator HILL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Leader of the Government in the Senate. I refer to expectations expressed today by respected economists that, as a result of the government's lax fiscal policy, interest rates are expected to rise by at least one per cent in the near future. Does the minister appreciate that this will add $864 a year to the average home loan? When will the government come clean and acknowledge that a failure of its policies will result in interest rate rises and that new home buyers and small businesses should be factoring this into domestic budgets and business plans?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1775" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —On the substantive matters in issue, I have nothing to add to what I said yesterday which, in essence, was that at some stage of the recovery interest rates will need to rise to ensure that inflation remains low. Official interest rates have fallen to their lowest level since the 1970s and we have to expect that there will be an increase in rates at some stage of the recovery. But interest rates will not rise in the near term because inflation in Australia is at historically low levels and is among the lowest in the Western world. That is the truth of the matter. Those are the fundamentals of the Australian economy, and there is no rational basis for any interest rates rise in the near term given that particular inflationary environment.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         On the subject of fiscal responsibility generally, we do not need to be lectured by the likes of Senator Hill and the opposition on this particular matter. Our responsibility has been to identify a path of fiscal management by this country which will return to budget in approximate balance within a few short years, 1996-97. That has been universally acknowledged to be a totally responsible approach to be adopted by the government and it is one that is, in fact, perfectly capable of achievement in a way that will produce a sustained low inflation but, at the same time, high growth environment.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The contrast is quite spectacular between the responsible approach that has been adopted by the government and the conspicuously, vulgarly, populist, opportunistic approach that has been adopted by members of the opposition on this as on every other matter. They sing with different tunes and different songs. Mr Costello says he wants a balanced budget; Mr Downer, of course, wants to spend money on everything under the sun that will appeal to this or that interest group as he systematically works his way around hawking his body to this or that interest group in an attempt to get away from the desiccated imagery of his predecessor.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         He has not persuaded anybody so far; he will not in the future because there is no substance or integrity in the opposition's policy. Those opposite might have changed their leadership, they might have changed their front bench, but there is an iron law of arithmetic that applies in this sort of situation; that is, nothing plus or minus nothing still equals nothing.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="1775" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BH4">
          Senator HILL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. Is it not the real case, as Mr Mark Hopkinson, the head of financial markets in Schroeders, said this morning, that the political stakes are pretty high in this exercise? Is it not the real fact that the government is concentrating on the internal political consequences rather than giving Australian business and home buyers a real appreciation of what is to logically follow from its fiscal failures? Does the minister not recognise that yesterday bond yields soared to their highest levels since April 1992 and short-term interest rates rose sharply? Does this not logically mean that in the relatively near future there will be a substantial lift in interest rates, speculated today to be at least one per cent? The government should be advising home buyers and small business to be taking this into account.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1775" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I made perfectly clear that, the way this system operates, we cannot work on the assumption that movements of this kind can be resisted in perpetuity. It is the case that at some stage of the recovery cycle we do have to anticipate some rise in interest rates. But there is no ground for anticipating such a rise in the near term when the fundamentals remain as solid as they are. If the opposition had any responsibility at all in this respect, it would be trying to get some sanity and balance back into the bond market, not talking up the irrationality that is conspicuously there at the moment.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         There are no fundamental reasons in the Australian market. There is a bit of volatility that is generated by the situation in the United States and overseas. But, if we look at the fundamentals of the Australian market—the underlying inflation rate and the reasonable expectations this economy has for the future—there is simply no foundation for the behaviour of the markets in this respect at the moment. For the opposition to talk up the degree of irrationality that is prevailing at the moment is to perform no service at all to home owners, home buyers or anyone else.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1776">
      <title>
       Wet Tropics Tree Planting Scheme
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="XI4" page="1776" party="ALP" speaker="Reynolds Sen The Hon M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XI4">
          Senator REYNOLDS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I address my question to the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories. The minister will be familiar with the wet tropics tree planting scheme initiated by a number of Far North Queensland councils. This valuable scheme is currently funded only until 30 June this year. Can the minister report on the future of this very important project, which has both employment and environmental values?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="ENVIRONMENT, SPORT AND TERRITORIES" nameid="5K4" page="1776" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am pleased to say to Senator Reynolds and other senators that the government has committed a further $3 million over the next two years to enable the Queensland wet tropics tree planting scheme to continue. As I indicated to the Senate on 7 June, Commonwealth funding for the existing program was due to cease on 30 June this year. That closure of the scheme would have resulted in a loss of staff, infrastructure and significant expertise at a time when the Commonwealth is seeking to establish more work opportunities for people in that area.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Obviously, I am delighted with this decision that has been made. It is going to end the uncertainty that has existed in relation to this very successful scheme—uncertainty, of course, that has been stirred up by opposition senators, particularly Senator Ian Macdonald, who was gleeful about the supposed end of this scheme for his own partisan political purposes, implying as he did that the scheme would end and workers would be thrown out onto the scrap heap.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YW4" speaker="Senator Ian Macdonald">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YW4">
           Senator Ian Macdonald
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —If I hadn't arranged it, you wouldn't have done anything about it.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I hope that you go and apologise to them and their families for the uncertainty that you have caused. You do not give a damn about the welfare of the workers who are involved in this scheme and you certainly do not give a damn about the environmental benefits of this scheme that are well known to—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="7E4" speaker="Senator Vanstone">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="7E4">
           Senator Vanstone
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Why don't you stick to things you know?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YW4" speaker="Senator Ian Macdonald">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YW4">
           Senator Ian Macdonald
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Stick to kneecapping.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will stick to kneecapping you, Senator, and it is not very difficult. This is your best own goal since you proposed 15 per cent—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LI4" speaker="Senator Patterson">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LI4">
           Senator Patterson
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President, I raise a point of order.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —on sewage in the last federal election. Can I formally congratulate you on—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Senator Patterson has a point of order.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LI4" speaker="Senator Patterson">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LI4">
           Senator Patterson
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President, thank you for finally recognising me. The minister finally had the good grace to sit down. I draw your attention to the fact that the minister was directing his comments directly to Senator Macdonald. I ask him to direct them through you.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! There is a nice balance about all these things. In the robust debate of question time, I normally allow comments across the chamber. Strictly, in accordance with standing orders, they should come through me. Given the exchange between the two, I was prepared to allow it to flow.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, this particular scheme's track record in environmental management and repair means that we will be well placed to provide very valuable on-the-job training and supervision under Commonwealth labour market programs, such as the regional environmental employment program, which was announced as part of the jobs compact component of Working Nation.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Under the new funding arrangements, management of the scheme will be transferred to a joint board comprising 11 local councils, where it will be jointly administered with other tree planting schemes currently operating in that region. This scheme will also be incorporated as a community based employment company. A consultant will be engaged to develop a business plan which will enable the company to take advantage of REEP and a range of other labour market programs. The plan will also develop a range of opportunities to attract funds from private enterprise and local government. Federal funding for the scheme will cease at the end of the 1995-96 financial year, after which time we certainly hope and believe that this scheme will be on a self-sustained footing.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The wet tropics tree planting scheme, despite all the best efforts of the opposition, has been a popular and successful initiative of this government. Its restructuring offers great potential for a cooperative approach towards meeting environmental, labour market, and industry development objectives. I am sure that, with the exception of Senator Ian Macdonald, all Australians will be delighted with this decision.
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1777">
      <title>
       Economy
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="BX5" page="1777" party="LP" speaker="Gibson Sen B.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BX5">
          Senator GIBSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Leader of the Government in the Senate. The minister must now concede that the financial markets are in panic mode and that the government's budget and deficit strategy are in crisis. I ask the minister whether he agrees with the following comment by Gerry van Wyngen in this morning's
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Australian Financial Review
         </emphasis>
         :
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         If long-term bond rates remain near 10 per cent, while the short-term money market rates set by the Reserve Bank remain around 4.75 per cent, the economic recovery will become skewed and eventually crumble.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1777" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have already said all that needs to be said on that subject. If there is any irrationality in the financial markets, there is no point in stroking it further by questions of that kind coming from the opposition. It is time for a few steady nerves and cool heads in this situation, not the kind of talking up that the lot opposite seem to be so anxious to do.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="BX5" page="1777" party="LP" speaker="Gibson Sen B.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BX5">
          Senator GIBSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I have a supplementary question. Society Generale economist Ms Ivana Bottini says the reason for the market panic is that `Australia did not have enough savings'. When will the government reassess its deficit strategy and advise the business community, particularly the small business community, of what to expect in interest rates and increased taxation in the near future? Will that reassessment come by way of a mini-budget?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1777" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Ditto.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1777">
      <title>
       Aircraft Noise in Darwin
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="PF4" page="1777" party="ALP" speaker="Colston Sen M.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="PF4">
          Senator COLSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question, which is directed to the Minister for Defence, relates to aircraft noise in Darwin and follows a question asked by Senator Jones on 4 May. In answer to Senator Jones's question, the minister indicated that he had asked the Deputy Chief of Air Staff, Air Vice Marshal Les Fisher, to visit Darwin to investigate the issue of military aircraft noise in that city. Has Air Vice Marshal Fisher now reported and, if so, could the minister advise the Senate of the results of the investigation which he foreshadowed last month? Will the minister make the report of the Deputy Chief of Air Staff available to the Senate?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE" nameid="UI4" page="1777" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UI4">
          Senator ROBERT RAY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As I foreshadowed in the Senate last month, the Deputy Chief of Air Staff, Air Vice Marshal Fisher, visited Darwin from 10 to 13 May to undertake a full investigation into aircraft noise in Darwin. His brief included allegations that visiting pilots were straying from their designated flight paths and agreed procedures. As part of that investigation, a wide range of Darwin people were interviewed, including community leaders, business leaders, residents and other interest groups. I will summarise the major findings of the investigation.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         There was no evidence that the United States marine corps pilots strayed from flight plans. There was evidence of one marine corps pilot not complying with an air traffic direction. The pilot misunderstood the requirements and was counselled by the marine corps authorities to prevent a recurrence. There was evidence that noise abatement procedures were breached. However, the noise abatement procedures promulgated by the Royal Australian Air Force lacked clarity and could be misunderstood, especially by foreigners. In addition, they were not fully effective in reducing military jet noise to reasonable levels. No arrangements were in place to ensure that all pilots had received and understood the procedures. Lastly, the public relations effort for exercises by foreign services operating from Darwin has not been effective.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I have now had an opportunity to consider Air Vice Marshal Fisher's report and its conclusions. I have agreed to a number of sensible changes to existing procedures which will minimise aircraft noise. Revised noise abatement procedures will be put in place which more closely reflect the suburban disposition of Darwin and the concern of residents. They will require military fast jet aircraft to conduct straight-in approaches by day and night, except during major defence exercises such as Pitch Black and Kangaroo. Arrangements will be put into place to ensure that all pilots comply with the revised noise abatement arrangements.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Additional resources will be provided to control and monitor foreign force activities. A much greater effort will be made to ensure that the Darwin community is kept fully informed of why, when and for how long foreign military aircraft will be operating from Darwin and of the efforts being made to minimise noise. With regard to the last part of the honourable senator's question, I can advise the Senate that Air Vice Marshal Fisher's report will be tabled in the Senate tomorrow.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1778">
      <title>
       Public Hospitals
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="8U4" page="1778" party="AD" speaker="Lees Sen M.H.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8U4">
          Senator LEES
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the minister representing the minister who represents the Minister for Human Services and Health. I refer the minister to the current sale and the proposed closures of public hospitals in a number of states. Is the Commonwealth monitoring the sale and closure of our public hospitals in the various states and, if so, can the minister give us some idea of how many hospitals have actually been closed and how many are being put to tender? Is the government concerned about these closures? What action is the federal government taking to either prevent the closures or to ensure that the closures and sales do not in any way lead to inequities in access to hospital services, particularly in rural Australia? Finally, will the Commonwealth government now be contributing less money to those states that are closing down or selling off their public hospitals?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY" nameid="RF4" page="1778" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have just checked my briefing folder; I do not have a brief on this subject before me, so I cannot authoritatively answer the detailed elements of the honourable senator's question. I will put those detailed elements on notice and provide an answer as soon as possible—certainly this week. I can say that the Minister for Human Services and Health, Dr Lawrence, does have a very keen overview of what the changes are in the health system. She is, of course, taking cognisance of the efforts to sell off hospitals in the public and private health systems and she is concerned about the impact on the total health effort in Australia as a consequence. I will refer the detailed questions, which require specific answers, to Dr Lawrence and will provide Senator Lees with her reply.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1779">
      <title>
       Trade Promotion in Indonesia
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="AX5" page="1779" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen C.V.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="AX5">
          Senator CHRIS EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Industry, Science and Technology. The minister would be aware of my continuing interest in the Australian involvement in the important Australia Today promotion currently under way in Indonesia. Can the minister inform the Senate what steps are being taken to build on the white paper industry initiatives, particularly the focus on fully utilising Australia's rich science and technology base, as part of our involvement in the Australia Today promotion?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY" nameid="RF4" page="1779" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do acknowledge Senator Chris Evans's close interest in this matter. Last Saturday in Jakarta I had the pleasure of showing the Indonesian Vice-President, General Try Sutrisno, through the major exhibition showcasing Australian science and technology capability. The exhibition was entitled `Visions for the Future'.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="7E4" speaker="Senator Vanstone">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="7E4">
           Senator Vanstone
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Who cares if you were there? Tell us about the exhibition, you great dork.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —This is an extraordinary intervention. Here is an exhibition which showcases the best in Australian science, which was viewed by the Vice-President of Indonesia, and which is regarded by the Indonesian media and expert commentators as a key exhibition and one of the best of its kind, and the opposition complains about it. That is a disgusting reflection on the opposition's priorities.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         President Suharto and the Minister of State for Research and Technology, Dr Habibie, both visited the exhibition in May this year, which was then premiered as part of Ristek, the Indonesian science and technology exhibition. Their strong interest in the exhibition led to the invitation to include this exhibition in the Jakarta Fair, which the Vice-President opened on Saturday morning and which is Indonesia's largest yearly trade fair.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         This exhibition represents areas in science where Australia is a world leader and, importantly, areas in science that have a direct, useful and practical application to the needs of Indonesia and, on a broader scale, the needs of this region. It covers the areas of energy, environmental technology, telecommunications and environmental technology.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="H15" speaker="Senator Campbell">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="H15">
           Senator Campbell
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Nano-technology?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As Senator Campbell interjected, nano-technology is included, as is aerospace technology, medicine, biotechnology, engineering and education. The exhibition forms part of the major trade and cultural promotion, Australia 94, that Australia is undertaking in Indonesia over the next few weeks.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         As I have said, the `Visions for the Future' exhibition showcases some of the best examples of Australian science and technology and is compelling because of the interactive nature of the displays. Interactive touch-screen guides introduce people to Australia's remarkable achievements in science and technology in both English and Bahasa Indonesian. They refer people to the companies and institutions that manufacture the particular exhibits. It will be particularly important in showing Indonesians from a wide range of backgrounds that there are significant numbers of areas in which Australian expertise can assist Indonesia's economic development.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I am very pleased that the exhibition had already led to the signing of $12 million in joint ventures between one of the Australian participants and a new Indonesia based company that will carry out environmental and research monitoring. There are many other examples of areas of potential cooperation between our two countries. For example, Australian scientists have developed the world's most efficient solar cells and solar powered streetlights. As well, Australian researchers were the first in the world to build the bucky-balls, large soccer ball shaped molecules of carbon, which will have enormous use in industry, the environment and health care. Australian scientists have synthesised a new drug that may cure and prevent all forms of influenza virus. The world's aircraft manufacturers are turning to the Australian development—
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1780">
      <title>
       Minority Groups
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="GX5" page="1780" party="LP" speaker="Troeth Sen J.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="GX5">
          Senator TROETH
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister representing the Prime Minister. Has the minister noted the comments of his ministerial colleague Gary Johns that for too long the Labor government has been responding to the demands of minority groups, which he defined to include `women, migrants, blacks and homosexuals', rather than the real and genuine needs of mainstream Australia? Was Mr Johns outlining a new government strategy to refashion itself so as to crudely attempt to appeal to those many Australians who have been ignored by the policies of this government?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1780" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My understanding is that Mr Johns has been rather misunderstood on the point he was making. As I am advised, he was emphasising the virtues of tolerance in Australian society and recognising the need for people to live together. In a subsequent communication to the centenary advisory committee, he said:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        I was alluding to a quote from Donald Horne's How to be Australia paper which said "We should show the world how to be a nation without being nationalistic—
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="Senator Alston">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President, I raise a point of order. The minister is not being asked how Mr Johns attempted to extricate himself by rewriting political history. He is being asked whether or not Mr Johns used those words and whether they represent the government's official position. Senator Bolkus disagrees with Mr Johns; does the minister disagree with him?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! There is no point of order. I am sure Senator Evans is answering the question.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is not always entirely reasonable to rely on what people say. It is what they mean to say that matters. Mr Johns meant to say:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        We should show the world how to be a nation without being nationalistic and how to be tolerant without falling apart.
       </para>
       <para>
        Mr Johns, like the rest of us, is against things falling apart. That is a very sensible observation to make about the social fabric of this country.
       </para>
       <para>
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Honourable senators interjecting—
        </emphasis>
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! I do not know whether Senator Troeth can hear the answer but I cannot.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —In making a substantial contribution to informed and sensible national debate on this matter, what Mr Johns meant to say was perfectly reasonable and perfectly sensible. I do not think he or the government needs to make any apology for it.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="GX5" page="1780" party="LP" speaker="Troeth Sen J.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="GX5">
          Senator TROETH
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I ask a supplementary question. Does this mean that we now need to `tolerate' women in Australia? Also, why has the Prime Minister not reprimanded Mr Johns for providing such a damning report card on the Labor government's 10 years in office?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1780" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The only point that needs to be made in addition to what I said before is that Mr Downer made himself conspicuous by responding not to what Mr Johns meant to say but to what Mr Johns was construed as saying about these divisive tendencies. He did not cover himself with any glory at all in this respect, nor has he on any of the other half dozen issues on which he has flipped and flopped in a half-baked populist way since he was elected to the leadership. I have nothing more to say on that subject.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1780">
      <title>
       North Korea
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="DX5" page="1780" party="GWA" speaker="Margetts Sen D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DX5">
          Senator MARGETTS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister for Foreign Affairs. In light of the current crisis on the Korean peninsula and in light of Australia's role both as a supplier of uranium to the region and as chair of the International Atomic Energy Agency board of governors, will the minister inform the Senate how the decision by Australia to support any UN sanctions was reached? Was the issue debated by either the Labor parliamentary caucus or cabinet? If the matter was not debated at either level, who made the decision to support UN sanctions and on what basis? Will the minister release details of the role played by the Australian chair of the IAEA's board of governors in the North Korean stand-off? Did Australia's position on the IAEA require the Australian government to agree to UN sanctions against North Korea even at the risk of war on the peninsula? Would the minister explain why Australia, as a nation concerned with the preservation of the nuclear non-proliferation treaty, supports US efforts to impose UN sanctions on North Korea?
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1780" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The question of UN sanctions in relation to North Korea remains hypothetical at this stage. Hopefully, in the light of the recent developments that I talked about yesterday, it will not be necessary to go down that particular path. But, if UN sanctions ever are applied in this situation, Australia has an obligation as a UN member to support those sanctions. It would be quite unthinkable for us to do otherwise. In the event that mandatory measures are adopted by the Security Council, Australia, like every other member of the UN, would be bound to implement them.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Support for the UN in these respects has been a longstanding pillar of Australian foreign policy and there is absolutely no need in that context to have any formalised approval procedures as new situations evolve. If they are consistent with established principle and established approaches—as this is, as I have just described—there is no issue that needs to be considered case by case.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         So far as our role in relation to the International Atomic Energy Agency is concerned, we played the very responsible role that one would expect us to be playing as a longstanding member in good standing of that particular organisation and as chairman of it during the recent troubled period. We are a country with a very strong commitment to the IAEA and to the nuclear non-proliferation treaty. We do take the view that it is appalling for any country to walk away from its obligations under that particular treaty and we will always, as a result, be among those willing to apply appropriate measures in situations where countries do not discharge their obligations formally and solemnly entered into. That, regrettably, was the situation so far as North Korea was concerned.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Senator Margetts was impliedly asking me about the situation in relation to Japan and other countries that might be closer perhaps to possessing nuclear weapons. I just say, in anticipation of that, that in the case of Japan it is a country with very good standing as a member of the non-proliferation treaty and the Atomic Energy Agency. It is not a matter of Australia ignoring anything in relation to Japan's nuclear conduct in this respect. We have absolutely no doubt whatsoever that the only nuclear activity in which Japan has been engaged, or is likely to be engaged, is in relation to peaceful purposes.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         In the case of other countries that may have nuclear weapons possession potential—Israel, India, Pakistan are those that are most commonly mentioned in this respect—the situation is that, regrettably, they are quite outside the nuclear non-proliferation treaty. They are not parties to any of these international obligations and, as such, there is no basis on which the international community can effectively respond to any new development. That is a situation we would very much like to change and have been working actively diplomatically for a very long time to try to change, not least in the context of the nuclear non-proliferation treaty review conference which comes up next year.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="DX5" page="1780" party="GWA" speaker="Margetts Sen D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DX5">
          Senator MARGETTS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I ask a supplementary question. Does this mean that Australia will be jumping on the bandwagon with any particular country that the United States of America thinks is a good mark in relation to nuclear non-proliferation?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1780" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That is not quite the way in which I would put it. When a country is in flagrant and deliberate violation of its solemnly entered into treaty obligations under something as important as the nuclear non-proliferation treaty, it is very difficult for the United States, Australia or anyone else in the international community to simply stand back and say that that kind of behaviour should go unresponded to. At the same time, of course, in a very delicate situation of this kind where we are trying to take into account not only the effect of past actions but possible future actions, it does make sense to try, so far as humanly possible, not to make the situation any worse and to go down the path of a rational and negotiated solution. That, as I said yesterday and elsewhere, is the way we believe this situation should evolve if it possibly can.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1782">
      <title>
       National Flag
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="WW4" page="1782" party="LP" speaker="Kemp Sen C.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="WW4">
          Senator KEMP
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Leader of the Government in the Senate. Is it correct that, as reported in the newspapers this morning,  Mr Keating has ruled out a referendum prior to any change in the flag? Is it correct, therefore, that the government proposes to make a change in the flag without seeking the formal approval of the Australian people? Further, if the government is not prepared to support a referendum, what approach does the government have in mind to test public opinion on this issue?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1782" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The flag has never been enshrined in the constitution, not surprisingly, given that there have been so many different ones during the course of our national history, as those opposite have never been prepared to acknowledge. It has always been a matter of statutory provision, no more than that, and as such, not being in the constitution, it would not be appropriate to apply to any decision about the flag the kinds of procedures that are appropriate for constitutional change, that is, a formal referendum with all the complicated requirements and enormous expense associated with that.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         However, the government has made clear on many occasions that, firstly, details of how any new flag might be chosen have not even been considered by the government. It is not on the agenda at the moment. Secondly, we have made clear—and nothing that Mr Keating has said has changed this—that no scheme for a change would be contemplated which did not involve some act of choice by the Australian electorate between the current design and any proposed new design or alternative designs that might be put. What kind of act of choice might be most appropriately involved in the situation is one for determination closer to the time. The government has made it perfectly clear that we do not see this as being a matter for unilateral government action. It is a matter on which the community should have a say.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="WW4" page="1782" party="LP" speaker="Kemp Sen C.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="WW4">
          Senator KEMP
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I have a supplementary question. As Senator Gareth Evans knows, we have had a problem in recent weeks of the government rewriting history. We have had one national flag since 1903, so he was wrong on that. It was a national flag that the Labor Party was prepared to fly and be proud of.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UI4" speaker="Senator Robert Ray">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UI4">
           Senator Robert Ray
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —What is the question?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="WW4">
          Senator KEMP
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Thank you, Senator. Could the honourable senator keep quiet for a moment? In 1992 it was said that a cabinet paper was being prepared on this whole issue, on how the government proposes to make a change to the Australian flag. What happened to that cabinet submission? What forced the government to change its mind? Surely the Australian people are entitled to know what the government has in mind when it talks about an act of choice.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1782" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am not aware of anything having happened to take further any preliminary discussion that might have been involved in 1992. But let me tell the Senate what happened in 1967. That was the year when Mr Harold Holt, as leader of the then government, on behalf of the government dumped the Royal Australian Navy's white ensign with its red cross of St George, under which thousands of Australians had served and died in three wars in the naval capacity, in favour of the RAN's present ensign with the Southern Cross in blue. There was not any active public discussion or public choice. There was no referendum, no publicity, no nothing; it was just a unilateral stroke of the pen. It was a flag under which Australians in their thousands had fought and died in three wars.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That is the kind of regard the other side has for this particular issue. That is the kind of selective indignation, that is the kind of selective history, we have whenever this particular issue is raised. Let us have no more nonsense. Let us have a little bit of informed, rational and sensible debate.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1782">
      <title>
       Small Business
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="656" page="1782" party="ALP" speaker="Forshaw Sen M.G.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="656">
          Senator FORSHAW
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Small Business, Customs and Construction. I understand that the minister recently hosted the 10th National Small Business Forum in Canberra consisting of representatives of major small business organisations. What matters were discussed at the Small Business Forum? What were the principal outcomes arising from the forum?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="SMALL BUSINESS, CUSTOMS AND CONSTRUCTION" nameid="4J4" page="1782" party="ALP" speaker="Schacht Sen The Hon C.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="XW4" speaker="Senator Kernot">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="XW4">
           Senator Kernot
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You need to have another go.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Kernot interjects. As I said yesterday, we are delighted that the Australian Democrats have suddenly discovered small business. I do not know how long this will last but we are very pleased that Senator Kernot has discovered it. This is a big improvement on members of the opposition, who never ask a question about small business other than Senator Boswell, whom I have acknowledged before as the only one on the other side who has a genuine interest in this matter.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The present Leader of the Opposition, Mr Downer, at one stage in his career was the shadow minister for small business. After a short period as shadow minister—he announced that there would be a major new policy on small business, which never saw the light of day—in May 1989 he was dumped and sacked as shadow minister for small business and sent to the back bench. When Mr Downer gets up now and talks about his interest in small business we can only hope that he does a better job than when he was shadow minister in 1988-89. This is typical of the opposition, which has no interest in small business whatsoever.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The Small Business Forum held on 10 June was another successful meeting of that forum at which nearly 30 small business and industry organisations were represented. Senator Kernot would be interested that the matters discussed included presentations from the Commonwealth Development Bank and the Export Finance Insurance Corporation about the availability of finance to small business and how the industry statement released in early May has made it easier for small business to get access to that finance. We also had presentations from Senator Cook, who explained the creation of Ausindustry, and Mr Gary Johns, the Assistant Minister for Industrial Relations.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="WW4" speaker="Senator Kemp">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="WW4">
           Senator Kemp
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —What did he mean to say?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I want to point out, over the heckling from those opposite—who never ask a question about small business—that, as a result of that presentation from Mr Johns, we are now establishing arrangements whereby a subgroup of the Small Business Forum will hold regular meetings with Gary Johns to discuss issues obviously relating to issues of industrial relations as they affect small business. The Small Business Forum was very pleased to be able to have that structure established, where it can put its views, even if they are not the same as the government's views. We are not afraid of hearing the constructive criticism which overwhelmingly is the basis of the work of the Small Business Forum.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The Small Business Forum, established by this government, is a great success. It is much more successful than the effort Mr Downer made when he was shadow minister and much better than the effort of those opposite—who never ask a question. To show the strength of this organisation, I will table for the Senate the list of the membership of the Small Business Forum and the Small Business Coalition—organisations which, obviously, most senators opposite have no idea even exist.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1783">
      <title>
       Afghanistan: War Crimes
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="YH4" page="1783" party="LP" speaker="MacGibbon D.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YH4">
          Senator MacGIBBON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Foreign Affairs. Is the minister aware of allegations that, despite warnings to Senator Ray when he was the migration minister in May 1989, a number of alleged war criminals who were members of the Najibullah regime in Afghanistan, a regime which is said to have executed 1 1/2 million of its own citizens in its civil war, have been granted permanent residency in Australia? Has the former deputy head of Khad, the ruthless secret service in Afghanistan, been granted permanent residency? Has the former vice president of this repressive regime been granted a temporary visa? Was the government aware of the background of these two individuals when residency and a temporary visa were granted to them?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1783" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The government is not yet fully apprised of the status and other relevant details of the persons in question. The identity of two of them has been established, but nothing is known of the third person referred to on the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          7.30 Report
         </emphasis>
         at this time. The Department of Immigration and Ethnic Affairs is considering an application for refugee status from one of the persons named at this stage. The second person has resident status in Australia, having entered under the humanitarian program. His visa was issued in New Delhi after all normal requirements had been assessed as met. The allegations in question are known to the Australian security authorities and they are being investigated at the moment. At this stage it is not possible to add anything further to that information. If and when further details do come to hand—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="Senator Alston">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I wrote to you—
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Most of Senator Alston's correspondence deserves to be ignored. Whether that one was ignored, I do not know. I myself was not aware of the particular allegations having been made until now. The authorities apparently have been. The matter is being investigated. We will give a further answer as soon as we can.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="YH4" page="1783" party="LP" speaker="MacGibbon D.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YH4">
          Senator MacGIBBON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I have a supplementary question. It is five years since Senator Ray was warned by the Afghan refugees.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UI4" speaker="Senator Robert Ray">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UI4">
           Senator Robert Ray
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —It was not.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YH4">
          Senator MacGIBBON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My information is that it was May 1989. But that is irrelevant. The supplementary question to Senator Evans is: can he give an assurance to the parliament that there was no grubby contra deal done by ASIS, which is his personal responsibility, for information given by these alleged war criminals in return for residency status?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="1783" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator MacGibbon ought to know perfectly well that no Australian government ever has or ever can comment on matters relating to intelligence and security.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YH4" speaker="Senator MacGibbon">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YH4">
           Senator MacGibbon
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —That is not the point. I am asking you to give an assurance.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am certainly not aware of any deal whatsoever being made with anybody on this matter. Certainly, it is my own clear view that no Australian security agency ever has or ever would knowingly assist the entry to Australia of any individual who had been involved in terrorist or war crime activity of this kind.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1784">
      <title>
       Port Hinchinbrook Development Proposal
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="HX5" page="1784" party="AD" speaker="Woodley Sen J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="HX5">
          Senator WOODLEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories. In relation to the Port Hinchinbrook development, is it the case that many of the popular tourist destinations in the area already receive the maximum allowable number of visitors? Does the minister agree that the proposed Hinchinbrook development, which involves a 250-boat marina, would require an increase in visitation to levels that are unsustainable or would force out existing tourist operators, or both? Is the minister aware that some local tourism and development authorities in the area have come out against the Port Hinchinbrook development? Is the minister of the opinion that the development would seriously degrade the natural values of the Hinchinbrook Channel world heritage area?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="ENVIRONMENT, SPORT AND TERRITORIES" nameid="5K4" page="1784" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My portfolio's concerns about the possible impact of the Port Hinchinbrook marina development on the world heritage values of the Great Barrier Reef have been conveyed, as I think Senator Woodley knows, to the Queensland coordinator general's department. My department's submission, along with many others from concerned individuals, is being assessed and considered by Queensland authorities. Queensland government officials came to Canberra on 14 June to discuss the Commonwealth's concern. I understand that Queensland authorities are doing more work to assess the impact of the project on the area's world heritage values and that an environmental management and monitoring plan for the project is being negotiated with the developer.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         My department's main concerns relate to the potential impact of the dredging on the marine fauna and flora in the Hinchinbrook Channel and of increased tourist activities in the sensitive reef and rainforest communities of the region. My department has appointed a consultant to review the world heritage values of the area which surrounds the marina and also to report on any world heritage impacts the development may have and on any management procedures that may be required to protect world heritage features.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         It is premature for the government to consider any use of Commonwealth powers to protect world heritage values. However, as I have said to Senator Woodley before in answer to a previous question on this development, I can assure the Senate that the government will act to protect world heritage values of the Hinchinbrook Channel and the surrounding areas if this proposal does not take sufficient measures to ensure that these values are not threatened. I expect the work being undertaken by the consultant that has been appointed by my department to be concluded within the time scale of a month. I am hopeful that we will receive at least a draft report on these matters from the consultant by the end of June.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1785">
      <title>
       Telecommunications Towers in ACT
      </title>
      <question electorate="ACT" nameid="VI4" page="1785" party="LP" speaker="Reid Sen M.E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VI4">
          Senator REID
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Housing and Regional Development. Why have towers been built in the ACT before a plan for the construction was approved as required by the national capital plan?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="IMMIGRATION AND ETHNIC AFFAIRS" nameid="XE4" page="1785" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XE4">
          Senator BOLKUS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do have some advice on this issue from the relevant minister and that is that at his request the National Capital Planning Authority did in fact seek legal advice on the extent to which telecommunications carriers were subject to the provisions of the national capital plan. The authority was established under the Australian Capital Territory (Planning and Land Management) Act 1988. That provided that no works would be undertaken in designated areas specified in the national capital plan without the written approval of the authority.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I am informed by the NCPA that legal advice provided is that the telecommunications exemption activities regulations, subsection 116(1), exempt the telecommunications carriers from the application of state and territory planning laws. The regulations do not refer to Commonwealth law and, as such, the carriers are not exempt from the provisions in the national capital plan. That is the short end of the legal advice.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Under the terms of the national capital plan, any proposed major expansion of hilltop use will be subject to the development of a comprehensive telecommunications plan. Such a plan does not yet exist. I am further informed that talks are being held between the NCPA, the ACT planning minister, Bill Wood, the ACT Planning Authority and senior representatives of Telecom, Optus and Vodafone, being the three mobile phone carriers involved. I am further informed that all parties have accepted the legal position.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         As a starting point to the development of the telecommunications master plan for the ACT, the carriers are providing the NCPA with details of all present and proposed future installations. Further advice is that the NCPA and the ACT Planning Authority are working together to develop the master plan. This will result in an amendment to the national capital plan, which will involve full public consultation. It is expected that that process will take some three to four months.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That is about as much as I can give Senator Reid on this issue at this particular time. If she requires anything further, I will take it up with the minister.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="ACT" nameid="VI4" page="1785" party="LP" speaker="Reid Sen M.E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VI4">
          Senator REID
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I ask a supplementary question. How long will it be then before the plan for telecommunication construction will be available? The draft was first published in March of 1992. When will that be tabled in the parliament as a completed document? What will the minister do to prevent further construction of towers on hilltops of the national capital until such time as the matter has been resolved?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="IMMIGRATION AND ETHNIC AFFAIRS" nameid="XE4" page="1785" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XE4">
          Senator BOLKUS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will get further information.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1785">
      <title>
       Trade: Health Services
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="SF4" page="1785" party="ALP" speaker="Cooney Sen B.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="SF4">
          Senator COONEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister for Trade. Does the government see any potential for the sale overseas of Australia's health system and services? If so, does it intend to realise that potential in any way?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="ACT" gov="1" ministerial="TRADE" nameid="5I4" page="1785" party="ALP" speaker="McMullan Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5I4">
          Senator McMULLAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —This is a very important aspect of the growth in services trade and services exports, which are such a big part of increases in international trade, not only for Australia but also internationally, particularly in the health area in our region. Of course, health exports go beyond the mere provision of services to issues of equipment. Australia has a reputation—a well deserved reputation—of being at the leading edge in many health and medical technologies and there is the potential for this to become a major new export sector.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         My understanding and advice is that Australian expertise is recognised internationally in a number of areas of technology in the health area. The services supplied in surgery are well known to a number of Australians and internationally as being of world leading quality. Of course, there is significant aged care expertise, amongst others, which could be referred to. Australia offers higher clinical standards at rates which are competitive in the region.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The government commissioned a major study on services exports generally. The study suggests that health export revenues have the potential to increase by an average of 25 per cent over the next five years from roughly $30 million last year. It appears on the basis of that survey and other evidence that Australia is well placed to take advantage of developing markets for health products and services in the Middle East and Asia—a product of the changing living standards in those areas and the burgeoning middle class in that region. The government is actively encouraging the health industry to form strategic alliances to increase exports and promote the internationalisation of Australian health suppliers.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         There is, for example, through the Melbourne-based Australian medical and services export group, which represents, as I understand it, about 25 companies, a very interesting example of the success of this type of cooperation. The group is expecting sales worth $18 million to $20 million to Thailand over the next year for equipment and services. There are other significant strategic alliances in scientific research and R&amp;D generally which have the potential to generate significant revenue for Australia.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         A particularly significant area of the market relates to Japan's rapidly increasing population of elderly people. There are opportunities there for the provision of health services and aged care. The special trade representative John Button, who is well known to Senator Cooney, led a health mission to Japan as recently as November of last year. As a result, several initiatives were developed to enable Australian health providers to capture opportunities in this market, and I think most Australians would welcome that.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         In April I discovered that there is significant potential in the Middle East for Australian-Saudi joint ventures to improve the Saudi health system at significant potential profit to Australia. There is a significant amount of Australian involvement in health in the Middle East already but there is significant potential for it to be significantly enhanced.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UW4" speaker="Senator Crane">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UW4">
           Senator Crane
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —There have been lots of `significants'—five in a row.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5I4">
          Senator McMULLAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —A significant proposal was put forward to me that has the potential to return $200 million a year to Australian health providers—which, I am sure Senator Crane would agree, is very significant. In addition to health services there is the potential for export of medical equipment, which exports currently represent over $300 million a year and I think all of those opposite would welcome.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1786">
      <title>
       Australian Broadcasting Corporation: Mr John Bannon
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="FF4" page="1786" party="LP" speaker="Chapman Sen H.G.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Communications and the Arts. At a time of increasing—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="RF4" speaker="Senator Cook">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="RF4">
           Senator Cook
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Tell us about Richo. Slide out of that, you sleaze.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order, Senator Cook! I ask you to withdraw that.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Withdraw that, you—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —No, I will ask Senator Cook to withdraw, Senator Chapman. I do not need your help.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="RF4" speaker="Senator Cook">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="RF4">
           Senator Cook
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President, of course I withdraw the word, but I wish Senator Chapman could withdraw his questions of the last sitting week when he indulged in mud-slinging of the worst sort under parliamentary privilege.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Senator Cook, that is a debate you might wish to take up at some other time. I have asked you to withdraw the expression, and you have.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Again, I ask the Minister representing the Minister for Communications and the Arts: at a time of increasing public concern about the appropriateness of the ABC being involved in commercial ventures, why has the government appointed to the ABC board the disgraced former Premier of South Australia, Mr John Bannon—a man found by a royal commission to have had a leading role in the $3 billion loss by the State Bank and a man clearly unable to resist the temptation to encourage statutory authorities to become heavily involved in high risk, blue sky private sector activities? Furthermore, how can the ABC be seen to be politically impartial when it has foisted on it a former national president of the ALP?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Honourable senators interjecting
         </emphasis>
         —
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! None of this exchange is helpful to question time, to the Senate or to the standing of the Senate.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="ACT" gov="1" ministerial="TRADE" nameid="5I4" page="1786" party="ALP" speaker="McMullan Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5I4">
          Senator McMULLAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am aware there has been some media speculation about pending ABC board appointments. The Minister for Communications and the Arts has advised me that he has not announced any new appointments at this stage. Honourable senators will simply have to contain their excitement about that for a little while longer.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I can say one thing absolutely clearly: if it were true that John Bannon is to be appointed to the board, his reputation would withstand any reflection made on it by Senator Chapman. Senator Chapman has a record of throwing inaccurate, unjustified sleaze at Australians of dignity. I am sure John Bannon will handle this attempt with the dignity lacking in the way Senator Chapman treats the Senate with his continuing gutter tactics.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="FF4" page="1786" party="LP" speaker="Chapman Sen H.G.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. In view of the minister's failure to answer the question and given that he says this matter is still being considered, I ask him to seriously reconsider this appointment. Also, was the Chairman of the Australian Broadcasting Corporation, Mr Mark Armstrong, and/or the Managing Director, Mr David Hill, consulted about this particular appointment?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="ACT" gov="1" ministerial="TRADE" nameid="5I4" page="1786" party="ALP" speaker="McMullan Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5I4">
          Senator McMULLAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Alston and Senator Chapman have spent one whole hour in a huddle and if this is the best they can do, they need to improve.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="1787">
      <title>
       Meat Industry Levies
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="1X4" page="1787" party="ALP" speaker="West Sen S.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1X4">
          Senator WEST
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy. Meat industry levies are used to raise funds for the operations of the Australian Meat and Livestock Corporation, the Meat Research Corporation, the national residue survey and the Exotic Animal Disease Preparedness Consultative Council and for cattle disease eradication. Can the minister advise the Senate of the changes to the cattle transaction levy and the impact on industry revenue?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY" nameid="OF4" page="1787" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thank Senator West for her question and her continuing interest in rural issues. It is correct that the levies are used to fund the organisations that Senator West has named. I am pleased to announce reductions in those levy rates to the Senate. The new rates will apply from July of this year. The rates will see the cattle transaction levy fall from $4 to $3.60. The slaughter levy on sheep will fall from 55.8c to 47.7c per head, and on lambs it will fall from 105.8c to 89.7c. These reductions in the levies will provide producers with an additional $16 million in their pockets, which I am sure the industry will welcome.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         These reductions reflect the fact that levy collections in recent years have been higher than expected because of the level of sales and the important decisions that have been taken by two of the corporations to reduce the level of  reserves that are being held by them. The government has also been able to reduce the national residue survey component of the levy for sheep and lambs by improved efficiency in the delivery of that program. In addition, the government has agreed to a request from the Cattle Council of Australia for an additional 8c levy component of the transaction levy to be paid directly into the NRS trust fund. This will ensure product quality for the cattle industry through targeted residue testing and producer education. I congratulate the cattle industry on taking this initiative.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The ability to meet consumer demand for clean food will play a large part in determining the future prosperity of the industry in Australia. The reductions in the levy rates confirm a downward trend in livestock industry levy rates. Prior to December 1991, the cattle transaction levy was as high as $6.25. Within the next few weeks, I will release an important industry discussion paper which will focus on the recommendations of the Industry Commission to the government to improve the productivity and competitiveness of this very important Australian industry—the meat industry.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         An important component in that equation is the role played by statutory bodies in the industry. I encourage all industry participants to take a serious and constructive look at those arrangements and to participate in the industry consultative process that will take place on that discussion paper.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="VD4" speaker="Senator Gareth Evans">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="VD4">
           Senator Gareth Evans
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President, I ask that further questions be placed on the
          <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
           Notice Paper
          </emphasis>
          .
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
    </qwn>
    <debate page="1788" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1788">
      <title>
       Wet Tropics Tree Planting Scheme
      </title>
      <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="YW4" page="1788" party="LP" speaker="Macdonald Sen I.D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YW4">
          Senator IAN MACDONALD
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Queensland)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (10.33 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate take note of the answer given by the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories (Senator Faulkner), to a question without notice asked by Senator Reynolds this day, relating to a tree planting scheme in the Queensland wet tropics heritage area.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
        The new Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories, Senator Faulkner, has made a fool of himself since he first took on this portfolio. He has had a lot of catching up to do, but he has not done it very successfully. His inauspicious start was when he was asked about a sensitive environmental, political question in North Queensland. He told the media that he could not stop to answer it because he had a plane waiting for him and he could not face the media. It turned out, as the media reported with great merriment, that the plane Senator Faulkner was waiting to catch was a VIP plane which went when he wanted it to. He became the laughing stock of the media in North Queensland on that beginning, and he has not recovered since.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         He is now having great difficulty with the Oyster Point-Port Hinchinbrook proposal—a proposal that has been approved by the Queensland state Labor government and one which the state Labor government is encouraging to go ahead, subject to stringent environmental conditions which have been imposed. Senator Faulkner is now being captured by the radical left wing greenie movement to try to stop it. He does not understand that it is a major development for North Queensland—one which will create a huge number of jobs.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Senator Faulkner is also in trouble over the skyrail project in Cairns—a project which his department has approved. It is now being targeted by the radical greenie movement. People are coming up from Byron Bay and elsewhere—most of whom are drawing unemployment benefits—to deliberately interfere with the construction of that project, even though it has been approved by both the Queensland government and the Commonwealth government. The proposal by some of these radical green movement people is to interfere with helicopter safety, to sit in trees, to obstruct machinery, and to do whatever they can to stop this project.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Senator Faulkner's other difficulties in the north include his government's stopping funding for the tree planting project. I am pleased to say that, no doubt as a result of my raising this matter a couple of weeks ago in the Senate, Senator Faulkner has had another look at this project and has realised that some money should be given to it and that it should go ahead. I am pleased that Senator Faulkner has had a change of heart on that proposal. I say to Senator Faulkner that, as is the case with most things relating to the wet tropics world heritage area, the Labor government has simply messed up the management of these projects that are intended to try to help with employment—the employment that the Labor government destroyed because of its insensitive management of the wet tropics world heritage listing of the rainforest.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The underlying principle behind Senator Faulkner's providing money for this tree planting scheme is to create jobs. But has he listened to those people who have told him that the way this project has been managed has in fact cost jobs? The giving away of these trees willy-nilly—many would say to friends of certain people in the business up there, friends of certain government officials—has meant that private nurseries which used to make a living out of selling trees have simply gone out of business. So some jobs are created with government money but, at the same time, as a result, the government put people out of work, closed businesses down and created bankruptcies. That is typical of the way the Labor government has acted throughout the whole sorry saga of the management of the wet tropics world heritage listing. While money is given for this tree planting scheme, and I am pleased to see that happening, it is in fact costing jobs and costing businesses.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         What the government should do is use that money to support private businesses. My understanding is that the government would get twice as many trees for the same cost if it went through private businesses. As well, the government would create the same number of jobs but would get twice the number of trees to plant. It seems to make sense that it should be done in the right way.
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="ENVIRONMENT, SPORT AND TERRITORIES" nameid="5K4" page="1789" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (New South Wales-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (10.38 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am pleased to see that the position of some in the opposition has been moderated so that I have only now just been captured by the radical left wing. It makes a change from the rhetoric that others have now espoused in this place for a very long period of time.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I accept Senator Ian Macdonald's grudging congratulations on this matter. I can assure Senator Macdonald that this matter had absolutely nothing to do with him or any other member of the opposition. You raised it in this place and when you did, I indicated in this chamber that Senator Collins, Mr Crean and I had met and had the matter under consideration. A cabinet submission was in the process of being prepared. You did everything you could to sabotage the wet tropics tree planting scheme.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Let us be absolutely clear about your position. You could not care less about the workers who are employed under this scheme. You could not care less about the environmental benefits that this scheme can bring. You do not care at all about the broad level of community support that this scheme has had in North Queensland and you are appalled that the government has continued its strong commitment. You were in here bleating about broken promises and letting people down. Now you are saying that the scheme does not come up to expectations. I say to you, senator, and to other senators, that the government's position on this matter is clear. Our commitment—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Colston)
         </emphasis>
         —It might be better to direct your remarks through the chair.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I would be very happy to direct my remarks through you, Mr Acting Deputy President, because I know you are very open-minded on this matter. The government's position and commitment are very clear. This scheme has seen a very effective infrastructure built up. I think four nurseries with eight vehicles have been established. It has seen considerable expertise built up in nursery operations and in tree planting techniques.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The government is proud to say that it has been primarily responsible for this occurring and it is proud to say that it is responsible for this scheme continuing, which has been enhanced by the announcements I have made today about a development plan. Our expectation is that we will be able to link in with other Commonwealth government labour market programs.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I refer to the general issues raised by Senator Ian Macdonald about my concern for other matters in North Queensland. I am going to take seriously my responsibilities in protecting world heritage values in the Queensland wet tropics and other world heritage areas in this nation.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YW4" speaker="Senator Ian Macdonald">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YW4">
           Senator Ian Macdonald
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Is this another factional brawl?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Senator Ian Macdonald, you have made your contribution.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am going to take my responsibilities seriously in that regard. I can assure Senator Macdonald and other senators that I will continue my commitment in relation to the protection of world heritage values.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YW4" speaker="Senator Ian Macdonald">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YW4">
           Senator Ian Macdonald
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Tell this to the Queensland right.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Senator Ian Macdonald, I have told you that you have made your contribution. You will remain silent.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I can also say that we as a government will not be involving ourselves in the sort of position that Senator Macdonald and other opposition members have put forward. He is known in North Queensland for what he is—an environmental vandal who could not care less about the environmental values, the heritage values or the world heritage values in Far North Queensland. He stands condemned for his record.
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="WA" nameid="H15" page="1790" party="LP" speaker="Campbell Sen I.G.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="H15">
          Senator CAMPBELL
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (10.43 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am going to speak for only a minute because I know that Senator Chapman has some important things to contribute.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="5K4" speaker="Senator Faulkner">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator Faulkner
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —That would be a change.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="H15">
          Senator CAMPBELL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Faulkner wanders around the chamber and throws abuse around. It will be interesting to see whether the Acting Deputy President calls him to order. He probably will not. For Senator Faulkner to call Senator Ian Macdonald an environmental vandal is just a joke; it is untrue. But, of course, we know that Senator Faulkner, as the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories, or the minister for anything, never allows the truth to get in his way. He will abuse people, including those in the opposition and those in the community, ad nauseam.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         We remind Senator Faulkner that whenever he abuses the truth, seeks to misled the people of Australia or abuses our colleagues we will not let him get away with it. We know that Senator Macdonald cares about North Queensland and the people of North Queensland. He does not race off to a luxury jet aircraft when things get a bit hot up there. Senator Macdonald stays up there and does it tough.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Question resolved in the affirmative.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1790">
      <title>
       Minority Groups
      </title>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="N26" page="1790" party="LP" speaker="Abetz Sen E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="N26">
          Senator ABETZ
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (10.45 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate take note of the answer given by the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Gareth Evans), to a question without notice asked by Senator Troeth this day, relating to comments made by the Special Minister of State (Mr Johns) on minority groups.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
        The question asked by Senator Troeth was excellent. The problem is that the answer given was an absolute disgrace. Firstly, the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Gareth Evans) told the Australian people that we should not believe what a minister of the Crown said but that we should somehow interpret what he meant to say. Clearly, that is not a good enough standard for a person who seeks to draw the salary and/or the accompaniments of being a minister of the Crown.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Further, the answer was nothing short of a wholesale humiliation of the minister by the Leader of the Government in the Senate, because the Leader of the Government in the Senate told the Australian people what the minister actually meant. The minister was not saying, `Look, I accidentally said this but I meant to say something else.' Senator Evans was putting words into the minister's mouth. That is very embarrassing from the government's point of view and this needs to be highlighted to the Australian people. The comments of Gary Johns follow on from comments—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Colston)
         </emphasis>
         —Order! Use the proper terms of address. `Mr Johns', please.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="N26">
          Senator ABETZ
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I apologise. The comments of Mr Johns follow on from the comments of another minister, Mr Kerr. We have a government in disarray, ministers going off all over the place and the Leader of the Government in the Senate trying to put it all back together again and telling us what they actually meant to say. That is not good enough.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The other point that needs to be made about Senator Evans's answer is that he has an absolutely condescending and patronising attitude towards mainstream Australia. He said that we have to tolerate these groups. Which groups? Women, who make up a majority of the Australian population, migrants and blacks. There are not many people left in the Australian community when we start knocking out all those groups which, supposedly, we have to tolerate.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         During question time I got one of the attendants to provide me with a
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Macquarie Dictionary
         </emphasis>
         . What does `tolerate' mean? It means to put up with, to endure or sustain as pain or hardship. So Senator Evans is saying that the Labor Party will put up with, and will endure or sustain the pain or hardship caused by women, blacks and migrants in the community. The government asserts that it is concerned about social justice, fairness and equity yet it uses such condescending and patronising language to mainstream Australia.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The only person in the Labor Party who seems to want to treat migrants, at least, as equals is Senator Carr. He is busily signing them up to the Labor Party to assist in stacking the branches in Victoria. It may well be that Senator Carr also tolerates them and puts up with the pain simply to get the gain of stacking branches. It would appear that the attitude of the Leader of the Government in the Senate from his language today is that he will tolerate these groups, and that is nothing short of a disgrace. Senator Troeth's question was a fair and proper question. It shows that she has a commitment to true equality and social justice. Senator Evans today has shown the people of Australia how condescending, patronising and two-faced the Labor Party is to mainstream Australians, namely, women, blacks and migrants. To marginalise them as this minister has is an absolute disgrace.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="1I4" page="1791" party="ALP" speaker="McKiernan Sen J.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1I4">
          Senator McKIERNAN
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (10.50 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I rise to speak to the motion to take note of Senator Gareth Evans's reply to Senator Troeth's question. When Mr Johns's comments were reported in the Australian media I also had some concerns about the content of what Mr Johns was purported to have said about the various minority groups in Australia. My inquiries of Mr Johns and of his office revealed that the reports of what he said were not completely and utterly accurate.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="6E4" speaker="Senator Tambling">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="6E4">
           Senator Tambling
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —What did you say in the phone call?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1I4">
          Senator McKIERNAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I said many things in the phone call, but my phone calls will remain private between me and the minister's office. I used a mobile phone because last week I was travelling extensively throughout this country on parliamentary business. As it was on a mobile it may have been monitored; I am not sure. If it were monitored, it probably would have been transcribed and reported.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Mr Johns's purported comments caused some concern not only to me but also to other members of the Labor Party who voiced that concern to me. I have been able to assure them that the reports of Mr Johns's comments are not accurate. I was actually quite pleased that Senator Troeth raised this matter. It means that we can get a response on the record and set the record straight. It is not always easy to get the record straight on matters such as this, and I am pleased that Senator Troeth gave Senator Evans the opportunity to square the ledger in some way.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         In his contribution to the debate a short while ago, Senator Abetz raised the matter of Senator Carr's contribution to the Australian Labor Party and his caring for migrants in our community who are alleged to be a minority group. Yesterday, I sought to ask a supplementary question of the Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs, who has the portfolio responsibility for migration in this country. Unfortunately, my supplementary question was not properly framed and the Deputy President quite rightly ruled it out of order. I was asking about Senator Bolkus's comments on the Channel Nine
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Sunday
         </emphasis>
         program—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="N26" speaker="Senator Abetz">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="N26">
           Senator Abetz
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Acting Deputy President, I raise a point of order. How is this relevant to the minister's answer given in the Senate just a while ago? Senator McKiernan is trying to engage in a debate that would be more properly in the province of the debate on the adjournment.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1I4">
          Senator McKIERNAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am responding to comments Senator Abetz raised in the discussion. He raised the matters. If they were irrelevant to the debate he should not have raised them. But as he has raised them, I should have the right to respond.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Colston)
         </emphasis>
         —The usual practice is to allow a reasonable amount of latitude here. Senator Abetz did raise the matter and Senator McKiernan is responding to it. I rule that he is in order.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="N26" speaker="Senator Abetz">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="N26">
           Senator Abetz
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I raise a point of order, Mr Acting Deputy President. I draw your attention to the fact that at no stage did I raise Senator McKiernan's question yesterday, Senator Bolkus's answer yesterday, Senator Mckiernan's attempted supplementary question or the Deputy President's ruling thereafter. Those matters were not canvassed by me in any shape or form. Senator McKiernan is clearly abusing the process.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Senator Mckiernan is not abusing the process. Senator Mckiernan may raise those matters in his response.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1I4">
          Senator McKIERNAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Thank you, Mr Acting Deputy President. The matter I raise is branch stacking, which Senator Abetz did raise in his contribution here a short while ago. I am addressing the matter of branch stacking because Senator Bolkus has in his possession the membership of the Liberal Party of South Australia. He told the people of Australia on Sunday that he had this in his possession.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         As happens in all political parties at preselection time—certainly in most political parties—there are some bitter struggles between the contestants who are challenging for office. It appears that in South Australia there is such a challenge going on in one particular seat at the moment. The membership list of the Australian Labor Party of where those people are living and who they are supporting in this particular virulent preselection battle makes interesting reading. It would appear that if there was any branch stacking going on in this country, that branch stacking is alive and well in the Liberal Party in South Australia. That stacking includes the recruitment of migrants to this country in support of particular candidates from one side or the other in the various preselection contests that are going on.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I welcomed the question from Senator Troeth on this matter to give Senator Gareth Evans and the government the opportunity to set the record straight as to what Mr Johns was reported to have said about the influence of minority groups in our society. I think that is welcome. I am quite happy to rise in this place and add my voice in support of that.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Question resolved in the affirmative.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1792">
      <title>
       Australian Broadcasting Corporation: Mr John Bannon
      </title>
      <speech electorate="SA" nameid="FF4" page="1792" party="LP" speaker="Chapman Sen H.G.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (10.55 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate take note of the answer given by the Minister for Trade (Senator McMullan), to a question asked by Senator Chapman this day, relating to a proposed appointment to the board of the Australian Broadcasting Corporation.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
        In answering—or should I say failing to answer—that question Senator McMullan refused to confirm whether Mr Bannon had been appointed to the ABC board. The Minister for Trade (Senator McMullan) who represents the Minister for Communications and the Arts (Mr Lee) in this place is either incompetently ill-informed or is deliberately dissembling to avoid this important and controversial issue.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         He said in his answer that we will have to wait to see what appointments have been made to the ABC board. We do not have to wait at all because this morning Mr Bannon has publicly confirmed, of all places, on ABC radio that he has been appointed to the board of the ABC. We might ask in relation to that appointment: what possible credentials does Mr Bannon bring to the board of the ABC apart from his longstanding political ties to the Labor Party?
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="N26" speaker="Senator Abetz">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="N26">
           Senator Abetz
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Business experience.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Abetz interjects, `Business experience.' That was what I was coming to. As I indicated in my question, we found a complete lack of competent business experience on the part of Mr Bannon. He was found to be heavily involved in the financial disgrace—the $3 billion loss by the State Bank in South Australia—which has bankrupted South Australia, put our economy behind the eight ball, and has now created the need for the present new state Liberal government to try to retrieve that situation and put South Australia back on the road to prosperity.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Apart from that demonstrated incompetence with regard to matters financial, it is entirely inappropriate that a person with that track record is appointed to the board of the ABC at a time when there is massive controversy surrounding the commercial activities of the ABC, particularly with regard to Australian Television International and the ABC's proposed venture into pay television. Mr Bannon is obviously oblivious to commercial realities in relation to management.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="JI4" speaker="Senator Panizza">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator Panizza
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —He has proved that.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —He has proved that, as Senator Panizza rightly interjects, because of his failure to adequately control the affairs of the State Bank when he was Premier—a failure which has been clearly identified by the royal commission into the State Bank. So he brings absolutely nothing of benefit to the board of the ABC. He failed to exercise adequate responsibility as Premier in relation to that State Bank and equally he will fail in similar matters with regard to the ABC board.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         A major responsibility of the board of the Australian Broadcasting Corporation is to look at its financial situation to ensure that the ABC is prudently managed with regard to its financial matters. Quite clearly, John Bannon does not have anything to offer the board in this regard and his appointment on that basis is entirely inappropriate. It is purely a political appointment. That brings into question the capacity of the ABC to remain politically impartial when it has appointed to its board a person who is so clearly identified with the Labor Party.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="WW4" speaker="Senator Kemp">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="WW4">
           Senator Kemp
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Rod Cameron is on the board, too.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As Senator Kemp says, Mr Cameron is also there. Periodically in the past we have had former politicians appointed to the board. I recall that Neville Bonner was appointed. But we certainly have not previously had someone of the political profile of Mr Bannon, a former state Labor premier and a former national president of the Labor Party, appointed to the board of the ABC. He now has a prestigious position as a member of the ABC board, and that clearly compromises the ABC's impartiality with regard to political matters.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         There are two clear reasons why this appointment should not proceed. The first is the demonstrated incompetence of Mr Bannon with regard to matters financial, which is obvious from the report of the State Bank royal commission and his responsibility in that issue. The second is the political bias with which the ABC will now be charged as a result of having someone of Mr Bannon's ilk on its board. Quite clearly, the government ought to reconsider this matter. I wonder—as I ventured in my supplementary question—whether either Mr Armstrong or Mr David Hill was consulted with regard to this appointment and what might be their views on it. Certainly the government ought not to proceed with this appointment, because it is entirely unacceptable.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="SMALL BUSINESS, CUSTOMS AND CONSTRUCTION" nameid="4J4" page="1793" party="ALP" speaker="Schacht Sen The Hon C.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Small Business, Customs and Construction)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.02 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not know whether it has been confirmed that Mr Bannon will be appointed to the ABC board. If he is appointed, it will be a very good appointment. Senator Chapman did acknowledge that Neville Bonner, a former Liberal senator from Queensland, was appointed to the ABC board. That was done by this government. Those opposite did not scream and complain about his appointment after they had dumped him from the Senate.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         In the 1970s it was John Bannon at an ALP national conference who moved the motion which subsequently became ALP policy that there be a staff representative elected by all the staff to the board of the ABC. That position still holds in the ABC.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="FF4" speaker="Senator Chapman">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="FF4">
           Senator Chapman
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —What has that got to do with it?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Those opposite talk about Mr Bannon's interest. I think the staff of the ABC would be very happy that Mr Bannon moved that motion and got that policy adopted so that they have a board representative—something the Liberal Party never really supported. Today we have had Mr Chapman's effort—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="N26" speaker="Senator Abetz">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="N26">
           Senator Abetz
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Acting Deputy President, I raise a point of order. Earlier this morning you pulled me up for referring to somebody by an incorrect title. I would ask you to require the minister to refer to Senator Chapman by his proper title.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para first-indent="16">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Colston)
          </emphasis>
          —I was seeking some information and I did not hear it. If that is the case, I ask the minister to do so.
         </tab>
        </para>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="H15" speaker="Senator Campbell">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="H15">
           Senator Campbell
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Acting Deputy President, I raise a point of order. Could you inform the Senate what time limit is on this debate. My understanding is that question time finished at 10.33 a.m., which would mean that the time for this debate has expired.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —There is one minute, 23 seconds to go.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —We have Senator Chapman continuing his extraordinary performance. We first had the questions about the dog kennel at the Prime Minister's residence, which absolutely fell to the ground and made him a laughing stock. Then we had the questions raised about the so-called Queensland investigation, smearing former Senator Richardson and others, which he had to withdraw. It was publicly quoted last week that Mr Downer finally said to him, `You have no substance to those. Don't go on with them—not another word.' He was not game to say one word outside that door. Now, finally, the gutter politics of Senator Chapman continue with the attack on John Bannon.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         This is typical of an opposition bereft of policy. It can only abuse the personality and cannot in any way talk about policy. This is typical of why those opposite will consistently be in the position of losing elections. That is why they have lost five in a row at the federal level. They allow Senator Chapman to run their policy and all he wants to do is continue to abuse people under parliamentary privilege, and now he is abusing Mr Bannon's supposed appointment when he did not abuse Neville Bonner's appointment at all.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Colston)
         </emphasis>
         —Order! The time allocated to this debate has expired.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Question resolved in the affirmative.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1794" type="Documents">
     <title>
      DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1794">
      <title>
       Tabling
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Colston)
         </emphasis>
         —Pursuant to the order of the Senate agreed to on 18 August 1993, I advise honourable senators that the Manager of Government Business lodged government documents with the clerk immediately after prayers today. A list of the documents is attached to today's red. As the Senate will be adjourning early today to enable estimates committees to meet, there will not be an opportunity to consider the government documents that have been tabled. However, the documents will be listed on the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Notice Paper
         </emphasis>
         and senators will have the opportunity to consider them during general business on Thursday, 30 June 1994.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </proctext>
      <speech electorate="NT" nameid="6E4" page="1794" party="NP" speaker="Tambling Sen G.E.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6E4">
          Senator TAMBLING
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Northern Territory)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.07 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Acting Deputy President, I would like to indicate that I find that to be a most unsatisfactory arrangement inasmuch as allocating consideration of those documents to the last day of the sitting of this parliament will, in effect, preclude it. As the document entitled
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          National action plan: Australia
         </emphasis>
         is a most important document, I seek leave to take note of that paper and to speak to it with the normal accordance that should be afforded.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I have been advised that this is always the case when we rise early for estimates.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6E4">
          Senator TAMBLING
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It may be the case that we do it, but I hope that the government is not seeking to camouflage the importance of this important paper. For that reason, I wish to pursue the normal courtesies and debate on this important matter.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Leave granted.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1795">
      <title>
       National Action Plan: Australia
      </title>
      <speech electorate="NT" nameid="6E4" page="1795" party="NP" speaker="Tambling Sen G.E.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6E4">
          Senator TAMBLING
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Northern Territory)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.08 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate take note of the document.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
        The document tabled today entitled
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         National action plan: Australia
        </emphasis>
        and accompanying comments by Senator Gareth Evans QC was initiated by the Minister for Foreign Affairs (Senator Gareth Evans) and presented on 22 February 1994 to the 50th session of the United Nations Commission on Human Rights in Geneva. It is an insult to this parliament that it has only now surfaced and been tabled in this place. My colleague Senator Rod Kemp has highlighted this matter and I think it is only as a result of his actions and his reservations that we now see it being presented.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         If we turn to the detail of the report, we see that it is a document that ought to demand the attention of each and every parliamentarian. Just about every area of government activity is now subjected to, in one form or another, a national action plan that is subservient to United Nations issues and proposals that flow from an international agenda that has been put forward. Of course, this is important.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I highlighted last night in the adjournment debate that the government had failed to table a north Australia social justice strategy which was distributed last week by the Deputy Prime Minister, Mr Howe. That report—and I refer people to the adjournment debate last night—went into a whole range of issues, in fact more than 240, that were specifically addressed with regard to disadvantage and Labor's social justice priorities on north Australia. That hidden report also highlighted over 170 specific strategies for social justice in north Australia. If we then turn to the national action plan for human rights, which has now been tabled, we find that a whole number of the issues are totally confusing and inconsistent. It is important that these should be drawn to everyone's attention.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         With regard to the areas that specifically affect me in my shadow ministry portfolio of housing, on page 33 of today's report there is an entire listing of a proposed national action plan for housing. This in turn has to be tested against the government's budget priorities and housing issues that have arisen.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         With regard to the north Australian social justice strategy, which I drew to the attention of honourable senators last night, on page 69 of today's report there is an entire section on protecting the rights of rural and isolated people. We find that on page 70 of the proposed national action plan there are only three sentences that address the issues of the rights of rural and isolated people. I refer to the issue that was raised last night in the social justice plan where pages and pages and over 170 strategies were highlighted.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I turn to the area in today's report that lists the issues that relate to protecting the rights of indigenous people. This again needs to be drawn into the other document that was tabled by me, not by the government, last night. On pages 40 and 41 of today's report there is a list of issues relating to indigenous rights. Naturally the government is crowing about the issues relating to the Native Title Bill and the initiatives that it has put through recently with regard to ATSIC. But there is also the commitment to Aboriginal self-determination, and tucked away is a statement of commitment that subjugates this government to issues relating to the United Nations that are totally inconsistent with other plans and proposals that it is putting forward.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Again I refer honourable senators to the north Australia social justice strategy that I mentioned last night. Because this is going to achieve some local consumption there is only one very small three-page chapter on the specific issues relating to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people. You just indicated, Mr Acting Deputy President, that this report, if we were lucky, would have been on the agenda for the last day of sitting. Quite frankly, it would have disappeared into the bowels of the library forever and would never have received proper and due consideration. I hope that several of my other colleagues will also take the opportunity to comment on this report.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="WW4" page="1796" party="LP" speaker="Kemp Sen C.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="WW4">
          Senator KEMP
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.13 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I rise to speak briefly on the document
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          National action plan: Australia
         </emphasis>
         . As my colleague Senator Tambling said, it was tabled in Geneva in February. Now, four months later, it has been tabled in this parliament only because it was drawn to the attention of the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Senator Gareth Evans, at the last estimates hearings on 24 May that this report had not been tabled in the parliament. I note that the same estimates committee is meeting this afternoon. That is the reason why the department has decided to table this report today without, I might say, any proper reason for debate.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         There are two things that I want to draw particular attention to. The first is that the handling of this report shows the attitude of this government to the parliament versus the United Nations. Priority is given to rushing what is a major, important report—in some ways a report which will cause concern in the Australian community—to Geneva, not to consulting with the Australian people or the parliament.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Secondly, this document demonstrates in so many ways that Senator Evans and his colleagues are obsessed with these UN conventions and that they desire to incorporate the UN system more and more into our legal system. Senator Evans is very proud of the fact that ours was the first country to table a national action plan as requested. Senator Evans wants this document to be a model for all other countries. This self-promotion of Senator Evans at the UN is becoming a habit. We certainly hope that it has nothing to do with his career plans for when he leaves this parliament.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I want to draw the parliament's attention to specific issues on pages 6 and 7 of this document, which deal with the attitude of this government to opening up appeals and complaints to UN committees, thereby incorporating UN committees into our legal system. Yesterday in the Senate I tabled the names of the people on the three committees that the Hawke and Keating governments have decided should play a role in our domestic disputes. As noted yesterday, many of the members of those committees are nominated by governments which simply do not practise human rights as we understand them.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         When talking about the sovereignty of a nation and about being proud to be Australian, one of the things we would not do is overturn the philosophy of the Australia Act and involve United Nations committees in Australian domestic law and constitutional law. We would not do it because we believe in the philosophy of the Australia Act; it is appropriate for domestic issues to be treated in our domestic courts and in our parliaments and for laws to be ruled on by known judges.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         There was no need to take the decision to involve the United Nations in our domestic activities. As distinct from Senator Evans, Senator Schacht has been quite honest about the effect of this. Senator Schacht was the Chairman of the Joint Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade when it produced a report that looked at the issue of human rights around the world. That report recognised the fact that UN conventions and treaties have the capacity to limit the sovereignty of nations. Senator Schacht was quite clear about that, and I have no particular argument with him.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         However, the republican Mr Keating and the republican Senator Evans have raised the issue of the independence and sovereignty of our country. The natural question is: why on earth has a decision been taken to involve these UN committees in our domestic activities? This parliament was never asked whether they should be involved; no law was ever passed in this parliament to permit it.
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          The trouble is that an increasing number of cases will now go offshore to be ruled on by these committees in Geneva. That is a big problem for Australia and a problem that will grow in the years to come because these committees will make rulings that do not have the support of any significant section of the Australian community except for the group that feels it has a particular problem.
          <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
           (Time expired)
          </emphasis>
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="SMALL BUSINESS, CUSTOMS AND CONSTRUCTION" nameid="4J4" page="1797" party="ALP" speaker="Schacht Sen The Hon C.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Small Business, Customs and Construction)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.18 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I wish to debate the motion to take note of the document entitled
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          National Action Plan: Australia
         </emphasis>
         . I rise to speak not because I was provoked by Senator Kemp mentioning my name, but because I was struck by three things. First of all, Senator Kemp has been carrying on this scare campaign for some time. I think he sees it as a good way of building up his support amongst the backwoodsmen and women of the Liberal Party in Victoria.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The second thing is that he confuses the arrangements the Australian government takes into account in ratifying the various UN agreements. Thirdly—this is the thing that really struck me—is that he is complaining that this is done without reference to the parliament. That happens because that is the way it is laid out in the constitution of Australia—the constitution that yesterday he was waxing lyrical about, saying that it had no deficiencies and should not be changed in any way—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="WW4" speaker="Senator Kemp">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="WW4">
           Senator Kemp
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Acting Deputy President, I raise a point of order. I do not mind Senator Schacht debating what I have actually said, but it is simply absurd for him to throw up straw soldiers and then proceed to bang them down with vigour. If he wants to quote me, he should quote me accurately and not invent.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para first-indent="16">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Colston)
          </emphasis>
          —Perhaps I could give you some advice. If you want to raise a point of order, raise a point of order. That was not a point of order. If you wish to make a comment about something that has been said, there are procedures in the Senate to do that at a later stage.
         </tab>
        </para>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Kemp has been campaigning on this matter. Yesterday he spoke to a motion and an MPI, accusing the government of wanting to change the constitution.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="WW4" speaker="Senator Kemp">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="WW4">
           Senator Kemp
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —No, that wasn't what I said. I said that you were distorting everywhere.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Hang on. Senator Kemp made a very impassioned speech accusing the government of wanting to change the constitution in all sorts of ways—of tearing it up and so on. Yesterday he spoke lyrical in defence of the constitution. But he now complains that the constitution does not give the Senate or the parliament the power to ratify international agreements. The power lies with the executive. That is how the constitution was written nearly 100 years ago—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="WW4" speaker="Senator Kemp">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="WW4">
           Senator Kemp
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —By Australians?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —By a group of people who believed that was the way it ought to be written. That is how they saw the performance of the executive of government. There was no reference that these things have to be approved by parliament. We are different from the American Senate, which has to approve all foreign treaties. That example was already there, but they ignored it. They chose the example of Great Britain, where the executive could do that off its own bat without reference to the parliament of Westminster. That may well be a deficiency in our constitution, but it will be changed only by holding a referendum. It may be a referendum that Senator Kemp will choose to support. Maybe the treaties ought to be ratified by resolution after debate in the parliament. But the government has every right to do what it is doing because that is what the constitution says—a constitution which Senator Kemp now goes around this country saying is wonderful and not in need of revision.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The Leader of the Opposition (Mr Downer) is saying, `If it ain't broke, why mend it?' That is what he is saying all over the country. Mr Downer is saying, `It is a wonderful constitution. Why change it?' Senator Kemp is now squealing that the constitution allows the executive to ratify UN conventions without reference to the parliament. He has identified an area where he now believes the constitution is broke and he wants to fix it. So he has been caught out. Mr Downer at one level says that it is a wonderful constitution and at another level Senator Kemp wants to say the opposite—that it is terrible that under this constitution the executive can do what it is doing. So he has been caught out. This is typical of the duplicity and the double standards of this opposition, which has no consistency on policy. The only thing it wants to do is nitpick on particular issues and lose all consistency of policy and substance.
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
         .
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="VW4" page="1798" party="LP" speaker="Herron Sen J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Queensland)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.23 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I was fascinated also by the document entitled
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          National action plan: Australia
         </emphasis>
         , particularly in respect of health policy. It is obvious to me that the authors of this document were totally unaware of the ACTU-caucus working party. The objectives in this report have no relationship at all to the government's ACTU-caucus working party and the decisions that it handed to cabinet yesterday. This is yet another example of the government having no idea what to do about the crisis in health care in this country, other than pretend that it does not exist.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         As far as I am aware, the only thing that the former health minister did in relation to health in the year he occupied that position was to recognise there were problems. He produced a mechanism to do something about them, which has been effectively dumped by the ACTU-caucus working party. No solutions at all have been put forward. I was fascinated to read on page 24 of this document:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Specific action includes:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        .
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         restructuring the way general practice is organised and financed . . .
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
        It is a pity the Royal Australian College of General Practitioners or the Australian Medical Association were not aware of this document. Effectively what happened in the budget in May is that the rebates to patients were reduced to half of what they would have been had the original decision of the government and the line that it sold those two bodies before the budget gone ahead. The patients were duchessed by the government, because only when they get their rebates will they discover that the rebates are half what they should have been with the increase. It is another way of bringing in co-payment, because that is eventually what will occur.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Another thing that is occurring in terms of restructuring is the introduction of divisions and accreditation into general practice. Already accreditation has fallen foul of the organisers, and the RACGP is not prepared to go ahead under the government's design. It is an attempt to do away with fee-for-service practice and to introduce that amount of money into the accreditation process. Page 25 of the action plan states:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        . introducing further measures to reduce waiting lists for public patients by allowing public patients to be treated in private hospitals . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        Honourable senators will recall that that was the $100 million. It was not spent, and $78 million of it has gone into the Aboriginal health program. Nobody denies that that money needs to be spent. This document, tabled today, states what the government is going to do. It is going to introduce further measures to reduce waiting lists for public patients by allowing public patients to be treated in private hospitals. That has been withdrawn totally, yet the action plan still states that that is going to occur. The thing that really drew my ire was this statement on page 25:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The Breast Cancer Screening Program aims to screen 1.7 million women over 40 years old by 1995/96 and to continue to offer screening every two years.
       </para>
       <para>
        The government's own accreditation process states:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The program is being progressively implemented in all states and territories over a five-year period and is planned to be fully operational in 1996 when it is anticipated that 860,000 women per year will be screened.
       </para>
       <para>
        That is exactly half the number that is stated in this report. I put to you, Mr Acting Deputy President, that this report is almost a farrago of lies. It is a wish list, a pious presentation to the international community as to what the government would like to do but has not got the wit to do. There is nothing about, for example, the free fall that is occurring in private health insurance where people are dropping out of the private health system and are dependent on the public health system.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Whether Senator Crowley likes it or not, there are only two systems: the public hospital system and the private hospital system. If patients drop out of the private hospital system, they need to be looked after by the public hospital system—not by the Salvation
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
        Army. There is no other body available. They are dependent on the public hospital system. No matter what anybody says in the government, somebody has to look after those people. They still have accidents, they still have babies. They are going to be dependent on the public hospital system. That issue is not addressed in this document; it is not even mentioned.
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="1799" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6H4">
          Senator HARRADINE
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.28 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I want to enter this debate very briefly to comment upon what Senator Schacht said. I am not defending the opposition at all, but he appeared to accuse it of reversing its public stance on the constitution by pointing to a supposed flaw in the constitution which prevents the parliament from exercising its authority in respect of treaties. There is nothing in the constitution which would prevent the parliament from determining this issue. In fact, there is a notice of motion under my name that there be established a Senate committee to consider treaties prior to their signature by the government and to enable the parliament—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="4J4" speaker="Senator Schacht">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="4J4">
           Senator Schacht
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —So what?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6H4">
          Senator HARRADINE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am saying so what.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="4J4" speaker="Senator Schacht">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="4J4">
           Senator Schacht
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —No matter what the committee recommendation is, the government will not take any notice of it.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6H4">
          Senator HARRADINE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The government will take notice of the committee. If the government does not take notice of the committee, any action that the government takes to implement any decisions pursuant to articles of a convention or a treaty would be overruled by parliament, if it had the numbers.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="4J4" speaker="Senator Schacht">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="4J4">
           Senator Schacht
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —By parliament, not by the Senate.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6H4">
          Senator HARRADINE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —By the parliament. In other words, if the government brings legislation in, utilises the external affairs power, points to an article of a particular treaty for that purpose and ignores a decision of a Senate committee which had been previously tabled in the parliament in respect of that article, then we would not expect to get that legislation through the parliament.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I am saying that there is nothing in the constitution which would prevent a proper discussion by the parliament and the public of matters relevant to international treaties prior to their being signed. That is all very good. I am not suggesting that the executive prerogative should be overruled by parliament because we would then diminish parliament's proper functions of audit and control. But what I am suggesting is that the parliament should have more say over treaties and international instruments of this nature.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The process should be a lot more open than it is at present. As a member of the human rights subcommittee of the Joint Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade, I need to advise the Senate that we did consider this report, but we also expressed concern that the report was developed prior to any consultation with us. The human rights subcommittee of that Joint Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade was not consulted prior to this document being developed. We expressed that view.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Having said that, I do not think anyone is putting a blanket condemnation on the work that has been done in this document. Much of this work has been very worth while. I think there is something to be said for Australia taking a lead on human rights issues for its own sake and as an example for other countries to follow. Nevertheless, I do make the point that it is important that the department and the government openly provide opportunities for the parliament and the public to consider matters relevant to treaties prior to their being signed or agreed to.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="WA" nameid="H15" page="1799" party="LP" speaker="Campbell Sen I.G.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="H15">
          Senator CAMPBELL
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.33 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I want to speak about the national action plan. I support the comments of my Senate colleagues. The broad thrust of their arguments has been that this really is a glossy picture of Australia's human rights record. It has been put together very quickly. It is a monument to the federal government's international posturing on human rights and its ignoring of them at home in Australia. I will pick out three examples in the report in the short time available to me.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I would also like to refer to the very process, to which Senator Harradine has just referred, of putting the report together. We see in the tabling statement of Senator Gareth Evans that the national action plan was put together by the Australian federal government and that there was effectively no consultation with the states. One of the things that we have to do in a democracy, if we want to protect human rights, is to ensure that power is kept close to the people. Australia has chosen to do that by having a federal system of government. That is something that we will celebrate in the years leading up to the centenary of our federation, but it is something that has been undermined by this federal government in particular over the last 11 years. It has sought to centralise more power here in Canberra away from the state and local levels of government and to concentrate more and more power in the hands of the executive.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         It is a great pity that Senator Evans was so keen to rush off and have this report tabled in the United Nations on 22 February when on 21 June it is being tabled in the Australian Senate. In other words, the government goes off to the United Nations and tables our national action plan before it is considered by a joint committee of the parliament and before it comes into the Senate. This is a classic monument to the way this arrogant, tired government treats the Australian parliamentary process. So it is a bit of joke that here we are saying what a great democracy we are.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         There are a couple of other points in this report. There is a chapter on labour relations, which Senator Abetz will not be surprised to hear. I will leave it to him to make some comments about that. The plan goes through all the high sounding principles in relation to ensuring that people have the right to just and favourable conditions of work and the right to form and join trade unions. I hope that our international friends who read this report will recognise that nowhere on all the pages regarding people's rights to join unions is there any mention of the right for Australians not to join unions if they so choose.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That is a freedom that this federal government denies people in industrial trade unions. It is also a freedom that this government specifically seeks to deny students on campuses. This government uses its coercive financial powers to force young Australians to join unions and pay hundreds of dollars in membership fees against their will. It needs to be highlighted to the international community that this government is not far dinkum about giving Australian citizens the freedom to choose not to join unions. They are coerced into joining unions.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Another section of this report goes to the government's credibility in relation to strengthen democratic processes. Page 71 says:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        These mechanisms include the scrutiny of government by parliamentary committees and administrative processes which provide for access to information and review of decisions.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is interesting to note that the Senate passed resolutions on 5 May and 10 May asking that the Minister for Administrative Services table documents in relation to his portfolio. He held this parliament in contempt and continues to do so. That is how fair dinkum the government is about accountability and democratic institutions. If it does not suit the government, it does not give the parliament the information.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Equally, a commitment was given by this government in March to increase the powers and financial resources of the Auditor-General, yet in last month's budget it cut the resources of the independent Auditor-General in Australia by 17 per cent. This is a great commitment to accountability. The Auditor-General has said publicly that his office cannot carry out its statutory obligations. That too should be recognised by the international community when it sees Senator Evans trying to win a Nobel Peace Prize for human rights, or become Secretary-General of the United Nations, or whatever else he is trying to do with this document. He is not fair dinkum and his actions do not match his words.
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          (Time expired)
         </emphasis>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Calvert)
         </emphasis>
         —The time for taking note of this document has expired.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Motion (by
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          Senator Abetz
         </emphasis>
         ) proposed:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the debate be now adjourned.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="JI4" speaker="Senator Panizza">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator Panizza
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —When Senator Schacht gave leave to discuss this document I thought we were not limited to half an hour. Could you give me some advice on that?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —My understanding was that the time limit was 30 minutes and it expired at 11.38 a.m.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="JI4" speaker="Senator Panizza">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator Panizza
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Where has that understanding come from? Is it in the normal standing orders? I thought it was open.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Leave was given under the normal conditions which would allow half an hour.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para first-indent="16">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          Question resolved in the affirmative.
         </tab>
        </para>
       </interject>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <petition.grp page="1801">
     <title>
      PETITIONS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10001" speaker="The Clerk">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10001">
          The Clerk
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Petitions have been lodged for presentation as follows:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <petition nameids="TW4" page="1801" presenters="BOURNE">
      <title>
       Women: Pension Age
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in the Parliament assembled:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The Petition of the undersigned strongly opposes attempts by the government to raise the pension age for women from 60 to 65 years.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Your Petitioners ask that the Senate oppose this proposed change.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="TW4">
         Senator Bourne
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 38 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="TF4" page="1801" presenters="COULTER">
      <title>
       National Forest Policy
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       We are dismayed at the continuing destruction of old growth and wilderness forests around Australia, despite the National Forest Policy Statement jointly signed by the Commonwealth and all States except Tasmania.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Intensive logging, most often to feed a voracious woodchip industry is underway or planned for many high conservation value forests. These forests should be protected by the commitments of the Commonwealth and State Governments under the NFPS.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       THESE FORESTS INCLUDE:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Coolangubra Wilderness and other areas of the S.E. Forests of NSW along with rainforest and other N.E. areas of NSW including Wingham, Mistake, Richmond Range, Chaelundi, North Washpool, Barrington and Dorrigo.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The Southern Highlands, Great Western Tiers and Tarkine Wilderness of Tasmania.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The Karri and Jarrah forests of S.W. Western Australia.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The Errinundra Plateau and Other areas of the East Gippsland forests of Victoria.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The rainforests of the Proserpine region of Queensland.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       We request that the Government act urgently to protect our precious forests by utilising the Commonwealth's legal and constitutional powers, including:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Refusal of export woodchip licences
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Powers to control corporations
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Protection of areas listed on the register of the National Estate
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Protection and effective funding of areas identified for their World Heritage values
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Genuine and effective action by the Government to protect these and other old growth and wilderness forests is critical. A comprehensive plantation strategy rather than exploiting native forests is the way forward for a truly environmentally responsible timber industry. We further request that the Government take effective action without further delay.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="TF4">
         Senator Coulter
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 107 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="VJ4" page="1801" presenters="WATSON">
      <title>
       National Flag
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth that:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        1.The majority of Australians are completely satisfied with the existing Australian national flag.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        2.We therefore request that the Senate ensures that the Australian national flag, as provided in Section (3) of the Flags Act, is not changed or replaced without first being voted upon and approved by the people of Australia in a national poll.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="VJ4">
         Senator Watson
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 83 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="VI4" page="1801" presenters="REID">
      <title>
       Child Care Standards
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled:
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       The petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia asks that the Childcare Rebate Act 1993 and the Social Security (Home Child Care and Partner Allowances) Legislation Amendment Act 1993 be amended with the application of common principles. To ensure that all parents with dependent children are treated equally, allowing maximum freedom of choice in child rearing.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       These Acts need to be amended to take account of:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        the fact that 60% of married women in the workforce who have children, would prefer to stay at home and mind their children, but for economic reasons can't afford to (Institute of Family Studies Survey).
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        the failure to provide for equitable choice for women and families in allowing parents the maximum right to choose the most appropriate form of care for their children.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        that there be recognition of a parent at home as a formal occupation reflecting its economic value and worth to society.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        the need for equal payment of any subsidies and allowances for the care of children, paid directly to the parent.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        the recognition that a family with more than one child incurs extra expenses.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Your petitioners request that the Senate amend the Childcare Rebate Act 1993 and the Social Security (Home Child Care and Partner Allowances) Legislation Amendment Act 1993.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="VI4">
         Senator Reid
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 200 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <para>
      Petitions received.
     </para>
    </petition.grp>
    <debate page="1802" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      NOTICES OF MOTION
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1802">
      <title>
       Austudy: Rural Communities
      </title>
      <speech electorate="SA" nameid="EP5" page="1802" party="LP" speaker="Ferguson Sen A.B.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="EP5">
          Senator FERGUSON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (a)notes that:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (i)rural commodity prices are expected to increase in 1995 by up to 12 per cent,
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (ii)surveys show that farm business profit would again be negative for most rural industries over the 1993-94 financial year and the Australian Bureau of Agricultural and Resource Economics predicts only slightly better performance for the 1994-95 financial year, and
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (iii)1995 will be the fifth successive year of farm business losses; and
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (b)calls on the Government to ensure equal educational opportunities for all young Australians by ensuring that Austudy benefits become available to all children from low income rural families, regardless of their asset levels.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1802">
      <title>
       Tasmania: Homosexual Laws
      </title>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="N26" page="1802" party="LP" speaker="Abetz Sen E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="N26">
          Senator ABETZ
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate congratulates the Tasmanian Attorney-General, the Honourable Ronald Cornish MHA, for his strong and principled stance in:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (a)opposing the Federal Government's plan to override the laws of the State of Tasmanian as determined by its democratically-elected Parliament;and
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (b)rejecting the United Nations (UN) findings in the Toonen case on the basis that:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (i)the UN failed to apply the most basic rules of natural justice,
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (ii)the UN held its hearings in private,
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (iii)the UN made its preliminary findings before the Tasmanian Government could respond to the Toonen submission which was a distortion of the truth,
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (iv)the UN made blatantly incorrect findings, and
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (v)the UN body which made the findings is undemocratic, unelected and includes representatives from countries such as Cuba.
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1802">
      <title>
       Convention on Biological Diversity
      </title>
      <speech electorate="SA" nameid="TF4" page="1802" party="AD" speaker="Coulter Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="TF4">
          Senator COULTER
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (a)notes that 20 June 1994 marked the first anniversary of Australia's ratification of the Convention on Biological Diversity;
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (b)expresses grave concern that, since ratification, threats to Australia's biological diversity have not abated but have in fact increased due in large part to the destruction of habitat from the continued logging of old-growth forests and wilderness areas and the large-scale clearance of native vegetation, particularly in New South Wales and Queensland;
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (c)recognises that Reedy Marsh in Tasmania, habitat of rare and threatened species, is just one of a large number of areas across Australia threatened by destructive logging activity; and
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (d)calls on the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories (Senator Faulkner) to nominate native vegetation clearance as a key threatening process under the Endangered Species Protection Act 1992 and to ensure that areas of high conservation value are excluded from the 1994 woodchip licences in accordance with the moratorium clause of the national forest policy.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1802">
      <title>
       Fringe Benefits Tax
      </title>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="VJ4" page="1802" party="LP" speaker="Watson Sen J.O.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VJ4">
          Senator WATSON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate notes—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (a)that the Government appears to have overlooked the impact of the fringe benefits tax (FBT) on revenue in the 1994-95 Budget announcement enabling acquisition of shares by employees in the Government-owned airline Qantas; and
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (b)that, if implemented in the approved form, the acquisition of share proposal would result in an FBT liability of $20 million which must inevitably reduce the budget asset sale value of Qantas.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1803">
      <title>
       Refugees
      </title>
      <speech electorate="WA" nameid="DX5" page="1803" party="GWA" speaker="Margetts Sen D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DX5">
          Senator MARGETTS
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (a)notes that:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (i)the week beginning 19 June 1994 is Refugee Week, which is designed to raise awareness in the community of the plight of the world's 20 million refugees,
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (ii)the number of refugees has risen by 800 000 in the past year due in part to crises in Bosnia, Rwanda and Yemen, and
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (iii)refugees are the product of economic, political and personal insecurity caused by war, famine, poverty, violence, ethnic strife and social and economic inequality; and
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (b)calls on the Australian Government to maintain its existing peacekeeping efforts in Afghanistan and Cambodia, and to urge the world community to strengthen peace-making activities in countries which are currently not the centre of world attention such as Angola, Somalia, Iraq and Kuwait in order to minimise the plight of refugees.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1803">
      <title>
       Prime Minister: Piggery
      </title>
      <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="LE4" page="1803" party="LP" speaker="Baume Sen M.E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LE4">
          Senator MICHAEL BAUME
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (New South Wales)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (a)notes that:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (i)the Honourable Edward Obeid MLC, a New South Wales right-wing factional colleague of the Prime Minister (Mr Keating) and a `mate' of former Senator Richardson, became, on 22 April 1994, a director of Jensay Pty Ltd, Mr Keating's formerly half-owned member company of his piggery group which was shown as the owner of the group's Meek's Road, Marrickville property, with the company's fixed and floating Commonwealth Bank charge over its assets being discharged on 29 April 1994,
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (ii)on 22 April 1994, Mr Obeid also became a director of a new company, Olympia Group Pty Ltd, over whose assets Macquarie Bank Ltd has a fixed and floating charge dated 29 April 1994, coincidental with the technically bankrupt Keating piggery group company, Olympia Refrigeration (Sales) Pty Ltd and its subsidiaries discharging, on 5 May 1994, a fixed and floating charge over its assets, held by the Commonwealth Bank as part of the piggery group's huge, and largely bad, debt to the Commonwealth Bank,
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (iii)Mr Obeid's solicitor in this and other matters, such as the remarkable recent settlement with the Tax Commissioner of his tax problems relating to a superannuation scheme, is Mr Greg Keating, who acts as secretary of his brother Paul's family investment company, Pleuron Pty Ltd, and
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          (iv)Mr Obeid and his son Paul Obeid appear to have bad luck with fires in companies of which they are directors; and
         </tab>
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (b)seeks an assurance that the security held by the Commonwealth Bank over the Keating piggery group debts, against which a provision for bad debts of $4.5 million has already been made, has not been further diminished by these arrangements, as both Jensay Pty Ltd and Olympia Refrigeration (Sales) Pty Ltd are still shown as owned by the piggery group.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1803" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ORDER OF BUSINESS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1803">
      <title>
       Finance and Public Administration Committee
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Motion (by
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          Senator Burns
         </emphasis>
         ) agreed to:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That notice of motion No. 901, standing in the name of Senator Coates and relating to a meeting of the Standing Committee on Finance and Public Administration, be postponed till the next day of sitting.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1803">
      <title>
       Departmental Files
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Motion (by
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          Senator Harradine
         </emphasis>
         ) agreed to:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That notice of motion No. 544, standing in the name of Senator Harradine and relating to the tabling of index lists of departmental files by the Leader of the Government in the Senate, be postponed till Thursday, 23 June 1994.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1804">
      <title>
       Classification of Publications Ordinances
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Motion (by
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          Senator Panizza
         </emphasis>
         ) agreed to:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That business of the Senate notices of motion Nos 1 and 2, standing in the name of Senator Tierney and relating to the Classification of Publications (Amendment) Ordinance, be postponed till the next day of sitting.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1804">
      <title>
       Legal and Constitutional Affairs Committee
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Motion (by
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          Senator Panizza
         </emphasis>
         ) agreed to:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That business of the Senate notice of motion No. 3, standing in the name of Senator Campbell and relating to the reference of a matter to the Standing Committee on Legal and Constitutional Affairs, be postponed till the next day of sitting.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1804" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1804">
      <title>
       Procedure Committee
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="1804">
       <title>
        Report
       </title>
       <proctext>
        <para first-indent="16">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Calvert)
          </emphasis>
          —I present the first report of 1994 of the Procedure Committee, relating to the Senate committee system.
         </tab>
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          Ordered that the report be printed.
         </tab>
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          Ordered that consideration of the report be made an order of the day for the next day of sitting.
         </tab>
        </para>
       </proctext>
       <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="1804" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="6H4">
           Senator HARRADINE
          </name>
          <electorate>
           (Tasmania)
          </electorate>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —by leave—I hope that this debate will take place prior to the introduction of the changes to the standing orders that have been foreshadowed by Senator Collins.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </speech>
       <speech electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="ENVIRONMENT, SPORT AND TERRITORIES" nameid="5K4" page="1804" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="5K4">
           Senator FAULKNER
          </name>
          <electorate>
           (New South Wales-
          </electorate>
          <role>
           Manager of Government Business in the Senate)
          </role>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —by leave—I think there has been an understanding on both sides of the chamber, including the minor party and independent senators, that there will be an opportunity for full debate on this matter at a later stage. That opportunity will occur at the beginning of the next sittings.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para first-indent="16">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          It was the intention of the Procedure Committee that this document come before the Senate in this form so that honourable senators would have an opportunity over the break to read and digest it. As Manager of Government Business in the Senate, it is my intention to give notice of the appropriate changes to standing orders. There is no intention to block debate on these issues, which are of interest to all honourable senators.
         </tab>
        </para>
       </speech>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="1804">
      <title>
       Estimates
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="1804">
       <title>
        Meetings
       </title>
       <proctext>
        <para first-indent="16">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Calvert)
          </emphasis>
          —Before I call on the Manager of Government Business in the Senate to move the adjournment, I advise honourable senators that estimates committee arrangements for today are as follows: Estimates Committee A is to meet in the Main Committee Room and will be televised on channel 21 and broadcast on FM band 92.7; Estimates Committee B is to meet in committee room 2S1 and will be televised on channel 22 and broadcast on FM band 90.3; and Estimates Committee C is to meet in committee room 2S3 and will be televised on channel 23 and broadcast on FM band 91.1.
         </tab>
        </para>
       </proctext>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1804" type="Adjournment">
     <title>
      ADJOURNMENT
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Motion (by
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Faulkner
        </emphasis>
        ) proposed:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        That the Senate do now adjourn.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <debate.sub1 page="1804">
      <title>
       Tokic, Mr Josef
      </title>
      <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="LE4" page="1804" party="LP" speaker="Baume Sen M.E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LE4">
          Senator MICHAEL BAUME
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (New South Wales)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.53 a.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will not keep the Senate long, but this matter will be submerged if I do not raise it now. It relates to funds being sought from the Advance to the Minister for Finance for an ex-gratia payment to Mr Josef Tokic, as approved by the Minister for Finance (Mr Beazley) in April 1994.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The Senate would be aware that Mr Tokic received a bullet wound to the neck while taking part in a demonstration outside the Yugoslav Consulate-General in Woollahra, Sydney, in November 1988. Mr Tokic sued the government of Yugoslavia for damages for negligence in respect of the incident. In December 1991 the court awarded him $46,854, including costs. The application for funds from the Advance to the Minister for Finance stated:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        An ex-gratia payment was sought on the grounds that it was not possible to execute the judgment against the Government of Yugoslavia. The defendant government (Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia) no longer exists and is unlikely to be replaced by a government which would assume the judgment debt. Due to the current political circumstances in the former Yugoslavia, the Australian government cannot exert the level of diplomatic influence it would in normal situations. Because of consular immunity, it is not possible to take action against the Consul-General of the Government of Yugoslavia in Sydney, or other assets of the Government held in Australia.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The Minister for Finance approved an Act of Grace payment, due to the unique circumstances which exist to prevent Mr Tokic enforcing the judgment. The Act of Grace payment is made on the condition that the judgment debt is assigned to the Commonwealth.
       </para>
       <para>
        There is no doubt that all honourable senators would support the fact that Mr Tokic is to receive his money. It is a disgrace that it has taken so long for him to get his money—from December 1991. The problem is why on earth this government is not proceeding against the property held by the former government of Yugoslavia in Australia. It seems to me totally inadequate to say that consular immunity prevents the government from doing so.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I draw to the government's attention the fact that in the United States the various cities are now proceeding against the consular and diplomatic officials for multimillions of dollars in relation to back parking fines that have resulted from the arrogant way in which diplomatic and consular representatives have ignored the rules in relation to parking in those municipalities and cities.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I am under the impression that if the government had such a mind it could well proceed against assets held here by the former government of Yugoslavia. I regret, firstly, the massive delay in making the payment to Mr Tokic and, secondly, the fact that the government has shown no enthusiasm in pursuing this matter. As a result the taxpayers of Australia have to foot the bill—of course, Mr Tokic is totally entitled to get the money—when the government of Australia should be
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
        exercising, what I understand to be, its rights to get restitution from the former government of Yugoslavia.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         One of the factors involved is that it has taken so long for the government to do anything about it. That may have increased the problems involved. If the government has taken a different view from the view taken by the United States authorities, I think it owes it to the Senate and to the people of Australia to explain why. The Americans can pursue diplomats for these judgment debts, as I understand it in these matters, whereas the Australian government apparently finds itself incapable of doing so.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Question resolved in the affirmative.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para justification="CENTERJUST">
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senate adjourned at 11.57 a.m.
        </emphasis>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1805" type="Documents">
     <title>
      DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="1805">
      <title>
       Tabling
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The following documents were tabled pursuant to sessional order agreed to on 18 August 1993.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        1.ADVANCE TO THE MINISTER FOR FINANCE—MAY 1994.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        2.SUPPORTING APPLICATIONS OF ISSUES FROM THE ADVANCES TO THE MINISTER FOR FINANCE—MAY 1994.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        3.MINISTER FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS—National Action Plan on Human Rights, Australia and accompanying comments by Senator the Hon Gareth Evans QC.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        4.WOOL RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION—Annual Report 1 July—30 November 1993—including the Auditor-General's report—section 29 of the Primary Industries and Energy Research and Development Act 1989.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The following documents were tabled by the Clerk:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Public Service Act—Determinations—1994 Nos 33-37, 45 and 48-52.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
   </chamber.xscript>
   <answers.to.questions page="1806">
    <title>
     ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS
    </title>
    <proctext>
     <para>
      The following answers to questions were circulated:
     </para>
    </proctext>
    <answer.to.qon page="1806">
     <title>
      Fuel Excise
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="574">
      (Question No. 574)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="BE4" page="1806" party="LP" speaker="Newman Sen J.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BE4">
         Senator Newman
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Treasurer, upon notice, on 6 September 1993:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        With reference to the increased excise on fuel oil by 3 cents per litre in the 1993-94 Budget of 17 August 1993:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) Does the Government realise that because of its decision to add that extra 3 cents per litre, 300 jobs will be lost from one mining operation in Tasmania alone and million of dollars in expenditure through other Tasmanian businesses will be affected as a result?
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) Will the Government supply what information it has on the impact on Australia's mining industry of the excise increase on fuel oil?
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="RF4" page="1806" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="RF4">
         Senator Cook
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Treasurer has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) The Government has received representations from the mining operation referred to by Senator Newman. In the 1994-95 Budget the Government announced a reduction of 1.977 cents per litre in the customs and excise rates for fuel oil, effective after 10 May 1994.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        In addition, the Government has recently taken many other measures to lower business costs. I draw the honourable Senator's attention to the reduction in corporate tax rates, and the recent introduction of a number of measures to lower the cost of business investment—including the acceleration of depreciation deductions, the development allowance, and the temporary 10 per cent general investment allowance.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) The Government has received representations from the mining industry concerning the excise on fuel oil. Much of this information has been supplied on a commercial-in-confidence basis, and I do not propose to release it.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1806">
     <title>
      Tobacco
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1162">
      (Question No. 1162)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="7U4" page="1806" party="AD" speaker="Bell Sen R.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="7U4">
         Senator Bell
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Treasurer, upon notice, on 4 March 1994:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) What is the purpose of the Industry Commission's inquiry into the tobacco growing and manufacturing industries.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) What is the Commission's schedule of consultations with "other interested groups", particularly groups concerned with the health effects of tobacco smoking.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) What is the justification for an inquiry into "the potential for further development of the [tobacco] industry" when Government action indicates a recognition that tobacco smoking is harmful to health.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (4) What is Australia's international approach in relation to tobacco and health.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="RF4" page="1806" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="RF4">
         Senator Cook
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Treasurer has provided the following information in answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) The Industry Commission is the Government's principal industry review body. Its role is to expose the costs of economic inefficiencies in Australia and suggest practical ways of improving industry performance.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The Government's current assistance arrangements for the tobacco industry will terminate on 30 September 1995. The purpose of the Industry Commission inquiry is to advise the Government on the appropriate tariff level to apply after that date to imports of tobacco leaf and manufactured tobacco products. It is normal Government policy to have a Commission inquiry before the Government considers tariff changes to any industry sector. The inquiry will cover a broad range of issues affecting industry competitiveness and assistance arrangements.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) The Commission has visited the following organisations, companies and individuals:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
        Australian Capital Territory
       </emphasis>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Australian Medical Association Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Australian Tobacco Marketing Advisory Committee
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Commonwealth Department of Primary Industries and Energy, Rural Division
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Department of Health, Housing and Community Services
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Research and Development Council
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
        Victoria
       </emphasis>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Myrtleford Grower Forum—11 participants
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Myrtleford Grower visits—S.La Spina, L. Saccutelli, G. Allan, L. Brandellero, T. and D. Bonacci, G. Lunardi, B. Phillips, L. and G. Cossignani, P. Merlo, J. and D. Moore and B. Burtina
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Myrtleford Growers' Selling Centre
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Ovens Research Station
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Philip Morris Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Shire Councils of Bright, Myrtleford and Oxley
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Growers of Victoria
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Leaf Marketing Board—Victoria
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Victorian Anti-Cancer Council
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Victorian Department of Food and Agriculture
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Victorian Health Promotion Foundation
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Women in Tobacco Group
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
        New South Wales
       </emphasis>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Coraki growers—(3)
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       David Collins and Helen Lapsley
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Inverell Shire Council
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       New England Rural Counselling Service
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       New South Wales Cancer Council
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       NSW Department of Agriculture
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       New South Wales Rural Assistance Authority
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Rothmans of Pall Mall (Australia) Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Shed meeting—Ashford, Tenterfield
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Stuart Alexander and Co Pty Ltd
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Leaf Marketing Board—New South Wales
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Institute of Australia Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       W.D. &amp; H.O. Wills (Australia) Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
        Queensland
       </emphasis>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Arthur Graham, ATMAC and TRDC Chairman
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Dimbulah farm visits, P. De Martin, B. Hensen, W.Dal Santo, E. Crema, and P. Cibau
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Discussion forum—T. Gilmore, B. Katter, Mareeba Information and Support Centre, Mareeba
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Chamber of Commerce, Australian Tobacco for Australian Consumers Group, G. Gowan (coffee grower), North Queensland Fruit and Vegetable Growers Association, Young Tobacco Farmers Organisation, MBA Export Cooperative
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Glasshouse Mountains farm visits—(2)
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Glasshouse Mountains growers meeting—(16) attended
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Mareeba farm visits—N. McCart, Cosentino Bros, J. Sabin, and V. Prismic
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Mareeba Shire Council
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       North Queensland Tobacco Growers Cooperative Association
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Queensland Department of Primary Industries
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Queensland Industry Development Corporation—Brisbane Head office
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Queensland Industry Development Corporation—Mareeba Branch office
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Queensland Water Resources Commission Tobacco Leaf Marketing Board—Queensland
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Southedge Research Station
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Organisations and individuals who have made submissions to the inquiry are listed below. Further submissions are likely in response to the Commission's draft report which was released on 7 April 1994.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Agricultural Assessments
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Alchin, Terry M.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Australian Council on Smoking and Health (WA) on behalf of:
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Australian Cancer Society
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Anti-Cancer Council of Victoria
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Anti Cancer Foundation of the Universities of South Australia
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Cancer Foundation of Western Australia
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       NSW Cancer Council
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       ACT Cancer Society Inc
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       National Heart Foundation
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Public Health Association
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Royal Australian College of Physicians
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Australian Medical Association
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Adventist Health
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Australian Customs Service
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Australian Medical Association Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Australian Tobacco for Australian Consumers
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Australian Tobacco Marketing Advisory Committee
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       AWU-FIME Amalgamated Union
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Canberra ASH Incorporated
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Ciavarella, Mr Cyril
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Federated Tobacco Workers Union of Australia
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Federation of Australian Retail Tobacco Trade Associations
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Gapella, Mr Jorge
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Gilmore, Mr T.V.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Gilmore, Mr Tom, MLA
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Hei-Tana Management
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Joalma Poultry Farm
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Katter, Hon Bob MP and Hon Lou Lieberman MP
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Kiell Tobacco Pty Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Mareeba Chamber of Commerce
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Mareeba District Fruit and Vegetable Growers' Association
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Masterton, Jackie
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       McDonald, Cr Sally
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       McLees, Kevin and Maureen
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       New South Wales Government
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Non-Smokers' Movement of Australia
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Philip Morris Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Queensland Sales Representatives and Commercial Travellers' Guild
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Queensland Cancer Fund
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Queensland Government
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Revrenna, Mrs Caterina
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Rindo, George and Lena
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Rothmans of Pall Mall (Australia) Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Savoy Club Myrtleford Welfare Sub-Committee
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Shires of Bright, Myrtleford and Oxley
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Smith, Mr Kevin
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Smith, L.D. &amp; L.M.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       South Queensland Tobacco Growers' Co-Operative Association Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Stuart Alexander &amp; Co Pty Ltd
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Institute of Australia Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Leaf Marketing Board—New South Wales
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Leaf Marketing Board—Queensland
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Leaf Marketing Board—Victoria
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Growers Council of Australia
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tobacco Growers of Victoria
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Tomasoni, Vic and Rosa
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       WA Tobacco Retailers' Association Inc
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       WD &amp; HO Wills (Australia) Limited
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Women in Tobacco Farming
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Young Tobacco Farmers Organisation
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) The Government considers tobacco smoking is a major health concern and has taken a wide range of taxation, regulatory and educational measures to discourage tobacco consumption. These measures severely restrict tobacco consumption but do not prohibit it. So long as consumption is not prohibited, the efficiency of its production, the level of protection and the effect on prices (and hence consumption) are relevant matters for Government consideration. Thus, in terms of its industry policy, the Government considers—as noted in the answer to question (1) above—that the tobacco industry should be generally treated like other industries.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (4) This question is identical to Senate Question 1161, recently asked of the Minister for Health.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Please see
       <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
        Hansard
       </emphasis>
       of 3 May 1994, page 122.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1808">
     <title>
      Treasury: Electoral Profiles
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1198">
      (Question No. 1198)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="VIC" nameid="LI4" page="1808" party="LP" speaker="Patterson Sen K.C.L.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LI4">
         Senator Patterson
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Treasurer, upon notice, on 8 March 1994:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) Does the department, or any of its agencies, produce electoral profiles (or other like documents) outlining relevant programs, services or other forms of assistance provided in individual federal electorates; if so, when were these electoral profiles (or other like documents) first produced and how frequently are they produced
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) Is a copy of these electoral profiles (or other like documents) provided to the Parliamentary Library; if not, why not.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) Please provide a copy of the most up-to-date edition of each of these electoral profiles (or other like documents) for all federal electorates to the Parliamentary Library.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="VIC" nameid="RF4" page="1808" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="RF4">
         Senator Cook
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Treasurer has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The Department of Treasury, Australian Taxation Office, Insurance and Superannuation Commission, Industry Commission, Royal Australian Mint, Prices Surveillance Authority, and the Trade Practices Commission do not produce electoral profiles. However, the Australian Bureau of Statistics has provided the following information:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) The ABS compiles five-yearly statistical profiles of federal electorates using data from the Census of Population and Housing. These profiles were produced for the first time following the 1971 Census.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) Yes
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) The Parliamentary Library already has the profiles of federal electorates produced from the 1991 Census.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1808">
     <title>
      Companies: Foreign Ownership
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1282">
      (Question No. 1282)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="QLD" nameid="XW4" page="1808" party="AD" speaker="Kernot Sen C.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="XW4">
         Senator Kernot
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Treasurer, upon notice, on 28 March 1994:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) Given that Australians have a right to know who controls the country's assets and industries, what is the total level of foreign ownership, other than freehold land, of the following industries in Australia: (a) processed food; (b) chemicals; (c) pharmaceuticals; (d) confectionary and beverages; and (e) banking.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) If these figures are not available, why not.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) What proportion of our overseas debt stems from foreign ownership of our companies.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="QLD" nameid="RF4" page="1808" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="RF4">
         Senator Cook
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Treasurer has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) &amp; (2)
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        In recent years the Government's economic policy has included the objective of integrating the Australian market with the global economy and exposing local industries to international and domestic competitive pressures. The liberalisation of Australia's foreign investment policy has been one part of the deregulatory and market reform initiatives.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Information on foreign investment in Australia comprises of statistics collected by the Foreign Investment Review Board and the Australian Bureau of Statistics. The Board's statistics relate to foreign investment proposals examined by the Board and are substantially different from the ABS statistics on foreign investment in Australia which seek to measure actual investment transactions between residents of Australia and non-residents.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        In the past the ABS has also conducted surveys of particular industries on the level of foreign ownership. The limited statistical information released by the ABS on foreign ownership of Australian industries is provided below.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Foreign Ownership by Industry Sector-Selected Years, Per Cent of Value Added
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign ownership
      </para>
      <para>
       `Other        Total               Australian
      </para>
      <para>
       `Direct' Identified'   foreign ownership   ownership
      </para>
      <para>
       Mining ((a))
      </para>
      <para>
       1972-73             37.5       12.0            49.5             50.5
      </para>
      <para>
       1982-83             33.6       16.8            50.4             49.6
      </para>
      <para>
       1984-85               —         —            44.7             55.3
      </para>
      <para>
       Minerals processing ((b))
      </para>
      <para>
       1972-73               —         —            39.7 ((j))       60.3
      </para>
      <para>
       1981-82             27.6       18.6            46.3             53.7
      </para>
      <para>
       Manufacturing ((c))
      </para>
      <para>
       1972-73             27.7        3.5            31.2             68.8
      </para>
      <para>
       1982-83             28.4        4.5            32.9             67.1
      </para>
      <para>
       1986-87             25.8        5.1            30.9             69.1
      </para>
      <para>
       Private Sector Construction ((d))
      </para>
      <para>
       1984-85               —         —             9.6 ((j))       90.4
      </para>
      <para>
       Life Insurance((e))
      </para>
      <para>
       1973                18.8       18.0            36.8             63.2
      </para>
      <para>
       1983-84             24.5       15.8            40.3             59.7
      </para>
      <para>
       General Insurance ((f))
      </para>
      <para>
       1972-73               —         —            45.4 ((j))       54.6
      </para>
      <para>
       1983-84             32.5       1.63             4.1             65.9
      </para>
      <para>
       Registered financial corporations((g))
      </para>
      <para>
       1984                26.5       9.43             5.9             64.1
      </para>
      <para>
       1986                  —         —            38.1 ((j))       61.9
      </para>
      <para>
       Agricultural land((h))
      </para>
      <para>
       1983-84               —         —             5.9 ((j))       94.1
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport((i))
      </para>
      <para>
       1983-84               —         —             5.1 ((j))       94.9
      </para>
      <para>
       Banking((k))
      </para>
      <para>
       1986                  —         —            21.0 ((j))       79.0
      </para>
      <para>
       Source: Various ABS industry studies
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Notes:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (a) Based on value added—ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control of the Mining Industry, Australia, 1981-82, 1982-83, 1984-85 (Cat No. 5317.0).
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        A split between `direct' and `other identified' is not available for studies undertaken in 1984-85 and subsequently.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (b) Based on value added—ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control of the Mining Industry and Selected Mineral Processing Industries, Australia, 1981-82 (Cat No 5317.0).
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (c) Based on value added—ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control of the Manufacturing Industry, Australia, 1982-83, 1986-87 (Cat No 5322.0). Statistics for 1982-83 and 1986-87 are not directly comparable with those for 1972-73.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (d) Based on value added—ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control of the Private Sector Construction Industry, Australia, 1984-85 (Cat No 5343.0).
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (e) In terms of the value of premiums received for life insurance policies and annuities—ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control of the Life Insurance Industry, Australia, 1983-84 (Cat No 5311.0).
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (f) In terms of the value of premiums received—ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control of the General Insurance Industry, Australia, 1983-84 (Cat No 5309.0). Statistics for 1983-84 are not directly comparable with those for 1972-73.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (g) Based on value of corporations' assets—ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control of Registered Financial Corporations, Australia, 1984, 1986 (Cat No 5334.0). Excludes the category "Retailers". At end of June 1986 assets (loans outstanding) reported for the category `Retailers' were $63.8 million of which foreign ownership accounted for 100 per cent.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (h) Based on number of hectares. By location, the highest level of foreign ownership was in the NT, in which 13.0 million hectares or 18.2 per cent of its agricultural land was estimated to be foreign owned. Corresponding figures for the States were Queensland, 8.4 million hectares (5.3 per cent); WA, 3.6 million hectares (3.1 per cent); SA, 2.7 million hectares (4.3 per cent); NSW, 0.7 million hectares (1.1 per cent); Tasmania, 0.05 million hectares (2.1 per cent); and Victoria, 0.06 million hectares (0.4 per cent)—ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control in Agriculture, Australia, 1983-84 (Cat No 5536.0).
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (i) Based on value added—ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control of the Transport Industry, Australia, 1983-84 (Cat No 5335.0).
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (j) It is not possible to disaggregate total into `direct' or `other identified' foreign ownership.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (k) Based on value of banks' assets—ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control of the Banking Industry, June 1986 (Cat No 5347.0) ABS: Foreign Ownership and Control of the Life Insurance Industry, Australia, 1983-84 (Cat No 5311.0) provides an explanation of `direct' and `other identified' categories of foreign ownership.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) It is not possible to determine the proportion of Australia's overseas debt that stems from foreign ownership of companies in Australia. Some overseas borrowings are undertaken as a result of the links between subsidiaries in Australia and their overseas parent companies. For example, the proportion of debt in foreign direct investment in recent years in Australia has been around 20 per cent. Australia's thin capitalisation laws act to limit tax deductions for interest on debt owed to a foreign controller (or a non-resident associate of a foreign controller) where the debts exceeds the permitted ratio of foreign debt to foreign equity. The permitted debt to equity ratio is generally 3:1. For financial institutions the ratio is 6:1.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1810">
     <title>
      Women: Appointment to Government Boards
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1356">
      (Question No. 1356)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="VIC" nameid="LI4" page="1810" party="LP" speaker="Patterson Sen K.C.L.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LI4">
         Senator Patterson
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Minister for Tourism, upon notice, on 3 May 1994:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        With reference to the Federal Labor Caucus motion of 21 August 1988 requiring women to be appointed to at least 25 per cent of places on Government boards, councils and committees:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        For each of the boards, councils and committees to which the Minister has the power to appoint members, and for all of these combined:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) How many positions were available for appointment on 21 August 1988 and how many are now available.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) How many of these positions were held by women on 21 August 1988 and how many are now held by women.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) What changes, do the resulting proportions represent since the Labor Caucus motion.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="VIC" nameid="UI4" page="1810" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="UI4">
         Senator Robert Ray
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Minister for Tourism has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) On 21 August 1988, a total of 38 positions on three boards, committees and councils were available for appointment. In 1994 there are five boards, committees and councils with a total of 57 positions available for appointment.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) In 1988, three of the positions were held by women and in 1994 seven of the positions are held by women.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) In 1988, 7.9 per cent of positions available for appointment were held by women and 12.3 per cent are currently held by women.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1810">
     <title>
      Road Transport
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1390">
      (Question No. 1390)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="7U4" page="1810" party="AD" speaker="Bell Sen R.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="7U4">
         Senator Bell
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Minister for Industrial Relations, upon notice, on 12 May 1994:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) Is the Minister aware of claims by Mr Neville Irwin, some of which were published in the
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Courier Mail
        </emphasis>
        on 14 February 1994 and in
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Big Rig
        </emphasis>
        of 13 to 26 August 1993, that he was required by two road transport companies, Cenrim Pty Ltd (Frigtrans) and Jaytron Pty Ltd (Stocktrans), to drive inter-state trucks in excess of legal distances and working hours, that these breaches were concealed from authorities by the maintenance of multiple log books, that Mr Irwin took illegal drugs to maintain his driving regime, and that he was underpaid by $20 834 for work performed between 2 August 1990 and 11 December 1991.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) Has any action been taken by the department on Mr Irwin's allegations of over-work and under-payment; if so: (a) what action has been taken; (b) will the Minister take action in view of the seriousness of Mr Irwin's allegations and the failure of previous investigations to resolve them; and (c) if action has been or will be taken, will it be co-ordinated with the Department of Transport to ensure that cross-jurisdictional problems do not impede a proper investigation; if not, why not.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) (a) What jurisdiction does the department have to regulate working conditions in the inter-state road transport industry; and (b) what action has been taken to; (i) establish, and (ii) enforce, safer and fairer working conditions in the inter-state road transport industry.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="UI4" page="1810" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="UI4">
         Senator Robert Ray
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Minister for Industrial Relations has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) Yes, representations by Mr Les Scott, MP, Federal Member for Oxley on behalf of Mr Irwin were made to me on 25 March 1994.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) Yes.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (a) &amp; (b) I wrote to Mr Scott, who presented Mr Irwin's allegations, outlining that because Mr Irwin was not employed under a federal award, the Commonwealth Department of Industrial Relations does not have the jurisdiction to pursue any payments which may be owed to him by his former employers, Cenrim Pty Ltd and Jaytron Pty Ltd.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The New South Wales Department for Industrial Relations and Employment, Training and Further Education (DIRETFE) has the jurisdiction to investigate Mr Irwin's complaint. (DIRETFE did not initially investigate the complaint as it was already being investigated by the Transport Workers Union).
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        If Mr Irwin fails to get a satisfactory response from the Transport Workers Union, he could again write to the Hon Kerry Chikarovski, New South Wales Minister for Industrial Relations and Employment, seeking a full investigation of his entitlements.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        I understand that Mr Irwin's concerns have also been communicated to Mr Hamill, the Minister for Transport in Queensland.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (c) Yes.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) (a) The regulation of working conditions such as driving hours and log books is the responsibility of State and Territory jurisdictions.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        A range of other working conditions is expressed in awards and other instruments made by industrial tribunals, federal and State. The parties to these awards, and not the Department of Industrial Relations, can seek to have these awards varied by the Australian Industrial Relations Commission.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Where employees are covered by federal awards, including federal transport industry awards, the Industrial Relations Act 1988 provides authority for unions and the Department of Industrial Relations to enforce compliance with existing federal award conditions. There are regulations under the Act which have been in force since 30 June 1993 requiring employers to keep appropriate time and wages records, and to issue payslips to their employees.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3)(b)(i) The Commonwealth is concerned with safety issues and has actively supported the establishment of safer and fairer practices in the road transport industry through the National Road Transport Commission, an autonomous body whose brief is to improve road safety and transport efficiency, through devising uniform national standards, including enforcement standards. The Commonwealth has also contributed to the development of guidelines for self regulation by the Road Transport Forum. These guidelines aim to set standards for health, training, maintenance and management within the industry. In addition, the Commonwealth, through the Federal Office of Road Safety, has made a major contribution towards improving the safety of the road transport industry through a number of safety studies, extensive research into the use of drugs by heavy vehicle drivers and important studies into fatigue .
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (b)(ii) The implementation and enforcement of legislation covering the road transport industry is the domain of State and Territory agencies.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="1811">
     <title>
      HMAS Huon
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="1407">
      (Question No. 1407)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="5F4" page="1811" party="LP" speaker="Calvert Sen P.H.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5F4">
         Senator Calvert
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Defence, upon notice, on 20 May 1994:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) What costs have been incurred in the closure of HMAS
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Huon
        </emphasis>
        to date.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) What costs will be incurred up until the final closure.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) What is the breakdown of these costs.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (4) What are the plans for HMAS
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Huon
        </emphasis>
        following its closure.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (5) How many people have lost their jobs as a result of the closure of HMAS
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Huon
        </emphasis>
        .
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (6) What has happened to the furniture which was used by staff at HMAS
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Huon
        </emphasis>
        .
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (7) If the furniture has been disposed of, what costs were incurred during disposal, and what monies were raised through disposal.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="UI4" page="1811" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="UI4">
         Senator Robert Ray
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) The total costs incurred to date of relocating HMAS
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Huon
        </emphasis>
        's residual functions is $271 800.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) The only additional costs will be for the removal to Anglesea Barracks Hobart, estimated to be $8500.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) The cost breakdown is:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       $
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Modifications in Anglesea Barracks      250 000
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Modifications for Diving Store           14 000
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Freight for machinery and Plant           5 300
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       Purchase of telephones                    2 500
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       TOTAL                                   271 800
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (4) Future use options for HMAS
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Huon
        </emphasis>
        are currently being examined. In the meantime, responsibility for the property will be passed to the Estate Management Branch in the Department which will
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       ensure appropriate management arrangements for the property are in place.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The Navy will retain use of the boatshed and wharf for the reserve diving team and the wharf to economise on ship visits for smaller vessels. The wharf is not part of the title for HMAS
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Huon
        </emphasis>
        .
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (5) Navy personnel will be redeployed to higher priority tasks. Seven civilian employees have been redeployed within Defence. Two civilian employees have accepted voluntary redundancy packages.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (6) The majority of the furniture has been, or will be, relocated to the Navy Support Office in Anglesea Barracks. A small number of trestle type tables and chairs have been transferred to the Department of Administrative Services for sale by auction. In addition, the Wardroom furniture, owned by the officers at
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Huon
        </emphasis>
        , has been, or will be, transferred to the Wardroom mess at HMAS
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Waterhen
        </emphasis>
        .
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (7) The furniture designated for disposal is currently with the Department of Administrative Services for public auction. The details of costs incurred and monies raised are not yet available.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
   </answers.to.questions>
  </hansard>
 </body>
</html>
