<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" "hansard.dtd">
<html>
 <body>
  <hansard chamber="Senate" date="22/02/1994" page="859" parliament.no="37" period.no="3" proof="No" session.no="1">
   <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
     <day.start date="22/02/1994">
      Tuesday, 22 February 1994
     </day.start>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         The PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. Michael Beahan)
        </emphasis>
        took the chair at 2.00 p.m., and read prayers.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </business.start>
    <qwn page="859">
     <title>
      QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
     </title>
     <question.block page="859">
      <title>
       Australian Secret Intelligence Service
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="859" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BH4">
          Senator HILL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Foreign Affairs as the minister responsible for ASIS. Is it the case that ASIS is holding tens of thousands of files on ordinary Australians, as suggested by the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Four Corners
         </emphasis>
         program last night? Does ASIS have access to personal files held by other government organisations such as Telecom, the Department of Social Security, Medicare and the Australian Taxation Office? Is the Privacy Commissioner aware of the existence of these files, and does he have any role in preventing the inappropriate use of this information?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="859" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My understanding is that ASIS does have some files, as one would expect in an organisation of that nature, even though its brief extends to activities outside the country rather than inside. They are essentially of an administrative nature. The number of them that could be so described I am not sure of; I will need to get further information about that.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The arrangements for oversight and ensuring that privacy guarantees and so on are observed here, as elsewhere, are effectively centred in the office of the Inspector-General of Intelligence and Security, an office that was, of course, set up following the second Hope royal commission as the primary method of oversight and scrutiny of ASIS administration. I am confident that no privacy invasion issues have arisen as a consequence—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="Senator Alston">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —On what basis?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —On the advice that I have received when I have asked about this in the past. I have not sought or received further information about that specific issue since last night; I will do so. But, when I have inquired about this in the past—as I have, because the issue has been raised in various ways in the past—I have been satisfied that the files that are maintained are essentially for in-house purposes and that the oversight arrangements that apply in house and the scrutiny arrangements that apply so far as the independent mechanism of the Inspector-General of Intelligence and Security are concerned are sufficient between them to ensure that no privacy issue of any proper concern in fact arises.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="859" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BH4">
          Senator HILL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I reiterate that part of my question that sought to find out whether in fact ASIS has access to personal files held by other government departments such as Telecom. I mentioned Telecom in particular but I referred also to the Department of Social Security, Medicare and the Australian Taxation Office. Also, following from the minister's answer, is the minister saying that the Inspector-General of Intelligence and Security is aware of all the files that are held, that he has had access to them and that he is satisfied that they do not go beyond issues of national security?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="859" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is my understanding—and I will seek further information on that matter—that there is no right of access of any automatic kind to those files which might exist elsewhere. Whether any access has in fact been sought on any occasion in the past is something about which I will seek an answer. Whether it is possible to give any further information publicly about this or any other matter of an operational nature is, of course, a difficult question, as is always the case when one is talking about a security organisation. But I do not think, from the briefing that I can recall having in the past on this issue, that any question of this kind arises.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         ASIS is basically not that kind of organisation. Its brief does not extend to domestic matters of this kind. I cannot think of any circumstances where it would be relevant to seek information of the kind that might be held. But I am not in a position to give an absolute answer, so I will not. Could I ask Senator Hill to repeat the last part of his supplementary question?
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="BH4" speaker="Senator Hill">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="BH4">
           Senator Hill
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Is Senator Evans saying to the Senate that the Inspector-General of Intelligence and Security is aware of all of these files, that he has had access to them and that he is satisfied that they do not go beyond issues of national security?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That is my understanding. Part of the inspector-general's brief is to protect the interests of Australian citizens. In order to do that he must, of course, have complete access at his own discretion and choosing to anything he wants to. That is my understanding of the way the system works. Again, if I have any further information to offer on that subject, having sought a more detailed briefing on this specific aspect of the question, I will be happy to give that information if it is possible to do so.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="860">
      <title>
       Meat Inspection Services
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" gov="1" nameid="FX5" page="860" party="ALP" speaker="Murphy Sen S.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FX5">
          Senator MURPHY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy. As the minister is no doubt aware, concerns have been raised about the new charging regime for meat inspection services which came into effect on 1 January 1994. My question comes in two parts. First, what action does the government intend to take to address the concerns raised regarding the charging structure? Secondly, what does the government intend to do to ensure that the Australian Quarantine and Inspection Service operates in an efficient and cost-effective way?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY" nameid="OF4" page="860" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thank Senator Murphy for his question and his courtesy in giving me notice that he would ask this question. This matter is of interest not just to members of the government but also to a number of senators in the opposition and Senator Woodley from the Australian Democrats. I have held a number of meetings over the last few weeks with interested senators on this issue.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The introduction of new meat inspection charges in January followed extensive consultation with industry bodies and consideration by the Senate Standing Committee on Rural and Regional Affairs. Notwithstanding this very exhaustive consultative process, there have been a number of concerns raised about the impact of the new charging regime, particularly on smaller operators. I might add that this problem occurred because the original proposal put forward by the government was for a three-tiered system that contained not just an establishment charge and an inspector charge but also a throughput charge that would have actually reflected the situation of the operators with a smaller turnover.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The proposal was changed to the current two-tiered system as a result of representations that were received by that senate committee and by opposition senators. I have considered the concerns that have been raised about the impact on smaller operators and I have decided on certain changes to the previously announced registration charges. In fact, I discussed this matter just today with the shadow minister, John Anderson, prior to making this statement.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         As well as the reduction in rates for the 1993-94 financial year, I have determined that the revised six-monthly rate for 1993-94 will be maintained through to 31 December this year. Increases in establishment registration charges as from 1 July 1994, which had been foreshadowed in discussions with industry, will now not take place.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YE4" speaker="Senator Boswell">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YE4">
           Senator Boswell
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Hear, hear!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Thank you, Senator Boswell. This will allow the government a period to the end of calendar year 1994 in which to examine, in consultation with the industry, the whole question of inspection charges. I have asked AQIS to convene an industry charging review committee to consider further AQIS meat inspection costs and the appropriate charging structures and rates necessary to achieve appropriate cost recovery levels. Any new rates agreed will apply from 1 January 1995. There is a procedural matter in relation to the decision to reduce a number of the registration charges. The rules for the making and tabling of regulations require me to table the original regulations, which I will do today.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I propose to table the new regulations by 24 March which will give effect to the changes I have outlined. As well, I am addressing the question of AQIS charges. I am also giving great priority to reducing AQIS costs. As the government announced in the 1993-94 budget, there is to be a major process of reform and efficiency improvement in AQIS. This process involves a restructuring of the Canberra office and regional support services. Efficiency measures in AQIS field services are also being developed. It is my intention to pursue these reforms vigorously. I will shortly be making a more detailed announcement on these matters. I table the revised charges.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="861">
      <title>
       Taxation
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="DJ4" page="861" party="LP" speaker="Short Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct a question to the Leader of the Government in the Senate. I remind Senator Gareth Evans of the Prime Minister's now infamous comments on the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Lateline
         </emphasis>
         program of 19 November 1992 when he emphatically stated:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        . . . what I am promising is not to put up tax..
       </para>
       <para>
        I further remind the minister of the remarks of the then Treasurer, Mr Dawkins, on 14 November 1993, that he is:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        . . . opposed to future tax increases to meet the cost of any new obligations which come up.
       </para>
       <para>
        I also remind the minister that, since becoming Treasurer, Mr Willis, on 23 December last, said:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        . . . obviously the Government has no plans to raise taxes . . . ,
       </para>
       <para>
        And:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        . . . we certainly would not be wanting to raise taxes. . .
       </para>
       <para>
        So I ask: will the minister give the Australian people an assurance that this year's budget will honour the commitment of treasurers Dawkins and Willis and the commitments made to Australians by the Prime Minister and other senior ministers prior to the 1993 federal election, or will this budget simply be another round of deceptions and broken promises like the 1993 budget?
       </para>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="861" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As to one particular revenue measure—that is to say, the possibility of a jobs levy to fund work experience and training programs for the long-term unemployed—that prospect was canvassed in the green paper on employment opportunities. That is not new. There was a government document. That is out in the open and opposition senators know very well what the arguments are.
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          Quite properly, the green paper acknowledged that funding issues are a matter for separate government decision in the context of the budget and that is where that issue now remains.
         </tab>
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         As with every budget the government will, of course, give consideration to the need for revenue measures. Typically, any such consideration is given not at the outset but, rather, towards the end of the budget deliberations and, consistent with established practice, the government will not be commenting on specific tax proposals in advance of the budget. If those opposite can remember what it was like to be in government—and I know it is a long time, and I know it has escaped any residual memory that any of them on the front bench might have had—they would know that that is the position that any responsible government would adopt on any similar occasion.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="DJ4" page="861" party="LP" speaker="Short Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. In view of that totally equivocal statement, I ask whether the minister stands by his own assurance in this place on 5 October last—that is, just six months ago—that the government would not:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        . . . go down the path of introducing any new taxes. . .
       </para>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="861" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That remains the case. The particular exception to that is the possibility of a jobs levy, which opposition senators might choose to construe, technically, as a tax; but there is no mystery or secret about that. I have nothing further to say on that subject.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         We did make perfectly clear, as I said, as the Prime Minister before me said and as others have done, that we certainly were not going to go down the path of a consumption tax, a GST, a VAT or any of those particular nasties that the opposition has been committed to in the past and is now deeply embarrassed about, and that undertaking absolutely holds.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="WW4" speaker="Senator Kemp">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="WW4">
           Senator Kemp
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr President, on a point of order. The question was very clear and specific: whether the government would stick by its promise not to introduce any new taxes.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="RF4" speaker="Senator Cook">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="RF4">
           Senator Cook
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —That wasn't the government promise. It was the burden of taxes.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="WW4" speaker="Senator Kemp">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="WW4">
           Senator Kemp
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —As I was saying before the comment by Senator Cook, the government said it would not introduce any new taxes—Senator Evans said that in this chamber. That is the question which he has to address his mind to, not some other issue regarding our own policy. We are asking about the government's policy.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —There is no point of order.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —What we have said consistently is that we will not be increasing the burden of taxation. That is no doubt what Senator Cook was thinking of a moment ago. We have also said quite clearly that there will be no new taxes. We said that in the context of the argument about GST, VAT, and everything else. Any revenue measure would be dealt with in the budget in that context. The jobs levy is a separate issue. We have always acknowledged that, and we will be making a separate decision about that.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="862">
      <title>
       Compulsory Voting
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="AX5" page="862" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen C.V.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="AX5">
          Senator CHRIS EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Administrative Services. Is the minister aware of the WA
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Sunday Times
         </emphasis>
         editorial and comment piece in last Sunday's edition concerning compulsory voting? Given the recent community debate on this topic, has the government reassessed its support for compulsory voting in Australia?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="ACT" gov="1" ministerial="TRADE; ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" nameid="5I4" page="862" party="ALP" speaker="McMullan Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5I4">
          Senator McMULLAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thank Senator Chris Evans for the question and for drawing the articles in question to mind. The
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Sunday Times
         </emphasis>
         and some honourable senators here have been running this issue for some time. It is not very hard to understand. The most basic logic or intellect would enable people to see there is some superficial, pseudoliberal-democratic attraction to that simple argument that the right to vote should entail the right not to vote. That could be argued at a first year philosophy tutorial, but someone would say in return that the response of a citizen in a democracy is that people have to consider the consequences of the policy they are advocating.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="Senator Alston">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Why has every other country got it wrong?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5I4">
          Senator McMULLAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Alston is wrong about that. He should go back to playing Torquemada and not worry about this. The fact of the matter is simply that the research on who does not vote is overwhelmingly clear, and it has been consistent throughout the world for as long as I can recall there being research. There is nothing recent, because all those people who do the research say it is a settled question. Everybody knows that it is people of lower socioeconomic status who do not vote; less well-educated people, blue-collar workers and the unemployed. People who have less contact with others in their immediate neighbourhood do not vote.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I know that some people argue that it is in some way apathetic or less intelligent people who do not vote. I have to say that is a very insulting argument, but I do not attribute that to Senator Minchin, who has not said that. I have to say that I do not agree with his argument, but he has not made that point.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The concern is that these citizens are not voting, not through greater apathy but because these are the people who already feel excluded from the political system. These are the people who feel that the political system does not serve their interests. An agreement to go to voluntary voting would only reinforce that problem. It is reinforced doubly because these are the people who most need the assistance of government. It is inherent in the nature of a democratic political system that it responds to the active electorate. The skew in the political system would go disproportionately towards those who vote and to the interests of those who vote, and the political system would tend to get skewed away from those in greatest need of government policies. Those whom the policies are designed to serve are those least likely to be assisted.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I find that this a profoundly disturbing trend. I would be shocked to think there are people advocating this policy for partisan advantage. I suspect that they would not dream of it; that everybody who advocates it would get partisan advantage from it is undoubtedly a coincidence. Notwithstanding that, the fact is that it is a fundamental question of principle; we should not allow the political system to develop in such a way that it ignores and underestimates the interests of those most in need of government assistance. That tends to disempower further those who are already feeling locked out of the political system. What is worse, there is a tendency to reinforce the power of special interest groups and the zealots. We can be sure that in the United States every member of the National Rifle Association votes, and that is one of the reasons why it has disproportionate power in the American political system.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I think as a question of principle and as a question of serious consideration of the consequences of an action, it is irresponsible for any government and any participant in the political process who operates within a system of compulsory voting to be advocating turning the clock back to a system that advantages the already privileged.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="863">
      <title>
       Australian Secret Intelligence Service
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" nameid="TW4" page="863" party="AD" speaker="Bourne Sen V.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="TW4">
          Senator BOURNE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister for Foreign Affairs. It relates to last night's ABC
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Four Corners
         </emphasis>
         program. What independent oversight of ASIS currently exists? What is so unique about ASIS that, unlike ASIO, the CIA and MI6, it is exempt from all parliamentary scrutiny? Finally, does the minister accept that in the interests of accountability, the government should urgently establish a legislative framework to scrutinise ASIS in the same way as ASIO reports to a joint parliamentary committee?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="863" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It needs to be understood in the light of various calls that have been made for judicial inquiries and so on into the various things that were said in the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Four Corners
         </emphasis>
         program last night and, indeed, in earlier newspaper articles, that there has been a very substantial judicial scrutiny of ASIS already in its recent history, beginning with the first Hope royal commission in 1977. That commission concluded that ASIS should continue as an organisation under the supervision of the Minister for Foreign Affairs. It also established some oversight machinery in the form of the permanent heads committee and the security committee of cabinet.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The second Hope royal commission that was set in train by the Labor government after coming into office in 1983 also scrutinised very minutely ASIS's operations as a result, in the first instance, of the Sheraton Hotel incident, which provoked and justified that degree of scrutiny. In Mr Justice Hope's report arising out of that second royal commission he addressed but rejected the notion of a parliamentary committee in favour of the proposal to establish an Inspector-General of Intelligence and Security—which I referred to in answer to an earlier question—which institution has in fact been in place since 1986, with a very full and wide-ranging brief to ensure not only that these agencies comply with their guidelines and statutory obligations and responsibilities, but also that they respect human rights.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I can confirm that under that legislation the inspector-general was given totally wide-ranging powers, including delving into any material he wants to within any of the organisations in order not only to redress particular grievances but also to see for himself how human rights standards, including privacy, are being maintained.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The second Hope royal commission also specifically resulted in a clear government determination that ASIS would not hold weapons and not maintain a capability for special operations or special political action. It was not that ASIS ever had conducted those sorts of operations—notwithstanding a fair bit of public speculation and mythology to that effect—but the government did firmly rule them out from 1985 onwards, denying ASIS the means even to maintain such a capability.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         As to the scrutiny provisions that operate in other countries, I think there has probably been some degree of misunderstanding about just how wide ranging those congressional and parliamentary oversight arrangements are. In the United Kingdom, for example, we are seeing right now the passage of an intelligence services act. It makes provision for the appointment of a commissioner who is equivalent, in effect, to our inspector-general, as I understand it, and the establishment of a tribunal to deal with the kinds of matters that have long been dealt with by us, for example, with our security appeals tribunal.It also establishes an intelligence and security committee of parliament jointly constituted from the House of Commons and the House of Lords whose oversight extends over the external intelligence agency in the UK, not just the internal one, and which might be thought to have some relevance as a result.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         What needs to be understood—and I do not think it is—is that that legislation specifically allows access by the committee to information to be prohibited in those circumstances where the head of the relevant security service involved certifies that the information is sensitive. And sensitive information includes, among other things, that which might lead to the identification of, or provide details of, sources of information or operational methods; information about particular operations which have been, are being or are proposed to be undertaken; or information provided from another government unless that has been specifically cleared. In effect, there is a total capacity in the way the legislation is drawn to inhibit the access by that particular parliamentary committee to particular information or allegations.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         If Senator Bourne asks me a supplementary question I will tell her about the situation in the US.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="864">
      <title>
       International Performance Indicators
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="PF4" page="864" party="ALP" speaker="Colston Sen M.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="PF4">
          Senator COLSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Industry, Technology and Regional Development. I refer to the project announced by the Prime Minister in March 1991 on international performance indicators. Would the minister advise what was the objective of this project and whether a report has now been provided? If there now is a report, what were the findings and were any reasons advanced for those findings?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT" nameid="RF4" page="864" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —There is a report arising from this project announced by the Prime Minister in 1991. In fact, there has been a series of reports, but the report out today from a joint study by the Bureau of Industry Economics and the Business Council of Australia is
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          International Performance Indicators: Overview
         </emphasis>
         .
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Broadly put, the reason for the government sponsoring this report is that with the phasing down of tariffs and the introduction of some transitory support schemes for industry, as we open the Australian economy to international competition in the traded goods area, there is a need also to make the non-traded goods area of the economy efficient and competitive. The way to do that is to push forward micro-economic reform, as the government has been vigorously doing, but to audit that against international benchmarks and against world best practice performance to demark the area in which Australian infrastructure and transport and communications industries can lift their game to the world best practice level so that the overall competitiveness of our economy is increased, not just that area affected by tariff changes.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         We have pursued a vigorous micro-economic reform agenda. What this report shows in five areas—electricity generation and distribution; rail freight; telecommunications; road freight; and the waterfront—is that, measured against both productivity gains and the list of costs to users, we have been successful in lifting the performance in those areas of the economy where we have pursued micro-economic reform; although in a salutary note the report also says that in many sectors of the economy there is a way to go before we get those sectors up to world best practice.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I was asked in the question whether I could give some indication of that. It has been discovered in this report that for commodities such as coal and wheat the Australian waterfront is performing at near or at world best practice. We are the best in the world, or very close to it, in terms of operating efficiencies. But Australian port authorities and ancillary coal handling charges are over eight times higher than those of our cheapest competitor, meaning that the costs to the users are higher. Australian industrial electricity prices were ranked as fourth cheapest in the OECD in 1990, but were still 40 per cent higher than our cheapest competitor.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The remarks in this report about telecommunications relate to a period before Optus came into competition with Telecom and therefore to an old competitive circumstance. I will not delay the Senate by referring to that. Road freight was found to be operating at close to world best practice in terms of price and reliability. Australian rail freight systems have improved both in labour and capital productivity, especially on the interstate network. State rail charges, however, are nearly twice as high as our most competitive rail system, Australian National, compared to US best practice rates.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The report also provides some interesting comparisons of performances between the states. For instance, on rail freight charges the New South Wales price per net transport kilometre is 50 per cent above the equivalent measure for Australian National. This sort of comparative benchmarking is a useful tool in spotlighting the deficiencies and measuring progress.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The reasons why these outcomes are evident are referred to in the report as a lack of competition in certain state-owned monopolies, the fact that the rate of change in demand is not adequate, or the fact that there is an inadequate use of technology in those particular areas. It is an important report and I commend it to the Senate.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="PF4" page="864" party="ALP" speaker="Colston Sen M.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="PF4">
          Senator COLSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. In view of the minister's answer, will the issues of micro-economic reform, to which he referred, be taken up in this Friday's COAG meeting?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT" nameid="RF4" page="864" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Yes. The COAG meeting this Friday is, of course, an opportunity to consider the Hilmer report. The Hilmer report and the report that has just now been released, the one I referred to, relate to micro-economic reform changes necessary in the Australian economy and require a national response. The debate about this is concentrated on what the federal government is doing. The difference here is that it requires a national response and, therefore, all levels of government—federal, state and local—to contribute to lifting the level of competitiveness in Australia. Of course, the federal government wants to see the Hilmer report universally adopted by the states. That view is supported by the Business Council of Australia. Its President, Mr Ralph, said so much in a comment he made yesterday. But we want to see that, in cooperation with the states, we find a way of introducing true competition and, therefore, ensuring a more competitive and efficient economy and improving the overall competitiveness of Australia, not just at the federal level but nationally.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="865">
      <title>
       Community Grants
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="H15" page="865" party="LP" speaker="Campbell Sen I.G.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="H15">
          Senator CAMPBELL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories. I refer the minister to the grant of $1 million made to Altone Park in the marginal electorate of Perth just 10 days before the last federal election by the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories—and whiteboards. Why was $750,000 towards that grant allocated from the general revenue? Whose departmental budget was the $750,000 taken from? What other grants made by Mrs Kelly under the community cultural, recreation and sporting facilities program were supplemented by additional funds from the general revenue? Did the Minister for Finance and the Prime Minister approve the $750,000 and any other additional general revenue funds allocated by Mrs Kelly?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="HEALTH" nameid="4E4" page="865" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have some—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="Senator Alston">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —We know you are embarrassed.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not feel embarrassed.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LD4" speaker="Senator Alston">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LD4">
           Senator Alston
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I wasn't talking to you.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Oh. I have been asked about a development at Altone Park. I have some notes because, obviously, this has come up somewhere before. I have to concede that they are not enough to satisfy all the parts of Senator Campbell's question, but I will go through what I have and then add anything that I can either at the end of today's question time or tomorrow. As far as I know about the Altone Park development, Mrs Kelly informed shire officials that $250,000 would be allocated from the community cultural, recreation and sporting facilities program and the balance of the $1 million committed was to be met from funds allocated in the 1993 budget. This was made public during the campaign.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The Prime Minister had nothing to do with the administration of the program. It was properly Mrs Kelly's area. The government was already well aware of the Altone Park project, which had a total budget of more than $7.5 million. The project had been granted $100,000 in 1991-92, which was paid in 1993, and $250,000, which is yet to be claimed, in the 1992-93 round of the facilities program.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="DJ4" speaker="Senator Short">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="DJ4">
           Senator Short
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —When was that announced?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I would have to check that. But one has to assume that it was announced in the 1992-93 round. I doubt very much that it has been announced that the $250,000 has not yet been claimed. I am not certain; I would have to check that. But that is the information that I have here. The only other point to make is that none of that involves any breach of the guidelines because the project did not receive more than the maximum $250,000 grant from any one round of the program.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="H15" page="865" party="LP" speaker="Campbell Sen I.G.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="H15">
          Senator CAMPBELL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I thank the minister for his answer. There are a couple of points that he did not address and I hope that he will come back later with further information. One point in particular was what other grants made by Mrs Kelly under this program were supplemented with additional funds from general revenue? The other point, which he should be able to address now, is that he said in the answer to the question that the Prime Minister had no involvement with this program. He did not say whether the Minister for Finance or the Prime Minister had knowledge or approval of the $750,000 specifically referred to in this question.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="HEALTH" nameid="4E4" page="865" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Again, I will have to check on that and get back to Senator Campbell as soon as I can.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="866">
      <title>
       Royal Jelly
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="1X4" page="866" party="ALP" speaker="West Sen S.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1X4">
          Senator WEST
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Family Services. Is the minister aware of the reports about the dangers of royal jelly and the tragic death of a young girl in New South Wales recently? What action is being taken by the federal government to warn consumers of the possible risks of taking royal jelly?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="SA" gov="1" ministerial="FAMILY SERVICES" nameid="ZF4" page="866" party="ALP" speaker="Crowley Sen The Hon R.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZF4">
          Senator CROWLEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thank the honourable senator for her question. Medical research and the Therapeutic Goods Administration have recently identified 11 cases of severe allergic reaction, including the tragic death of an 11-year-old girl in Cooma and four life-threatening episodes, following the ingestion of royal jelly and royal jelly products. All cases occurred in people with a history of asthma or allergic reaction, and included 10 women and one man. Ten of the cases were reported in the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Australian Medical Journal
         </emphasis>
         in November 1993 and January 1994. They are believed to be the first reported cases in the world linking the ingestion of royal jelly with severe allergic reaction in asthma or allergy sufferers.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The TGA has reviewed the clinical evidence and has determined that consumer safety requires the placement of warning labels on royal jelly products, recommending they should not be consumed by asthma and allergy sufferers. As some royal jelly products are classified as food items, the TGA has also coordinated its activities with the National Food Authority which is arranging for similar warnings to be included on such products. The Australian Association of Asthma Foundations, all consumer organisations and relevant industry and professional bodies are being advised of these developments, and their assistance is being sought to give very wide circulation to this information.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Medical research is being done also at the Alfred Hospital in Melbourne to identify the particular protein or proteins within royal jelly responsible for the allergic reaction. The TGA will continue to monitor the developments, and may have to vary its warning as the information emerges.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         It cannot be stressed too seriously that allergic reactions to products like royal jelly can be fatal. Sadly, that has already happened and we think it is very timely that a product warning be placed on any food product or therapeutic product containing royal jelly. The warning for therapeutic products will read, `Warning. This product contains royal jelly and is not recommended for asthma and allergy sufferers as it can cause severe allergic reactions'.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Alternative medicines and foods have a very significant market in this country, and the National Food Authority is concerned that people might be frightened off alternative preparations such as royal jelly, which is a very significant market spinner in that industry. However, I believe that the concerns of the industry are not significant or important enough to outweigh the government's concern that, if the warnings are not placed on products in the light of the evidence to hand, there may be more severe reactions or even fatalities.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         This warning particularly alerts people with asthma or a history of allergy that there may be a danger if royal jelly is taken. It also advises people that one does not have to have a history to develop an allergy to some food products. So, while it gives good counsel to asthma and allergy suffers in particular, it is a warning to people in general to note the advice in relation to this product.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="867">
      <title>
       Prime Minister: Piggery
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" nameid="O15" page="867" party="LP" speaker="Tierney Sen J.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="O15">
          Senator TIERNEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories. I refer to the Prime Minister's joint venture piggery in the Hunter Valley, which the Environmental Protection Agency says creates a high risk to the environment because it will pollute the land, water and air—an environmental trifecta. Why should we believe that the government is serious about the environment when the Prime Minister has such a blatant disregard for it when making a buck is at stake?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="HEALTH" nameid="4E4" page="867" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I could not hear the last part of the question. There was some noise in the chamber. Could Senator Tierney repeat the last part of the question?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Would you like to repeat the last part of your question, Senator Tierney.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="NSW" nameid="O15" page="867" party="LP" speaker="Tierney Sen J.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="O15">
          Senator TIERNEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Certainly. Everyone else heard it but I am happy to repeat it. Why should we believe that this government is really serious about environmental concerns when the Prime Minister has such blatant disregard for the environment when making a buck is at stake?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="HEALTH" nameid="4E4" page="867" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I find that an extraordinary question. I am not certain what those opposite would say about what is inherent in that question—that one cannot have piggeries because they pollute. That is absolutely inherent in the question, absolutely what the honourable senator said, and he cannot walk away from it.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         In terms of polluting the land, the water and the air, as Senator Tierney has claimed, I understand that a report is being prepared on this subject. There has been an extensive environmental inquiry which has gone through the appropriate processes of the New South Wales government because it is within its power to say yea or nay, or to say yes with conditions.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="O15" speaker="Senator Tierney">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="O15">
           Senator Tierney
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —It hasn't said yes yet.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —No, it has not. I do not think the report has come down. Maybe Senator Tierney has knowledge of what the report will say, but I do not. All I can say is that the Prime Minister's piggery, or any other piggery, has to go through the proper environmental processes laid down in state legislation. That is exactly what is occurring.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="NSW" nameid="O15" page="867" party="LP" speaker="Tierney Sen J.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="O15">
          Senator TIERNEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I am glad the minister has made those points because what the EPA has said about this has been widely publicised in the papers. Let me tell the minister what it found. It found continued land degradation affecting the site, the impact of odour affecting the air and salty effluent affecting the water. The minister says that I am against piggeries. We are not against piggeries; we are against piggeries that are inappropriate for that site. Will the Minister representing the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories tell the Prime Minister to move this inappropriate industry out of the beautiful Hunter Valley where it is wrecking the environment?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="HEALTH" nameid="4E4" page="867" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I think it is up to the environment authorities in New South Wales to determine exactly what kind of piggery is appropriate, where it would be appropriate, how it would be managed and what safeguards should be applied to it. That process has been gone through at great length and in great detail. I await, as I am sure do those opposite, let alone the Prime Minister, what the environmental authorities in New South Wales might decide. I am sure, as is the case with every other citizen or every other proposer, that the Prime Minister will abide by the law and abide by those decisions.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="868">
      <title>
       Rural Australia
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="HX5" page="868" party="AD" speaker="Woodley Sen J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="HX5">
          Senator WOODLEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I draw the attention of the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy to an article in the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Weekend Australian
         </emphasis>
         of 12 and 13 February titled `The unsettling of Australia'. The article describes the continuing decline in the population, income and morale of rural Australia. Does the minister agree that rural Australia is in serious decline, and does the minister agree with the University of Queensland demographer, Dr Martin Bell, who states:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The negative impact of out-migration will be exacerbated in the prevailing climate of `economic rationalism' which promotes the closure of private and public services to country towns.
       </para>
       <para>
        What plans does the government have to reverse these disastrous trends, or does the government intend in the future to feed Australia with imported food?
       </para>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY" nameid="OF4" page="868" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The poor old English language continues to suffer—in this case from the use of the word `out-migration' in the question. There is emerging evidence—and a great deal of this, as I am sure Senator Woodley knows, was delivered at the ABARE Outlook 1994 conference earlier this year—that the downturn in the rural sector in Australia has bottomed, with signs of recovery in both rural land markets and the price of land, and in the economy generally.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Since the late 1980s, a group of producers has continued to face difficulties in achieving long-term profitability but, on the other hand, indications are that many potential investors are benefiting from the build-up of property size and value-adding activities. In terms of the population decline, the facts are, as the statistics demonstrate, that we are in no different position in Australia than in any other developed country in the world.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         We have one of the most efficient agricultural sectors in the world. The more efficient it becomes with the technological advances that are enjoyed by Australian primary industries, the build-up of land ownership will continue. With the continued efficiency provided by technological change and enhanced management techniques, the rural population will continue to decline from the historically high levels that it has enjoyed in the past. The recovery that we are generally experiencing domestically and the improved recovery that is being experienced around the world will improve the situation for Australian farmers. We can expect to see ongoing restructuring in rural industries, particularly among farmers who have longer-term profitability problems.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The government's support for the farmers whom Senator Woodley is concerned about is very significant. A major scheme has been offered. I think the wool industry is substantially happy with the achievements that this government has made in improvements in the wool industry, the achievements of which are particularly due to the efforts of the former minister, Mr Crean. The rural adjustment package is being funded this year to the tune of $170 million, which is a significant amount of support. As Senator Woodley would know, that is only one part of the picture. The drought-affected farmers in Queensland, for example, have received in excess of $20 million in direct assistance to enable them to cope with their problems. Indeed, cabinet approved a further $7 million at the beginning of this year for those particular farmers.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The government also has a whole host of associated programs. Landcare is one. It is designed to improve the long-term profitability of Australian agriculture. The government is funding that program this year to the tune of $105 million. It would take far longer than the four minutes allowed for my answer to go into that range of programs. But I will mention one initiative in particular that, in addition to everything that I have just said, will provide for enhanced future profitability of Australian farmers. I refer to the agribusiness programs that are being developed, particularly to encourage exports of Australian primary produce into Asia.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         In respect of the infrastructure difficulties that Senator Woodley referred to in the last part of his question, the government is of course currently considering the Kelty regional development report. Our examination of that report will assist in formulating future policy for regional Australia.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="869">
      <title>
       Community Grants
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="VJ4" page="869" party="LP" speaker="Watson Sen J.O.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VJ4">
          Senator WATSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Finance. Was the administration of Minister Kelly's grants consistent with the accountability prescriptions within the Audit Act, Finance regulations and Finance directions? What action did the Department of Finance, as the responsible policeman, or the government's relevant minister take in response to the Auditor-General's report?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT" nameid="RF4" page="869" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —This question calls for considerable detail in terms of an answer. Since I am here merely as a representative of the Minister for Finance—
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="Senator Collins">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Merely!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Well, since I am here as a representative of the Minister for Finance, I propose to take Senator Watson's question on notice and reply to it in due course.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="VJ4" page="869" party="LP" speaker="Watson Sen J.O.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VJ4">
          Senator WATSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. Given the importance of the accountability issues involved in the question, and given that the Senate estimates committees will be starting shortly, could Senator Cook report back at the conclusion of question time today?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT" nameid="RF4" page="869" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Out of respect for the Senate, I will endeavour to do that. But, since we are about 11 minutes short of concluding question time, I feel it may not be possible in that short space of time to get the answer to a question that calls for such a comprehensive and encyclopaedic answer.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="869">
      <title>
       Coode Island: East Coast Armaments Complex
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="AW5" page="869" party="ALP" speaker="Carr Sen K.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="AW5">
          Senator CARR
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Defence. Is the minister aware of recent press reports in Melbourne that the Australian government is standing in the way of the relocation of the Coode Island chemical facility to the Point Wilson area? Are these reports true? What is the Australian government's position regarding the new east coast armaments complex?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE" nameid="UI4" page="869" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UI4">
          Senator ROBERT RAY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The Senate will recall that cabinet made a decision last December identifying Jervis Bay and Twofold Bay as two options for relocating the armaments depot, but it also left open the possibility of Point Wilson in Victoria. We made it very clear at the time, though, that we were not going to solve the problems of western Sydney by compounding problems that exist in the western area of Melbourne. As such, with the planned relocation of the Coode Island facility to Point Wilson, we in the federal government said that that must have priority in the course of determining where we send the armaments depot. That is still our position.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         If the Victorian government will eventually make a decision, and publicly announce that decision, to go to Point Wilson, it will have right of way. But the secondary issue to that is this: we have been looking at whether it is possible to have either co-location or co-access to Point Wilson for the armaments depot. Even though technically it is probably feasible to have co-location, it is a very hard symbolic thing to sell to have a chemical complex on one side of the road and a safe ammunition depot on the other, even though every study might show that there is no chance whatsoever of an interaction between the two.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         So what we are now looking at and hoping to discuss with the Victorian government in the next couple of weeks is co-access to a wharf and actually locating the two a reasonable distance apart so that no-one, no matter what conspiracy theories they may be indulging in, would be able to argue that there was any danger.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Last week again the Victorian government fell back on the old canard that it cannot make a decision on Coode Island because the federal government has not finally made a decision on the east coast armaments complex. I say to that: in terms of priority, if the Victorian government wants to move the Coode Island facility to Point Wilson, it can announce it tomorrow and we will comply with that decision. If it did announce it tomorrow we would then seek to have studies made to determine whether co-access to the wharf is a feasible thing. I know that would in many ways generate enormous support from the areas around Geelong that Senator Carr and I represent. There is a great employment initiative there. It would also mean that some of the more sensitive environmental areas that were previously identified could be taken off the scene.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="870">
      <title>
       Animal Diseases
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="YE4" page="870" party="NP" speaker="Boswell Sen R.L.D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YE4">
          Senator BOSWELL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy. I refer to the February 1994 AQIS bulletin documenting a case of mad cow disease in Canada that resulted from a cow imported from the UK in 1987. I ask the minister: does this mean that diseases such as mad cow disease or mystery swine disease which originate in Europe can be transmitted to other countries but not become active for years? What is the scientific consensus on diseases such as mystery swine disease and PRRS becoming active after a period of dormancy? In view of the answers to those questions, if the minister can give them to me, can the minister inform me whether Danpork has applied to AQIS to import pig meat? Where will these imports come from?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY" nameid="OF4" page="870" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —In order to provide a comprehensive answer to Senator Boswell's question, I advise him that these issues are canvassed very well in a discussion paper which I released only about a fortnight ago. I will ensure that his office gets a copy of it this afternoon.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UI4" speaker="Senator Robert Ray">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UI4">
           Senator Robert Ray
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Give him a big print version.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will make sure that it is in National Party font for them.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="YE4" page="870" party="NP" speaker="Boswell Sen R.L.D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YE4">
          Senator BOSWELL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr President, I ask a supplementary question. I ask again the last part of my earlier question. Has Danpork applied to AQIS to import pig meat? Where will those imports come from?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY" nameid="OF4" page="870" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —There have been applications made, as Senator Boswell knows full well, even though he is pretending that he does not, for the importation of pig meat from Denmark. Indeed, that is the very reason that I issued the discussion paper about a fortnight ago—so that it can be given the widest possible public distribution and comment.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The question of Australia's position on these issues is well known and will remain consistent—that is, that any concerns this government has are legitimate concerns of protection for the Australian industry and do not in any way create artificial barriers to the importation of these products. It is a serious issue with serious potential impacts on Australian agriculture. For that reason, we have dealt with it in the appropriate way. A discussion paper has been issued and we are soliciting the widest possible comment on it. I will ensure that Senator Boswell's office gets a copy of the discussion paper today.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="870">
      <title>
       Horticulture
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="XI4" page="870" party="ALP" speaker="Reynolds Sen The Hon M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XI4">
          Senator REYNOLDS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy. The minister will be aware that the report of the horticultural task force was released this morning in Melbourne by Senator Sherry. Given the importance of horticulture to many regions of Australia, can the minister indicate what he sees as the main implications of this report? How can it assist rural industry growth in regional areas?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY" nameid="OF4" page="870" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Horticulture is a key industry in Australia with 80,000 growers currently engaged in it and 11,500 people employed in processing. Its gross value of production is about $3 billion a year and it had exports of $646 million in 1991-92. But it is a highly fragmented industry with a very heavy domestic orientation and, with some notable exceptions, a generally poor export record.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Against this background and in light of the February 1993 Industry Commission report on horticulture, the government established a task force which was chaired by my colleague Senator Sherry. Its task was to consider future directions and to development industry strategy for growth. The task force has done that. It has clearly identified the potential and challenges for the horticultural industry. I commend the members of that task force and the chair, Senator Sherry, on producing an extremely useful and valuable report.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The potential—outlined in that report—exists to triple the value of horticultural exports from Australia to approximately $2 billion by the year 2000, but this will not be achieved with the existing industry structures, the prevailing industry attitudes or the current regulatory arrangements. The task force has suggested in its 61 recommendations fundamental changes for the horticultural industry. It has identified the Australian Horticultural Corporation as the organisation that should be charged with driving these changes. Its role should become more commercially oriented, particularly in terms of industry adjustment, export market development and the domestic marketing and planning activities of participating industries.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The task force has also recommended the establishment of a strong industry identity and focus through nationally representative peak industry bodies. The government will give careful consideration to the 61 recommendations of the task force. Given the unprecedented change in our economy throughout the last decade, we will work with this particular industry to ensure a stronger and more internationally competitive future for this country. In conclusion, I table the report from the task force.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="871">
      <title>
       Taxation: Jobs Levy
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="JI4" page="871" party="LP" speaker="Panizza Sen J.H.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="JI4">
          Senator PANIZZA
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is to the Minister representing the Prime Minister. Before determining the policy on the introduction of a new tax in the form of a jobs levy, is it the government's intention to read to its decision makers, including Senator Carr, loudly and slowly so it can sink in, the lessons learnt after they took the decision to abolish negative gearing of rental properties—a decision they had to reverse with egg on their faces?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="871" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have got nothing to add to what I said earlier about the jobs levy. It is obviously a matter for consideration and decision by the government in the budget context.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="BH4" speaker="Senator Hill">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="BH4">
           Senator Hill
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —It is an exception.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is a financing mechanism that may or may not be appropriate to fund unemployment, training and support measures of that kind, separate and distinct, specifically related to that program, if it is introduced at all. If anything was said by Mr Beazley on the weekend about that issue, it ought to have given the opposition some cause for pause before believing that it was in fact likely we would go down any such path. But I make no final statement on this. Obviously it is to be resolved in a budget context, as all these things are.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="871">
      <title>
       Breast Cancer
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="FE4" page="871" party="ALP" speaker="Zakharov Sen A.O.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FE4">
          Senator ZAKHAROV
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Is the Minister for Health aware that a cancer specialist, John Forbes, has accused him of a lack of commitment in the fight against breast cancer? Can the Minister tell the Senate what action the government is taking to reduce the incidence of breast cancer and the suffering it causes?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="HEALTH" nameid="4E4" page="871" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am aware of the statements of John Forbes over the past few days.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="VW4" speaker="Senator Herron">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="VW4">
           Senator Herron
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —A good man, too. The leading expert in Australia.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I heard Senator Herron's interjection, that he is the leading person in his field in Australia, and I think that is probably true. I do not doubt that for a second. I take the view though that his research into what is a critical area and a real problem is nonetheless one researcher looking at one area. As a minister, I have to look at a lot more than that. But in all that he has said I do not believe that he has made any real acknowledgment of what has been done over the past few years, which I think is worth putting on record. This year $30 million has been allocated to the screening program, and that is to be matched by the states.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SE4" speaker="Senator Bishop">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SE4">
           Senator Bishop
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —But nothing for research.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That is not true and you know it—$1.4 million. By June, we will be screening 630,000 women a year, rising to 850,000 a year by 1996.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SE4" speaker="Senator Bishop">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SE4">
           Senator Bishop
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —One to two million—that is chicken feed.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That's chicken feed? You're joking! A further 425,000 diagnostic mammograms were performed under Medicare last year at a cost of $27 million. It is a pretty sad error not to acknowledge that they are going on.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Obviously, early detection means early treatment and therefore the real possibility of a cure. That is why we have agreed to those things that I have just outlined. But, more importantly, in April last year I asked the states to agree to make breast cancer a priority for work in a new national health policy. I got Professor Forbes to address the state ministers; none of them had met him or heard of him before, but I got him there to do it.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         After that, I then asked my department to develop specific goals and strategies for improving prevention, research, diagnosis and treatment for breast cancer. Since then, the experts in cancer and women's health who have helped draw up the draft discussion paper, which will be discussed today in Brisbane by the health ministers advisory committee, include: Professor Lowenthal, Dr Weisberg, Dr John Lowe, Dr Ray Snyder, Dr Graham Dickie, Dr Leanna Darvall and Mr Colin Furnival. That is a pretty impressive group of people who have been consulted since.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That paper, which will be discussed today by the advisory committee to the ministers, includes strategies for treatment, prevention, education and research. The overriding goal in that paper is to reduce breast cancer mortalities by 10 per cent over the next few years. It will include best practice guidelines by 1997; clinical centres for research and treatment; and community education on treatment and care options. In the budget this year there will be an announcement of the largest single increase in funding for medical research since Federation.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="BE4" speaker="Senator Newman">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="BE4">
           Senator Newman
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —About time.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —If one looks at the Fraser government's record, it ought to be remembered that those opposite spent nothing. We will spend plenty—the largest single increase since Federation. More important than that, it will be spent by the National Health and Medical Research Council, by experts in their field, by peers reviewing peers; not by politicians sticking their noses in and making political decisions. That is the wrong way to go. The opposition tried it with its arts policy and failed. It should learn its lesson and not try it here.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="VD4" speaker="Senator Gareth Evans">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="VD4">
           Senator Gareth Evans
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr President, I ask that further questions be placed on the
          <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
           Notice Paper
          </emphasis>
          .
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="872">
      <title>
       Australian Secret Intelligence Service
      </title>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="872" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Bourne asked me a question about, among other things, parliamentary scrutiny of the CIA. I did not get time to respond to that part of the question then, but I do so now. The situation in the United States is that there are select committees on intelligence in both the Senate and the House of Representatives, together with Senate and House committees on appropriations. The appropriations committees, or the relevant subcommittees, leave detailed work, including on budgetary matters, to the operational committees, so the relationships with those committees are essentially formal in character.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         There is quite a substantial working relationship with the two operational intelligence committees, and quite a lot of information is given. However, it is important to realise the limitations in the United States on the supply of information from the executive in sensitive matters. There is an agreed provision, for example, whereby, by presidential directive, sensitive operational material can be provided only to an inner group of the relevant congressional committees.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Moreover, there is a further provision which is the result of the continuing stand-off between the congress and the executive in terms of legislation which embodies this or leaves it out, as the case may be, and that is a presidential directive whereby in extreme cases, where determined by the president in consultation with the cabinet committee, the congress is not to be advised, even in a limited fashion, about particular matters. The stand-off is a result of the fact that congress does not want such a provision, the executive has insisted on it, and the indications are that if ever it went to legislation, the legislation would be vetoed if it did not contain such an exceptional provision.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         All that points to the reality of very significant inherent limitations, even in a relatively apparently open system like the United States, which confront efforts to have parliamentary oversight of particularly sensitive intelligence operations. I have described the similar provisions which are there on the face of the legislation in the United Kingdom.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         It is because of the inherent limitations involved in any such parliamentary scrutiny that successive governments in Australia have taken the view that it is not especially helpful as a contribution to the oversight of ASIS in Australia, and that that oversight would be better exercised through, in particular, the machinery of the Inspector-General of Intelligence and Security, together with the additional oversight that is exercised by the permanent heads committee of the intelligence community, and also the cabinet security committee. I think that gives additional—and hopefully helpful—background to Senator Bourne and anyone else interested in the policy of this matter.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="873">
      <title>
       Community Grants
      </title>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="HEALTH" nameid="4E4" page="873" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —In question time on 10 February Senator Kernot asked me a series of questions. I have quite a long answer. I seek leave to table it.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Leave granted.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
    </qwn>
    <debate page="873" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ORDER OF BUSINESS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="873">
      <title>
       Estimates Committees
      </title>
      <speech electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="873" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BH4">
          Senator HILL
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Leader of the Opposition)
         </role>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave—I ask the Manager of Government Business in the Senate (Senator Faulkner) a question about the program. I have just given the minister notice of it. In order that sensible planning can be made for the rest of the day and night, can I be assured that it is the intention of the government that the estimates committee meetings this afternoon will finish at 8 p.m. in accordance with the timetable that the majority in this place forced upon us a few weeks ago?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE SCIENCE AND PERSONNEL; VETERANS' AFFAIRS" nameid="5K4" page="873" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (New South Wales-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Manager of Government Business in the Senate)
         </role>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave—As honourable senators would know, the way the estimates committee processes have worked in the past—and this is even more true now, given that only a limited number of estimates committee hearings are set—it is up to the estimates committees themselves to determine those sitting hours. It would be very sensible, given the sorts of constraints that we have in our parliamentary timetable, that the estimates committees meeting not only tonight, but also on Thursday, deal with as much business as is practicable, but also, as they always do, take into account that there is a reasonable hour beyond which any committee ought not sit.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I make the observation that in my experience over the five years I have been in the Senate it has never been the government's intention to prolong the hearings of estimates committees. I will not be as ungenerous as to do it, but I could name one or two senators from the opposition who themselves have been responsible for many hours of estimates committee hearings on wild goose chases that are unproductive not only for the scrutiny of government but also for the opposition.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I hope that good sense does prevail and I urge Senator Hill to discipline those senators sitting behind him to ensure that that occurs. Traditionally, estimates committees in this place have sat late, unfortunately. But this is a matter that is really up to the estimates committees themselves to work through at appropriate times with the ministers at the table. There is no intention to change the way in which estimates committees have operated, but I have no doubt that estimates committees chairmen will take account of issues such as appropriate meal breaks, and I wish us all well for later on this evening.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="873" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS ON NOTICE
     </title>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="YW4" page="873" party="LP" speaker="Macdonald Sen I.D.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YW4">
         Senator IAN MACDONALD
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Under the 30-day rule contained in the order of the Senate of 28 September 1988—apparently I have to ask this immediately following question time, which is something the Procedure Committee might have a look at—I ask the Minister representing the Treasurer, Senator McMullan, for an explanation as to why the responsible minister has not answered my question.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="Senator Collins">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator Collins
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —You will have to ask the right minister first.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="VD4" speaker="Senator Gareth Evans">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator Gareth Evans
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Cook is now the Minister representing the Treasurer.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YW4">
         Senator IAN MACDONALD
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I am asking Senator McMullan. I gave Senator Cook notice that I was going to ask him some questions but he has answered them.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Mr President, I am indicating question No. 832 directed to the Minister representing the Minister for Transport—I thought that was Senator McMullan; question No. 833 to the Minister representing the Minister for Transport; question No. 834 to the Minister representing the Minister for Communications and the Arts; question No. 835 to the Minister representing the Minister for Transport; question No. 836 to the Minister representing the Minister for Transport; and question No. 905 to the Minister for Trade. I think they all belong to Senator McMullan. If I did say the Treasurer earlier, I have made a mistake and I apologise for that. I gave Senator McMullan notice that I would be raising these questions with him.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="ACT" gov="1" ministerial="TRADE; ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES" nameid="5I4" page="874" party="ALP" speaker="McMullan Sen The Hon R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5I4">
         Senator McMULLAN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Australian Capital Territory-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Minister for Trade and Minister for Administrative Services)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I acknowledge that Senator Macdonald did give advice about those outstanding questions. I sought to have answers ready for him today but I can assure him I will have them this week.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="YW4" page="874" party="LP" speaker="Macdonald Sen I.D.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YW4">
         Senator IAN MACDONALD
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
        <time.stamp>
         (3.14 p.m.)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        That the Senate take note of the statement.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       I find Senator McMullan's explanation unsatisfactory. Some of these questions have been outstanding for quite some time. As I said previously, I gave a similar notice to Senator Cook, who was able to get me the answers to two questions and indicate that a third would be given to me this afternoon and a fourth by the end of the week. I think Senator McMullan might be able to do a fraction better than this. Some of these questions have been outstanding since November and there seems to have been adequate time to answer them. Some of them are questions that I wanted to pursue in estimates this afternoon, and it is very difficult to do that.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="H15" speaker="Senator Campbell">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="H15">
          Senator Campbell
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That is why you do not have the answers.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YW4">
         Senator IAN MACDONALD
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Senator Campbell is quite right. That is why I do not have the answers. I note Senator Collins's intervention. They were questions originally addressed to him, many of them relating to the CAA and the enormous mess that Senator Collins made while he held that portfolio. I was hoping that with a new minister we would have been able to get some answers to those questions.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        I do not consider Senator McMullan's answer that he will get the answers by the end of the week satisfactory. I do not intend to move any further motion at this time, but I say to Senator McMullan that it would be appreciated if I could get those answers some time today so that they could be used in the estimates committees later on today.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Question resolved in the affirmative.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="874" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="874">
      <title>
       Breast Cancer
      </title>
      <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="SE4" page="874" party="LP" speaker="Bishop Sen B.K.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="SE4">
          Senator BISHOP
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (New South Wales)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (3.16 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate take note of the answer given by the Minister for Health (Senator Richardson) to a question without notice asked by Senator Zakharov this day, relating to the funding of breast cancer research.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
        If I sounded angry when I was interjecting, I am and I was. I am angry because Senator Richardson and his government have been in power for 11 years and every day six to seven women in Australia die of breast cancer. Three mothers of children who are friends of one of my children died this year. Another has just been diagnosed, and another has had a double mastectomy. A sum of only $1 million to $2 million a year is provided for research funds in this country. Yet the government had the temerity to say in its
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Women's Budget Statement
        </emphasis>
        accompanying the budget papers last year that $51.84 million was provided for the strategy to deal with AIDS in women. It said:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The Strategy identifies women as a priority target group for education, because their ability to negotiate safe sex or safe drug-taking practices could be reduced by a self-perception of low risk, an imbalance of power in relationships and social stereotyping.
       </para>
       <para>
        It continued:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        At 28 February 1993, 129 cases of women with AIDS and 71 deaths had been reported.
       </para>
       <para>
        For that, $51.84 million was given. Six to seven women die every day of breast cancer and $1 million to $2 million is given. This document is a travesty of the government's attitude to women's health. It shows how superficial, arrogant and insensitive this government has been for 11 years to a problem that needs attention.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Senator Richardson said today that this government was finally going to do something about it and that the bleating of politicians had done nothing. Believe me, there are a lot of women politicians who have done a lot to bring this matter to the attention of this government, which has listened with stone ears.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         If I sounded angry then and angry now, I am very angry. If women are to be treated in a cynical way by this government over a problem that they face which is real when research should have been going on for years, and if the issue is to be used as a political football, I for one will not have it said. The concern on this side of politics is a very real one, and to have that contemptuous answer stand unanswered is just not acceptable. It is time this government paid attention to the problem of breast cancer. It is far too late for Senator Richardson to try to take credit for something which this government has neglected for 11 years.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="VW4" page="875" party="LP" speaker="Herron Sen J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Queensland)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (3.19 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I support Senator Bishop. I am appalled at the paltry sum that the Minister for Health (Senator Richardson) announced today. On 12 May last year, Senator Richardson stated in answer to a question without notice:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        . . . at the health Ministers meeting, which I think from memory is in the first week of July, a suggestion on how we might make a national campaign on breast cancer the first trial for the national health policy.
       </para>
       <para>
        Here we are, nearly a year later, and in that time over 500 women have died of breast cancer in this country. What has the minister done in that last year? Nothing; not a thing. He attacked Professor Forbes on the radio this morning. I pulled the minister up this afternoon and he admitted that Professor Forbes is one of the leading researchers in Australia. Professor Forbes has been battering his head against government for years and years to get breast cancer on the agenda. As Senator Bishop said, $51 million was provided for AIDS research and $1.2 million goes from the National Health and Medical Research Council into breast cancer research, $750,000 of which goes to one institution. It is not that there is a shortage of researchers.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The tragedy in this country really is that for 40 years the mortality rate from breast cancer has not changed. The incidence is increasing. The paltry sum that the minister has announced will probably cope with only the number of extra women who are getting breast cancer in this country because of the ageing population. It is almost an epidemic; it is approaching that stage. In America, at the moment, one in nine women will get breast cancer in their lifetime. At the moment in Australia it is between one in 12 and one in 13 women. Within the next nine years, one in 10 women will get breast cancer in their lifetime. We could describe it as an epidemic in the country.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         But it is not just detection that is the problem. We do not have the radiotherapy facilities. The College of Radiologists in Australia, which encompasses the radiotherapists, has been crying out for years about the lack of money going into the development of radiotherapy in this country and the training of radiotherapists. As this epidemic increases, there will not be the facilities to give the women the best possible treatment available, which is early detection.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I instigated the Senate Standing Committee on Community Affairs inquiry into breast cancer screening in Australia. The reason I did that was that breast cancer screening in this country fell way behind. We are about 10 years behind the countries that have instituted breast screening programs. That is why I instituted that inquiry. It has become evident, in our inquiries, that the facilities vary from state to state. There is no national agreement on the coding.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         We are so far behind that, because of the statistics involved, we will not even be able to demonstrate in this country whether screening will reduce the mortality. I heard Senator Richardson say today that he will reduce the mortality rate of breast cancer by 10 per cent or something in the next few years. I have news for him. It has not occurred in the last 40 years. A politician saying that by throwing a bit of extra money at it the mortality rate will decrease by 10 per cent is absolute rubbish.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="VJ4" speaker="Senator Watson">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="VJ4">
           Senator Watson
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —It is irresponsible.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is irresponsible. He is politicking on this. He politicked on it a year ago for a cheap shot on the fact that he was going to do something about it. He has done nothing. The government has been in power for 11 years. It has become a bit of an issue now and he will race off. It will be the same with Aboriginal health. I have the figures; I will give him a bit of a warning.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="BE4" speaker="Senator Newman">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="BE4">
           Senator Newman
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —He ran away from a debate on air about it today. He would not debate that.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —He ran away from the debate earlier today, as Senator Newman says. I have the figures on Aboriginal health. His next thing will be on Aboriginal health—photographs of him walking around Arnhem Land with an Aboriginal lady. He is going to fix it. I have the figures for Aboriginal health and I will produce them for him each year on the year to see what he has done about Aboriginal health. I can tell the Senate that he will not achieve anything.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LI4" speaker="Senator Patterson">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LI4">
           Senator Patterson
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —They have been in for 11 years.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The government has been in power for 11 years. These issues have become political. He wants to point score off them. He will not be forgiven by the women of Australia and their families who are affected by this dreadful disease for making it a political issue.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="876" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6H4">
          Senator HARRADINE
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (3.24 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I was very disappointed in the response given by the Minister for Health, Senator Richardson. I was particularly concerned to hear him, as I understood it, question the fact that members of parliament should be involved in trying to ensure that priority is given to this particular burning question. Ask widowers what they think about this situation. Ask the daughters and the fathers of women who have died of breast cancer.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="VJ4" speaker="Senator Watson">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="VJ4">
           Senator Watson
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —The sons and daughters.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6H4">
          Senator HARRADINE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Yes, the sons and daughters, but ask the daughters particularly, because they are told it is not hereditary but familial. Ask them what they think about the paltry amount of money that is provided for research in this area. We represent those people, and I appeal to the minister not to respond as he has done but to do something practical to reverse what I believe is discrimination against women in this country in respect of one of the greatest health problems with which they and their families have to contend.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The government should consider what has been said here today and over a period of time. I heard what Senator Herron said about his efforts in respect of the inquiry. I know that the House of Representatives committee is looking into the question—this question has been looked into for too long. What is needed is action and government commitment in the way of appropriate funding; not the discrimination meted out by the government to these people.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Question resolved in the affirmative.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="876">
      <title>
       Taxation
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="DJ4" page="876" party="LP" speaker="Short Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (3.27 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate take note of the answer given by the Minister for Foreign Affairs (Senator Gareth Evans), in response to a question without notice asked by Senator Short this day, relating to taxation increases.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
        I asked Senator Evans today whether, on behalf of the government, he would give the Australian people an assurance that this year's budget will honour the commitments of the preceding Treasurer, Mr Dawkins, and the current Treasurer, Mr Willis, and the commitments given by the Prime Minister, Mr Keating, during the run-up to the 1993 federal election and since, that there will be no further tax increases.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         To refresh the memory of the Senate on this, I suppose the most famous of all these statements was that of the Prime Minister on the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Lateline
         </emphasis>
         program in November 1992, just three months before the election. He said `What I am promising is not to put up tax'. That came after statements made in the budget debate by, amongst others, the then Treasurer, Mr Dawkins. But on 16 September 1992, Mr Dawkins emphasised to parliament, `This will be achieved without resort to any new taxes'—`this' being the two-stage income tax cut being promised by the government at that time. He also said, `We can pay for our personal income tax cuts'. The saga went on and on and eventually the promise was broken—very rapidly in fact—in the 1993 budget when the proposed second stage of cuts did not occur.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         It was those tax cuts that the government had run to the election on. When the Prime Minister was questioned about the matter he arrogantly said, `Look, those cuts are legislated. They are law; l-a-w, law'. What he really meant was that they were `Lie; l-i-e, lie', because that is precisely what happened. The Prime Minister and the government lied their way into office with such promises which they broke as soon as they were elected.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The Leader of the Government in the Senate, Senator Evans, himself is on very shaky ground in this area. Only six months ago, on 5 October 1993, he told the Senate that the government would not `go down the path of introducing new taxes'. He probably thought he was in pretty good company because at around that time the then Treasurer had said in the parliament that he was—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        opposed to future tax increase to meet the cost of any new obligations which come up. See my job—
       </para>
       <para>
        Mr Dawkins said—
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        as resisting any claims for tax increases. . . my view is to say if there are new things to spend money on we have to adjust priorities to accommodate them. . .
       </para>
       <para>
        Mr Willis, the Treasurer who succeeded Mr Dawkins, just a couple of months after that, on 23 December, said, `Obviously the government has no plan to raise taxes, and we certainly would not be wanting to raise taxes'. In my question today I asked Senator Evans whether the government would stick by those commitments. He refused to give such a commitment; he was totally equivocal about it. Indeed, he gave a quite extraordinary answer. He said, `Oh well, there was a possible jobs levy but we would not count that', and left it at that.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That raises two fundamental questions. I am glad to see that Senator Evans is here at the moment. I hope he will respond to these two questions that automatically flow from that incredible answer. The first question is this: does he not regard a job levy, or a levy, as a tax? It would appear from what he said today that he does not regard a levy as a tax.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The second question I put to him, and I hope he is listening and will respond, is this: even setting aside that aspect, is he or is he not saying that there will be no new additional taxes? That is a question that the Senate and the Australian people demand an urgent answer to.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="WW4" page="877" party="LP" speaker="Kemp Sen C.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="WW4">
          Senator KEMP
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (3.33 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I rise to support my colleague Senator Short on this issue. In the last election the fundamental debate was on the issue of taxes. It was very clear from all public polls and opinion polls taken since the election that taxes was regarded as the fundamental issue.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="UI4" speaker="Senator Robert Ray">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="UI4">
           Senator Robert Ray
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You all stood up and cheered Fightback.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="WW4">
          Senator KEMP
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The government policy on taxes was, as Mr Keating said, not to raise taxes, to keep taxes as they were. Senator Ray went around the electorate, as did Senator Evans who is in the chamber now, assuring people that there would be no tax rises under this government. So we went to the election and, as a result of the promise that was made by Mr Keating, the government managed to sneak into office. As soon as they got into office, Mr Keating and his colleagues set about breaking the fundamental promise they had made to the Australian people.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Today we had an astonishing performance from Senator Evans. We now know that Senator Evans is not talking about a tax increase but that he is calling the tax increase a levy. So when is a tax rise not a tax rise? Apparently when it is a levy. Later on in question time, as he stumbled around trying to explain to Senator Short why the government was not keeping its promises, Senator Evans said that it was not a tax rise but a financing mechanism.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         All I can say is: may we be saved from further levies and financing mechanisms, because the government's broken tax promises have already cost the Australian electorate an additional $3 billion in a full year. If Mr Keating had been honest with the Australian people and gone to the electorate and said, `We are going to raise taxes across a vast series of areas, including fuel taxes, fuel excises, sales taxes and so forth', does anyone believe that this government would have been elected to office? Of course it would not have been. The government deliberately denied that there would be any possibility of a tax rise. Indeed, as my colleague Senator Short pointed out, the government promised tax cuts.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I believe that Senator Short has drawn attention to a really fundamental issue—that this government lied its way into office and, within months of winning an election on the promise that there would be no tax increases, it increased taxes by some $3 billion. After that, in order to try to quieten public concern, Mr Willis made an announcement. Does Senator Evans remember all the newspaper headlines about no more tax rises? It took only a few months for that further promise to be broken. Senator Evans is quite right to feel embarrassed about this. I know he does not want to use the words `tax rise'; he would prefer to the use the word `levy'. But, at the end of the day, it is the Australian people who will pay and pay dearly.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I believe this government has broken its fundamental promise to the Australian people. I believe the Australian people understand that. That is why Mr Keating has no moral authority whatsoever in this country. Senator Evans gets up and tries to lecture people about standards and morals. We know that it is Senator Evans who, day after day, has to defend the big lie of Australian politics made before the 13 March election that the Labor Party would not increase taxes.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="BX5" page="878" party="LP" speaker="Gibson Sen B.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BX5">
          Senator GIBSON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (3.37 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I rise to support what my colleagues Senator Short and Senator Kemp have said in response to Senator Gareth Evans's answer to Senator Short's question asked earlier today. As my colleagues have said, potential tax increases are really a serious matter for the Australian community. The Australian community has been misled by the government. The really serious issue for the longer term future is that, whilst the Australian economy is now recovering, business investment has not recovered. It is business investment which sets the scene, not for tomorrow but for a few years time when we get into the next dip in the economy.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         As I have said in this chamber several times, it is a fact that investment in plant and equipment of less than six per cent of GDP is the lowest rate since World War II. Whilst the Treasury figures which came out this week show that the rate has risen marginally for the latest quarter, it is still nowhere near the amount that is required over the next several years to sustain this economy and provide jobs for our children and grandchildren. We have a long way to go.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         A jobs levy—a financing mechanism, as Senator Evans calls it—would really be another impediment to investors considering investing in Australia today. In this morning's
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Australian
         </emphasis>
         , the Managing Director of ICI Australia made the point that his industry is ready to spend billions of dollars in setting up and expanding chemical exports, provided that the impediments to those investments are considered by government and removed. One of the points he made was that the government ought to consider giving a five per cent tax rebate to make up for the indirect taxes which businesses pay in this economy. But this government increased indirect taxes in the last budget.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Whilst those opposite mouth all the rhetoric about being concerned about jobs and being concerned about the community, the actual fact is that they are doing exactly the reverse. This matter is very serious. My colleagues and I are against any increases in taxes. What the government should be looking at is reducing its expenditure rather than increasing taxes—regardless of whether it calls such an increase a financing mechanism or a jobs levy.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS" nameid="VD4" page="879" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Foreign Affairs)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (3.40 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not know whether it is ever worthwhile seeking to clarify these matters because members of the opposition never take any notice anyway. Let me just say that such confusion as beats in their breasts and their heads today is a product of not being able or not wanting to draw a distinction between three quite separate situations: firstly, whether a particular revenue measure is a tax at all; secondly, whether it is a new tax; and, thirdly, whether it involves an increase in tax. They are three quite separate questions, and if honourable senators can understand the difference between those three questions they can understand perfectly well what I, the Prime Minister, the Treasurer and everyone else has been saying over the years.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="BE4" speaker="Senator Newman">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="BE4">
           Senator Newman
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Thanks for the help, professor.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As I say, it is almost a complete waste of time drawing these distinctions, but let me begin at the beginning.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="6H4" speaker="Senator Harradine">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="6H4">
           Senator Harradine
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Ha, ha!
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I know that Senator Harradine is totally familiar with these issues. There is a threshold question, as a matter of constitutional law and as a matter of Senate practice, as to whether a particular revenue measure is properly describable as a tax or whether it is properly describable as a fee, a charge or a levy. When a revenue measure is selective in its application—not of general application to the community as a whole but with a particular target group—it is very often appropriate to describe it not as a tax at all but as a levy or in some other way, such as a fee or a charge.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         So I make no judgement as to whether a jobs levy, if it were to be introduced, would properly be described as a tax. That might be a matter for argument around the place but it is certainly not a matter for assumption on the part of the opposition. That is the first point I was seeking to make, and that is not a matter for jocularity, parody or anything else; it is just a matter for plain, straightforward understanding on the opposition's side, which is a little bit much to ask for, I know, but I do ask for it.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The second question is whether or not one is introducing a new tax and what we may have said on the subject of new taxes. I do not think the Prime Minister was ever explicit in ruling out new taxes as such—`no new taxes'. The Treasurer was on one occasion in August 1992, I think before the budget, when he said:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        We will not be introducing new taxes.
       </para>
       <para>
        What precisely the context of that particular remark was I am not sure—whether he was saying so in the context of that budget or purporting to offer a promise more generally; one would have to see the context of the remark.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Certainly my own remark on 5 October, which has been quoted today, that the government would not be going down the path of introducing new taxes was simply, again, descriptive of the situation as it stood after the last budget. I am not to be taken as having made any general promise or commitment in that respect.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="DJ4" speaker="Senator Short">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="DJ4">
           Senator Short
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —When do your statements have any commitment?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is just a matter of understanding what I am saying and not making up what I am saying and not injecting any more content into it than actually existed. That is what I want to say on the subject of new taxes.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Of course, in the context of the last election, before the last election there was one new tax that we were very specifically ruling out and we made that absolutely clear, and that was a GST. Senator Short must wish in retrospect that he had made a similar commitment. He might be doing a little bit better now than he was at the time or is now.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The third question—and it is a distinct one again—is not whether one is introducing a new tax but whether one is increasing an existing tax. On this there is a lot of argument backwards and forwards about what was said before the last election in that respect. The point to be made once again in this regard—and we made it on innumerable occasions—is that the Labor government did not rule out before the last election or at any time subsequently the possibility from time to time of there being revenue increases. What we did rule out was any increase in the overall burden of taxation. Right at the very beginning—in the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Lateline
         </emphasis>
         contribution of the Prime Minister on 19 November—the context of his response to Mr O'Brien on that occasion made that absolutely clear. He did say:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        . . . what I'm promising is not to put up tax.
       </para>
       <para>
        But that was immediately after a sentence in which he said that his object and the government's object was to maintain the tax to GDP ratio that we roughly have at the moment. He said that our object was:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        . . . to maintain the tax to GDP ratio we roughly have at the moment. In other words, what I'm promising is not to put up tax.
       </para>
       <para>
        Honourable senators opposite and I know that what he was saying was that there would be no increase in the overall burden—the tax to GDP proportion—and that is exactly what we are delivering on because the burden throughout the 1980s of tax to GDP was of the order of 23 or 24 per cent and in our particular projections—and all these figures have been on the public record before and debated in this place—we are anticipating no more than that, getting up to about 23 1/2 per cent by 1996-97.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         So there is a difference between new taxes and existing taxes and there is a difference between not increasing a tax and increasing an existing tax; and, understood in the way that I have stated, there is absolutely no inconsistency in anything the government has said, and certainly no deception of the Australian public.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Question resolved in the affirmative.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="880" type="Documents">
     <title>
      DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Order! Pursuant to the order of the Senate agreed to on 18 August 1993, I advise honourable senators that the Manager of Government Business in the Senate lodged government documents with the Clerk immediately after prayers today. A list of the documents is attached to today's red. As the Senate will be adjourning early today to enable estimates committees to meet, there will not be an opportunity to consider government documents that have been tabled. However, the documents will be listed on the
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Notice Paper
         </emphasis>
         and senators will have the opportunity to consider them during general business on Thursday, 3 March 1994.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <petition.grp page="880">
     <title>
      PETITIONS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10001" speaker="The Clerk">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10001">
          The Clerk
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Petitions have been lodged for presentation as follows:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <petition nameids="7U4" page="880" presenters="BELL">
      <title>
       Woodchip Licences
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The Petition of the undersigned shows:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Australia's old growth forest and wilderness areas are being diminished as a result of continued logging. The Federal Government has granted new woodchip export licenses despite its agreement for a moratorium on logging in high conservation areas.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Your Petitioners ask that the Senate should:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       apply conditions retrospectively to woodchip licences in order to meet Commonwealth obligations, and
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       exclude from licences, woodchip derived from old growth forests and wilderness areas.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="7U4">
         Senator Bell
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 19 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="7U4" page="880" presenters="BELL">
      <title>
       Jarosite Dumping
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        We the undersigned respectfully call upon the Federal Government to (a) reverse the decision to extend the time allowed Pasminco EZ to dump jarosite at sea, and (b) endorse and comply with the December 1995 deadline established by the London Dumping Convention.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="7U4">
         Senator Bell
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 24 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="7U4" page="880" presenters="BELL">
      <title>
       Chemical Registration
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        We the undersigned respectfully call upon the Federal Government to introduce legislation that will require the National Registration Authority to provide all available information on registered chemicals.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="7U4">
         Senator Bell
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 23 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="7U4" page="881" presenters="BELL">
      <title>
       Chemical Spraying
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        We the undersigned respectfully call upon the Federal Government to phase out aerial spraying in accordance with recommendation 39 of the report of the Senate Select Committee on Agricultural and Veterinary Chemicals in Australia.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="7U4">
         Senator Bell
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 22 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="EU4" page="881" presenters="O'CHEE">
      <title>
       National Flag
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The petition of the undersigned shows:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        We the undersigned citizens respectfully submit that Australia should retain the current National Flag which has flown over the country since Federation. This flag
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        symbolises the world's oldest democracy
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        represents our history, our culture and our language
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        enjoys the support of the vast majority of the Australian people
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        symbolises the sacrifice of our armed servicemen and women
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Your petitioners therefore request that:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Australia should retain the current national flag.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="EU4">
         Senator O'Chee
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 89 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="LI4" page="881" presenters="PATTERSON">
      <title>
       National Flag
      </title>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth that:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       1.The majority of Australians are completely satisfied with the existing Australian national flag and condemns the attack on the Australian flag by the Prime Minister Mr Keating while he was overseas.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       2.We therefore request that the Senate ensures that the Australian national flag, as provided in Section (3) of the Flags Act, is not changed or replaced without first being voted upon and approved by the people of Australia in a referendum.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="LI4">
         Senator Patterson
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 40 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <para>
      Petitions received.
     </para>
    </petition.grp>
    <debate page="881" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      NOTICES OF MOTION
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="881">
      <title>
       Breast Cancer
      </title>
      <speech electorate="ACT" nameid="VI4" page="881" party="LP" speaker="Reid Sen M.E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VI4">
          Senator REID
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Australian Capital Territory)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (a)notes that breast cancer remains the leading cause of death in women in Australia with 2 600 women dying from breast cancer each year;
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (b)deplores the fact that Australia spends a pitiful amount on research into the causes and treatment of breast cancer, about 20 cents per woman per year, compared to the United States of America which spends about $5 per woman per year;
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (c)condemns the Minister for Health (Senator Richardson) for inferring that it is `fashionable' and `sexy' to have breast cancer; and
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (d)calls on the Minister and the Government to prove that they are committed to research into the causes and treatment of breast cancer by substantially increasing research funding for breast cancer in the 1994-95 Budget.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="881">
      <title>
       Taxation
      </title>
      <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="O15" page="881" party="LP" speaker="Tierney Sen J.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="O15">
          Senator TIERNEY
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (New South Wales)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate—
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (a)condemns the national left wing of the Australian Labor Party for seeking to increase personal tax rates, increase the company tax rate and introduce a jobs levy, which is in fact a tax on jobs;
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (b)notes that this has split the Government, with the Minister for Finance (Mr Beazley) stating that it was not in the interests of the public or the economy to have further increases in taxation;
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (c)calls on the Labor Government to reaffirm it's commitment not to increase taxes; and
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (d)condemns the Prime Minister (Mr Keating) for failing on 21 February 1994 to rule out considering tax increases in the 1994-95 Budget.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="882">
      <title>
       Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade Committee
      </title>
      <speech electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="LH4" page="882" party="ALP" speaker="Jones Sen G.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LH4">
          Senator JONES
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Queensland)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the time for the presentation of the report of the Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade on sexual harassment in the Australian Defence Forces be extended to 9 June 1994.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="882" type="Personal Explanation">
     <title>
      PERSONAL EXPLANATIONS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="PJ4" page="882" party="LP" speaker="Teague Sen B.C.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="PJ4">
         Senator TEAGUE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I seek leave to make a personal explanation as I claim to have been misrepresented.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Leave granted.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="PJ4">
         Senator TEAGUE
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —In the
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Canberra Times
        </emphasis>
        of 17 February and also in the
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Courier-Mail
        </emphasis>
        of 19 February, articles appeared containing words suggesting that I had branded `deceitful and untrue' the RSL's submission to a current Senate inquiry.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        In fact, except for that sentence, the article in the
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Canberra Times
        </emphasis>
        is a very fair account. Similarly, in the
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Courier-Mail
        </emphasis>
        there were various assessments made by the writer. But it is not true that I had said that the actual submission of the RSL was deceitful or untrue. I said that it was a most surprising submission which included a number of most unfortunate Aunt Sallies and one area which, in my view, was plainly wrong, but the articles took my criticisms of the RSL's submission and put them in words which were not my own words. I mention this because it was brought to my attention this morning that there was this article in the
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Courier-Mail
        </emphasis>
        , much of which is built around my so depicting the RSL submission. For example, it states:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        To suggest that they, or the RSL's national president Major-General "Digger" James, could put their names to a document that is "deceitful and untrue" is simply ludicrous.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       I make the point again that I did not say that the submission was deceitful or untrue. To make it quite clear, the particular sentence in the RSL's submission that I took grave exception to and which I claim to be wrong states:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        To recruit or train a military force and then to recoil in horror when its members occasionally exhibit unseemly aggressiveness or even brutality towards one another is either deceitful or stupid and certainly unfair to the general membership of the armed forces.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para>
       I regard that statement as most unfortunate. No-one in the RSL has reiterated those words, I am grateful to say, but it could not stand without criticism. I believe it is quite wrong for the RSL, or anyone, to believe that the Australian Defence Force recruits only aggressive people, as though they are a small minority of the Australian public, and then to excuse sexual assault or other brutality between individual members and claim that this is the natural outcome of aggressive people having been recruited to the defence service. I hope that my personal clarification puts the real problem all the more in focus, and not some words which I did not use of the submission.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="882" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ORDER OF BUSINESS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Motion (by
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Reid
        </emphasis>
        , on behalf of
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Hill
        </emphasis>
        )—agreed to:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        That business of the Senate, Notice of Motion No. 1 standing in the name of the Leader of the Opposition be adjourned or postponed until 1 June 1994.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="882" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="882">
      <title>
       Public Interest Whistleblowing Committee
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="882">
       <title>
        Extension of Time
       </title>
       <proctext>
        <para first-indent="16">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          Motion (by
          <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          </emphasis>
          <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
           Senator Newman
          </emphasis>
          )—by leave—agreed to:
         </tab>
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          That the time for the presentation of the report of the Select Committee on Public Interest Whistleblowing be extended to 30 June 1994.
         </tab>
        </para>
       </proctext>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="882" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      HALL, MR KEN G.
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Motion (by
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Reid
        </emphasis>
        , on behalf of
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senator Patterson
        </emphasis>
        )—by leave—agreed to:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        That the Senate—
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (a)mourns the loss of the `grandfather' of the Australian film industry, producer Ken G Hall; and
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (b)recognises his achievements in founding the Australian film industry which included:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (i)creating the newsreel company, Cinesound,
        </tab>
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (ii)raising the profile of Australian film internationally with his academy award winning film
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Kokoda Front Line
         </emphasis>
         ,
        </tab>
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (iii)bringing characteristically Australian culture to the screen in works such as Dad and Dave, and
        </tab>
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         (iv)receiving the Order of Australia as well as an Order of the British Empire.
        </tab>
       </tab>
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="883" type="Committee">
     <title>
      COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="883">
      <title>
       Superannuation Committee
      </title>
      <debate.sub2 page="883">
       <title>
        Terms of Reference
       </title>
       <proctext>
        <para first-indent="16">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          Motion by (
          <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
           Senator Reid
          </emphasis>
          , on behalf of
          <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
           Senator Watson
          </emphasis>
          )—by leave—agreed to:
         </tab>
        </para>
        <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          That the resolution of the Senate of 19 May 1993, providing terms of reference of the Select Committee on Superannuation, be modified to omit paragraph 2 and substitute the following paragraph:
         </tab>
        </para>
        <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
         That the committee report to the Senate not later than the last sitting day of each June and December until the end of Parliament or until the committee presents its final report, whichever first occurs.
        </para>
       </proctext>
      </debate.sub2>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="883" type="Bill">
     <title>
      VETERANS' AFFAIRS LEGISLATION AMENDMENT BILL (No. 3) 1993
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="883">
      <title>
       Consideration of House of Representatives Message
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Message received from the House of Representatives intimating that it disagrees to the amendment made by the Senate.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Ordered that consideration of the message in committee of the whole be made an order of the day for the next day of sitting.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="883" type="Bill">
     <title>
      BILLS RETURNED FROM THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Message received from the House of Representatives intimating that it had agreed to the amendment made by the Senate to the Corporate Law Reform Bill 1993.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="883" type="Bill">
     <title>
      MINISTERS OF STATE AMENDMENT BILL 1994
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="883">
      <title>
       First Reading
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Bill received from the House of Representatives.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Motion (by
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          Senator Robert Ray
         </emphasis>
         ) agreed to:
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That this bill may proceed without formalities and be now read a first time.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Bill read a first time.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="883">
      <title>
       Second Reading
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE" nameid="UI4" page="883" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UI4">
          Senator ROBERT RAY
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Defence)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (3.55 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That this bill be now read a second time.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para>
        I seek leave to have the second reading speech incorporated in
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Hansard
        </emphasis>
        .
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Leave granted.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          The speech read as follows
         </emphasis>
         —
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Unless the parliament provides otherwise, section 66 of the constitution prescribes a maximum annual sum for the payment of salaries to ministers. Amendments to the Ministers of State Act 1952 which sets this sum are thus required from time to time to cover changes to ministerial salaries. The sum appropriated is to meet the expected cost of salaries and no more. While the act covers the total cost of salaries it does not set the amount of individual salaries to ministers.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The enactment of the Remuneration and Allowances Act 1990, has had, amongst other things, the effect of linking the basic salary levels for parliamentarians to the top of the senior executive service band one level in the Australian Public Service.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        There is also a similarly proportioned increase in the salaries of ministers of state. Following the enactment of the Remuneration and Allowances Act the government set in train arrangements to ensure that the relativities established between the salaries of parliamentarians at that time are maintained. That is, ministers' salaries are increased at the same rate and at the same time that salaries of senators and members of the parliament increase. Ministers receive the same increase in additional salaries as members of the parliament and are phased in the same way. Increases of the same order and timing for office-holders of the parliament, including the opposition leadership, derive from the Remuneration and Allowances Act and funds for those increases are appropriated by that act.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The amount proposed to be appropriated accords with increases awarded to members of the parliament arising from increases of 1.4 per cent and 1.5 per cent ratified by the Industrial Relations Commission for members of the senior executive service of the Australian public service effective from 10 March 1993 and 11 March 1994 respectively. The increased amount required in subsequent financial years accommodates the full year effect of the increase.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        I commend the bill to the Senate and present the explanatory memorandum to the bill.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Debate (on motion by
         <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
          Senator Reid
         </emphasis>
         ) adjourned.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="884" type="Adjournment">
     <title>
      ADJOURNMENT
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Before I put the question for the adjournment, I advise honourable senators that estimates committee arrangements for today are as follows: Estimates Committee A is to meet in the main committee room and will be televised on channel 21 and broadcast on FM band 92.7; Estimates Committee B is to meet in committee room 2S1 and will be televised on channel 22 and broadcast on FM band 90.3; Estimates Committee C is to meet in committee room 2S3 and will be televised on channel 23 and broadcast on FM band 91.1. I now put the question:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         That the Senate do now adjourn.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <debate.sub1 page="884">
      <title>
       Compulsory Voting
      </title>
      <speech electorate="SA" nameid="JX4" page="884" party="LP" speaker="Minchin Sen N.H.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="JX4">
          Senator MINCHIN
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (3.57 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —In question time today the Minister for Administrative Services (Senator McMullan) used a dorothy dixer from his former colleague in the west, Senator Chris Evans, to defend the ALP's position on compulsory voting. It is incredible how sensitive the ALP has become on this issue. This is the second time since July that the ALP has used the forum of the parliament to defend its position on compulsory voting. It would appear the ALP is well aware that it is starting to lose the argument on this very important issue.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Senator McMullan used the argument about how voluntary voting would disenfranchise the underprivileged, as though the opposition was suggesting that people should be denied the right to vote. He dismissed arguments about voluntary voting as first-year philosophy arguments.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The issue here is one of naked ALP self-interest about compulsory voting. The ALP has a vested interest in retaining compulsory voting because it believes it gets a very significant advantage from the system of forcing people to vote. It is terrified that its own core voters would not vote if they were not forced to the polls; that is what this issue is about.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Senator McMullan tries to dress it up with arguments about disenfranchising people, and saying that this is really not an issue that we should be addressing. This is really all about the fear that is struck into the heart of the ALP about the notion that people might have the right not to vote. It is very interesting that a former adviser to Mr McMullan, one Rod Cameron, hailed as the ALP's greatest asset through the 1980s as their researcher, is probably Australia's most passionate advocate of voluntary voting. He realises the stupidity of forcing people to vote who have absolutely no interest in election outcomes.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The irony on our side is that there are some Liberals who believe that the ALP would be the beneficiary of having voluntary voting. I have arguments with some on my side who say that the ALP would be better at getting out the vote. That only demonstrates that on our side it is a matter of principle. We genuinely believe that the right to vote must entail the right not to vote. The ALP does not have one shred of principle on which to stand on this issue. Its self-interest is utterly naked. Its attitude to underprivileged voters is utterly condescending and contemptuous. The tragedy is that the ALP thinks it has to force its own voters to the polls or it will lose elections.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The ALP never mentions in this debate the fact that the overwhelming number of democracies in the world do not force their voters to vote. We are the only English speaking democracy that does so. We are one of only five countries in the world that I can find that forces voters to vote.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Senator McMullan dismisses the right not to vote as a first-year philosophy argument. I remind him that in 1970 Holland changed from compulsory to voluntary voting for the very reason that for years some of the most eminent people in Holland had considered this issue. They reported to the Dutch parliament that, as a matter of high principle, the right to vote must entail a right not to vote. As a result Holland got rid of compulsory voting, leaving Australia now as one of the very few countries to retain this very undemocratic system.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The ALP also fails to mention that, in the overwhelming majority of countries that have voluntary voting, voter turnout is around 80 per cent—eight out of 10 voters choose to exercise their right to vote and turn out to vote. The United States of America is often cited by Labor activists as an example of what happens under voluntary voting. But it is the great exception to the rule: for a whole variety of reasons that are inherent to the US it has a low voter turnout. Voluntary voting in the United States tells us that there are real problems with the American political system, and that is why people are not turning out to vote. American political commentators know their system is sick because of that low turnout.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The ALP also fails to acknowledge that almost every analysis of the United Kingdom and United States experience with voluntary voting shows that, for every election studied since World War II, there would have been no change in election outcomes if the polls had been conducted by compulsory voting. It simply would not have changed the outcome of national elections held in those countries since the war. A further irony is that under voluntary voting in America the Democrats, the soul brothers of the Labor Party, have an iron grip on the house of representatives, and have had such a hold for 40 years. So voluntary voting is hardly disenfranchising the core vote of the Democrats in that country and what would be the core vote of the Labor Party in this country. It is tragic that the Labor Party has this perception that it would suffer from giving the people the right not to vote.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The problem in Australia is that, frankly, until now there has been a cosy conspiracy between the parties about compulsory voting. It has been easier for the major parties to have the law force people to exercise their franchise. In other words, the responsibility is taken away from the parties to persuade people of the virtues of exercising their right to vote. That means that we have an electoral system where the total focus is on a handful of swinging voters in a handful of swinging seats. Due to compulsory voting the great majority of voters in this country have almost nothing to do with the political process because they can safely be ignored by the major parties.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The major parties should have the responsibility of persuading voters of the virtues of voting, and if they do not then they will pay the price. It would rejuvenate the sick position of the voluntary organisations of our political parties in Australia—organisations that are in a poor state. This would give organisations a real purpose, a necessity to get out into otherwise safe seats and persuade voters of the need to vote. Compulsory voting is wrong in principle and wrong in practice. It is about time the ALP faced up to the need to give voters the right not to vote.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="885">
      <title>
       Population Growth and Development
      </title>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="885" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6H4">
          Senator HARRADINE
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (4.04 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Today I want to deal with the government's intended review of the link between population growth and development. Unfortunately, that has now become an expensive exercise with predictable conclusions if the expressed views of the participants are any guide. The Senate will recall that in this chamber, on 27 October 1993, the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Senator Gareth Evans, said:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        . . . we proposed that an appropriate development economist—someone with an international reputation who is fully independent and has no axe to grind on these matters in issue—be asked to spend a few months reviewing the available evidence as to the nature of the relationship between the variables I have mentioned and reporting to the government on that issue.
       </para>
       <para>
        That was after the budget included a proposal by the Minister for Development Cooperation and Pacific Island Affairs, Mr Bilney, for a threefold increase in funds for population programs and a fivefold increase over a period of four years. Incidentally, this money will be diverted from other development cooperation programs in an already very low overseas official development assistance budget.
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The government decided that a review and assessment be undertaken of the literature relating to population growth and development and that that be conducted by an internationally recognised development economist. Initially, I welcomed an objective analysis of the intellectual underpinning of government policy in this area. Actually, I had raised this matter and questioned AIDAB representatives on these issues over a period of time in estimates committees. The Senate will recall that on 7 October 1993, I told the Senate that, if the government were serious about its deficit reduction strategy, it was inappropriate for a minister to commit this sort of expenditure on controversial policies for more than a short period and certainly not for a four-year period, well beyond the term of this parliament.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Although it was claimed by some sections of the media that the person chosen for the review would have to meet my approval, this was never and is certainly not the case. The appropriate development economist whom Senator Evans envisaged would spend, in his words, `a few months reviewing the available evidence' has turned into nine people, each one to contribute a chapter in a book. Those nine people are all, except one, working in American institutions; and the exception is working in a UK institution. Surely to goodness there are world renowned development economists working in Australia. Yet none of these were appointed to conduct the review.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Neither the structure of the inquiry nor most of its participants meet the criteria proposed by the government itself, expressed by Senator Evans on 27 October. I invite honourable senators to read what he said and see whether the new structure and most of the participants meet that criteria. If there was to be a change of structure, if there was to be a review conducted by a number of people, why were not scholars with well-argued differing viewpoints invited to contribute? They have not been invited to contribute. Yet here we have $320,000 of aid money being spent by the government on this particular inquiry which does not meet the criteria nor the structure as originally announced by the government.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         In a letter that I received from Mr Bilney's office dated 15 February, my office was told that, `The government was careful to select in-dependent specialists who were internationally well-regarded to undertake the inquiry'. Yet the minister had told me a couple of weeks ago that he had not heard of most of the appointees. They were appointed by Professor Ahlburg, the principal reviewer. Therefore, the minister had not heard of them, let alone understood their expressed views.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Although the government stated that the consultant to be involved in the review was to have no axe to grind, the positions of most of the appointees require defence. Research carried out by my office shows that most of the appointees have a public position of support for population programs of the type proposed by AIDAB, for which there was a substantial increase in the recent budget, and for the next three successive budgets, and which expenditure should have been the subject of this review. Yet most of them are supporting those particular programs.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         I could give a number of examples but I know time is against us, so I seek leave of the Senate to have incorporated into
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Hansard
         </emphasis>
         further comments on this matter.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Leave granted.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          The document read as follows
         </emphasis>
         —
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         In addition, two of the appointees, Cynthia Lloyd and Mark Montgomery, are both currently involved in research work for the Population Council which is pro-population control. Professor Montgomery has endorsed concerted efforts towards family planning to lower urban growth rates in Sub-Saharan Africa. ("Accommodating urban growth in Sub-Saharan Africa"; Population growth and reproduction in Sub-Saharan Africa, ed by George T.F. Acasdi, Gwendolyn Johnson-Acsadi and Rodolfo A. Bulatao. Washington, D.C., World Bank 1990. 74-88. (World Bank Symposium).
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Dr. Cynthia Lloyd advocates cutting out child subsidies because they encourage people to have children. She writes: "any government of a developing country seeking to introduce programs designed to reduce population growth would do well to consider all available means of increasing the direct and/or indirect cost of children as currently perceived by couples in the reproductive age group". (An Economic Analysis of the impact of Government on Fertility: Some Examples from the Developed Countries in vol 22 of Public Policy (1974) pp489-512.)
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Professor Ian Diamond, appointed to contribute the chapter on family planning has stated that in Botswana "ideal family size remains high. . . . the mean ideal family size for all women was 4.7 children; for those in a union the ideal was 5.4. It should be an early goal of the population policy to reduce this figure if a sustained fertility decline is to occur. . . ." (Naomi Rutenberg and Ian Diamond Fertility in Botswana: The Recent Decline and Future Prospects Demography vol 30 No 2 May 1993 p 155).
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         "Not only does it seem somewhat out of place for an Englishman in this post-colonial era to be musing about an apparent need to persuade black Africans to stop breeding, but one wonders how these poor black people are to be reprogrammed," "What if they don't want to change? It is a short step from this sort of sentiment to coercive target driven population control programs and the abuses of human rights they necessarily entail."
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         One of the most serious flaws with the review is the failure to have a person of international stature examining the human rights implications of population programs. From a survey of written work, it seems Dr. Karen Oppenheim-Mason, who will be writing the "human rights" chapter of the review, has not had a prominent role in subjecting coercive population control programs to scrutiny. She is involved in a project relating to "Women and Development" funded by the Rockefeller Foundation—an institution with a long history of support for population programs.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The argument of the population controllers and their political supporters has been that rapid population growth is a crucial negative factor in the economic development of developing countries.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        For a number of years now, both inside and outside the Parliament, I have publicly challenged those assertions.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        When the 1993/94 budget was announced it contained a three-fold increase in finance for population programs for 93/94 over the previous year and a five-fold increase over four years. This is at a time when the ratio of Official Development Assistance to Gross National Product is, except for one year, at an all time low. This will result in the transfer of funds from poverty alleviation and development co-operation to international population bureaucracies and population control programs.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        This increased spending on population control was introduced at a time when the Government had embarked on a deficit reduction strategy which included increases in indirect taxes.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        On October 7, 1993, I told the Senate that if the Government were serious about a deficit reduction strategy it was inappropriate for a Minister to commit this sort of expenditure on controversial policies for more than a short period—and certainly not for a four year period, well beyond the term of this Parliament.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The suggestion to test the assumptions upon which the Minister proposed such an increase was made by the Government. The Government decided that a review be undertaken of the literature relating to population growth and development to be conducted by an internationally recognised development economist who did not have a public position to defend, or in the words of Foreign Minister Senator Evans, no axe to grind.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        I initially welcomed an objective analysis of the intellectual underpinning for policy in this area, having urged it at Senate Estimates Committee meetings.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Neither the structure of the "inquiry" as now constituted, nor most of its participants meet the criteria proposed by the Government itself and expressed to the Senate by Senator Evans on 27 October 1993, as follows :
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        ". . . we proposed that an appropriate development economist—someone with an international reputation who is fully independent and has no axe to grind on these matters in issue—be asked to spend a few months reviewing the available evidence as to the nature of the relationship between the variables I have mentioned and reporting to the government on that issue."
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The "appropriate development economist" whom Senator Evans envisaged would spend a few months reviewing the available evidence has turned into nine people—each one to contribute a chapter in a book. This was not the original intention as stated in the Senate on October 27. With the change in structure why were not scholars with well argued differing viewpoints invited to contribute?
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The Minister for Development and Pacific Island Affairs, the Hon Gordon Bilney, has appointed as team leader, Professor Dennis Ahlburg of the University of Minnesota, a long-time consultant with the World Bank who has expressed views in support of population programs of a type proposed for the Pacific by AIDAB.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Professor Ahlburg has contracted eight people to assist with the review, most of whom have publicly stated positions in support of population programs. Although the Government stated the consultant to be involved in the review was to have "no axe to grind" the positions of most of the appointees are ones which require defence.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        In a letter from Minister Bilney's office dated February 15, I was told that "the Government was careful to select independent specialists who are internationally well regarded to undertake the inquiry." Yet the Minister had already told me he had not heard of many of the appointees.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        My office is currently in the process of a search of the written views of the appointees. A large number of articles have been received and more are coming. It is also receiving information from international contacts as to the otherwise expressed views of the appointees.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Those whom Ahlburg has appointed to provide the chapters on housing and health have published positions which require defence. In that sense they have an axe to grind or an intellectual sand castle to defend, and should not have been appointed. The Minister was not aware of their published positions prior to their appointments;  I have had searches done and although the appointees were little known, what was known shows that they support population programs of the type proposed by AIDAB.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        There is no credible development economist who would now say that population growth is a necessary crucial negative factor in economic development. As to food, agricultural scientists and the World Bank point out that agriculture prices are at their lowest level in history and that world food production is rising faster than population. Hunger does exist among plenty; people are living in extreme poverty.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The argument that population has to be controlled to achieve economic development has always been dubious.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        There has been one basic theme to the argument:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        By reducing population growth countries can increase savings for investment and thus achieve a sustained take off to higher economic growth rates.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        This has led to corollaries such as
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Countries should not subsidise families through family allowance programs since these have the effect of increasing the rate of population growth;
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Countries should use so-called non-coercive incentives such as cash payments, priority for housing and schooling etc for parents with fewer children.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Taking the fundamental argument first, at its most simplistic it seems to assume that output is fixed and that by reducing the numbers of the population, we can produce a greater output per head.  This is obvious nonsense.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        First, it ignores the greater efficiencies in production which can arise through specialisation which becomes possible in serving larger markets. How often, for example, do we hear that the Australian market is too small for our companies and that they must expand overseas to keep up with best world practice?
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Second, even if it were true that simply cutting numbers increased output per head, who should the population planners cut? The young or the aged or the mentally and physically disabled?  From their pseudo-rational utilitarian viewpoint, the planners might find a greater so-called economic return by culling those who are longer productive rather than potential workers and taxpayers.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Sometimes the argument is a little more sophisticated. For example, Andrew Mason, one of the persons chosen for this review, has advanced the argument that a demographic transition from a high fertility high mortality population to a low mortality low fertility population creates an opportunity for economic growth. Because families pass through a phase where there are few elderly dependants and few child dependants and the past baby boom is of working age, a developing country may be able to increase its savings and investment. This is supposed to lead to a permanently increased rate of economic growth.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Thus in his co-authored study on
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Population Growth and Economic Development: Lessons from Selected Asian Countries
        </emphasis>
        at pp 54-55 the statements are made that "Efforts to reduce fertility have immediately reduced the number of child dependants without reducing the number of adults of working age. The result has been a rapid increase in per capita income for three reasons: (1) fewer children has meant fewer mouths to feed; (2) fewer children has enabled more women to enter the labour force; and (3) fewer children has led to lower aggregate consumption, higher saving, and additional investment in physical capital. . . . . As the [demographic] transition is completed, labour force growth slows and savings rates return to lower levels, the rate of economic growth should return to rates not substantially different from those observed prior to the transition . . . family planning efforts apparently have been successful in bringing down birth rates. This externally induced decline in fertility has had an important bearing on . . . the size and productivity of their labour force, the level of saving, and the growth of per capita and total product. Thus the evidence presented here indicates that the rapid pace of economic growth is, in part, a consequence of successful family planning efforts."
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        However, the sorts of economic models used by writers such as Andrew Mason suffer from the same problems as the sorts of models used by the Treasury and the Reserve Bank in giving Australia the greatest recession since World War II. These models do not project far enough into the future.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Just as there can be a favourable demographic pattern for a time, so it can change to an unfavourable one. Japan, Germany, most of Europe, the USA and Australia are experiencing the economic strains of ageing populations. With unfunded social security spending and a declining base of taxpaying younger workers, the treasuries of most advanced countries are facing a perpetual battle for solvency.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        As tax rates are increased to make up the revenue, fewer taxpayers can afford to raise children and more emigrate or simply evade taxes. History may not repeat itself, but depopulation seems to be creating a situation of flux in Europe not seen since the days of the later Roman Empire.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        In a very real sense, the measured economic growth from having fewer children and more investment is a statistical illusion. The concept of gross domestic product by definition excludes human capital. The birth of a pig is seen as a positive, the birth of a child is not. But if we consider human capital as a resource similar to physical capital the concept of GDP changes completely.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        For example economists have suggested that investment in human capital in the USA dwarfs investment in physical capital. If we are to believe most economic writers, human capital is crucial to economic growth and competitiveness. If it were not we would hardly be spending so much on education and training.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        But you cannot have investment in human capital without parents investing their time and energy in rearing children. When we take human capital into account we see that the so-called economic growth is a shift from investing in people to, at best, investing in  plant and equipment. But the apparent increase in physical capital may not even be enough. The growth in incomes per head may even be frittered away in higher consumption, as many of today's workers expect someone else's children to pay the taxes to support them in old age.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        If anyone doubts the primacy of human capital over physical capital in development, look at Japan and Germany from 1945 to 1960. The physical destruction of the greatest war in history was overcome well within a generation. As John Stuart Mill observed the knowledge and skills of the people of a country are more important than its stock of capital.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Another statistical illusion used in promoting the benefits of population control programs is the suggestion that GDP is increased by increased female labour force participation when they have fewer children.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The first error in this assertion is to ignore the disutility of labour—a woman may be happier not being in the paid labour force and enjoying her children. Second, the shift of work out of the home into the factory does not necessarily mean increased economic welfare. A poor woman in the developing world who works in a factory and pays for baby formula instead of breastfeeding is increasing GDP per head but her family's welfare may be reduced rather than increased.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The problem with Professor Mason and his colleagues is in the assumptions of their models. It is bad enough when economic modellers inflict recession on us: but playing with demography may be a terminal disease for nations.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        A corollary of the view that population growth needs to be reduced to improve economic growth is the suggestion, made by Dr. Cynthia Lloyd, another of the appointees (in her article
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         An Economic Analysis of the Impact of Government on Fertility: Some Examples from the Developed Countries
        </emphasis>
        in vol 22 of
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Public Policy
        </emphasis>
        (1974) pp 489-512) that "any government of a developing country seeking to introduce programs designed to reduce population growth would do well to consider all available means of increasing the direct and/or indirect cost of children as currently perceived by couples in the reproductive age group." (at p 507).
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Dr. Lloyd suggests that "in all developed countries of the world, costs of children would be even higher than they now are were it not for extensive subsidies to children in the form of family allowances . . . ."  She even describes tax allowances for dependants as child subsidies.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Unfortunately, the facts seem to have got overlooked. The Australian Bureau of Statistics in its fiscal incidence analysis has shown that most families pay their own way—by and large two parent couples with children receive no net subsidy from the Treasury. She is also wrong in describing child tax allowances as a subsidy—they are no more a subsidy than the tax free threshold.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        So talk of non-coercive inducements to parents by way of fiscal penalties or bribes is wide of the mark. It is coercive to tax people without regard to dependants and then offer them a so-called subsidy paid for out of their own money.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Sometimes advocacy of family planning occurs without any real analysis in support of the proposal. For example, Professor Mark Montgomery, another of the appointees, in a chapter on "Accommodating Urban Growth in Sub-Saharan Africa" in a World Bank Symposium on
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Population Growth and Reproduction in Sub-Saharan Africa
        </emphasis>
        urges the need for "concerted efforts toward family planning" to lower urban growth. Yet, unlike the rest of the chapter, which analyses economic arguments for correcting distortions in the financing of urban infrastructure and labour market imperfections, no real evidence or analysis is offered in support of the a priori policy conclusion in favour of birth control. He does not explain why or how couple's fertility decisions are distorted or why governments have superior knowledge to decide optimum fertility decisions for their peoples.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Sometimes those who advocate population control programs seem to think they know better than the people themselves about what they need. For example Professor Ian Diamond, the appointee to contribute the chapter on family planning, has stated that in Botswana "ideal family size remains high. . . . the mean ideal family size for all women was 4.7 children; for those in a union the ideal was 5.4. It should be an early goal of the population policy to reduce this figure if a sustained fertility decline is to occur. . . . " (Naomi Rutenberg and Ian Diamond
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         Fertility in Botswana: The Recent Decline and Future Prospects
        </emphasis>
        Demography vol 30 No 2 May 1993 p 155).
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Not only does it seem somewhat out of place for an Englishmen in this post-colonial era to be musing about an apparent need to persuade black Africans to stop breeding, but one wonders how these poor black people are to be reprogrammed. What if they don't want to change?  It is a short step from this sort of sentiment to coercive target driven population control programs and the abuses of human rights they necessarily entail.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        One of the most serious flaws with the review is the failure to have a person of international stature examining the human rights implications of population programs. From a survey of written work, it seems Karen Oppenheim-Mason, who will be contributing the "human rights" chapter for the review, has not had a prominent role in subjecting coercive population control programs to scrutiny. She is involved in a project relating to "Women and Development" funded by the Rockefeller Foundation—an institution with a long history of support for population programs.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The Australian Government acknowledges the rights of couples to choose freely the number of children they have. It has stated it will not support coercive programs.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        R.E Stenshold, Assistant Director General Appraisal, Evaluation and Sectoral Studies Branch, AIDAB has stated: "It is Australian policy that aid is directed only to international organisations that fully respect the rights and beliefs of the peoples they serve."
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Because the violation of human rights inherent in many population programs is a pressing issue requiring serious attention, a person of international repute should have been appointed.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The central point of this inquiry is supposed to be a review of relevant literature on the question of population and development.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Will this "review of the literature" include the work of women, particularly those in developing countries, who have condemned population programs as racist, eugenic, anti-women and anti-poor?
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Will  "Reproductive Rights and Wrongs: The global Politics of Population Control and Contraceptive Choice" by Betsy Hartmann be read and noted? Hartmann states in that book: "the complexities of the argument and the wide variation in opinion have largely been screened from public view."
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        I hope the "complexities of the argument" and the "wide variation in opinion" will not be screened by the academic appointees.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        And what about other literature documenting the violation of human rights inherent in target-driven population programs funded by the Australian taxpayer?
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        What of the book: "Imperialism and the Control of Women's Fertility: New hormonal contraceptives, Population control and the World Health Organisation" by the Amsterdam-based Indian women's health activist Sumati Nair.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        In it, Nair documents the development and trials of new long-acting provider controlled contraceptives and the Anti-HcG vaccine. Does the Senate know that International Planned Parenthood Federation and the World Health Organisation have approved and recommended Norplant for general "contraceptive" use in family planning programs while admitting that not enough is known about the long-term effects of this contraceptive?
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        She writes of "the misery and suffering" caused by contraceptive testing, and the inundation of unsafe hormonal contraceptives in a context of an inadequate health care system.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The book condemns the World Health Organisation's Special Program for Research Development and Research Training in Human Reproduction (HRP). She writes that WHO is merely promoting the interests of the population control lobby.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        And what about the written work against the anti-HCG vaccine—which works not by preventing conception, but by making a woman's immune system produce antibodies to attack the embryo. Will this critical material merit attention for the review panel? Will the panel note that this vaccine is currently being trialled on women in third world countries in the absence of informed consent? Who's helping fund the trials of this vaccine? Australia. And who helped develop it in the first place in collaboration with the WHO? Australia's very own professor Warren Jones. And why does Professor Jones think this vaccine is such a great achievement? I quote from an article in the West Australian May 31, 1990: "He said it would be vital in controlling the world's swelling population.." and in an AAP article: "On Current Statistics, overpopulation threatens to be the real misery of the world—it makes the AIDS problem look like a tea party."
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Perhaps Third World women's activists are right to feel that the new provider controlled contraceptives and abortifacients are not designed to empower them or raise their status, but to control them.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        There are other books I could mention. "Norplant: Under her Skin" produced by the Women and Pharmaceutical Project in the Netherlands documenting field studies by women's groups in Indonesia, Finland, Brazil, Thailand and Egypt; "A Question of Control" by Health Action International; and the many publications put out by the development policy organisation UBINIG in Bangladesh opposing population control programs.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Then there's the banned book which I have referred to in this chamber before. "The Right to Reproduce: A History of Coercive Sterilization" by Stephen Trombley. The review team should take a look at that one, but they'll be lucky to find a copy. It's no longer on sale thanks to threatened libel action the International Planned Parenthood. The IPPF didn't like references to funding by large US corporations, nor did it take kindly to a critical light being shed on it's anti-fertility activities in the Third World. So much for freedom of speech.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Then of course is the work of the China expert Dr. John S. Aird who has collected a remarkable amount of documentation from sources within China on the workings of the coercive one-child policy. Those of you who were concerned enough would have read the document John Aird produced for this chamber titled:"Foreign Assistance to Coercive Family Planning in China" which I tabled in May 1992.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        And if the team is at all concerned with upholding human rights, then it must read the latest book by Steven Mosher "A Mother's Ordeal." Anyone attempting to maintain the myth that China's population control program is not coercive; anyone who thinks that forced abortions up to the ninth month of pregnancy; forced sterilisations, fines, punishments, and discrimination against "illegal" children are not a daily fact of life for the people of China, needs to read this book.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        In appointing the nine academics to conduct the review, the Government seemed to forget this country's "Buy Australian" campaign. A total of $320,000 of Australian aid money is being spent on academics (sight unseen) in American universities and population centres. Not one cent is provided to development economists in Australian institutions.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Given the background and the expressed views of the participants, I hope I am not being unduly cynical in suspecting that the outcome of this review will be that there is no proof that population growth is a necessary crucial negative factor in economic development, population growth is substantially the cause of environmental degradation, ill health, low housing etc and therefore more money from international organisations and world governments should be provided to meet an unmet demand for contraception.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Will the so called "right to contraception" eclipse the basic human right to form and found a family and the rights of couples to determine family size without the interference of the State?
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Will it eclipse the right of women to exercise free and informed consent before having dangerous long-acting contraceptive and abortifacient drugs injected into them?
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Will the review team put forward real alternative policies to the mass dumping of contraceptives on the developing world?
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Will it tackle the real reasons for maternal mortality, such as respiratory diseases, parasitic infections, genital mutilation, shocking hospital conditions, anaemia, malnourishment and lack of vaccination, transport and diagnosis facilities for difficult births—often first births.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The Ehrlich theories have been proven wrong.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The world has not run out of food. The real cost of food has fallen and most countries are seeing a surplus of labour arising in agriculture. Indeed, as we know in Australia, commodity prices for agricultural produce have tended to be depressed by glut than driven up by scarcity.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Nor has the evidence shown that population growth is a crucial negative for economic development. On the contrary, there are plenty of examples of territories with both rapid population growth proceeding in tandem with rapid economic growth. For example, Hong Kong, has coped with a huge expansion of its population since World War II while raising living standards dramatically. Malaysia has experienced strong economic growth at the same time as its population is advancing. Few economists would now assert that rapid population growth as such is a negative for economic development.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The population controllers continue to pile up more reasons to justify their interventions. Not only is the fertility of poor women in poor countries now to blame for slow economic growth, it is also responsible for other problems, particularly environmental degradation, poor health and poor housing.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        If the fertility of poor women from poor countries continues to be blamed for these situations, target driven programs will continue to be funded.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        But here again they fail to look deeper at the root causes of these problems—economic mis-management by governments, war, corruption, the absence of a stable rule of law and political maladministration. Nor should we overlook the simple reality of greed and man's inhumanity to man. It is easier for governments, in particular, to blame their populations than to admit their failures, just as it easier for Australian governments to blame the world economy for our problems instead of looking to what they can and should be doing. But we should not be sidetracked by excuses. The present economic position of the Philippines owes more to the late President Marcos' administration than to its people.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The poet Milton saw reality more clearly when he wrote:
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        "Accuse not Nature, she hath done her part;
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        do thou but thine, and be not diffident
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Of wisdom, she deserts thee not, if thou
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
        Dismiss not her, when thou most needest her nigh"
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        When it comes, for example, to environmental degradation, rather than treating human beings as some sort of vermin not fit to roam the earth, we should look at the reasons behind pressure on resources. Often, it will be seen that bad land tenure and land taxation systems are a major cause of problems. When peasants from North East Brazil are driven off the large estates and denied land to live on, of course they will head towards the Amazon rain forest or into the favelas of Rio de Janeiro.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Similarly, with poor housing it will often be found that high land prices caused by tax-induced speculative pressures have meant people do not have enough to spend on the structures they wish to live in. In other cases, there is simply no security of tenure at all and people have no legal right to build anything.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        There is not space here to examine all the causes of every social or economic problem, but any careful observer, before blaming population growth as the cause of any problem, will undertake a real examination of more proximate and immediate causes of the particular problem being investigated.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Another new propaganda line says that there is an "unmet demand for contraception"; that access to these "modern" methods is a basic right; and that governments should contribute substantially to population control programs to meet this unmet demand.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Developing world women have a lot of other unmet needs but these have fallen by the wayside because of the overemphasis on contraception.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        Finally, a more cynical line is starting to emerge to justify population control programs. Perhaps the review team will also cite alleged "self interest" as a reason for funding population control. The U.S., which recently increased population control spending, admitted this as a reason for doing so.
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        J. Brian Atwood, director of the Agency for International Development, said population is directly linked to political stability. "There's a very serious problem that is on the horizon here with respect to food security. We are now seeing the levelling of food production in the world as the population increases. This is contributing to instability."
       </para>
       <para font-size="-=2">
        The review team has a serious task before it. I hope that my concerns will be allayed and its publication will examine the relative costs and benefits of population programs in achieving improvements in development indicators vis a vis alternative policies.
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6H4">
          Senator HARRADINE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not want it to be considered that the matters I have raised in the incorporated document are at all exhaustive. Nor do I want it regarded that the material that I have quoted from is material that I agree with, but I have raised certain issues there which I think are important. I thank the Senate for allowing the incorporation.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="892">
      <title>
       Compulsory Voting
      </title>
      <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="VW4" page="892" party="LP" speaker="Herron Sen J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VW4">
          Senator HERRON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Queensland)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (4.12 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Time ran out earlier this afternoon for motions to take note of answers to questions. I wish to speak on the compulsory voting issue. I support Senator Minchin's statement on the adjournment in relation to compulsory voting. I thought it would be useful for those who study this issue to have listed in
         <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
          Hansard
         </emphasis>
         the countries that do have compulsory voting. It is difficult to obtain that material, and I have had an interest in this for some years.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Australia is the only English-speaking nation in the world that has compulsory voting. There eight other countries that have compulsory voting. They are Argentina, Belgium, Brazil, Greece, Liechtenstein, Luxembourg, Zaire and Italy. But recently Italy had a referendum, and I understand that part of that referendum was the question of whether or not to go back to voluntary voting. But at present it still does have compulsory voting.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         As Senator Minchin noted, the Netherlands discontinued compulsory voting in 1971. It is interesting to go through the history of compulsory voting in this country. A private member's bill was introduced into the Australian parliament on 16 July 1924. It was supported by all parties at that time and passed on 31 July 1924. It has not been reviewed since.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         In finalising that list I should mention there are three separate areas which have partial compulsory voting. Austria has compulsory voting for its president in three of the states. In France the Senate has compulsory voting, as do some cantons of Switzerland. But they are the only countries in the world that have any interest in compulsory voting. Yet it is dredged up here in Australia as being some article of faith as part of democracy, when surely democracy and, in turn, liberty, should be extended to the freedom not to vote.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         There seems to be in the Labor Party some peculiar view that research has shown that it favours the non-socialist parties. Interestingly, analysis shows that it really does not matter much whether there is compulsory voting or non-compulsory voting. Purely on the aspect of freedom of choice, surely there is an argument to have the right not to vote. I welcome a debate on this, but neither time nor place is convenient at the moment. I look forward to such a development.
        </tab>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="893">
      <title>
       Ministerial Reply
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE" nameid="UI4" page="893" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UI4">
          Senator ROBERT RAY
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Defence)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (4.15 p.m.)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Minchin and Senator Herron are totally wrong. There is nothing in the Commonwealth Electoral Act that refers to compulsory voting. What it refers to is compulsory attendance at the polling booth. Neither they nor I will know whether anyone voted in an election, nor should we ever know. That choice is up to the elector. The elector may make the choice in the privacy of the polling booth whether to fill out the ballot paper.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         There is no law in this land that can compel anyone to vote. Those opposite are wrong. The matter was considered in discussions of the electoral committee when I was on it in the early days in 1983-84 when we considered a whole raft of electoral reforms. Let me note for the record that some interest by the coalition parties has been shown in electoral reform, because from 1949 to 1983 they did nothing in the electoral area other than to malapportion electorates.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Even when this was cleaned up in 1974-75, the National Party blackmailed the Liberal Party because that party did not agree to introduce the 5,000 square kilometre provision into the Electoral Act. Those opposite did nothing about closing hours or reforming postal votes. They did nothing about electoral funding or proper redistributions. They atrophied and did nothing about electoral reform for about 40 years. Now there is a sudden interest in this. I do not know whether it is in their self-interest or whether compulsory attendance at booths rather than compulsory voting should be done away with. But this great libertine thing they are pressing always has a great element of hypocrisy because their party would not extend the same right to electors, the right not to have a compulsion on them to extend their preferences.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         The coalition says it should not be compulsory to vote—there is a more technical way to put it—but if it is, it should be compulsory for preferences to be extended. The coalition has always opposed an optional preferential system. It will not give the voter the choice there. So the coalition wants to give the voters the choice as to whether they go to the polling booth, but once they are there the coalition wants to compel them. If it is so into freedom and so on, it should give voters the choice. If voters want to extend their preference right out through the candidates, the coalition should allow them to do so; but it does not.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         We have a relatively fair system of electoral laws in this country, but self-interest has always intervened on the way through. One of the classic cases is that of changing governments in New South Wales. Every time there was a Labor government we got rid of postal votes—because they did not help us. Every time the coalition won, that was the end of absentee voting; and so on. But we do have a relatively fair electoral system in this country, standing up and measured against any other electoral system in the world. It is all a matter of checks and balances, and some compromises. So there will never be the perfect system; there is no perfect system for any country.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         When coalition senators say they oppose compulsory voting, they are really saying they oppose compulsory attendance at a polling booth. We will never know whether a person voted, nor should we. I hope that if they are going to pursue this as an issue, intellectually they will try to grasp whether they should continue to advocate compulsion of extension of preferences, or whether they should extend that freedom as well.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Senator Harradine has raised an issue in the chamber today. I am sure my colleague, Gordon Bilney, will read Senator Harradine's speech with interest. I have followed the developments of these particular issues only on the fringes.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="6H4" speaker="Senator Harradine">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="6H4">
           Senator Harradine
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I thought you were going to talk about ticket voting.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UI4">
          Senator ROBERT RAY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I could talk all day on electoral matters, but no-one would be here to listen to me.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="VW4" speaker="Senator Herron">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="VW4">
           Senator Herron
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I would be interested.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UI4">
          Senator ROBERT RAY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Another time.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
         Question resolved in the affirmative.
        </tab>
       </para>
       <para first-indent="16">
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator West)
         </tab>
        </emphasis>
        —Before the Senate adjourns, I remind members of Estimates Committees A, B and C that the committees will start in approximately five minutes. Estimates Committee A will meet in the main committee room, Estimates Committee B in 2S1 and Estimates Committee C in 2S3.
       </para>
       <para justification="CENTERJUST">
        <emphasis font-weight="BOLD">
         Senate adjourned at 4.19 p.m.
        </emphasis>
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="894" type="Documents">
     <title>
      DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para first-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The following documents were tabled pursuant to sessional order agreed to on 18 August 1993:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       National Board of Employment, Education and Training—Report—Science and Technology Education:  Foundation for the Future—section 30 of the Employment, Education and Training Act 1988.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Tiwi Land Council—Annual Report 1992-93—section 37A of the Aboriginal Land Rights (Northern Territory) Act 1976.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Cotton Research and Development Corporation—Annual Report 1992-93—including the Auditor-General's report—section 28 of the Primary Industries and Energy Research and Development Act 1989. (Submitted to/received by previous Minister for Primary Industries and Energy, 20 December 1993/22 December 1993 and submitted to/received by Minister for Primary Industries and Energy, 27 January 1994/1 February 1994)
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Companies and Securities Advisory Committee—Annual Report 1992-93—including the Auditor-General's report—section 63M of the Audit Act 1901.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       (final manuscript, 10 December 1993/17 December 1993—printed copy, 21 January 1994/8 February 1994)
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commission—Annual Report 1992-93—including the Auditor-General's report—section 72 of the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commission Act 1989.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Central Land Council—Annual Report 1992-93—section 37A of the Aboriginal Land Rights (Northern Territory) Act 1976.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commercial Development Corporation—Annual Report 1992-93—including the Auditor-General's report—section 189 of the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commission Act 1989.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Aboriginals Benefit Trust Account—Annual Report 1992-93—including the Auditor-General's report—section 41D of the Audit Act 1901.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Family Law Council—Annual Report 1992-93—section 115 of the Family Law Act 1975.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2">
       (final manuscript, 16 December 1993/17 December 1993—printed copy, 27 January 1994/9 February 1993)
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       National Board of Employment, Education and Training—Australian Research Council Evaluation Program—Reviews of Grants Outcomes No.12—Molecular Biology 1987-1991—section 27 of the Employment, Education and Training Act 1988.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       National Training Board Ltd—Annual Report 1992-93—including the Auditor-General's report.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Advance to the Minister for Finance—December 1993.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Advance to the Minister for Finance—January 1994.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       Supporting Applications of Issues from the Advances to the Minister for Finance—December 1993 and January 1994.
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       National Board of Employment, Education and Training and its Australian Research Council—First Annual Report on The Collaborative Activities of the Institute of Advanced Studies, The Australian National University—section 30 of the Employment, Education and Training Act 1988.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
   </chamber.xscript>
   <answers.to.questions page="895">
    <title>
     ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS
    </title>
    <proctext>
     <para>
      The following answers to questions were circulated:
     </para>
    </proctext>
    <answer.to.qon page="895">
     <title>
      Repatriation Hospitals
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="772">
      (Question No. 772)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="QLD" nameid="YH4" page="895" party="LP" speaker="MacGibbon Sen D.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YH4">
         Senator MacGibbon
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Veterans' Affairs, upon notice, on 16 November 1993:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) What is the precise state of negotiations between the Commonwealth and the States in regard to the integration of the hospitals.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) What are the issues which are causing difficulties in each case.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) Who is conducting the negotiations in each case.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (4) What is the preferred timetable for resolving the situation in each case
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (5) What guarantees have been made, and what form have these guarantees taken, in regard to the treatment of veterans in Western Australia.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (6) What guarantees will be put in place to ensure that veterans are given priority in those states where privatisation occurs.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (7) In the case of each State, what consultations have taken place with the veteran community regarding the  future of the repatriation hospital in that State.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="QLD" nameid="5K4" page="895" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5K4">
         Senator Faulkner
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) Repatriation General Hospital (RGH) Hollywood has been sold to Ramsay Health Care Pty Ltd with settlement to be completed on 24 February 1994. MacLeod Repatriation Hospital was closed on 22 January 1993 and RH Kenmore is expected to be closed by 1 July 1994. The Queensland Government is expected to make a decision on whether the State will integrate RGH Greenslopes in February 1994. Negotiations in respect of RGH Daw Park and Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital are being undertaken at the Ministerial level. The Department of Veterans' Affairs and NSW Health officials are developing a position paper in respect of Lady Davidson Hospital Turramurra.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) The States need to be sure that the hospitals have a long term community role and financial and industrial matters need to be satisfactory for both the Commonwealth and the State.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) The Minister for Veterans' Affairs assisted by the Deputy President of the Repatriation Commission.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (4) February to March 1994.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (5) and (6) Entitled veterans and war widows will have the benefit of the Repatriation Private Patient Treatment Principles which will come into effect on 24 February 1994.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The Treatment Principles require the Repatriation Commission to provide timely treatment for veterans and war widows. In Western Australia veterans will be treated under contractual arrangements agreed with Ramsay Health Care Pty Ltd and as Repatriation private patients within the WA hospital system.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (7) A National Monitoring Committee was created and a Monitoring Committee in each of the States has been established as follows:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        NSW Treatment Monitoring Committee—5 November 1991
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Victorian Treatment Monitoring Committee—18 November 1992
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Queensland Treatment Monitoring Committee—12 October 1993
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        South Australian Treatment Monitoring Committee—29 June 1992
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Western Australian Treatment Monitoring Committee—12 November 1993
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Northern Territory Treatment Monitoring Committee—20 February 1992
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        ACT Treatment Monitoring Committee—29 April 1991
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Tasmanian Treatment Monitoring Committee—1 November 1991
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Prior to the establishment of these Committees, there has been extensive consultation with ex-service organisations in each State.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="895">
     <title>
      Veterans: Treatment Cards
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="839">
      (Question No. 839)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="QLD" nameid="YH4" page="895" party="LP" speaker="MacGibbon Sen D.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YH4">
         Senator MacGibbon
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Veterans' Affairs, upon notice, on 6 December 1993:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        With reference to the following treatment cards: Specific Treatment Entitlement Card, Service Pensioner Benefits Card, Dependant Treatment Entitlement Card, and Personal Treatment Entitlement Card :
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para font-size="-=2" left-indent="16">
       (1) How many veterans receive treatment under each card type.
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) What is the annual cost per veteran for treatment received under each card type.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) What is the annual cost of providing treatment to all holders of each card type.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (4) How many World War II veterans are in receipt of the Personal Treatment Entitlement Card.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="QLD" nameid="5K4" page="895" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5K4">
         Senator Faulkner
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) The estimated numbers of veterans and war widows receiving treatment under each card type for December 1993 are:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Specific Treatment Entitlement Card—82,150
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Service Pensioner Benefits Card—60,900
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Dependant Treatment Entitlement Card—83,450
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Personal Treatment Entitlement Card—115,150
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) The average annual costs of treatment for each card type during 1993-94 are estimated to be:
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Specific Treatment Entitlement Card—$734
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Service Pensioner Benefits Card—$3,127
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Dependant Treatment Entitlement Card—$3,701
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Personal Treatment Entitlement Card—$6,179
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) The costs of providing treatment to holders of each card type during 1993-94 are estimated to be ($ million):
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Specific Treatment Entitlement Card—$60.3 m
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Service Pensioner Benefits Card—$190.5 m
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Dependant Treatment Entitlement Card—$308.9 m
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        Personal Treatment Entitlement Card—$711.4 m
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (4) As at September 1993 the number of World War II veterans holding a Personal Treatment Entitlement Card was approximately 105 800.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The costs in (2) and (3) above have been based on 1993-94 budget estimates for medical services, pharmaceutical services, travel for medical treatment, and the treatment of veterans and war widows in departmental and non-departmental institutions.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="896">
     <title>
      Forests
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="967">
      (Question No. 967)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="SA" nameid="TF4" page="896" party="AD" speaker="Coulter Sen J.R.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="TF4">
         Senator Coulter
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories, upon notice, on 12 January 1994:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) To what extent has the Minister considered the report entitled
        <emphasis font-slant="ITAL">
         A study of the old-growth forests of East Gippsland
        </emphasis>
        (Draft, July 1993, Woodgate, Peel, Ritman, et al, DCNR Victoria) in allowing, refusing, or attaching conditions to export woodchip licences.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) Does the Minister accept the above report as satisfying the spirit of the National Forest Policy; if not, why not.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) In particular, does the above report satisfy the second criterion of the precautionary principle, as set out on page 49 of the National Forest Policy.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (4) Has the Minister written to the Victorian Government concerning the East Gippsland forests and, in particular concerning the above report and/or the East Gippsland Forest Management Plan (DCNR).
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (5) Will the Minister release with the answers to these questions any letters referred to in (4); if not, why not.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (6) Are there any agreed criteria between the Commonwealth and the States as to whether fauna are an integral component of any old-growth forest.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="SA" nameid="4E4" page="896" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4E4">
         Senator Richardson
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Minister representing the Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) Responsibility for the renewal of woodchip export licences and the attachment of conditions to them, lies with the Minister for Resources, the Hon David Beddall MP. As Minister for the Environment, I have only an advisory role in determining the conditions attached to woodchip export licences. The advice I provided to the Minister for Resources, prior to his decision to issue export licences, reaffirmed the need for Commonwealth decision-making to adequately incorporate its legislative and policy obligations concerning the environment.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        The Australian Heritage Commission (AHC) is currently in the process of identifying National Estate areas in the East Gippsland region through a joint project with the Department of Conservation and Natural Resources (DCNR). Data developed in the study of old-growth forests of Gippsland have been used in this process to assist in identifying National Estate places. Advice regarding this region was provided to the Minister for Resources by the AHC for his consideration in determining licence renewals and conditions.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) The Government is still awaiting the release of the final report of the East Gippsland old-growth study to evaluate. However, the study is expected to satisfy that part of the National Forest Policy Statement (NFPS) which calls for assessment of forests for old-growth values. As the first study of its kind, the Government expects that methodologies developed in this study will be of value in undertaking future old-growth assessments elsewhere.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) The methodology of the old-growth study is based on a series of assumptions with regard to data. These assumptions are based on expert scientific opinions and include a level of precaution. It should be remembered that the report from the study identifies old-growth forest in the region. It is not a management prescription and does not discuss management options to which the precautionary principle could be applied. These issues will be more appropriately addressed in the Forest Management Plan currently being developed by DCNR.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (4) I have written to the Victorian Government regarding forest and conservation matters, however there has been no correspondence specifically concerning the East Gippsland old-growth forest study or the yet-to-be-developed East Gippsland Forest Management Plan.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (5) There are no letters.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (6) The definition of old-growth forest agreed to by governments in the NFPS focuses on forest in which the upper stratum or overstorey is in the late mature to overmature growth phases. Old-growth itself is a structural condition of flora and the agreed definition of old-growth forest necessarily focuses on the floral components of the ecosystem. The importance of old-growth forest to the protection of many species of fauna is well understood.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="897">
     <title>
      Forests
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="991">
      (Question No. 991)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="WA" nameid="SN5" page="897" party="GWA" speaker="Chamarette Sen C.M.A.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="SN5">
         Senator Chamarette
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Minister for the Environment,
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Sport and Territories, upon notice, on 24 January 1994:
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) Does the National Forest Policy Statement moratorium clause protect forests of high conservation value other than old growth and wilderness forests.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) How much forest, other than old growth and wilderness, is of high conservation value.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) What types of forest, other than old growth and wilderness, have high conservation value.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="WA" nameid="4E4" page="897" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4E4">
         Senator Richardson
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Minister for the Environment, Sport and Territories has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (1) No. The NFPS clause in question only applies to activities that may significantly affect those areas of old growth forest or wilderness that are likely to have high conservation value.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (2) Signatory governments to the NFPS have agreed to review the appropriateness of the existing reserve system. As part of this review, all forest communities will be assessed against reserve selection criteria and areas of high conservation value identified for protection. Only when the results of the review are at hand will it be possible to say how much forest, other than old growth and wilderness, is of high conservation value.
       </tab>
      </para>
      <para first-indent="16" font-size="-=2">
       <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
        (3) The review referred to above will identify the types of forest, other than old growth and wilderness, that are of high conservation value.
       </tab>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
   </answers.to.questions>
  </hansard>
 </body>
</html>
