<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" "hansard.dtd">
<html>
 <body>
  <hansard chamber="Senate" date="14/09/1987" page="1" parliament.no="35" period.no="1" proof="No" session.no="1">
   <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
     <day.start date="14/09/1987">
      Monday, 14 September 1987
     </day.start>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA
      </para>
      <para>
       PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATE
      </para>
      <para>
       Hansard
      </para>
      <para>
       1987
      </para>
      <para>
       FIRST SESSION OF THE THIRTY-FIFTH PARLIAMENT
      </para>
      <para>
       (FIRST PERIOD)
      </para>
      <para>
       The Thirty-fourth Parliament was, by proclamation, dissolved on 5 June 1987. The Thirty-fifth Parliament was convened for the dispatch of business on 14 September 1987, and the First Session commenced on that day.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </business.start>
    <debate page="1" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      PROCLAMATION
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       The Senate met at 11 a.m., pursuant to the proclamation of His Excellency the Governor-General.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Clerk read the proclamation.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="1" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      OPENING OF THE PARLIAMENT
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The Deputy appointed by His Excellency the Governor-General for the opening of the Parliament, the Rt Hon. Sir Anthony Frank Mason, KBE, Chief Justice of Australia, and the Second Deputy, the Hon. Sir Ronald Darling Wilson, KBE, CMG, a Justice of the High Court of Australia, having been announced by the Usher of the Black Rod, entered the Chamber and took their seats on the dais.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Deputy directed the Usher to desire the attendance of the members of the House of Representatives.
      </para>
      <para>
       Members of the House of Representatives attending accordingly-
      </para>
      <para>
       The Deputy said:
      </para>
      <para>
       Members of the Senate and members of the House of Representatives:
      </para>
      <para>
       His Excellency the Governor-General, not thinking fit to be present in person at this time, has been pleased to appoint me his Deputy to declare open the Parliament of the Commonwealth, as will more fully appear from the instrument which will now be read by the Clerk of the Senate.
      </para>
      <para>
       The instrument having been read by the Clerk-
      </para>
      <para>
       The Deputy said:
      </para>
      <para>
       Members of the Senate and members of the House of Representatives:
      </para>
      <para>
       I have it in command from His Excellency the Governor-General to let you know that, after members of the Senate and members of the House of Representatives shall have been sworn, the causes of His Excellency calling this Parliament together will be declared by him in person at this place; and, it being necessary that a President of the Senate and a Speaker of the House of Representatives shall be first chosen, you, members of the Senate, will proceed to choose some proper person to be your President, and you, members of the House of Representatives, will retire to the place where you are to sit, and there proceed to the choice of some proper person to be your Speaker; and later this day you will respectively present the persons whom you shall so choose to His Excellency at such time and place as he shall appoint.
      </para>
      <para>
       Justice Wilson will attend in the House of Representatives for the purpose of administering the oath or affirmation of allegiance to honourable members of that House.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Second Deputy and members of the House of Representatives having retired-
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      SWEARING-IN OF SENATORS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The Deputy produced a commission authorising him to administer the oath or affirmation of allegiance and directed the Clerk to read the same.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Clerk read the commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Clerk produced and laid on the table the certificates of election of senators elected on 11 July 1987 to serve in the Senate from 1 July 1987 as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       NEW SOUTH WALES
      </para>
      <para>
       Kerry Walter Sibraa
      </para>
      <para>
       Michael Ehrenfried Baume
      </para>
      <para>
       Paul Alexander McLean
      </para>
      <para>
       Arthur Thomas Gietzelt
      </para>
      <para>
       Peter Erne Baume
      </para>
      <para>
       Graham Frederick Richardson
      </para>
      <para>
       David Gordon Cadell Brownhill
      </para>
      <para>
       Bruce Kenneth Childs
      </para>
      <para>
       Christopher John Guelph Puplick
      </para>
      <para>
       John Joseph Morris
      </para>
      <para>
       Bronwyn Kathleen Bishop
      </para>
      <para>
       William Robert Wood
      </para>
      <para>
       QUEENSLAND
      </para>
      <para>
       Margaret Reynolds
      </para>
      <para>
       Florence Isabel Bjelke-Petersen
      </para>
      <para>
       David John MacGibbon
      </para>
      <para>
       Malcolm Arthur Colston
      </para>
      <para>
       John Owen Stone
      </para>
      <para>
       Warwick Raymond Parer
      </para>
      <para>
       Gerry Norman Jones
      </para>
      <para>
       Ronald Leslie Doyle Boswell
      </para>
      <para>
       John Rees Black
      </para>
      <para>
       Bryant Robert Burns
      </para>
      <para>
       Michael John Macklin
      </para>
      <para>
       Glenister Sheil
      </para>
      <para>
       SOUTH AUSTRALIA
      </para>
      <para>
       Dominic John Foreman
      </para>
      <para>
       Anthony John Messner
      </para>
      <para>
       Janine Haines
      </para>
      <para>
       Nick Bolkus
      </para>
      <para>
       Amanda Eloise Vanstone
      </para>
      <para>
       Graham Ross Maguire
      </para>
      <para>
       Robert Murray Hill
      </para>
      <para>
       Rosemary Anne Crowley
      </para>
      <para>
       Hedley Grant Pearson Chapman
      </para>
      <para>
       Christopher Cleland Schacht
      </para>
      <para>
       Baden Chapman Teague
      </para>
      <para>
       John Richard Coulter
      </para>
      <para>
       TASMANIA
      </para>
      <para>
       Michael Carter Tate
      </para>
      <para>
       Brian Roper Archer
      </para>
      <para>
       Brian Harradine
      </para>
      <para>
       John Coates
      </para>
      <para>
       Mary Shirley Walters
      </para>
      <para>
       Terrence Gordon Aulich
      </para>
      <para>
       John Odin Wentworth Watson
      </para>
      <para>
       Arthur Ray Devlin
      </para>
      <para>
       Jocelyn Margaret Newman
      </para>
      <para>
       John Robert Devereux
      </para>
      <para>
       Paul Henry Calvert
      </para>
      <para>
       Norman Karl Sanders
      </para>
      <para>
       VICTORIA
      </para>
      <para>
       John Norman Button
      </para>
      <para>
       Austin William Russell Lewis
      </para>
      <para>
       Janet Frances Powell
      </para>
      <para>
       Gareth John Evans
      </para>
      <para>
       James Robert Short
      </para>
      <para>
       Alice Olive Zakharov
      </para>
      <para>
       Richard Kenneth Robert Alston
      </para>
      <para>
       Robert Francis Ray
      </para>
      <para>
       David John Hamer
      </para>
      <para>
       Bernard Cornelius Cooney
      </para>
      <para>
       Julian John McGauran
      </para>
      <para>
       Kay Christine Lesley Patterson
      </para>
      <para>
       WESTERN AUSTRALIA
      </para>
      <para>
       Peter Alexander Walsh
      </para>
      <para>
       Frederick Michael Chaney
      </para>
      <para>
       Patricia Jessie Giles
      </para>
      <para>
       Peter Drew Durack
      </para>
      <para>
       Peter Francis Salmon Cook
      </para>
      <para>
       Susan Christine Knowles
      </para>
      <para>
       James Philip McKiernan
      </para>
      <para>
       Noel Ashley Crichton-Browne
      </para>
      <para>
       Michael Eamon Beahan
      </para>
      <para>
       John Horace Panizza
      </para>
      <para>
       Jean Alice Jenkins
      </para>
      <para>
       Josephine Vallentine
      </para>
      <para>
       AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL TERRITORY
      </para>
      <para>
       Susan Maree Ryan
      </para>
      <para>
       Margaret Elizabeth Reid
      </para>
      <para>
       NORTHERN TERRITORY
      </para>
      <para>
       Robert Lindsay Collins
      </para>
      <para>
       Grant Ernest John Tambling
      </para>
      <para>
       The abovenamed senators, with the exception of Senators Peter Baume, Sanders and Zakharov, made and subscribed the oath or affirmation of allegiance.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Deputy having retired-
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="3" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ELECTION OF PRESIDENT
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="3" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr Clerk, I remind the Senate that the time has come when it is necessary for the Senate to choose one of its members to be President. I propose to the Senate for its President, Senator Sibraa. I move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That Senator Sibraa do take the chair of the Senate as President.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="VD4" speaker="Senator Gareth Evans">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator Gareth Evans
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have pleasure in seconding the nomination.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="EF4" page="3" party="LP" speaker="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="EF4">
         Senator CHANEY
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr Cumming Thom, I would like to indicate that the Opposition will not propose any Opposition senator for the position of President of the Senate. I take this opportunity to indicate that this afternoon we will be proposing Senator Hamer as the Deputy President and Chairman of Committees. There will be no Opposition nominee for the position of President.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The Clerk-There being no further proposals, Senator Sibraa is elected President of the Senate in accordance with the Standing Orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Sibraa having been conducted to the dais-
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
         <name nameid="EJ4">
          (Senator the Hon. Kerry Sibraa)
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Thank you, honourable senators. I was just told by my Leader and Deputy Leader that I should appear reluctant. If I had known when I stood in this place following my election as President on 17 February that I would soon have to go through the whole process of pre-selection, an election and party selection for this position again, I really doubt whether I would have been a candidate. I am, however, pleased that you have re-elected me. I am aware of the responsibilities involved and I look forward to working with you in a way which will reflect credit on the Senate, the Parliament and Australia. Again, thank you very much.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="3" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, it is my great pleasure to congratulate you on behalf of Government senators and, I think I can probably say, on behalf of all senators, because during your previous period of service as President of the Senate I think you discharged your duties with great impartiality and fairness. This was very much appreciated in the time leading up to the election that we have just been through. I am confident that you will carry on your duties in the same spirit. On behalf of Government senators in particular, I congratulate you and wish you well in your new period of office.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="EF4" page="3" party="LP" speaker="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="EF4">
         Senator CHANEY
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, on behalf of Opposition senators I congratulate you on your election to the presidency. It does not seem very long since you were first elected to that post. I recall that at that time we expressed our hopes of you as President and what we expected of you. I recall that before the election we expressed some satisfaction at the fairness which you had brought to the task of the President and the impartiality which you had shown. We look forward to seeing those same qualities in the presidency that you have now been awarded by the unanimous vote of the Senate. Mr President, we wish you well. As I say, we look to you to be the President of all the Senate-the property of all senators but, indeed, the property of none of us.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="1H4" page="3" party="AD" speaker="Haines Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="1H4">
         Senator HAINES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, on behalf of the Australian Democrats I offer our congratulations on your re-election as President and endorse the comments that were made by Senator Button and Senator Chaney. I say to the new senators who have been sworn in this day that they too will come to realise, as we have, that you are indeed impartial and an excellent President.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="LJ4" page="3" party="NP" speaker="Stone Sen J.O.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LJ4">
         Senator STONE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the National Party of Australia)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, on behalf of National Party of Australia senators, I have very great pleasure in congratulating you on your re-election as President of the Senate. I have, of course, known you for a very slight time indeed. However, everything that I am told and what I have so far seen assures me that in terms of fairness you will indeed be a President of the Senate in whom we will all have the most utmost confidence.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="4" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, I rise to congratulate you on your election to the high office of President of the Senate. The period for which you have been elected is going to be a very important time for this Senate not only because we will be changing venue but also because of the constant threat to the role of the Senate by executive governments of any persuasion. I was very pleased to see that before the dissolution of the Parliament you took heed of the expressions of concern on all sides of the Senate that the President and, indeed, the Standing Committee on Appropriations and Staffing should have final say about the administration of this particular chamber. I congratulate you and wish you every success. You will have my support.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="IG4" page="4" party="IND" speaker="Vallentine Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator VALLENTINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, as the independent peace Senator from Western Australia, I wish to add my congratulations to you on your re-election to the position of President of the Senate. I am sure that you will continue in the good way in which you began in the position in February this year. Also I hope that you will not be in that position for such a short time and that we will run the full term of office-in other words, that we do not have an election that will send us back to the polls earlier than we should go. I wish you all the best for the next term, Mr President.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="8V7" page="4" party="IND" speaker="Wood Sen W.R.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="8V7">
         Senator WOOD
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —As the Nuclear Disarmament Party senator for New South Wales, I wish to offer my congratulations. I appreciated your help, Mr President, during the orientation time for new senators and I am sure that you will serve in your position with great distinction.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am grateful to those honourable senators who have spoken-Senators Button, Chaney, Haines, Stone, Harradine, Vallentine and Wood-and for the complimentary remarks that they have made on this occasion. In reflecting on those remarks I am conscious of the responsibilities of the office of President, both in this chamber and in the wider context in which a Presiding Officer is required to carry out these responsibilities. Honourable senators can be assured that I will continue to preside over the proceedings of the Senate in the most impartial way I can. After occupying this chair for one session, I appreciate more than ever the standards of fairness which were set by my predecessors. I shall strive to maintain these high standards, which I trust will assist the Senate in its deliberation of matters important to all Australians.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        On what is almost certainly an historic occasion-the last time on which the opening of the Parliament of Australia will take place in the provisional Parliament House-I am very much aware of challenges facing the Parliament in the next 12 to 18 months. While I must accept responsibility for the Senate facing up to these challenges, I can only do that in the knowledge that I have the support of honourable senators. I refer particularly to the opening of the new Parliament House, the holding of the thirty-fourth Commonwealth Parliamentary Association conference here in Canberra and the reform of the administration of the Parliament. Honourable senators do not need me to remind them of the individual and collective implications of the move to the new building. However, we should all now be turning our minds to these matters. Some may be beyond our control-for example, the congregation of all Ministers in an executive area-but most-for example, working arrangements for senators and the appropriateness of the Standing Orders to the new building-are within the responsibility of this Senate and now is the appropriate time to start our consideration of them.
       </para>
       <para>
        I have recently returned from the thirty-third Commonwealth Parliamentary Association conference in Kuala Lumpur where, apart from the fact that I was elected President of the Commonwealth Parliamentary Association, I observed the very great opportunities which exist for the host Parliament in having 350 fellow Commonwealth parliamentarians gathered together. The organisational aspects of such a conference are significant but it is a challenge to which I am certain the Commonwealth Parliament will rise; and I am certain that the conference to be held here in September next year will be a highlight of our bicentennial year.
       </para>
       <para>
        The third area of concern to me is the administration of the Parliament. Honourable senators will recall that I wrote to all senators in May this year outlining certain intentions to change the administrative support to the Parliament. It is my intention to pursue these proposals during my term of office. There are many factors which I believe make it imperative that there be changes to the administration of the Parliament. These include the greatly increased scale of operation associated with the new Parliament House, developments in computer-based technology and the heightened awareness of the need for efficiency in using personnel and financial resources in both public and private organisations. It is my hope to put in place an administrative framework which addresses those needs and is capable of responding to any demands placed upon it in the foreseeable future.
       </para>
       <para>
        At the same time I wish to reassure honourable senators that as President I will not be party to any change which can be seen to challenge the constitutional role and independence of the Senate. I will not condone any proposal which would denigrate the role of any senators, either individually or collectively, or would threaten the high level of services provided to all senators. It is my intention to consult fully with honourable senators on the details of any proposals for administrative reform. The normal process of deliberation will not be circumvented, the Appropriations and Staffing Committee will be involved in this consideration and the proposals will be appropriately debated on the floor of this chamber. As I have made clear throughout my time as President, my door is always open and I would welcome the opportunity to discuss any of these matters with honourable senators.
       </para>
       <para>
        In conclusion, I again thank all senators for placing their trust in me. As I said in the Senate on 17 February this year on a similar occasion, I realise that my task is a difficult and responsible one. However, I will tackle it with enthusiasm and in a way in which I trust honourable senators will approve.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="5" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      PRESENTATION TO GOVERNOR-GENERAL
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="5" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I wish to inform honourable senators that His Excellency the Governor-General will be pleased to receive Mr President and such honourable senators as may desire to accompany him in the Library at 2.25 p.m. this day.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Honourable senators, prior to my presentation to His Excellency the Governor-General this afternoon the bells will be rung at 2.22 p.m. for three minutes so that honourable senators may attend in the chamber and accompany me to the Library.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Sitting suspended from 12.05 to 2.25 p.m.
       </para>
      </interject>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I invite honourable senators to accompany me to the Library where I shall present myself to His Excellency the Governor-General as the choice of the Senate to be its President.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The members of the Senate proceeded to the Library, and being reassembled-
       </para>
      </interject>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have to report that, accompanied by honourable senators, I presented myself to His Excellency the Governor-General as the choice of the Senate, and His Excellency was pleased to congratulate me upon my election.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="5" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      GOVERNOR-GENERAL'S SPEECH
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       His Excellency the Governor-General entered the chamber and, being seated, with the President on his right hand, commanded that a message be sent to the House of Representatives intimating that he desired the attendance of honourable members in the Senate chamber forthwith.
      </para>
      <para>
       Honourable members having come with their Speaker, His Excellency was pleased to deliver the following speech:
      </para>
      <para>
       Honourable Members of the Parliament of Australia:
      </para>
      <para>
       At the elections for both Houses of Parliament held on 11 July 1987, the Australian people once again elected the Labor Government and, with an increased majority, decisively renewed its mandate to pursue the task of national reconstruction.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government enters its third term in office with a full agenda of reforms to continue this essential and historic task.
      </para>
      <para>
       Like the policies implemented by the Government in its first two terms, these new proposals are designed to work towards two overriding and complementary goals.
      </para>
      <para>
       They seek to build a stronger, more competitive and more efficient Australian economy, and a fairer and more compassionate Australian society.
      </para>
      <para>
       The nation has made considerable progress towards these goals since March 1983.
      </para>
      <para>
       If the Australian people are to overcome the basic problems which confront us, further restraint in government spending will be required. The more efficient employment of our human and physical resources, the careful rethinking of inherited attitudes and the continued acceptance by the whole community of the need for hard decisions, will also be necessary.
      </para>
      <para>
       Because this is a task for the whole nation, it is fitting that the Government's program will encompass the period of our Bicentenary celebrations next year.
      </para>
      <para>
       These celebrations will generate great national pride and redouble our sense of national purpose and partnership. The Bicentenary will enable Australians to reflect and to build upon their substantial achievements in all facets of human endeavour.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government believes that this renewed national spirit will be an essential element in the successful reconstruction of the Australian economy to meet the challenges of our third century of European settlement.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government believes it is essential, as we come to the Bicentennial year, to recognise that 200 years of European settlement come after over 40,000 years of Aboriginal history. The Government will explore how best to reflect that recognition and the obligation which this involves for the whole community.
      </para>
      <para>
       This Government has directed and coordinated all aspects of government activity towards the task of reconstruction. Macroeconomic policy has been complemented by appropriate policies directed to the primary, manufacturing and services industries, education and training, foreign policy and overseas trade, the encouragement of research, the improvement of the nation's infrastructure and the streamlining of the public service.
      </para>
      <para>
       Social welfare policy has been progressively reformed to ensure that those Australians who are worst off receive the greatest possible assistance, while those who should not rely upon the government safety net find it more difficult to do so.
      </para>
      <para>
       The agenda for the third term reflects this coordinated and farsighted approach to the continued challenge of reform.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Australian Economy
      </para>
      <para>
       Reflecting the sharp decline in our terms of trade, the major preoccupation of economic policy over recent years has been to redress the consequent deterioration in our balance of payments and foreign debt positions. Corrective action on those fronts is essential to establish the pre-conditions for sustainable growth in economic activity and living standards. The Government's monetary, wages and fiscal policies have been geared towards these objectives, while seeking to spread the burden of economic adjustment fairly across the community. Structural policies also have been receiving particular emphasis.
      </para>
      <para>
       These policies are now bearing fruit. While the task of restoring external balance will take some considerable time, there is increasing evidence that the necessary structural adjustment processes are occurring. The current account deficit has been moving downwards and this is forecast to continue.
      </para>
      <para>
       While the Government acknowledges the need for responsible macroeconomic policies to be maintained, increased efforts will be made to improve efficiency and to remove constraints on improved output performance in the private and public sectors. That, ultimately, is the basis of the improved living standards to which we all aspire.
      </para>
      <para>
       Further steps will be taken to reduce the public sector's call on national savings for as long as economic conditions require. The Government expects all levels of government in Australia to contribute to the restraint that will be necessary to achieve these objectives.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue its wages policy which over the past four years has, together with the mature cooperation of the trade union movement, provided the foundation for outstanding employment growth, increased economic competitiveness and enhanced industrial stability. The continued reform of outmoded work and management practices to raise productivity will also receive the attention of the Government over the life of this Parliament.
      </para>
      <para>
       During its second term, the Government was presented with the Report of the Committee of Review into Australian Industrial Relations Law and Systems. Following extensive consultations with the major parties, the Government will be reforming the industrial relations system without changing existing sanction provisions in the Conciliation and Arbitration Act and other relevant legislation.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will also be finalising its policy on employee participation and industrial democracy following a period of extensive consultation.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will reintroduce legislation to establish the Office of the Insurance and Superannuation Commissioner and to set operating standards in respect of superannuation funds.
      </para>
      <para>
       In the area of taxation, the Government will be giving top priority to the legislative and administrative completion of its tax reform measures and to continuing its strong support for vigorous enforcement of the taxation laws.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Australia Card Bill will be reintroduced in the first week of the sittings. The Australia Card program is an integral part of the Government's tax reform package and is a fundamental instrument in improving the fairness of the Australian taxation and social welfare systems. It will stop individuals taking more from the welfare system than is their due. It will ensure that all Australians pay a fair share of taxation. The legislation for the Australia Card, and the Privacy bills, will ensure full protection of civil liberties.
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry Policy
      </para>
      <para>
       Throughout the past four years, the Government has implemented an industry and technology strategy which has aimed to build the competitive strength of Australian manufacturing and service industries to world standards. The Australian economy has been opened up to the challenges of international trade. Its emphasis on inward looking protectionism has been progressively shifted to the competitive search for overseas markets.
      </para>
      <para>
       Some notable successes have already been achieved. There is, however, still a long way to go in changing attitudes, marshalling the innovative skills of the Australian people, gaining the best value from our abundant resources and generating new technologies.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government plans to implement a development strategy for the Australian information industries to link them into world markets and expand our capacity to develop new information industries, products and services.
      </para>
      <para>
       It plans also to implement policies to encourage more value-added production in Australia, particularly through further processing of our mineral and agricultural resources, and to develop the full export potential of these industries.
      </para>
      <para>
       One of the objectives of Government purchasing policy will be to encourage the development of the Australian high technology industry.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will also seek to improve links between industry and CSIRO and education institutions to promote the kind of research and development vital to future wealth creation in Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will proceed with the formation of an Australian Research Council to enhance further the excellence of Australian research and its contribution to national economic and social development.
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign Affairs and Trade
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to assist Australian companies gain access to international markets and join in the dynamic growth of the Pacific rim economies. It will search for a more open trading system, particularly in agricultural trade. New initiatives include enhancing the effectiveness of AUSTRADE, and designing and implementing a strategy to attract productive foreign investment to raise our industrial capacity, quicken the transfer of technology and managerial know-how, and widen our access to foreign markets. The Government will facilitate international co-operation agreements between firms to develop and exploit new technologies, and to help Australian companies market their own technological innovations. The Government will develop a cooperative regional strategy, with the aim of helping Australian high technology industry tap the enormous potential of the ASEAN and Pacific regions.
      </para>
      <para>
       In its international policies, the Government will consolidate and develop relations with neighbouring countries in the ASEAN and South Pacific Forum regions. It will work for a lessening of superpower rivalry, particularly through the achievement of effective and verifiable arms control and disarmament measures. It will further our alliance relationship with the United States under ANZUS. It will promote effective development assistance programs to developing countries within the means available to it.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       The policies outlined in the Defence White Paper presented to the last Parliament will further enhance Australia's defence capabilities and increase the involvement of Australian industry. The Government will continue the Defence investment program and will ensure that our Defence Force structure and capabilities are developed within the policy of greater defence self-reliance and have prime regard for the security interests of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       Major capital equipment initiatives, including the construction of eight light patrol frigates and six conventionally powered submarines, will benefit significantly our self-reliant defence capability and our indigenous industry.
      </para>
      <para>
       Other Defence priorities include the continuing rationalisation of Defence factories and dockyards and further improvement of conditions of service in the Australian Defence Force.
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       In addition to the encouragement and promotion of Australia's traditional primary industries, which must remain a very high priority, the Government will help rural and provincial Australia gain greater access to Government programs.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will make every effort to ensure that Australian products meet international and domestic standards for chemicals associated with their production. It will introduce improved methods for clearance and registration of agricultural and veterinary chemicals for use in Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       In conjunction with the Governments of New South Wales, Victoria and South Australia, the Government will set in place legislation to replace the existing River Murray Commission with a Murray-Darling Basin Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       Responsible and environmentally sensible management of our forest resources will remain a priority for the Government and a broadacre afforestation program will be introduced. A balance must be maintained between the sustain- able commercial use of these production resources and the conservation and protection of areas that are sensitive or have special environmental value.
      </para>
      <para>
       In the resources area, the petroleum sector will be a focus for much Government action. Legislation necessary to give effect to the Government's decision to deregulate crude oil marketing with effect from 1 January 1988 will be introduced.
      </para>
      <para>
       In its third term, the Government will introduce legislation to give effect to its commitment to reduce the top excise rate on `old' oil. This measure is expected to lead to considerably higher rates of production and to guarantee new expenditure in petroleum exploration, both onshore and offshore, and substantial new investment in Bass Strait.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will, as a matter of priority, re-introduce its resource rent tax legislation to replace the royalties and excise on new offshore petroleum developments.
      </para>
      <para>
       Monitoring of coal export contracts will be maintained and the Government will be prepared to use its export control reserve power if it is necessary to protect the national interest and ensure adequate returns to Australia from the export of its coal resources.
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       Early in these sittings, the Government will introduce motions in both Houses formally to give the required three years' notice to terminate the Two Airline Policy and will also be shortly spelling out its plans and objectives for the domestic aviation industry.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government made an in-principle decision, in its second term, to establish a Civil Aviation Corporation to improve the efficiency of support for the aviation industry. Refinement of this concept will take place in the coming year.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government is also examining reforms to improve the efficiency and competitiveness of the shipping industry, with particular emphasis on the operation of the waterfront. There will also be an examination of air charter arrangements.
      </para>
      <para>
       The last four years have seen unprecedented changes in Australia's broadcasting environment. Legislation will be introduced to complete the reform of ownership and control rules for television and to make some much-needed changes to parts of the Broadcasting Act dealing with public broadcasting, licensing and Australian Broadcasting Tribunal procedures.
      </para>
      <para>
       The telecommunications industry is a vital part of Australia's economic infrastructure and a dynamically growing industry in its own right. The Government will ensure that its telecommunications policies are adapted to the changing international environment and facilitate the use by Australian industry of the most modern technology.
      </para>
      <para>
       Tourism
      </para>
      <para>
       The success of the Government's tourism promotion campaigns overseas, coupled with the depreciation of the Australian dollar, has resulted in a boom in international travel to Australia. Tourism is now one of Australia's largest and fastest-growing industries, and the Government will continue to pursue policies which maintain the competitiveness of our tourism-based industries.
      </para>
      <para>
       Legislation will be introduced during the Budget sittings to restructure the Australian Tourist Commission to enable it to operate as a much more efficient marketing organisation.
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Reforms
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government's determination to improve overall economic efficiency has already led to a substantial reform of the public sector. The Government's first act of its third term was the introduction of new administrative and ministerial arrangements which will strengthen ministerial control, streamline administration and improve both the efficiency and the economy of the business of government.
      </para>
      <para>
       The introduction of a two-level ministerial structure will entail amendments to the Ministers of State Act to permit the appointment of three additional Ministers. Amendments to the Acts Interpretation Act will put beyond doubt that references in legislation to a Minister include all Ministers administering the relevant department.
      </para>
      <para>
       Legislation will be introduced to replace the Public Service Board with a single, full-time Public Service Commissioner, and a part-time Management Advisory Board.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to give consideration to the most efficient and effective methods of providing its agencies with common services, such as design and construction of public works and property management.
      </para>
      <para>
       From the reconstruction of the nation's economy, I turn now to the Government's proposals to develop the nation's greatest resources, its people, so they too are equipped to manage the challenges ahead.
      </para>
      <para>
       Education and Training
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government's policies on education and training are designed to ensure that young Australians have the greatest possible opportunities in life ensuring that we build an economy capable of prospering in an increasingly competitive world.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government's immediate priority will be to direct education resources to alleviating Australia's skills shortage, particularly in high technology fields, and to widening our overall skills base.
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry must also play its part, by developing links with schools, higher education and technical education, investing more heavily in research and development, and maintaining an open dialogue with educational institutions.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government aims to continue its progress in lifting Year 12 retention rates to at least 65 per cent by the first half of the next decade.
      </para>
      <para>
       The apprenticeship system will continue to be a major source of employment and training opportunities for young people, providing about one third of all full-time employment opportunities for school leavers. In addition, the Australian Traineeship System will provide increasing opportunities for young people to undertake high quality training in non-trades areas.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government is committed to funding a National Policy on Languages which aims to ensure that all Australians master English, our common tongue, and that more Australians learn a second language. This will contribute to improvements in the skill level of the labour force, to diversification of employment opportunities and to the advancement of our trade and economic interests abroad.
      </para>
      <para>
       Job creation programs will be increasingly replaced by vocational training initiatives, to help equip people, through training or retraining, with the skills they need to compete in a changing job market.
      </para>
      <para>
       In making education more relevant to the economy, the Government will maintain its commitment to equity in education. The Government will continue targeting those disadvantaged in the labour market to receive special assistance with education and training.
      </para>
      <para>
       Social Security, Community Services and Health
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government's goal is that, by 1990, no Australian child need live in poverty. Accordingly, in this Parliament the Government will undertake a major restructuring of government support for children. To this end, and in fulfilment of an election promise, a new Family Allowance Supplement will be introduced to rationalise existing programs and provide substantially increased levels of support, subject to a family income test. Reforms to rental assistance and improved financial help for children with disabilities will also be introduced.
      </para>
      <para>
       In addition, in the Budget sittings of Parliament the Government intends to introduce legislation to establish the Child Support Agency as part of the Australian Taxation Office. This agency will ensure the efficient collection of maintenance payments.
      </para>
      <para>
       The second stage of the child maintenance reforms will be legislated in 1988. The Government is determined to safeguard the rights of children to adequate support and to remove the burden on the taxpayer where parents have the capacity to pay.
      </para>
      <para>
       In its first two terms of office, the Government increased the standard rate of pension from 22.7% of average weekly earnings to 24.4%. The Government will seek to make further increases where economic circumstances permit.
      </para>
      <para>
       At the same time, the Government has the objective of restoring parity between the single adult pension and benefit rates.
      </para>
      <para>
       Medicare, now endorsed by the electorate on three occasions, will remain the basis of health insurance in this country, thereby ensuring fairness and universality in health care provision.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will begin negotiations with the States on the funding arrangements for State public hospitals as the present Medicare agreements expire next year.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will also provide State and Territory Governments with extra funds over the next two years on a dollar for dollar basis to assist them to reduce waiting times in public hospitals.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government recognises the importance of prevention as well as cure and will continue to promote activities directed towards better health. It will be developing with the States the first comprehensive set of national health goals and strategies.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government is conscious of the enormous and continuing debt of gratitude we all owe to the veterans' community. It will introduce amendments to the Veterans' Entitlements Act and the Seamen's War Pension and Allowances Act to ensure that Special, that is TPI, and Intermediate rate pensions, once granted, continue to be payable indefinitely, except where there is evidence of fraud, significant improvement in health or resumption of employment.
      </para>
      <para>
       Full medical and hospital treatment will also be extended to all returned ex-servicewomen from the Second World War, and special compensation will be provided to surviving Australian ex-servicemen illegally interned in Nazi concentration camps for protracted periods during that war.
      </para>
      <para>
       In its third term of office the Government will continue its major reforms of residential care services for aged people, ensuring a balanced provision of appropriate accommodation and services. Enhanced assessment services will provide a better match between care needs and services.
      </para>
      <para>
       To ensure better coordination and equitable distribution of community services the Government has entered into joint funding and co-operative program arrangements with the State Governments. The Government will seek to redefine and develop these programs to ensure they remain effective, efficient and relevant.
      </para>
      <para>
       The fight against drug abuse in Australia will be continued under the National Campaign against Drug Abuse, to build on the achievements gained since the Campaign's establishment in 1985.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to fund AIDS education programs and prevention and research activities.
      </para>
      <para>
       In this the International Year of Shelter for the Homeless, the Government's commitment to public housing is demonstrated by its guarantee to provide over $2.1 billion in grants under the Commonwealth-State Housing Agreement over the next three years. The highly successful First Home Owners Scheme will continue.
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       I have already referred to the Government's intention to explore how best to reflect the recognition of over 40,000 years of Aboriginal history and the obligation which this involves for the whole community.
      </para>
      <para>
       In its first two terms the Government has increased real funding on Aboriginal programs by 50%. The Government will vigorously press on with a range of programs designed to improve the living conditions and future prospects of this group of Australia's citizens.
      </para>
      <para>
       Of particular importance will be the further development of the Aboriginal Employment Development Policy, designed to provide a range of measures to enhance Aboriginal economic independence.
      </para>
      <para>
       A Royal Commission to enquire into the tragically high number of Aboriginal deaths in custody has already been announced, and a series of discussions with the States has begun. This is a serious and complex problem but the Government believes a sympathetic and concerted effort by all can only achieve positive results.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government proposes to establish a new Commission to replace the Department of Aboriginal Affairs and the Aboriginal Development Commission, and legislation will be developed-for introduction, if possible, in these sittings-to this end.
      </para>
      <para>
       Women
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government is particularly proud of its record of achievement in regard to women's issues. It will continue to act to improve the quality of life for women-those at home and those in the workforce-by giving women a greater say, a better range of choices and a fair go.
      </para>
      <para>
       During its third term the Government will complete its promise of 20,000 new child care places and will implement major initiatives to improve the health of Australian women, involving a three year program of evaluation and trials of breast and cervical cancer screening procedures.
      </para>
      <para>
       The National Agenda for Women will be finalised and released, as the blueprint for future Government action to improve the status of women in Australia up to the year 2000.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will commence a $1.6 million education campaign with the objective of reducing the incidence of domestic violence in the community.
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration and Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       The National Agenda for a Multicultural Australia-to be developed over the next two years in conjunction with the Advisory Council on Multicultural Affairs-will give definition, direction and drive to the policy of multiculturalism. At the same time the Government's access and equity strategy will help ensure that Government services and programs are available fairly to all Australians. I referred earlier to the National Policy on Languages which will specifically address Australia's language needs.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will ensure that its immigration policy remains relevant to Australia's contemporary needs and has accordingly commissioned a review of Australia's immigration policies. The examination will be conducted in close consultation with interested community groups, including ethnic organisations.
      </para>
      <para>
       Equally, the Government is determined to maintain those essential services required by migrants on arrival in their new homeland. Additional funds will be provided for settlement services in 1987-88, based on increases in the Migration Program, including for the Adult Migrant Education Program which plays such a key role in successful settlement.
      </para>
      <para>
       Law and Justice
      </para>
      <para>
       The Constitutional Commission, established by the Government to consult widely with the community and to recommend changes to the Constitution, will report in 1988. The Government will consider closely the report of the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will develop further measures to improve the ability of law enforcement agencies to counter major crime. It will introduce the Cash Transaction Reports Bill, which lapsed on the dissolution of the last Parliament, to ensure adequate machinery to trace cash transactions in its effort to eradicate organised crime.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government has now completed a review of Australia's extradition legislation and a Bill to consolidate and modernise the extradition laws will be introduced during these sittings.
      </para>
      <para>
       In accordance with the Government's response to the report of the Review of Material relating to the Entry of Alleged War Criminals into Australia, legislation to amend the War Crimes Act will also be brought forward.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Bankruptcy Amendment Bill will be introduced during these sittings. That Bill will include measures to deal effectively with tax evasion and insolvency fraud.
      </para>
      <para>
       Another priority is to revise the National Companies and Securities Scheme to address inadequacies of the present system to ensure it operates as a genuinely national scheme in a way which will enhance our international competitiveness.
      </para>
      <para>
       Adequate consumer protection is an essential part of the Government's policies to ensure a fairer society. Government activity in this area will complement the national Price Watch network, a system of community-based committees to monitor and report on local supermarket prices.
      </para>
      <para>
       Legislation will be introduced during these sittings to amend significantly the Family Law Act to implement a reference of powers from some States on ex-nuptial children and to make the Court more efficient.
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliament
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government supports an increase in the term of the House of Representatives to four years to give greater stability and to encourage longer term planning. Fewer elections would also result in less cost and inconvenience to the electors. Legislation for a referendum on a four year term will be introduced in the life of this Parliament to allow Australians to have their say on the matter.
      </para>
      <para>
       Environment
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government's agenda for environmental action includes completion of the Commission of Inquiry into the Lemonthyme and Southern Forests of Tasmania and a policy response to the findings of that inquiry.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will also consult with the Queensland Government and other interested parties in proceeding towards nomination of the wet tropics of North-East Queensland to the World Heritage List by the end of 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government has nominated Kakadu National Park Stage 2 and Uluru (Ayers Rock-Mount Olga) National Park for inclusion on the World Heritage List. The Government will continue to protect the unique natural and cultural heritage of these and other Australian areas already on the list.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will introduce a program for the greater protection of endangered species and, cognisant of Australia's international responsibilities, will sign and ratify the Vienna Convention for protection of the earth's ozone layer.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Arts
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to pursue a uniquely Australian national arts program aimed at the development of excellence in the arts across a diverse range. It will continue to foster the widest public access to and participation in the arts. To this end, amendments to the Australia Council Act will be introduced.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will maintain Australian film production at a high level.
      </para>
      <para>
       Local Government
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government's commitment to the further development of Local Government-a commitment demonstrated so clearly in the initiatives of the past four years-will be continued with the aim of enabling Local Government to participate as an effective partner in the Australian system of government. Attention will be given to arrangement for the devolution of programs to Local Government.
      </para>
      <para>
       Honourable Members of the Parliament of Australia:
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government believes the initiatives I have outlined today are essential to continue the reconstruction of the national economy and the creation of a fairer society.
      </para>
      <para>
       It is your legislative task to consider and debate these initiatives as they are progressively introduced into the Parliament.
      </para>
      <para>
       As the representatives of the Australian people, whose interests these proposals are designed to advance, you bear a grave responsibility, and I wish you well in your task ahead.
      </para>
      <para>
       His Excellency the Governor-General and members of the House of Representatives retired.
      </para>
      <para>
       Sitting suspended from 3.52 to 5 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       The PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. Kerry Sibraa) took the chair at 5 p.m., and read prayers.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="12" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      COMMISSION TO ADMINISTER OATH
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I inform honourable senators that I have received from His Excellency the Governor-General a commission to administer to honourable senators the oath or affirmation of allegiance.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Commission laid on the table and read by the Clerk.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="12" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      GOVERNOR-GENERAL'S SPEECH
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I inform the Senate that I have received a copy of the opening speech which His Excellency the Governor-General was pleased to deliver to both Houses of the Parliament.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Motion (by Senator Button) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para>
        That consideration of the Governor-General's Opening Speech be an order of the day for the next day of sitting.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="12" type="Ministerial Arrangements">
     <title>
      MINISTERIAL ARRANGEMENTS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="12" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, I have the honour to inform the Senate that, following the election held on 11 July 1987, 27 Ministers were sworn in on 24 July 1987. I seek leave to incorporate in Hansard the details of the Ministry.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave granted-
      </para>
      <para>
       The document read as follows-
      </para>
      <para>
       COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT
      </para>
      <para>
       Third Hawke Ministry
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       PORTFOLIO
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTER
      </para>
      <para>
       REPRESEN-
      </para>
      <para>
       TATION
      </para>
      <para>
       IN OTHER
      </para>
      <para>
       CHAMBER
      </para>
      <para>
       DEPARTMENT
      </para>
      <para>
       ADMINISTERED
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       *PRIME MINISTER
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. R. J. L. HAWKE, AC, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR BUTTON
      </para>
      <para>
       Prime Minister and Cabinet
      </para>
      <para>
       *SPECIAL MINISTER OF STATE, Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for the Status of Women and for the Bicentenary, and Minister Assisting the Minister for Community Services and Health
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR THE HON. SUSAN RYAN
      </para>
      <para>
       MR HAWKE
      </para>
      <para>
       DR BLEWETT
      </para>
      <para>
       Prime Minister and Cabinet
      </para>
      <para>
       *ATTORNEY-GENERAL and Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Commonwealth-State Relations
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. LIONEL BOWEN, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       (Deputy Prime Minister)
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR TATE
      </para>
      <para>
       ***SENATOR EVANS
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR BUTTON
      </para>
      <para>
       Attorney-
      </para>
      <para>
       General's
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Consumer Affairs and Minister Assisting the Treasurer for Prices
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. PETER STAPLES, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR TATE
      </para>
      <para>
       ***SENATOR WALSH
      </para>
      <para>
       Attorney-
      </para>
      <para>
       General's
      </para>
      <para>
       **Parliamentary Secretary for Justice
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR THE HON. MICHAEL TATE
      </para>
      <para>
       MR BOWEN
      </para>
      <para>
       Attorney-
      </para>
      <para>
       General's
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR THE HON. JOHN BUTTON
      </para>
      <para>
       (Leader of the Government in the Senate)
      </para>
      <para>
       MR JONES
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry, Technology, and Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Science and Small Business
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. BARRY O. JONES, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR BUTTON
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry, Technology, and Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR TRANSPORT AND COMMUNICATIONS
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR THE HON. GARETH EVANS, QC
      </para>
      <para>
       (Deputy Leader of the Government in the Senate and Manager of Government Business in the Senate)
      </para>
      <para>
       MR DUNCAN
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Land Transport and Infrastructure Support
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. PETER DUNCAN, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR EVANS
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       *TREASURER
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. P. J. KEATING, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR WALSH
      </para>
      <para>
       Treasury
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR IMMIGRATION, LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND ETHNIC AFFAIRS and Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Multicultural Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. MICHAEL J. YOUNG, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       (Vice President of the Executive Council, Leader of the House)
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR REYNOLDS
      </para>
      <para>
       ***SENATOR BUTTON
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR BUTTON
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       **Parliamentary Secretary for Local Government
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR THE HON. MARGARET REYNOLDS
      </para>
      <para>
       MR YOUNG
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR FINANCE
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR THE HON. PETER WALSH
      </para>
      <para>
       MR DAWKINS
      </para>
      <para>
       Finance
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. BILL HAYDEN, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR EVANS
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign Affairs and Trade
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Trade Negotiations, and Minister Assisting the Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce, and Minister Assisting the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. MICHAEL DUFFY, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR EVANS
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR BUTTON
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR WALSH
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign Affairs and Trade
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS and Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Public Service Matters
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. RALPH WILLIS, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR BUTTON
      </para>
      <para>
       Industrial Relations
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR EMPLOYMENT, EDUCATION AND TRAINING
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. J. S. DAWKINS, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR RYAN
      </para>
      <para>
       Employment, Education and Training
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Employment Services and Youth Affairs, and Minister Assisting the Treasurer
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. A. C. HOLDING, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR RYAN
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR WALSH
      </para>
      <para>
       Employment, Education and Training
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR DEFENCE
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. KIM C. BEAZLEY, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR RAY
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       **Parliamentary Secretary for Defence Science and Personnel
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. ROS KELLY, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR RAY
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. JOHN KERIN, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR WALSH
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Resources
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. PETER MORRIS, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR WALSH
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR SOCIAL SECURITY
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. BRIAN HOWE, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR RICHARDSON
      </para>
      <para>
       Social Security
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. STEWART WEST, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR RAY
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Services
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Home Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR THE HON. ROBERT RAY
      </para>
      <para>
       (Deputy Manager of Government Business in the Senate)
      </para>
      <para>
       MR WEST
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Services
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR THE ARTS, SPORT, THE ENVIRONMENT, TOURISM AND TERRITORIES
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. JOHN BROWN, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR RICHARDSON
      </para>
      <para>
       The Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for the Environment and the Arts
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR THE HON. GRAHAM RICHARDSON
      </para>
      <para>
       MR BROWN
      </para>
      <para>
       The Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories
      </para>
      <para>
       *MINISTER FOR COMMUNITY SERVICES AND HEALTH
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. NEAL BLEWETT, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR RYAN
      </para>
      <para>
       Community Services and Health, Veterans' Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Veterans' Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. BEN HUMPHREYS, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR REYNOLDS
      </para>
      <para>
       ***SENATOR RYAN
      </para>
      <para>
       Veterans'
      </para>
      <para>
       Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Aboriginal Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       THE HON. GERARD L. HAND, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATOR TATE
      </para>
      <para>
       ***SENATOR RYAN
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal
      </para>
      <para>
       Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       *Minister in the Cabinet
      </para>
      <para>
       **Temporary title pending amendment of the Ministers of State Act 1952
      </para>
      <para>
       ***Temporary arrangement pending amendment of the Ministers of State Act 1952
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —In addition to the 27 Ministers, the list includes the three Parliamentary Secretaries who will be sworn in as Ministers after the Ministers of State Act 1952 has been amended. The list also shows those Ministers who constitute the Cabinet and provides details of representation arrangements in each chamber and the departments each Minister administers.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Senator Jones has been elected Government Whip and Senator Maguire and Senator McKiernan have been elected Deputy Government Whips.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="UJ4" speaker="Senator Walters">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UJ4">
          Senator Walters
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —How are you going to keep both deputies in order?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, I can see that the election has not changed the quality of the interjections; they remain abysmal. As honourable senators will be aware, the Government has made major changes to the structure of Commonwealth administration and I will be seeking leave to make a statement on those changes before Question Time tomorrow.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="15" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      LEADERSHIP OF THE OPPOSITION
     </title>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="EF4" page="15" party="LP" speaker="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="EF4">
         Senator CHANEY
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, I advise the Senate that, since the election, I have been returned as Leader of the Opposition and Senator Austin Lewis has been elected Deputy Leader of the Opposition. Senator Margaret Reid has been elected Opposition Whip and Senator Susan Knowles has been elected Deputy Opposition Whip. I make the point, Mr President, that this is the first time that women have held both of those positions in any chamber in the Commonwealth. I seek leave to incorporate in Hansard a list showing the shadow Ministry representation for the Opposition in both chambers.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The document read as follows-
      </para>
      <para>
       SHADOW MINISTRY REPRESENTATION
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Portfolio
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister
      </para>
      <para>
       Representation in other chamber
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       *Leader of the Opposition
      </para>
      <para>
       Howard
      </para>
      <para>
       Chaney
      </para>
      <para>
       *Trade and Resources
      </para>
      <para>
       Sinclair
      </para>
      <para>
       Stone
      </para>
      <para>
       *Treasury
      </para>
      <para>
       Peacock
      </para>
      <para>
       Stone
      </para>
      <para>
       *Primary Industry
      </para>
      <para>
       Lloyd
      </para>
      <para>
       Lewis
      </para>
      <para>
       *Industrial Relations
      </para>
      <para>
       Chaney
      </para>
      <para>
       Shack
      </para>
      <para>
       *Industry, Technology and Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       Lewis
      </para>
      <para>
       Moore
      </para>
      <para>
       *Foreign Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Spender
      </para>
      <para>
       Chaney
      </para>
      <para>
       *Business and Consumer Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Moore
      </para>
      <para>
       Short
      </para>
      <para>
       *Education
      </para>
      <para>
       Carlton
      </para>
      <para>
       Vanstone
      </para>
      <para>
       *Finance
      </para>
      <para>
       Stone
      </para>
      <para>
       Peacock
      </para>
      <para>
       *Health
      </para>
      <para>
       Tuckey
      </para>
      <para>
       Puplick
      </para>
      <para>
       *Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       Messner
      </para>
      <para>
       Blunt
      </para>
      <para>
       *Transport and Aviation
      </para>
      <para>
       Beale
      </para>
      <para>
       Messner
      </para>
      <para>
       *Community Services
      </para>
      <para>
       Blunt
      </para>
      <para>
       Vanstone
      </para>
      <para>
       *Administrative Services
      </para>
      <para>
       Fife
      </para>
      <para>
       Short
      </para>
      <para>
       *Environment, the Arts and the Bicentenary
      </para>
      <para>
       Puplick
      </para>
      <para>
       Smith
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       White
      </para>
      <para>
       Messner
      </para>
      <para>
       Social Security
      </para>
      <para>
       Connolly
      </para>
      <para>
       Vanstone
      </para>
      <para>
       Territories
      </para>
      <para>
       Braithwaite
      </para>
      <para>
       Vanstone
      </para>
      <para>
       Attorney-General
      </para>
      <para>
       Reith
      </para>
      <para>
       Lewis
      </para>
      <para>
       Employment, Training and Youth Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Shack
      </para>
      <para>
       Puplick
      </para>
      <para>
       Veterans' Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Fischer
      </para>
      <para>
       Messner
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration and Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Cadman
      </para>
      <para>
       Short
      </para>
      <para>
       Housing and Public Administration
      </para>
      <para>
       Porter
      </para>
      <para>
       Short
      </para>
      <para>
       Tourism and Sport
      </para>
      <para>
       Sharp
      </para>
      <para>
       Puplick
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Miles
      </para>
      <para>
       Messner
      </para>
      <para>
       Science and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       Smith
      </para>
      <para>
       Lewis
      </para>
      <para>
       Home Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Short
      </para>
      <para>
       Sharp
      </para>
      <para>
       Special Minister of State and Status Of Women
      </para>
      <para>
       Vanstone
      </para>
      <para>
       Porter
      </para>
      <para>
       Local Government
      </para>
      <para>
       Cameron
      </para>
      <para>
       Messner
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       * Denotes Shadow Cabinet portfolio.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="16" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      LEADERSHIP OF THE AUSTRALIAN DEMOCRATS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="1H4" page="16" party="AD" speaker="Haines Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="1H4">
         Senator HAINES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I wish to advise the Senate that since the election I have been returned as Leader of the Australian Democrats. Senator Michael Macklin is Deputy Leader and Whip. I seek leave to incorporate in Hansard details of portfolio distribution among Democrat senators.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The document read as follows-
      </para>
      <para>
       AUSTRALIAN DEMOCRATS' PORTFOLIO DISTRIBUTION
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Janine Haines, Leader of the Australian Democrats, has announced portfolio responsibilities among the seven Democrat Senators and these are detailed below:
      </para>
      <para>
       Janine Haines
      </para>
      <para>
       Federal Parliamentary Leader
      </para>
      <para>
       Prime Minister and Cabinet; Finance and Treasury.
      </para>
      <para>
       Michael Macklin
      </para>
      <para>
       Deputy Leader and Whip
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign Affairs and Trade; Attorney-General (except consumer affairs); Employment, Education and Training; Electoral and Constitutional matters (from Administrative Services).
      </para>
      <para>
       Norm Sanders ...
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence; Transport (from Transport and Communications); Environment (from Arts, Sport, Environment, Tourism and Territories); Energy and Resources (from Primary Industries and Energy).
      </para>
      <para>
       Janet Powell ...
      </para>
      <para>
       Social Security; Administrative Services; Consumer Affairs (from AG's); Primary Industry (from Primary Industries and Energy); Communications (from Transport and Communications).
      </para>
      <para>
       Paul McLean ...
      </para>
      <para>
       Veterans' Affairs; Industrial Relations; Small Business (from Industry, Commerce and Technology).
      </para>
      <para>
       Jean Jenkins ...
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs; Arts, Sport, Tourism and Territories (from Arts, Sport, Environment, Tourism and Territories).
      </para>
      <para>
       John Coulter ...
      </para>
      <para>
       Community Services and Health; Industry, Commerce and Technology (except Small Business).
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="16" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      LEADERSHIP OF THE NATIONAL PARTY OF AUSTRALIA
     </title>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="LJ4" page="16" party="NP" speaker="Stone Sen J.O.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LJ4">
         Senator STONE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the National Party of Australia)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, I wish to advise the Senate that I have been elected Leader of the National Party of Australia in the Senate. My Deputy is Lady Bjelke-Petersen and our Whip is Senator Tambling.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="16" type="Committee">
     <title>
      ELECTION OF DEPUTY PRESIDENT AND CHAIRMAN OF COMMITTEES
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       Motion (by Senator Button) agreed to:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the Senate do now proceed to elect a Deputy President and Chairman of Committees.
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="EF4" page="16" party="LP" speaker="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="EF4">
         Senator CHANEY
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I propose Senator Hamer and move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That Senator Hamer be appointed Deputy President and Chairman of Committees.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="NG4" speaker="Senator Lewis">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NG4">
          Senator Lewis
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I second the motion.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="16" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I will not be proposing anybody for Deputy President on behalf of the Government. In making that announcement, I should say that Senator Colston was elected by the Parliamentary Labor Party to contest the position of Deputy President but he has forsworn ambition in the interests of harmony. I think Senator Colston's graceful retirement should be acknowledged.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Are there any further nominations? There being no further nominations, Senator Hamer is elected Deputy President and Chairman of Committees in accordance with the Standing Orders.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="4H4" page="17" party="LP" speaker="Hamer Sen D.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4H4">
         Senator HAMER
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I thank the Senate for the confidence reposed in me. I think it is well known that there are problems with having a President and Deputy President from opposite parties but there are also great advantages. The disadvantages can be overcome by mutual confidence and respect. I worked with you, Mr President, for some months and I feel I have received that confidence and respect from you. In return for that, for this Parliament I pledge you my loyalty.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="EF4" page="17" party="LP" speaker="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="EF4">
         Senator CHANEY
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —On behalf of the Opposition I congratulate Senator Hamer on his election. I thank him for the very good service he gave the Senate in the last Parliament in the same position. Just as we expect impartiality from you, Mr President, the same is expected from Senator Hamer. We wish him well in this coming Parliament.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="17" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —On behalf of the Government I sort of repeat the speech I made about you this morning, Mr President, but in muted tones compared with the lavish comments I made about your performance. Senator Hamer has been very much respected by Government senators as a Deputy President. We look forward to a continuation of that conduct of the Senate and wish him well.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="1H4" page="17" party="AD" speaker="Haines Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="1H4">
         Senator HAINES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —On behalf of the Australian Democrats I extend our congratulations to Senator Hamer on being elected unopposed and look forward to an harmonious working relationship with him.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="LJ4" page="17" party="NP" speaker="Stone Sen J.O.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LJ4">
         Senator STONE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the National Party of Australia)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —On behalf of the National Party I join in the congratulations on Senator Hamer's election as Deputy President of the Senate. I have had the privilege of knowing Senator Hamer for some years and know him to be a person of the utmost impartiality and fairness of mind. He had already shown that by his past handling of the position. I have no doubt that he will continue to do so.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="IG4" page="17" party="IND" speaker="Vallentine Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator VALLENTINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I also congratulate Senator Hamer on his position and look forward to working as part of the committee system in this term of Parliament. I hope that I will have a close and harmonious relationship with him as well.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="17" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I congratulate Senator Hamer on his election to the position of Deputy President. I expect that he will conduct himself with the fairness and propriety that the high office demands.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I join honourable senators in congratulating Senator Hamer. I pay tribute to the supportive role that was provided to me by the Deputy President of the Senate in the last Parliament. Senator Hamer worked ceaselessly and tirelessly in a supportive role. I am grateful to him and I appreciate the assistance he rendered to me. I am sure that that will continue in the future.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="17" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      NOTICES OF MOTION
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I understand that a number of senators wish to give notices of motion. With the concurrence of the Senate and in accordance with past practice, to expedite the proceedings I propose to allow the leaders of the Government, the Opposition and the Australian Democrats, Senator Harradine and the Deputy Leader of the Australian Democrats to give notices of motion of their own and on behalf of other senators in accordance with the lists that have been circulated in the chamber. I will then have the notices of motion put on the Notice Paper in the order in which I would have called honourable senators if the notices had been given in accordance with the Standing Orders.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="17" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following notices of motion and contingent notice of motion:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The Leader of the Government in the Senate: To move-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 1-Rotation of Senators
      </para>
      <para>
       That, in pursuance of section 13 of the Constitution of the Commonwealth, the Senators chosen for each State be divided into two classes as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) The name of the Senator first elected shall be placed first on the Senators' Roll for each State and the name of the Senator next elected shall be placed next, and so on in rotation.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) The Senators whose names are placed first, second, third, fourth, fifth and sixth on the Roll shall be Senators of the second class, that is, the long-term Senators, and the Senators whose names are placed seventh, eighth, ninth, tenth, eleventh and twelfth on the Roll shall be Senators of the first class, that is, the short-term Senators.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-Sessional Orders
      </para>
      <para>
       1. Days and hours of meeting
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) That, unless otherwise ordered, the days and hours of meeting of the Senate be as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) During the first sitting week-
      </para>
      <para>
       Tuesday, 2 p.m.-6.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       8 p.m.-10.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wednesday, 10 a.m.-12.45 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       2 p.m.- 7.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       Thursday, 10 a.m.- 6.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       8 p.m.-10.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       Friday,  9 a.m.-12.45 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       2 p.m.- 3.45 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) During the second sitting week-
      </para>
      <para>
       Monday, 2 p.m.-6.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       8 p.m.-10.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       Tuesday,  2 p.m.- 6.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       8 p.m.-10.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wednesday, 10 a.m.-12.45 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       2 p.m.- 7.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       Thursday, 10 a.m.- 6.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       That, from the termination of the last sitting in the second week, the Senate stand adjourned until 2 p.m. on the third Tuesday after that termination, or such other time as may be fixed by the President or, in the event of the President being unavailable, by the Deputy-President, and that the time of meeting so determined shall be notified to each Senator; and the 4-weekly cycle then be repeated: Provided that the President, at the request of an absolute majority of the whole number of Senators that the Senate meet at a certain time, shall fix a time of meeting in accordance with such request, and such time of meeting shall be notified to each Senator.
      </para>
      <para>
       For these purposes a request by the Leader or Deputy-Leader of the Opposition in the Senate shall be deemed to be a request by every Senator of the Opposition and a request by the Leader or Deputy-Leader of the Australian Democrats shall be deemed to be a request by every Australian Democrat Senator:
      </para>
      <para>
       Provided further that a request may be made to the President by delivery to the Clerk of the Senate, who shall immediately notify the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       That, in the event of the President being unavailable, the Clerk without delay notify the Deputy-President, or, should the Deputy-President be unavailable, any one of the temporary Chairmen of Committees, who shall be required by the Senate to summon the Senate on behalf of the President, in accordance with this Resolution.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) That the Sessional Order relating to the adjournment of the Senate have effect at the terminating time each day.
      </para>
      <para>
       2. Adjournment of the Senate
      </para>
      <para>
       That, at the terminating time each day, the President put the question-That the Senate do now adjourn-which question shall be open to debate; if the Senate be in Committee at that time, the Chairman put the question-That the Chairman leave the Chair and report to the Senate; and upon such report being made the President forthwith put the question-That the Senate do now adjourn-which question shall be open to debate:
      </para>
      <para>
       Provided that if the Senate or the Committee be in division at that time the President or the Chairman shall not put that question till the result of such division has been declared; and if the business under discussion has not been disposed of at such adjournment it shall appear on the Notice Paper for the next sitting day.
      </para>
      <para>
       3. Routine of Business
      </para>
      <para>
       That, unless otherwise ordered and notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders, the Senate proceed with its ordinary business in the following routine:
      </para>
      <para>
       Week 1
      </para>
      <para>
       Tuesday:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) Petitions
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Notices of Motion
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Questions
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) Formal Motions-Discovery of Formal Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) Postponement and re-arrangement of Business
      </para>
      <para>
       Wednesday:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) Petitions
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Notices of Motion
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Formal Motions-Discovery of Formal Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Postponement and re-arrangement of Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) At 2 p.m., Questions
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) Any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) Consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) Consideration of Committee Reports pursuant to Sessional Order
      </para>
      <para>
       (10) Further consideration of Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       Thursday:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) Petitions
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Notices of Motion
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Formal Motions-Discovery of Formal Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Postponement and re-arrangement of Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) At 12.45 p.m., Matters of Public Interest
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) At 2 p.m., Questions
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) Any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) Consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order
      </para>
      <para>
       (10) General Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (11) Further consideration of Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       Friday:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) Petitions
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Notices of Motion
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Formal Motions-Discovery of Formal Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Postponement and re-arrangement of Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) At 2 p.m., Questions
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) Any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) Consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) Further consideration of Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       Week 2
      </para>
      <para>
       Monday:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) Petitions
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Notices of Motion
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Questions
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) Formal Motions-Discovery of Formal Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) Postponement and re-arrangement of Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       Tuesday:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) Petitions
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Notices of Motion
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Questions
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) Formal Motions-Discovery of Formal Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) Postponement and re-arrangement of Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       Wednesday:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) Petitions
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Notices of Motion
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Formal Motions-Discovery of Formal Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Postponement and re-arrangement of Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) At 2 p.m., Questions
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) Any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) Consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) Consideration of Committee Reports pursuant to Sessional Order
      </para>
      <para>
       (10) Further consideration of Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       Thursday:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) Petitions
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Notices of Motion
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Formal Motions-Discovery of Formal Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Postponement and re-arrangement of Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) At 12.45 p.m., Matters of Public Interest
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) At 2 p.m., Questions
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) Any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) Consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order
      </para>
      <para>
       (10) General Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (11) Further consideration of Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       4. Proposals pursuant to Standing Order 64
      </para>
      <para>
       That, unless otherwise ordered and notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) On Fridays in week 1 and Thursdays in week 2 the discussion of any proposal submitted to the Senate pursuant to Standing Order 64 not exceed one hour.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) The written statement of the proposed matter of public importance or urgency be handed to the President not later than 12.30 p.m. on each sitting day.
      </para>
      <para>
       5. Government and General Business-Precedence
      </para>
      <para>
       That, unless otherwise ordered, on all sitting days of the Senate Government Business take precedence of General Business, except that General Business take precedence of Government Business on Thursdays after Questions, any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64 and consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order, for a period not exceeding two and one-half hours; and that, unless otherwise ordered, General Business, Orders of the Day take precedence of General Business, Notices of Motion on alternate Thursdays.
      </para>
      <para>
       6. Petitions-Procedure for Presentation
      </para>
      <para>
       That, notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders, the procedure for the presentation of petitions be as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) A Senator wishing to present a petition shall lodge it with the Clerk.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) The Clerk shall make an announcement of petitions so lodged, indicating in respect of each petition the Senator who presents it, the number of signatures, and the subject matter of the petition.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Every petition so presented shall be deemed to have been received by the Senate unless a motion, moved forthwith, that a petition be not received, be agreed to.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) The terms of the petitions presented shall be printed in Hansard.
      </para>
      <para>
       7. Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committees-Reference of Annual Reports
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) That all annual reports of Government departments and authorities, including statutory corporations, laid on the Table of the Senate, stand referred, without any question being put, for consideration and, if necessary, for report thereon, to the Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committees.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) That the President transmit a copy of each report so tabled to the Committee which the President deems appropriate.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) That the Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committees may inquire into reports so received.
      </para>
      <para>
       8. Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committees-Reference of Bills
      </para>
      <para>
       That, after the Second Reading of a Bill (other than an Appropriation Bill, Supply Bill, or Bill imposing taxation), and notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders and without limiting the operation of Standing Orders 36aa and 196a, the following procedure apply:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) A motion (of which notice need not be given) may be moved to refer the Bill to a Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committee.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Upon a motion to refer a Bill to a Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committee, debate shall not exceed one hour, and a Senator shall not speak for more than ten minutes. If the debate be not sooner concluded, at the expiration of that time the President shall put any question on the motion and any amendment before the Chair.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) On reference of a Bill to a Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committee, a day shall be fixed for report by the Committee, by which day the final report of the Committee shall be brought up.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Upon a Bill being committed to a Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committee Pursuant to this Order, it shall be set down on the Notice Paper as an Order of the Day for further consideration following report from the Committee.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) The procedure adopted by a Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committee when considering a Bill under this order shall, as far as possible, be the same as that in Committee of the Whole:
      </para>
      <para>
       Provided that a Committee may ask for explanations from the Minister in charge of a Bill, or officers, relating to the clauses of the Bill.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) A Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committee shall have no power to make amendments to a Bill, but may recommend amendments or requests for amendments. No amendment or request for amendment may be proposed which would not be in order if proposed in a Committee of the Whole.
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) A report from a Legislative and General Purpose Standing Committee relating to a Bill shall be received by the Senate without debate and its consideration deferred until the reading of the Order of the Day for the further consideration of the Bill, when the procedure shall be as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) motion may be proposed that the report be adopted, and such motion shall be open to debate;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) on the motion for the adoption of the report, amendments may be proposed;
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) in these proceedings, the same right of speech and time limits shall apply as in debate in Committee of the Whole;
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) if amendments or requests for amendments be made, additional to any recommended by the report to any recommended by the report of a Standing Committee, the Chair shall propose a question-That the Bill as reported (with or without amendments or requests for amendments), and as further amended, be agreed to;
      </para>
      <para>
       (e) a motion may be moved by any Senator-That the Bill as reported from a Standing Committee be recommitted, in whole or in part, to the Standing Committee, or that the Bill as reported be committed, in whole or in part, to a Committee of the Whole; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (f) when the report from the Committee, or from a Committee of the Whole, is finally adopted, the Bill may be proceeded with in accordance with the procedures of the Senate.
      </para>
      <para>
       9. Consideration of Government Papers
      </para>
      <para>
       That, unless otherwise ordered and notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing and Sessional Orders:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) On all sitting days of the Senate, after Notices, papers may be presented by a Minister; such papers be considered pursuant to this Sessional Order after Questions and any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) When papers are called on by the President, pursuant to this Sessional Order, a motion may be moved, without notice, that the Senate take note of one, or several, of the papers.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) The debate on any motion moved pursuant to this Sessional Order be conducted as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) no Senator shall speak for more than 5 minutes;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) if debate pursuant to this Sessional Order is not concluded it shall be interrupted after 30 minutes, and the Senate shall proceed to the consideration of the Business of the Day;
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) if the debate is adjourned or interrupted by Sessional Order, a motion may be moved for the resumption of the debate either for the Thursday of that week at the time for the consideration of General Business, or for the next day of sitting; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) on Thursdays, at the commencement of General Business, when an Order of the Day is called on under this Sessional Order Senators who have previously spoken to that Order of the Day may speak again for not more than 5 minutes, and debate under this Sessional Order at that time shall not exceed 1 hour.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Where a paper is presented but is not called on under paragraph (1) because of the limitation of time provided by paragraph (3), the consideration of that paper be made an Order of the Day for the next day on which General Business is considered at the commencement of General Business, without any question being put, and where that Order of the Day is called on at that time a motion may be moved without notice to take note of that paper.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Where consideration of a paper is an Order of the Day in accordance with paragraph (4), it remain an Order of the Day for such succeeding day on which General Business is considered at the commencement of General Business till:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) the Order of the Day is called on and no motion to take note of the paper is moved;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) a motion to take note of the paper is determined; or
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) the Order of the Day is discharged from the Notice Paper.
      </para>
      <para>
       whichever first occurs.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) Where debates on motions moved under the provisions of this Sessional Order are adjourned until the next day of sitting and are called on in the normal course of business, Senators who have spoken to the motions under the provisions of this Sessional Order may speak again for the time allowed under Standing Order 407a.
      </para>
      <para>
       10. Consideration of Committee Reports
      </para>
      <para>
       That, unless otherwise ordered and notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders, where in any week there are Orders of the Day for the resumption of debate on motions for the consideration or adoption of reports of committees:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) On Wednesdays after Questions, any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64 and consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order, Orders of the Day relating to reports of committees presented to the Senate during that week be severally called on, in the order in which the respective reports were presented;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) if there were no committee reports presented during that week, or if debate on motions relating to such reports concludes before the expiration of one hour, Orders of the Day relating to committee reports presented prior to that week then be severally called on in an order which is the reverse of the order in which the respective reports were presented;
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) in any debate on such motions so called on, each Senator may speak for not more than 10 minutes; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) any debate pursuant to this Sessional Order be interrupted after the expiration of one hour:
      </para>
      <para>
       Provided that, where debate on any motion debated under the provisions of this Sessional Order is adjourned or is interrupted under the provisions of this Sessional Order, Senators who have spoken to such motion under the provisions of this Sessional Order may speak again to the motion for the time allowed under Standing Order 407a when the debate on the motion is again called on in the normal course of business.
      </para>
      <para>
       11. Time Limits to Speeches
      </para>
      <para>
       That, notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) No Senator speak for more than 30 minutes in any debate in the Senate. Any Senator may move that the time limit of 30 minutes be extended for 15 minutes; such motion forthwith be put without debate:
      </para>
      <para>
       Provided that where a right of reply is allowed in any debate a Senator speaking in reply speak for not more than 30 minutes:
      </para>
      <para>
       Provided further that, in debate on the First Reading of a Bill which the Senate may not amend, no Senator speak for more than 15 minutes.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) In Committee no Senator speak for more than 15 minutes at any one time on any one question:
      </para>
      <para>
       Provided that where the speech of a Senator is interrupted by this provision, and no other Senator rises to speak, the Senator so interrupted may continue to speak for a further 15 minutes but no longer continuously on any one question.
      </para>
      <para>
       12. Putting of Amendments
      </para>
      <para>
       That the Standing Orders have effect as if Standing Orders 141, 142, 143, 144, 145 and 149 were deleted and the following Standing Orders inserted:
      </para>
      <para>
       140. In respect of every amendment the President shall put a question-That the amendment be agreed to.
      </para>
      <para>
       141. An amendment to a motion may not be moved if it is the same in substance as an amendment already determined to the same motion, or would have the effect only of reversing an amendment already made.
      </para>
      <para>
       [Note: These Standing Orders are expressed to apply to amendments to motions, but by virtue of Standing Order 201 apply also to amendments moved to Bills in Committee of the Whole.]
      </para>
      <para>
       13. Proceedings on Bills
      </para>
      <para>
       That, notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders, the following procedures apply in respect of Bills:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) A Senator may present a Bill or two or more Bills after the Senate has agreed to a motion upon notice, setting out the long title of the Bill or Bills-That the Bill or Bills be introduced.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) After the presentation of a Bill or Bills, or after the receipt of a Message or Messages from the House of Representatives forwarding a Bill or Bills for concurrence, a motion may be moved without notice containing any of the following provisions:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) That the Bill or Bills may proceed without formalities (this shall have the effect of suspending any requirements for stages of the passage of the Bill or Bills to take place on different days, for notice of motions for such stages, and for the printing and certification of the Bill or Bills during passage);
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) In respect of two or more Bills-That the Bills may be taken together (this shall have the effect of allowing the questions for the several stages of the passage of the Bills (or any of them) being put in one motion at each stage, the consideration of the Bills (or any of them) together in Committee of the Whole, and the reading of the short titles only on every order for the reading of the Bills, the words in parentheses being applicable where there are more than two Bills);
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) That the Bill, or, where the provision referred to in subparagraph (2) (b) is agreed to, the Bills, be now read a first time.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Where a motion is moved containing two or more of the provisions set out in paragraph (2), at the request of any Senator the motion be divided and the provisions put as separate motions.
      </para>
      <para>
       14. Adjournment of Debates
      </para>
      <para>
       That, notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders, when debate on a motion is adjourned, by motion or by the granting of leave for a Senator to continue the Senator's speech, the resumption of the debate be made an Order of the Day for the next day of sitting without any question being put, unless a motion is agreed to fixing another time for the resumption of the debate.
      </para>
      <para>
       15. Matters of Public Interest
      </para>
      <para>
       That, unless otherwise ordered and notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing and Sessional Orders, on Thursdays at 12.45 p.m. till 2 p.m. matters of public interest may be discussed by Senators:
      </para>
      <para>
       Provided that no Senator shall speak for more than 15 minutes and provided further that, should a division be called for, such division shall be forthwith postponed till a later hour of the day, not being earlier than 2 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-Days and Times of Meeting
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) That, unless otherwise ordered and notwithstanding anything contained in the Sessional Orders, the days of meeting of the Senate for the period October to December 1987 be as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       Tuesday, 6 October to Friday, 9 October; Tuesday, 20 October to Friday, 23 October; Monday, 26 October to Thursday, 29 October; Monday, 2 November to Thursday, 5 November; Tuesday, 17 November to Friday, 20 November; Monday, 23 November to Thursday, 26 November; Monday, 7 December to Thursday, 10 December; and Monday, 14 December to Friday, 18 December.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) That, unless otherwise ordered-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) for the weeks commencing Tuesday, 6 and 20 October and 17 November 1987, and on Friday, 18 December 1987, the Sessional Orders relating to the Hours of Meeting and the Routine of Business for Week 1 apply; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) for the weeks commencing Monday, 26 October, 2 and 23 November, 7 December and 14 December 1987, the Hours of Meeting and Routine of Business for Week 2 apply.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-Suspension of Standing Order 14:
      </para>
      <para>
       That Standing Order 14 be suspended to enable the Senate to consider business beyond what is of a formal character before the Address-in-Reply to the Governor-General's Opening Speech has been adopted.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-Ministers of State Amendment Bill (No. 2) 1987 and Administrative Arrangements Bill 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to amend the Ministers of State Act 1952; and
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to amend the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 and the Public Service Act 1922 in connection with certain administrative arrangements, and for related purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-Australian National Railways Commission Amendment Bill 1987 (On behalf of the Minister for Transport and Communications, Senator Evans)
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to amend the Australian National Railways Commission Act 1983.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 7-Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Amendment Bill 1987 (On behalf of the Minister for Transport and Communications, Senator Evans)
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to amend the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1977, and for related purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 8-Bankruptcy Amendment Bill 1987 (On behalf of the Minister for Transport and Communications, Senator Evans)
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act relating to bankruptcy.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 9-Defence Housing Authority Bill 1987 (On behalf of the Minister for Home Affairs, Senator Ray)
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to establish a Defence Housing Authority.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 10-Contingent Notice of Motion
      </para>
      <para>
       That (contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under Standing Order 64)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button) moving an amendment to the motion.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="EF4" page="22" party="LP" speaker="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="EF4">
         Senator CHANEY
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act relating to the submission to the electors of a question in relation to the introduction of the Australia Card.
      </para>
      <para>
       I also give the following contingent notices of motion in my name and on behalf of my colleagues:
      </para>
      <para>
       CONTINGENT NOTICES OF MOTION
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="EF4">
         Senator Chaney
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give contingent notices of motion as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the President proceeding to the placing of business on any day)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate (Senator Chaney) moving a motion relating to the order of business on the Notice Paper.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Senate on any day concluding its consideration of any item of business and prior to the Senate proceeding to the consideration of another item of business)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate (Senator Chaney) moving a motion relating to the conduct of the business of the Senate.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Senate proceeding to the consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order)-That so much of the Sessional Order relating to the consideration of Government Papers be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate (Senator Chaney) moving a motion relating to the order in which the papers are called on by the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on any Senator being refused leave to make a statement to the Senate)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent that Senator making that statement.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under Standing Order 64)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate (Senator Chaney) moving an amendment to the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under Standing Order 64 and the expiration of the time provided for discussion of the motion)-That so much of the Standing and Sessional Orders be suspended as would prevent the Question on the matter of urgency being put forthwith.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on a Minister moving a motion that a Bill be considered an Urgent Bill)-That so much of Standing Order 407b be suspended as would prevent debate taking place on the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on a Minister moving a motion to specify time to be allotted to the consideration of a Bill, or any stage of a Bill)-That so much of Standing Order 407b be suspended as would prevent the motion being debated without limitation of time and each Senator speaking for the time allocated by Sessional Orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a Bill, or any stage of a Bill, has expired)-That so much of Standing Order 407b be suspended as would prevent further consideration of the Bill, or the stage of the Bill, without limitation of time or for a specified time.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a Bill, or any stage of a Bill, has expired)-That so much of Standing Order 407b be suspended as would prevent the question being put in respect of any amendments circulated by the Opposition, the Australian Democrats, or Independent Senators, and that such questions be put accordingly.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on Senator Walsh, in the course of the proceedings of the Senate, concluding any speech, statement, answer to a Question or comment)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate (Senator Chaney) moving a motion of censure of Senator Walsh.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on Senator Walsh, in the course of the proceedings of the Senate, concluding any speech, statement, answer to a Question or comment)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate (Senator Chaney) moving a motion that Senator Walsh be censured by the Senate and suspended from the sitting of the Senate for a period of 24 hours.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Hamer-I give contingent notices of motion as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the introduction of a Bill in the Senate, or the receipt of a Bill from the House of Representatives)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Hamer moving a motion to refer that Bill or part thereof to a standing committee.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent upon-(a) a Bill being introduced in the Senate or received from the House of Representatives; and (b) the Senate on any day concluding its consideration of any item of business and prior to the Senate proceeding to the consideration of another item of business)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Hamer moving a motion to refer the Bill to a Standing Committee.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="1H4" page="23" party="AD" speaker="Haines Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="1H4">
         Senator HAINES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to ensure that the Australia Card Act 1987 does not come into operation unless the national identification system proposed to be established by the Act has been first approved by a majority of Australian electors, voting at a referendum.
      </para>
      <para>
       I also give the following contingent notices of motion:
      </para>
      <para>
       CONTINGENT NOTICES OF MOTION
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="1H4">
         Senator Haines
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give contingent notices of motion as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the President proceeding to the placing of business on any day)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Australian Democrats (Senator Haines) moving a motion relating to the order of business on the Notice Paper.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Senate on any day concluding its consideration of any item of business and prior to the Senate proceeding to the consideration of another item of business)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Australian Democrats (Senator Haines) moving a motion relating to the conduct of the business of the Senate.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Senate proceeding to the consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order)-That so much of the Sessional Order relating to the consideration of Government Papers be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Australian Democrats (Senator Haines) moving a motion relating to the order in which the papers are called on by the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under Standing Order 64)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Australian Democrats (Senator Haines) moving an amendment to the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under Standing Order 64 and the expiration of the time provided for discussion of the motion)-That so much of the Standing and Sessional Orders be suspended as would prevent the Question on the matter of urgency being put forthwith.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on a Minister moving a motion that a Bill be considered an Urgent Bill)-That so much of Standing Order 407b be suspended as would prevent debate taking place on the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on a Minister moving a motion to specify time to be allotted to the consideration of a Bill, or any stage of a Bill)-That so much of Standing Order 407b be suspended as would prevent the motion being debated without limitation of time and each Senator speaking for the time allocated by Sessional Orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a Bill, or any stage of a Bill, has expired)-That so much of Standing Order 407b be suspended as would prevent further consideration of the Bill, or the stage of the Bill, without limitation of time or for a specified time.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a Bill, or any stage of a Bill, has expired)-That so much of Standing Order 407b be suspended as would prevent the questions being put in respect of any amendments circulated by the Australian Democrats, the Opposition, or Independent Senators, and that such questions be put accordingly.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="24" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following notices of motion and contingent notices of motion:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       NOTICES OF MOTION
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Harradine: I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the Senate-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) notes that persons under 21 years constituted 22.2 per cent of the Australian Public Service staff in 1966, falling to 12.2 per cent in 1974, and falling further to an all-time low of 5.6 per cent as at 31 December 1985, and
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) calls on the Federal Government to take positive action to remedy the apparent structural bias in appointment procedures, which at present discriminate against youth.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Harradine: I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) That-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) the committee known as the Joint Select Committee on Video Material, appointed by resolutions of the Senate of 19 March 1985 and the House of Representatives of 27 February and 19 March 1985, be re-appointed, under the same terms and with the same functions and powers;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) the committee have power to consider and use for its purposes the evidence and records of the Senate Select Committee on Video Material appointed during the 33rd Parliament and of the Joint Select Committee on Video Material appointed during the 34th Parliament;
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) the committee report on or before 26 November 1987; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) the provisions of this resolution, so far as they are inconsistent with the Standing Orders, have effect notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) That the Parliament calls on the Government, pending the report of the Joint Committee, to implement forthwith the recommendations of the Senate Select Committee on Video Material, in particular to ensure an immediate ban on video materials which have received the ``X'' classification by the Film Censorship Board, and that those interim measures remain in force until such time as the Parliament has considered Government action consequent upon the Joint Committee's report.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) That the foregoing resolutions be communicated to the House of Representatives by Message, with a request for the concurrence of that House in the resolutions.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Harradine: I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the Senate notes with concern that over the past 2 decades families have been subjected to increasing pressures from indirect taxation, as well as from direct taxation, and that moves to downgrade the spouse rebate and family allowances are a further example of this iniquitous trend of placing an inordinate taxation burden on families, particularly one-income families.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Harradine: I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the Senate-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) noting the Australian Broadcasting Corporation's (ABC) previous insistence in official statements and evidence to Senate Estimates Committee C that its decision to provide travel entitlements to homosexual partners of ABC staff members on the same basis as spouses, was based on advice given to the Board by its Equal Employment Opportunities Unit that the ABC was required by law to make this decision and that other corporations had so acted; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) noting that the ABC has now admitted orally and in writing to Estimates Committee C that the information on which its decision was based is incorrect and has acknowledged its error;
      </para>
      <para>
       calls on the ABC to immediately reverse its unsound and anti-social decision.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Harradine: I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the Senate, noting that-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) the Governor of Victoria (Dr Davis McCaughey) deliberately chose as the subject for the 23rd Tracy Maud Memorial Lecture the title ``medical Ethics: Who decides what and how?'' which in his speech he describes as ``one of public controversy'';
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) when referring to the question of human embryo experimentation, the Governor in his speech said: ``Even if legislation of a restrictive kind were to receive a majority vote, say in the Senate, or were to reflect public opinion as expressed in a public opinion poll, it would still be questionable whether it would be good democracy to impose it'';
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) Dr Davis McCaughey, in conjunction with another member of the National Health and Medical Research Council's Medical Research Ethics Committee (Dr Robert Jansen, now a director of an IVF clinic in New South Wales) drew up the pro-experimentation guidelines in 1982 which have given rise to so much public concern; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) these guidelines were subjected to the scrutiny of the Senate Select Committee on the Human Embryo Experimentation Bill 1985 which found that the marker event contained in the guidelines before which experimentation on human embryos could take place lacked inherent ethical validity and that the concept contained in those guidelines that the human embryo could be regarded as property, should be rejected,
      </para>
      <para>
       declares that:
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) the statement by the appointed Governor of Victoria, His Excellency Dr Davis McCaughey, which questioned whether it would be good for democracy in effect for executive governments to enforce laws passed by elected Parliaments restricting experiments on human embryos strikes at the heart of our system of Parliamentary democracy and raises fundamental questions as to the role of her Majesty's representatives in Australia,
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) the question of experiments on human embryos is a major matter of public importance which cannot be confined to and determined by selected scientists and ethics committees,
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) insofar as the Governor's statement seeks to undermine an Act of the Victorian Parliament which restricts experiments on human embryos, that is a question for the people of Victoria to determine, and
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) insofar as the Governor's statement relates to Federal legislation to restrict experiments on human embryos, as indeed has been recommended by a Senate Select Committee and the Family Law Council whose reports are now under consideration by the Federal Government, the statement of the Governor of Victoria might understandably be interpreted to be a reflection upon and an attempt to unduly influence the democratic processes of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       CONTINGENT NOTICES OF MOTION
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Harradine: I give contingent notices of motion as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the President proceeding to the placing of business on any day)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Harradine moving a motion relating to the order of business on the Notice Paper.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Senate on any day concluding its consideration of any item of business and prior to the Senate proceeding to the consideration of another item of business)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Harradine moving a motion relating to the conduct of the business of the Senate.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Senate proceeding to the consideration of Government Papers pursuant to Sessional Order)-That so much of the Sessional Order relating to the consideration of Government Papers be suspended as would prevent Senator Harradine moving a motion relating to the order in which the papers are called on by the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under Standing Order 64)-That so much of the Standing Orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Harradine moving an amendment to the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a Bill, or any stage of a Bill, has expired)-That so much of Standing Order 407B be suspended as would prevent further consideration of the Bill, or the stage of the Bill, without limitation of time or for a specified time.
      </para>
      <para>
       (Contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a Bill, or any stage of a Bill, has expired)-That so much of Standing Order 407B be suspended as would prevent the questions being put in respect of any amendments circulated by Senator Harradine, any other Independent Senator, the Australian Democrats, or the Opposition, and that such questions be put accordingly.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="2I4" page="25" party="AD" speaker="Macklin Sen M.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2I4">
         Senator MACKLIN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following notices of motion:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       NOTICES OF MOTION
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Macklin: At the request of Senator Sanders, I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to make provision for terminating the Agreement between the Government of the Commonwealth and the Government of the United States of America relating to the establishment of a Joint Defence Space Research Facility, and for purposes related thereto.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Macklin: Also at the request of Senator Sanders, I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to amend the Customs Act 1901 to give effect to the policy whereby Australia will refuse to allow the supply of Australian uranium to France until France ceases testing nuclear weapons in the South Pacific region.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Macklin: I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to prohibit the passage of nuclear-powered ships, and of vessels carrying nuclear weapons, through Australian waters or in the airspace over them.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Macklin: I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to prohibit the passage of ships carrying nuclear weapons through Australian waters.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Macklin: I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to prohibit the passage of nuclear-powered ships through Australian waters.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Macklin: I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to prohibit the passage of aircraft carrying nuclear weapons through Australian airspace.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Macklin: I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
      </para>
      <para>
       That leave be given to introduce a Bill for an Act to prohibit the exportation of nuclear materials, and for purposes connected therewith.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="26" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      ROTATION OF SENATORS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="26">
      <title>
       Notice of Motion
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="DJ4" page="26" party="LP" speaker="Short Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That, in pursuance of section 13 of the Constitution of the Commonwealth, the Senators chosen for each State be divided into two classes, as follows:
       </para>
       <para>
        The six Senators for each State whose order of election was determined in a re-count of ballot papers pursuant to section 282 of the Commonwealth Electoral Act 1918 and certified by the Australian Electoral Officer for that State shall be Senators of the second class, that is, the long-term Senators, and the remaining six Senators for that State shall be Senators of the first class, that is, the short-term Senators.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="26" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      DAY AND HOUR OF MEETING
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       Motion (by Senator Gareth Evans)-by leave-agreed to:
      </para>
      <para>
       That, unless otherwise ordered-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) the Senate meet on Tuesday, 15 September 1987, from 2 p.m. to 6 p.m. and 7.30 p.m. to 10.30 p.m.;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders, the Senate, on that day, proceed with its ordinary business in the following routine:
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) Petitions,
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) Notices of Motion,
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) Questions,
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) Any proposal pursuant to Standing Order 64,
      </para>
      <para>
       (v) Consideration of Government Papers,
      </para>
      <para>
       (vi) Formal Motions-Discovery of Formal Business,
      </para>
      <para>
       (vii) Postponement and re-arrangement of Business,
      </para>
      <para>
       (viii) Government Business, and
      </para>
      <para>
       (ix) At 7.30 p.m., Budget Statement and Papers 1987-88; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) the provisions of the Sessional Orders which applied at the last sitting of the Senate on 5 June 1987 have effect on 15 September 1987 in relation to:
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) the procedure for the presentation of petitions,
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) proposals pursuant to Standing Order 64,
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) consideration of Government Papers,
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) proceedings on Bills, and
      </para>
      <para>
       (v) adjournment of the Senate.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="26" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      DEATH OF RT HON. SIR BILLY SNEDDEN
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Order! It is with deep regret that I inform the Senate of the death on 27 June 1987 of the Rt Hon. Sir Billy Mackie Snedden, kcmg, qc.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="26" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-I move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate expresses its deep regret at the death, on 27 June 1987, of the Rt Hon. Sir Billy Mackie Snedden, kcmg, qc, member of the House of Representatives for the seat of Bruce from 1955 to 1983, Minister of the Crown from 1966 to 1972, Leader of the Opposition from 1972 to 1975 and Speaker of the House of Representatives from 1976 to 1983; places on record its appreciation of his long and meritorious public service and tenders its profound sympathy to his family in their bereavement.
      </para>
      <para>
       Sir Billy Snedden was born in 1926 in Perth, one of six children. He got involved in politics at a very young age-15 years, I think. After the Second World War, having joined the Liberal Party of Australia in 1944, he took a law degree at the University of Western Australia in Perth. He was admitted to the Bar of the Supreme Court of Western Australia in 1951 and to the Victorian Bar in 1955. He became a Federal member of parliament in 1955, winning the seat of Bruce for the Liberal Party, and he held that seat through successive elections until 1983.
      </para>
      <para>
       I think it is very important to record that during his 28 years of service in the Parliament he held a series of ministerial portfolios, including Attorney-General, Minister for Immigration, Minister for Labour and National Service and the Treasurer. He was the Deputy Leader of the Federal Parliamentary Liberal Party from August 1971 till December 1972 and became its leader and Leader of the Opposition following the 1972 election. He led the Liberal Party at the general election in May 1974, an election which the Liberals lost by five seats-the closest election result since 1961. In March 1975 he lost the Liberal leadership to Mr Malcolm Fraser, and the manner in which he accepted this loss was a tribute to his innate dignity and grace. In February 1976 he became Speaker of the House of Representatives, a position he occupied with dignity and impartiality. It was perhaps as Speaker that he achieved most and made his greatest contribution to the Parliament.
      </para>
      <para>
       Following his retirement he became a company director and served on a number of boards. He was also Chairman of the Melbourne Football Club from 1980 to 1985 and he followed the fortunes of that club, I understand, for many years.
      </para>
      <para>
       Sir Billy Snedden will be remembered as an Australian who gave a lifetime of service to his country, particularly in the parliamentary sphere, and on behalf of the Government I extend to his family our sincere sympathy in their bereavement.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="EF4" page="27" party="LP" speaker="Chaney Sen The Hon F.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="EF4">
         Senator CHANEY
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —On behalf of the Opposition I support the motion of condolence which has been moved by Senator Button on behalf of the Government. Billy Snedden was a person whom many of us worked with, knew well and were friendly with, and there is a great deal of sorrow among us at his death. He was, I think, a quintessential Australian success story, having had to leave school early as the last in a large family and his father having died when he was still a boy. He became a law clerk and then joined the Royal Australian Air Force as soon as his age permitted during the Second World War. I think he saw only training before the war ended. He then went to university and completed his law degree.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       From the earliest time after leaving university he made it clear that he intended Parliament to be his future. He ran for the State Parliament in the seat of Boulder, which I think experts such as Senator Robert Ray would tell us is not a seat for a Liberal to aspire to. He subsequently contested Fremantle against Kim Beazley Sr in the 1949 election and then in the subsequent election contested Mr Tom Burke for the seat of Perth. So by the age of 24 he had contested three elections. He then went off and tried his hand, I think, at being a public servant for a brief time. But he later obtained the seat of Bruce in Victoria in 1955.
      </para>
      <para>
       I first knew Bill Snedden from that time because he went into the same Parliament as my father. They were close friends. Indeed, they shared a room, I think, on the upper floor of the building. I think it was U41 which was known as the submarine. I think they had a lot more fun in Parliament then than we do now and certainly it was the scene of a lot of touch football, poker and general revelry. I certainly knew him as a very cheerful compatriot of my father's.
      </para>
      <para>
       He had a very quick rise in politics. He became the Attorney-General when he was still in his thirties. Indeed, that was my next contact with him. On my first circuit in New Guinea I went to the western southern highlands with the then Attorney-General when he was looking at the administration of justice in that territory. He went on to be the Minister for Immigration, heading a department in which he had served in a relatively junior capacity in Australia and Rome. He later became Minister for Labour and National Service and ultimately became the Treasurer in the McMahon Government. He was the Leader of the House, the Deputy Leader of his Party and, ultimately, the Leader of the Liberal Party and the Leader of the Opposition after the 1972 election.
      </para>
      <para>
       His was a very distinguished career. He was a man who is much remembered for being friendly and personable. He was the Leader of my Party when I came to this Parliament, and I must say that it was at that time that I formed the view that he had made a very great contribution to the Liberal Party. The defeat of the Party in 1972 was fairly demoralising after a very long period in government. As a member of the organisation, I saw the way he set about rebuilding the fortunes of the Liberal Party, involving not just the parliamentary Party but the Party organisation around Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       Whilst I agree with the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button) that Sir Billy's career was very appropriately capped by his distinguished period as the Speaker of the House, I think he made two major contributions. One was his contribution as Speaker and the other was his contribution to the restoration of the fortunes of the Liberal Party. He was, some thought-indeed, many thought-very unlucky not to win the 1974 election. He went within a hair's breadth of becoming the Prime Minister of this country. As history shows, he lost the leadership of his Party in 1975 to a challenge by Malcolm Fraser. It was my belief at that time, and it remains my belief, that Malcolm Fraser took over a party which was in very much better shape than it had been when Bill Snedden assumed the leadership of it in late 1972, and I believe that Bill Snedden was a substantial contributor to the restoration of the Liberal Government in this country.
      </para>
      <para>
       I agree, however, with the Leader of the Government that, in his accession to the speakership in 1976, Sir Billy Snedden's career found a particularly apt crowning. I often used to think, Mr President, that there was a parallel between Douglas McClelland and Bill Snedden in that each served as Ministers, although Doug McClelland I think in only one portfolio and for a briefer time. I thought that they both shared the distinction of being very well suited by both political background and temperament to the Presiding Officer's position. I, whilst not being able to see at first hand the work of the Speaker, heard nothing but good reports about Bill Snedden's capacity to defuse difficult situations with his humour, and I think that the job that he was able to do as Speaker was the result of his very wide political experience and his very great human experience.
      </para>
      <para>
       I deeply regret his death. My last conversation with him in Sydney was in terms of the dinner we would shortly share in Melbourne. I know that right around Australia his many friends grieve his death. I remember his two great political contributions with very great respect, and I hope that the memory of his contribution to Australian politics will be a consolation to his family on their losing him. On behalf of the Opposition I express our sympathy to them. Bill Snedden was our friend as well as our political colleague and we very much regret his death.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="1H4" page="28" party="AD" speaker="Haines Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="1H4">
         Senator HAINES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —On behalf of the Australian Democrats I would like to support the motion moved by the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button). Sir Billy Snedden's untimely death not only brought great personal sadness to the many people who knew and admired him but also was a great loss to the country he served so untiringly. His public and parliamentary career showed quite clearly how his many talents were utilised to the benefit of Australia. From the time he first entered parliament in 1955 he was obviously a man destined for higher office, and that promise was realised in the offices he held later in his career. His ministerial appointments included Attorney-General, Minister for Immigration, Minister for Labour and National Service and Treasurer, and in all of these he acquitted himself with great distinction and ability. His service on committees and his representation of his country at a wide range of international conferences also revealed a man with broad interests and a firm commitment to the concerns of ordinary Australians.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       As Senator Chaney has already indicated, Sir Billy, of course, came from a relatively humble background, and it speaks volumes for his character that he never forgot ordinary people when his own career advanced so rapidly. I suggest it is a pity that more people in this place do not take after Sir Billy in that regard.
      </para>
      <para>
       That advancement led him to the leadership of his own Party at a time, again as Senator Chaney mentioned, of some considerable difficulty for that Party. His conciliatory approach and ability to bring people together did a great deal to heal the breaches that had developed. I have no doubt that members of the Liberal Party of Australia recognise and acknowledge the very significant debt they owe him for this.
      </para>
      <para>
       Personally, of course, Sir Billy was an amiable, charming man with extensive interests outside the Parliament. His close links with ethnic communities around Australia went back to his service as an immigration officer during the 1950s and he maintained those links throughout his life. He was particularly close to the Italian community and was a fluent speaker of the Italian language. Another great passion of his, of course, was the Melbourne Football Club and it brought him enormous pleasure when he became its chairman. Shortly after Sir Billy's death-indeed, on the night before his funeral-I had the privilege of meeting some of his old friends from the club at a restaurant in Melbourne. Ross Mitchell, Stuart Spencer and Geoff Case were among a group dining at Masani's, which I understand was one of Sir Billy's favourite restaurants. They asked me to join them in their farewell to Sir Billy. The strength of feeling at that gathering was a moving testimony to Sir Billy's capacity for friendship in all spheres of life. I was enormously touched to have been made a part of it.
      </para>
      <para>
       The honours heaped on Sir Billy during his lifetime gave some indication of the debt we owe him: a member of her Majesty's Privy Council; a Knight Commander of the Order of St Michael and St George; and, finally, his election as Speaker of the House of Representatives. To this latter role he brought dignity and an eloquent argument for its independence. He served in it with great distinction and was deservedly admired on both sides of the House. His death was a great loss both to his many friends and to this country. I would like to join other speakers in extending the Australian Democrats' deep sympathy to his widow Joy-Lady Snedden-and his children.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="LJ4" page="28" party="NP" speaker="Stone Sen J.O.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LJ4">
         Senator STONE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the National Party of Australia)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I would like to support the motion moved by the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button). Bill Snedden was a Western Australian, as I was originally. I first knew him at the University of Western Australia when I became, as he did, a member of the council of the Guild of Undergraduates at that university, an institution which I think is normally known on this side of the continent as the student representative council. He was already involved at that stage, as I was not, in student politics. As Senator Chaney has said, he went on at a very early age to involve himself in real politics. After leaving the university he became an officer of the Department of Immigration and was a selection officer for three years in, I think, Rome and London before returning to Australia where he took up residence in Melbourne and, like some others, became a member of parliament for an electorate outside his birth place.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       He rose steadily in the ranks of the Liberal Party of Australia. He became Attorney-General in 1963 or thereabouts at the relatively young age of 36. After that he served for a time as Minister for Immigration and, of course, then also served as Minister for Labour and National Service. In March 1971, when Mr Gorton lost the leadership of his party and the prime ministership, the leadership of the Liberal Party was contested by Bill Snedden. I think it is interesting to reflect upon the rather different course that Australian politics might have taken had he been successful in that election for the leadership of the Liberal Party which, Mr President, you will recall was won by Mr McMahon. He became, in default of gaining the leadership and the prime ministership, Treasurer, and in that capacity I first worked for him as an official in the Treasury for nearly two years.
      </para>
      <para>
       I have several personal memories of that period. I remember accompanying him on a trip to London in the course of which I committed an indiscretion-I will not bore the Senate with the details of it-which was of some embarrassment to Bill Snedden. After properly reprimanding me he forgave me entirely and it was a tribute to his capacity as a human being and as a man that he behaved in that way to one of his officials at the time. I was also privileged to get off an aircraft with him in London a few months later. We were met, as Ministers are in those circumstances, as you know, Mr President, by the protocol people from the Foreign Office, who handed him a letter from the Chancellor of the Exchequer informing him that he had been appointed to the Privy Council-an appointment of which he was very proud.
      </para>
      <para>
       He brought down only two Budgets, which is somewhat more than some of his successors, and after the defeat of the Liberal Party in 1972 he became, as has been said, leader of that party for just over two years. He became Speaker of the House of Representatives and was knighted in 1978. In later years he was, I am sorry to say, estranged from his wife, Joy, a fine woman, to whom I offer my sincere condolences.
      </para>
      <para>
       It would not be appropriate to conclude these remarks without referring to Bill Snedden's great love for the Melbourne Football Club. This has already been mentioned, particularly by Senator Haines. It is a shame that he died before seeing his team first of all make its way into the final five and then play so superbly, both against North Melbourne and then last Saturday against the Sydney Swans. Had Bill Snedden seen those two games he would have died happy.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="VJ4" page="29" party="LP" speaker="Watson Sen J.O.W.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="VJ4">
         Senator WATSON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I wish to be associated with this condolence motion for a great friend, Sir Billy Mackie Snedden. He was a unique man in many respects. He was the first Leader of the Liberal Party to become Speaker of the House. As Leader of the Liberal Party, Bill Snedden was the first to really recognise the importance of Tasmania. He was the first leader on either side of politics to appoint a shadow Minister for Tasmania, recognising our special difficulties and our unique position in the Commonwealth. He deliberately visited Tasmania on many occasions not only for official events but also to gauge the views of the man in the street. It was this common touch which characterised Sir Billy throughout his career in public life.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       He rose from very humble beginnings in Western Australia to become a prominent Queen's Counsel, a knight of the realm and a Speaker who was recognised by the Times of London as one of the best the British Commonwealth has ever seen. Billy Snedden was elected to the seat of Bruce in 1955 and was re-elected 11 times. It is significant that he retired from Parliament of his own choice: such was his popular regard in his electorate. He was a man who was truly popular on both sides of the House and will be greatly missed. It is significant that he chose liberalism in which to make his career despite the fact that some believed his origins dictated otherwise. This showed that the Menzies philosophy of the Liberal Party as a party for all with ability was well-founded. This illustrated his distinguished career not only in the Parliament but also in the law and, after his retirement, in the world of business. He was a great parliamentarian and a great man and I personally will miss him.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="29" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I wish to associate myself with the comments that have been made by other senators on this condolence motion for a person who was a very good friend of mine. I seem to recall that I first met Billy Snedden when we on the executive of the Australian Council of Trade Unions had discussions with him when he was Minister for Labour and National Service. I think that was about 1969. I did not really get to know Bill Snedden very well until I came to the Parliament and when he became the Speaker of the House of Representatives. He chaired quite a number of meetings of committees of which I was a member or at which I was present for some reason. I was most impressed with the fair attitude that he displayed at those meetings. One aspect of his career which has not been emphasised to a great extent in speeches on this condolence motion was the necessary work that he did, with fellow parliamentarians, on behalf of this Parliament and of parliamentary institutions throughout the world. I wish to associate myself with the condolence motion and express sympathy to his widow and family.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="BJ4" page="30" party="NP" speaker="Sheil Sen G.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BJ4">
         Senator SHEIL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I rise to add my voice to support this motion of condolence to the family and relatives of Sir Billy Snedden. Of course, I knew of him for many years before I actually met him. In 1974 I was late in being sworn into the Parliament. The Parliament was already sitting by the time I got here. He was Leader of the Opposition and so he was the first person to welcome me to Parliament House. He was most civil, accommodating and considerate in doing so, and I have never forgotten it. He was a lone figure sitting at the top table in the joint party room and I remember noticing that he had one of the nicest fountain pens I had ever seen in my life, so I knew immediately that he was a man of discernment.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="4F4" speaker="Senator Button">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator Button
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thought you were going to say that you stole it.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BJ4">
         Senator SHEIL
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —No. I came to know him quite well during our term together here. He became one of my parliamentary patients-and, I must say, one of the more successful ones. He always seemed to get better when I looked after him. He became one of the dynamic members of our parliamentary tennis team-a game which he enjoyed as I do.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Sir Billy seemed to come from a more genteel age of courtesy, kindness and consideration. He always acted with a sense of fair play and he seemed to expect it in return, which is probably not one of the best attributes to have in this Parliament. When he did become disillusioned it seemed to sit fairly easily on his shoulders. I served under him on many parliamentary committees. He was always most competent, erudite and politically aware of a lot of things. I am sure committee members were happy to learn from his vast experience, particularly in foreign affairs but also on the Joint House Committee where he was a great instructor for us.
      </para>
      <para>
       As has already been said, he acquitted himself very well as Speaker of the House. He acquitted Australia equally well, particularly in the international forums of presiding officers of the parliaments. He made tremendous contributions which have been recorded in the magazine The Parliamentarian. I recommend those articles to all honourable senators to read. I know that they have been matters for consideration in debates on parliamentary procedures in nearly all the Western democracies. Of course, he made some pioneering contributions to the issue of the broadcasting and televising of parliament. These contributions are currently being considered within this Parliament. He was a gentleman of great talent. I am honoured and proud to have known him and I am sure that all honourable senators will wish to express their feeling of sympathy for his relatives.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="TH4" page="30" party="LP" speaker="Knowles Sen S.C.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="TH4">
         Senator KNOWLES
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I also wish to support the motion of condolence moved by the Government. The qualities that I most remember about Sir Billy Mackie Snedden are his sincerity, his kindness and, of course, his good humour. These qualities endeared him to a great number of Australians and, particularly, Western Australians. In particular he holds a special place in the memories of different generations of Young Liberals. In a crucial period in Liberal Party history, in 1949-50, Sir Billy Snedden was President of the Young Liberal Movement in Western Australia. He was not only an active and very successful President in the division at that time, but also a campaigner of courage and absolute tenacity. As we have heard already this afternoon, in 1948 he fought a by-election in the Australian Labor Party stronghold of Boulder in the goldfields, a seat where Labor had seldom been challenged, but it took Billy Mackie Snedden to take on that seat. In the 1949 Federal election he carried the Liberal banner in Fremantle and gained a solid 43 per cent of the vote against Mr Kim Beazley Sr.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       In the following election in 1951 he failed to win the seat of Perth by only 114 votes after a very hard fought campaign, and by a narrow chance of history he failed to establish a parliamentary career in his State of origin; but I must admit that he never neglected Western Australia. As a Young Liberal branch President and later as State President in Western Australia during the 1970s, I can never forget the encouragement that Sir Billy gave the Young Liberal Movement. He was never too busy to attend State conventions and generally offer his assistance to the up and coming Liberals of tomorrow. During this time he was serving as a distinguished Speaker in the House of Representatives. He had that gift of compelling respect, without displaying arrogance, both inside and outside the Parliament.
      </para>
      <para>
       Western Australians remember Sir Billy as the last Party Leader to address a meeting in Forrest Place in 1974, before it was closed as a political forum. He was unlucky not to become Prime Minister and Australians were also unlucky that he never had the opportunity to bring his very special qualities to that office. Sir Billy, as we have heard already, was the member for Bruce in Victoria, from the creation of the seat in 1955 until his retirement in 1983, but it was never a Liberal stronghold. I think to his credit he was a very conscientious campaigner for the more marginal seats throughout Australia, even at times when opinion polls and pundits were saying that he would be lucky to hold on to his own seat. His loyalty to the cause which he had embraced as a young man never faded after his loss of the Party leadership, and in this also he provided a very fine example to members of his Party and, I believe, to all Australians.
      </para>
      <para>
       Cynics may say that decency and humanity are a discount in politics. The respect in which we hold Sir Billy Snedden proves them absolutely wrong. I extend my sympathy to all his family.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NT" nameid="6E4" page="31" party="NP" speaker="Tambling Sen G.E.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6E4">
         Senator TAMBLING
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Northern Territory)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Sir Billy Snedden was a unique and special friend of the Northern Territory. I shared his friendship as a politician and I know that many other Territorians in many walks of life, from politics through to industry, also shared his support and encouragement. Sir Billy Snedden was also a great supporter of the Northern Territory's march forward for self-government. In many capacities he encouraged and supported many in the long fight that the Northern Territory has taken to advance its own causes in the political arena. He gave particular support to self-government and indeed followed that up as Speaker in a great way in the early years. After Cyclone Tracy Sir Billy Snedden showed a very compassionate and genuine concern for the people of Darwin. He was there very early after the event of Cyclone Tracy and he followed that through in the interest and concern that he showed the Darwin people.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       I would like to back up the comments of several other senators about the interest and support that Sir Billy always showed younger people. I have very fond memories of campaigning with him in a Legislative Assembly election in Darwin in 1977, when he insisted not only on going into the public forums and the major debates in public meetings but on adding to his itinerary special attention and special care and concern for the particular interests of primary school children. I join with others in extending sympathy to his family.
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I invite honourable senators to signify their assent to the motion by standing in silence.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Question resolved in the affirmative, honourable senators standing in their places.
       </para>
      </interject>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thank the Senate.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Motion (by Senator Button) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para>
        That, as a mark of respect to the memory of the deceased, the Senate do now adjourn.
       </para>
       <para>
        Senate adjourned at 5.45 p.m.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="31" type="Papers">
     <title>
      PAPERS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The following papers were tabled:
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Heritage Protection Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 153.
      </para>
      <para>
       Air Navigation (Charges) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 131.
      </para>
      <para>
       Audit Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 Nos 150, 168, 169.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Bureau of Statistics-
      </para>
      <para>
       Survey of Electricity and Fuels.
      </para>
      <para>
       List of names and addresses of major mining, manufacturing and electricity/gas production establishments for the bureau of resource economics.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian National University Act-Statute No. 195-University House Amendment No. 11.
      </para>
      <para>
       Banks (Shareholdings) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 Nos 126, 127.
      </para>
      <para>
       Bounty (Ship Repair) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 117.
      </para>
      <para>
       Bounty (Ships) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 116.
      </para>
      <para>
       Cheques and Payment Orders Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 130.
      </para>
      <para>
       Cocos (Keeling) Islands Act-Ordinance 1987-No. 1-Muslims.
      </para>
      <para>
       Commonwealth Electoral Act and Referendum (Machinery Provisions) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 Nos 118, 119.
      </para>
      <para>
       Commonwealth Teaching Service Act-Determinations 1987 Nos 1 and 2.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies (Acquisition of Shares) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 148.
      </para>
      <para>
       Criminology Research Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 167.
      </para>
      <para>
       Currency Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 142.
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Notices 1987-Nos 6-7-specified rate in respect to the diesel fuel rebate, dated 16 July 1987 and 13 August 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 Nos 115, 124, 140, 156, 162.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Force Remuneration Tribunal-Determination 1987 No. 5 and reasons, dated 10 July 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       Determinations 1987-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 39-Charge for Rations and Quarters.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 40-Overseas Living Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 41-Settling In and Settling Out Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 42-Travelling Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 43-Overseas Living Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 44-Settling In and Settling Out Allowance and Medical and Hospital Expenses of a Member's Family Overseas.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 45-Living Out Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 46-Sea-going Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 47-Education Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 48-Travelling Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 49-Reserve Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 50-Travelling Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 51-Travelling Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 52-Representation Allowance and Entertainment Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 53-Outfit Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 54-Overseas Living Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 55-Overseas Living Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 56-Travelling Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules No. 113.
      </para>
      <para>
       Departure Tax Collection Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 Nos 112, 159.
      </para>
      <para>
       Dried Vine Fruits Equalization Levy Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 136.
      </para>
      <para>
       Egg Industry Research (Hen Quota) Levy Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 133.
      </para>
      <para>
       Epidemiological Studies (Confidentiality) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 164.
      </para>
      <para>
       Excise Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Declarations (4) in respect of rebate and amount of rebate in respect of Bass Strait Oil, dated 12 May 1987, 10 June 1987, July 1987 and 12 August 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       Notices 1987-Nos 6-7-specified rate in respect to the diesel fuel rebate, dated 16 July 1987 and 13 August 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 Nos 123, 161.
      </para>
      <para>
       Export Control Act-Export Control (Orders) Regulations-Orders 1987-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-Export Meat Orders as amended (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 8-Export Control (Processed Fruits and Vegetables) Orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 9-Export Control (Fresh Fruits and Vegetables) Orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 10-Export Control (Fresh Fruits and Vegetables) Orders (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 11-Export Control (Fees) orders as amended (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 13-Prescribed Goods (General) Orders as amended (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       Fisheries Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Fisheries Notices 1987-
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 183, 184, 185-Prohibition on the taking of prawns off Northern Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 186-Prohibition of trawling in waters west of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       Nos 187, 188, 189-Prohibition of trawling in waters south of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 135.
      </para>
      <para>
       Futures Industry Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 111.
      </para>
      <para>
       Health Insurance Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 Nos 160, 163, 166.
      </para>
      <para>
       Health Insurance Commission Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 165.
      </para>
      <para>
       Home and Community Care Act-Variation to the Agreement between the Commonwealth of Australia and-
      </para>
      <para>
       New South Wales, made on 23 January 1986, dated 4 June 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       Northern Territory, made on 21 October 1985, dated 25 June 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       South Australia, made on 18 September 1985, dated 3 June 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasmania, made on 3 October 1985, dated 4 June 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       Western Australia, made on 17 October 1985, dated 16 June 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       Income Tax Assessment Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 120.
      </para>
      <para>
       Interstate Road Transport Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 141.
      </para>
      <para>
       Lands Acquisition Act-Statements (3) by the Minister describing lands acquired by agreement under subsection 7 (1).
      </para>
      <para>
       Meat Inspection Act-Meat Inspection (Orders) Regulations-Orders 1987-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-Meat Inspection (South Australia).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-Meat Inspection (Fees) as amended (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-Meat Inspection (General) as amended (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 125.
      </para>
      <para>
       National Companies and Securities Commission Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 128.
      </para>
      <para>
       National Parks and Wildlife Conservation Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 139.
      </para>
      <para>
       Navigation Act-Navigation (Orders) Regulations-Marine Orders 1987-No. 4-Part 23 (Equipment-Miscellaneous and Safety Measures).
      </para>
      <para>
       Patents Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 138.
      </para>
      <para>
       Postal Services Act-Postal By-laws 1987-
      </para>
      <para>
       Postal Amendment No. 3.
      </para>
      <para>
       Postal Amendment No. 4.
      </para>
      <para>
       Protection of Movable Cultural Heritage Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 149.
      </para>
      <para>
       Public Service Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Determinations 1987 Nos 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 49, 50, 51, 52, 53, 54, 55, 56, 57, 58, 59, 60, 61, 62, 63, 64, 65, 66, 68, 69, 70, 71.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 Nos 137, 157.
      </para>
      <para>
       Radiocommunications Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 Nos 151, 152.
      </para>
      <para>
       Rural Industries Research Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 134.
      </para>
      <para>
       Seamen's War Pensions and Allowances Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 121.
      </para>
      <para>
       Seat of Government (Administration) Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Determination made under the Health Authority Ordinance, dated 10 July 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       Ordinances 1987-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 21-Legal Practitioners (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 22-Tobacco Products (Health Warnings) (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 23-Health Authority (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 24-Workmen's Compensation (Amendment) (No. 2).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 25-Agents (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 26-Child Welfare (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 27-Children's Services (Miscellaneous Amendments) (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 28-Children's Services (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 29-Children's Flammable Nightwear (Repeal).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 30-Remand Centres (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 31-Australian Capital Territory Gaming and Liquor Authority.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 32-Betting (Totalizator Agency) (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 33-Liquor (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 34-Gaming Machine.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 35-Unlawful games (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 36-Housing Assistance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 37-Administrative Arrangements (Consequential Amendments).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 38-Business Franchise (Tobacco and Petroleum Products) (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 39-Stamp Duties and Taxes.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 40-Payroll Tax.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 41-Taxation (Administration).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 42-Co-operative Societies (Amendment) (No. 3).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 43-Financial Institutions Duty.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 44-Imperial Acts Application (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 45-Imperial Acts (Substituted Provisions) (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations 1987-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-Motor Vehicle (Third Party Insurance) (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-Children's Services.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 7-Gaming Machine.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 8-Liquor (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 9-Remand Centres (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 10-Business Franchise (Tobacco and Petroleum Products) (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       Securities Industry Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 129.
      </para>
      <para>
       Sex Discrimination Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 158.
      </para>
      <para>
       States Grants (Petroleum Products) Act-Amendments (4) to the schedules to the subsidy scheme in relation to the States, dated 16 June 1987 (2), 6 July 1987 and 17 July 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       Superannuation Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 Nos 114, 155.
      </para>
      <para>
       Telecommunications Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       By-laws-
      </para>
      <para>
       Telecommunications (Charging Zones and Charging Districts) Amendment No. 78.
      </para>
      <para>
       Telecommunications (Community Calls) Amendment No. 49.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulation-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 154.
      </para>
      <para>
       Veterans' Entitlements Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 122.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wool Marketing Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 132.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wool Tax Act (No. 1)-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 143.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wool Tax Act (No. 2)-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 144.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wool Tax Act (No. 3)-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 145.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wool Tax Act (No. 4)-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 146.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wool Tax Act (No. 5)-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1987 No. 147.
      </para>
      <para>
       Governor-General's Proclamations-Commencement of Acts: Proclamations by His Excellency the Governor-General are tabled, notifying that His Excellency had proclaimed the following Acts and sections of Acts to come into operation on the dates specified:
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Land (Lake Condah and Framlingham Forest) Act 1987-Provisions other than Part I- 1 July 1987 (Gazette No. S 157, 30 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Heritage Protection Amendment Act 1987-10 July 1987 (Gazette No. S 171, 7 July 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Capital Territory Gaming and Liquor Authority Act 1981-Repeal of the Act made by Statute Law (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act (No. 1) 1983-30 June 1987 (Gazette No. S 161, 30 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Institute of Health Act 1987-1 July 1987 (Gazette No. S 144, 26 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Bank Account Debits Tax Amendment Act 1987-Sections 7 and 8, and sub-section 9 (2)-1 September 1987 (Gazette No. S 191, 30 July 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Broadcasting (Ownership and Control) Act 1987-Provisions other than sections 1, 2, 15, 28, 33, 34, 35 and 36-1 July 1987; sections 15 and 28- 1 October 1987 (Gazette No. S 136, 23 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Cheques and Payment Orders Act 1986-1 July 1987 (Gazette No. S 131, 23 June 1987
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs and Excise Legislation Amendment Act 1987-Subsections 3 (2) and (3) and sections 8 to 16 (inclusive)-1 August 1987 (Gazette No. S 135, 23 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Disability Services Act 1986-5 June 1987 (Gazette No. S 110, 4 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Environment Protection (Impact of Proposals) Amendment Act 1987-1 June 1987 (Gazette No. S 106, 1 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Equal Employment Opportunity (Commonwealth Authorities) Act 1987-1 July 1987 (Gazette No. S 142, 26 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Health Legislation Amendment Act 1986-Sub- section 4 (1), sections 11, 15, 17 and 18, sub-section 19 (1) and sections 22, 24, 26 to 44 (inclusive), 48, 49 and 54-1 August 1987 (Gazette No. S 195, 31 July 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Jurisdiction of Courts (Miscellaneous Amendments) Act 1987-Amendments made by that Act to the Acts specified in the Schedule to that Act-1 September 1987 (Gazette No. S 217, 24 August 1987
      </para>
      <para>
       Pig Industry Act 1986-Provisions other than Part I, Divisions 1 and 9 of Part II and part IV-1 August 1987 (Gazette No. S 194, 31 July 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Protection of Movable Cultural Heritage Act 1986-I July 1987 (Gazette No. S 138, 25 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Public Lending Right Act 1985-1 July 1987 (Gazette No. S 131, 23 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Public Service Legislation (Streamlining) Act 1986-Section 20, subsection 22 (2), sections 36, 38 to 41 and 44, subsections 45 (1) and (3) and sections 46, 102, 105, 110 and 112-14 June 1987 (Gazette No. S 125, 12 June 1987); section 43, subsection 45 (2), sections 70 to 76, 78, 87, 113, 115 and 116, subsection 122 (2) and sections 123, 125, 129 and 131-20 July 1987 (Gazette No. S 178, 15 July 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Social Security Legislation Amendment Act 1983-Amendments of the Social Security Act 1947  made by items 1 to 9 (inclusive) and 16 in Schedule 1 to the Social Security Legislation Amendment Act 1983-1 July 1987 (Gazette No. S 146, 26 June 1987)
      </para>
      <para>
       Statute Law (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act (No. 1) 1983-See-Australian Capital Territory Gaming and Liquor Authority Act 1981
      </para>
      <para>
       Taxation Laws Amendment Act (No. 2) 1987-part VIII-1 August 1987 (Gazette No. S 191, 30 July 1987).
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
   </chamber.xscript>
  </hansard>
 </body>
</html>
