<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" "hansard.dtd">
<html>
 <body>
  <hansard chamber="Senate" date="18/09/1990" page="2499" parliament.no="36" period.no="2" proof="No" session.no="1">
   <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
     <day.start date="18/09/1990">
      Tuesday, 18 September 1990
     </day.start>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Colston) took the chair at 2 p.m., and read prayers.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </business.start>
    <debate page="2499" type="Ministerial Arrangements">
     <title>
      MINISTERIAL ARRANGEMENTS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2499" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-I inform the Senate that the Minister for Administrative Services, Senator Bolkus, will be absent from the chamber for the remainder of this week. Senator Bolkus is attending the official opening of the new Australian Embassy building and other portfolio related engagements in Japan. Any questions which would normally be directed to Senator Bolkus in relation to his portfolio and those he represents should be directed to Senator Cook.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <qwn page="2499">
     <title>
      QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
     </title>
     <question.block page="2499">
      <title>
       BUSINESS LEADERS: COMMENTS BY TREASURER
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="2499" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BH4">
          Senator HILL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Leader of the Government in the Senate. I ask: Does the Minister support yesterday's blanket condemnation of Australian business leaders by the Treasurer?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2499" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not know whether the word `blanket' is the right word to use on this occasion. I certainly support some criticisms which have been made of the business community by a variety of people. For example, I support some criticisms of the banks on the basis that their interest rate policies have not reflected a relaxation in monetary policy. I support some criticisms of business organisations in that they do not seem to be able to get a single view about major issues confronting Australian business.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="KI4" speaker="Senator Parer">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="KI4">
           Senator Parer
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Of course they don't.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Parer says, by way of interjection, `Of course they don't'. I suppose he is in favour in this rare case of letting 100 flowers bloom. But 100 flowers blooming in Australian business organisations is not necessarily the best outcome for a sensible contribution from business to a whole range of issues such as wages policy, industry policy generally, and so on. I think Senator Parer will find that many business leaders share that view.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I am not about sharing blanket condemnations of the business community but I think there are some reasons for criticism of the business community, just as there are legitimate reasons for the business community to criticise governments from time to time.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2499">
      <title>
       SYDNEY AIRPORT: THIRD RUNWAY
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="5K4" page="2499" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Can the Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support inform the Senate of the time and date of the release of the environmental impact statement (EIS) on the proposed third runway at Sydney (Kingsford-Smith) Airport? Can the Minister explain the factors that have led to the delay in the release of the EIS?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="2499" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The environmental impact statement will be publicly released in Sydney at the Powerhouse Museum at 3 o'clock tomorrow afternoon. It will be gazetted for public examination on the 20th of this month and the three-month period will be allowed to run from that date. I have in fact explained to the chamber before the reason for the delay in the original timetable that was established by the Government for this EIS, and it largely relates to the need for this document to be as exhaustive and as quality a document as possible. The delays were principally caused by the need to establish technical baseline data particularly in respect of the noise impact studies which I confidently predict will be a major item for debate in the next three months. It was also necessary to examine the planning strategy for Sydney Airport which was released just recently and prepared for the Federal Airports Corporation by a different firm of consultants in order to examine the traffic implications and strategies contained in that document, and that principally is the reason for the delay.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Requests have been made for the public examination period to be extended on the basis of what was said to be additional time given to Kinhill Engineers Pty Ltd for cleaning up their figures-or words to that effect. That assertion is simply not correct. The delay was caused for the reason that I have given. I cannot logically understand why the period that has elapsed for the preparation of the document itself is in any way related to the time that is now to be allowed for public scrutiny of it. Indeed, the statutory requirement under the Act for public examination is 28 days, and the Government in recognising the controversial nature of this EIS-and it will be subject to a great deal of debate-has allowed three times that statutory requirement for examination.
       </para>
       <para>
        I notice that the preliminary skirmishing on this issue has already begun. I said to Senator Faulkner earlier this morning that one of the reasons for the delay was that I had put in a last-minute bid to have the third runway replanned to go through the middle of his living room, but that was only in jest. The preliminary skirmishing has begun because it is an important issue that has serious implications for the people of Sydney whose needs should be considered and not simply brushed aside, and the wider implications of this airport as Australia's most important national and international airport. I have not the slightest doubt that there will be a vigorous debate with all of the issues thoroughly canvassed. I dare say some of it will probably seep into here over the next three months, and I look forward, as the Minister responsible, to participating in that debate.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="5K4" page="2499" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I ask a supplementary question. Given the complexities of the issues involved, will the Minister agree to extend the three-month period for public comment after the release of the EIS?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="2499" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is definitely going to go through the middle of the living room now. I have addressed that matter, but I just say again that I cannot logically understand the argument that, because additional time was required by the consultants to prepare the EIS, that should therefore of itself extend the time allowed for public examination of the document. I have a number of friends who have taken between three years and five years to put doctor of philosophy theses together but it certainly did not take that long for the examiners to assess them. I do not see how the two things are connected.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        As I said before, 28 days is allowed as the minimum requirement under the Act, and indeed the Government could have proceeded to have simply allowed that 28 days. The Government deliberately decided to extend that by a factor of three, because of what we acknowledge to be the intense interest in this particular debate, and I see absolutely no reason for that period to be extended.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2500">
      <title>
       CHILD-CARE WORKERS
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="LD4" page="2500" party="LP" speaker="Alston Sen R.K.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is to the Minister representing the Minister for Community Services and Health. I refer the Minister to last Friday's decision by the Industrial Relations Commission which awarded child-care workers up to 40 per cent wage increases, and the subsequent comments by both the President of the Victorian Child-Care Association, Mrs Anne Young, and the Federal senior executive of the Australian Federation of Child-Care Associations, Mr Chris Buck, who claims that child-care fees will rise by as much as $45 per week. In light of this, and in view of the fact that Australian Council of Trade Unions (ACTU) President, Martin Ferguson, indicated on Friday that talks would be sought with the Government about the impact of child-care subsidies, does the Minister concede that the Government will be forced to increase child-care subsidies? Has such an increase been taken into account in the Government's Budget Forward Estimates for child-care expenditure? If not, is the Minister concerned that many working parents, as a result of the Industrial Relations Commission decision, will no longer be able to afford child-care and that many smaller child-care operations will be unable to absorb the increased costs and will therefore be forced to close?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="2500" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The series of questions asked by Senator Alston deserve a very full answer. Therefore, I propose to ask the Minister for Community Services and Health to provide that full answer to the many parts of the question which Senator Alston quite correctly raised but which obviously from my brief I cannot completely and comprehensively answer.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="LD4" page="2500" party="LP" speaker="Alston Sen R.K.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="LD4">
          Senator ALSTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I ask a supplementary question. This decision has been regarded on almost all sides as a landmark decision. Is the Minister telling the Senate that in the intervening four days he has not taken any briefing on the subject and is not able to provide any further enlightenment to the Senate about the implications of this decision?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="2500" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is because I regard the question as such an important one that I will seek to obtain a very full answer from the Minister. I think that will be more satisfactory from the point of view of the chamber.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2501">
      <title>
       ARCHER BEND NATIONAL PARK
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="XI4" page="2501" party="ALP" speaker="Reynolds Sen The Hon M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XI4">
          Senator REYNOLDS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Can the Minister representing the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs report on negotiations between the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and the Queensland Government regarding the management of the Archer Bend National Park to better recognise the role of the traditional Aboriginal owners?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="2501" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —In 1982 John Koowarta and his community, at what was then Archer River Station, won a very significant victory in the High Court of Australia which forced the Queensland Government to register the transfer of title from this former pastoral lease to that community. Subsequently, the then Bjelke-Petersen Queensland Government robbed those people of that victory in declaring the entire area to be a national park. Since the change of government in Queensland, the Minister for Aboriginal Affairs has had discussions with Mr Goss, the Premier of Queensland, and with John Koowarta and his community.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The current position is that the Queensland Premier-in my view not surprisingly-is not minded to change the status of a national park now that it has been declared, for whatever reason, but is certainly prepared to consider very closely what can be done to formally recognise the rights of the Aboriginal community whose traditional land it is and who did win that very significant victory in 1982 that was later thwarted by the political actions of the then Government. The kinds of proposals that are currently being considered in these discussions are the possibility of lease back arrangements in the national park. That would be based on similar arrangements that currently operate at Uluru and Kakadu national parks in the Northern Territory.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2501">
      <title>
       MIRAGE AIRCRAFT: SALE TO PAKISTAN
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="8G4" page="2501" party="LP" speaker="Durack Sen The Hon P.D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8G4">
          Senator DURACK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to his remarks at a press conference in Islamabad on 5 August 1990 about the sale of Mirage jets to Pakistan. The Minister said:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        . . . if hostilities should seem more imminent than they do at the moment-
       </para>
       <para>
        that is, between the two countries of Pakistan and India-
       </para>
       <para>
        then Australia would review the terms of the contract-
       </para>
       <para>
        for the sale of the Mirage-
       </para>
       <para>
        and the delivery schedules under it . . .
       </para>
       <para>
        I ask the Minister: Has he seen reports in yesterday's Sydney Morning Herald which say that India and Pakistan have been exchanging heavy artillery fire along the Kashmir border, and which describe the exchanges as `the most serious escalation between the two countries since the uprising in . . . Kashmir began in January'? Would the Minister agree that these developments represent a significant escalation of tension between India and Pakistan and that, accordingly, the Government should now review the Mirage sale?
       </para>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="2501" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is the case, as I said in both India and Pakistan, that we would review the Mirage sale either if hostilities broke out between India and Pakistan or if the situation deteriorated to the extent that hostilities seemed imminent. The expression `hostilities' was intended to refer to full-scale war between the two countries rather than simply the exchange of fire, skirmishing or other kinds of aggravated military tension that have unfortunately been so endemic in that region for so long. I have seen quite a considerable flow of information about the current situation in Kashmir and border areas. It is not our judgment at this stage that this heralds full-scale hostilities in the sense in which I have used the term in the context to which Senator Durack refers. Obviously, we will keep the situation under close watch. The undertaking holds, but at the moment I do not regard it as being triggered by the circumstances there.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2502">
      <title>
       WAGE FIXING PRINCIPLES
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" gov="1" nameid="1G4" page="2502" party="ALP" speaker="Devereux Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1G4">
          Senator DEVEREUX
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister for Industrial Relations to the decision handed down in the Australian Industrial Relations Commission concerning the current wage system. Could the Minister advise honourable senators of the content and ramifications of this decision and in particular could he advise what significance the Industrial Relations Commission's decision has for the continued inclusion of the structural efficiency element in wage fixation?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="2502" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The decision was handed down by the Australian Industrial Relations Commission at 2 p.m. in Melbourne yesterday. It has been widely reported in today's press. From the Government's point of view, we welcome the decision. It is consistent with the Commonwealth's submission to the national wage case hearing which, as I pointed out in answer to a question asked by Senator Giles last week, was delivered by Ms Lynne Tacy of my Department. The Industrial Relations Commission in its decision recognised that the current wage fixing principles do not prohibit unions from serving on employers claims which are designed to raise issues about a change or new system of wage fixing, nor can there be any objections by employers to discussions to clarify such claims.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I also point out that I agree with the Commission, that both unions and employers participating in those discussions must bear in mind the obligation to avoid industrial action, the necessity for the Commission to approve any agreements that might be reached and the danger of raising in the community false expectations about wages. In case anyone believes that may be a sin of which only unions are guilty, I can cite a press release I saw the other day from the Confederation of Australian Industry which, in order to paint a graphic picture of what a wage explosion might do, could be in part guilty of creating an expectation as well.
       </para>
       <para>
        The point on which the expectation founders is the pop belief in the community that a 7 per cent aggregate wage outcome equals a 7 per cent wage increase. It does not. In calculating the aggregate wage outcome, one has to have regard for the pipeline effects of wages decisions feeding into this year from last year. We calculate that to be about 4 per cent to 4 1/2 per cent. One has to have regard for the wages drift component, which might be about one per cent. As well, we must have regard for the already committed wage increases in the Government-Australian Council of Trade Unions accord, which are for the September quarter consumer price index increase to be passed on in full to workers, six months later for an increase of $12, and for a phasing-in over two years of a 3 per cent superannuation hike. From the point of view of the 7 per cent average wage outcome, I pause in explaining the decision to clarify that it does not equal a 7 per cent wage increase for the year.
       </para>
       <para>
        To answer the second part of Senator Devereux's question-the Commission emphasised that there is a substantial level of agreement between the parties in terms of a continuance of the structural efficiency process. All parties are, I think it is fair to describe it, in `heated' agreement that that process of structural efficiency award restructuring workplace reform must go on. The Commission stressed that in its decision; we welcome that emphasis. We will attend and partake in next Monday's conference announced in the Commission's decision yesterday.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2503">
      <title>
       ATTENDANT CARE
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="8U4" page="2503" party="AD" speaker="Lees Sen M.H.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8U4">
          Senator LEES
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister representing the Minister for Community Services and Health to an article appearing in the Age yesterday and also to the Government's recently released attendant care review, both of which note that the average cost to the community of a place under this scheme is some $14,700 less than a place in a general nursing home and at least $80,000 less than a bed in a public hospital. As the Minister for Health has recently been expressing his concern about the increased cost of hospital care, I ask the Minister: Firstly, can the Government explain why it has only provided a mere 200 additional places under this scheme over the next four years when its own review conservatively identifies over 2,000 people who are potential clients of the scheme? Secondly, in view of the fact that the review identifies a further 51,000 people in the community with a potential demand for home based attendant care support, why has the Government provided only 350 places under the 3-2-5 scheme over the next four years to meet this demand? Finally, the Government has indicated its intention to act in part on two of the recommendations in this report. Does the Government intend to act, and to what extent, on the remaining 12 recommendations?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="2503" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Lees has raised several matters in her question and I would like to answer them in three different sections. She raised the question of the inadequacy of 200 additional places under the national attendant care scheme. The review report that she mentioned recommended that the attendant care scheme be expanded by 100 places a year and despite difficult economic circumstances the Government has been able to provide 200 places over the next two years.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        This Government has done more for people with disabilities than any government since Federation. Funding for services assisting people with disabilities has increased from $72.4m to $217.8m, a real increase of 52 per cent. Despite this enormous contribution the Government recently announced a further expansion of programs through a $172m package of additional accommodation, employment and rehabilitation services, including the further 200 attendant care places. This major expansion of support services complements a sweeping reform of income support in employment programs for people with disabilities and demonstrates this Government's real commitment to achieving a better deal for people with disabilities.
       </para>
       <para>
        Senator Lees went on to claim that the 350 accommodation support places provided in the recent Budget were inadequate. The decision to increase its already substantial funding under the Disability Services Act to provide a further 350 accommodation support places represents a very significant contribution by this Government. It more than doubles the number of places previously available under the 3-2-5 places scheme at increased funding levels that will enable the new places to better meet the needs of people with more severe disabilities. The 3-2-5 places scheme will be reviewed during the year and the Government will, no doubt, consider the results of such a review in considering the future allocation of funds for additional places.
       </para>
       <para>
        Senator Lees further asked whether the Government intended to act on the remaining 12 recommendations of the review. In fact, Government initiatives announced in the last Budget anticipated six of the 14 recommendations made in the review report. A further four recommendations were already being examined for implementation by the Department of Community Services and Health. All the recommendations deserve careful consideration and this Government's decision will be announced as soon as possible.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2503">
      <title>
       AGRICULTURAL PROTECTIONISM
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" gov="1" nameid="7I4" page="2503" party="ALP" speaker="Maguire Sen G.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="7I4">
          Senator MAGUIRE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade. While we have heard very much of the peace dividend following the end of the Cold War, is it now time for an agricultural dividend, that is, the release of public funds from a much needed reduction in northern hemisphere agricultural protectionism? I understand that subsidies to farmers are now running at $240 billion a year around the world. I ask the Minister: Would such a call for reduced agricultural protection benefit Australian producers?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="2503" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is self-evident that reduced agricultural protection would benefit low cost and low subsidising countries such as Australia, which are heavily dependent on exports for their continued survival. The costs of agricultural protectionism to efficient producers, consumers, taxpayers, developing countries, the environment and the fabric of international trade relations have been documented over many years, and it is ironical to note that, while events in the East which have made the peace dividend possible have moved very quickly, pressures for agricultural reform in the West have moved far more slowly.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        As Senator Maguire would know, agricultural reform is now a centrepiece for the current Uruguay Round of trade negotiations, where Australia, both individually and with Cairns Group colleagues, and now in very close collaboration with the United States of America, has pressed hard for substantial and progressive reductions in agricultural support and protection.
       </para>
       <para>
        The significance of agriculture for the outcome of the Uruguay Round is now recognised at the highest levels in the leading Western economies. Regrettably this recognition has yet to be visibly translated into the negotiations on agriculture in Geneva and time is running out. We will, of course, with others-as we were as recently as a few days ago with Dr Blewett in Vancouver at the Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation Trade Ministers meeting on this subject-continue to press for a big result, which will be needed to conclude the Uruguay Round successfully.
       </para>
       <para>
        It would indeed be ironical if, as Senator Maguire has intimated, with a peace dividend now in sight, the failure to deal with agricultural illiberalism were to generate tensions among the major Western countries which have so successfully pursued the cause of liberalism in the wider sense.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2504">
      <title>
       PETROL: PRICE
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="TH4" page="2504" party="LP" speaker="Knowles Sen S.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="TH4">
          Senator KNOWLES
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Treasurer. I refer to yesterday's decision by the Prices Surveillance Authority allowing a further increase of 1.75c per litre in the price of petrol, bringing the highest maximum wholesale price of petrol to 71.63c per litre in Sydney and 70.77 cents per litre in Perth. Given that the forecast price of oil in the Budget was stated at $23 per barrel and that the price of crude oil is currently reported at over $31 per barrel, on what basis of assessment was the Government's forecast made? Has the Government prepared any forecasts of the impact the inflationary effect of this will have on the Australian economy?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2504" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have to recall the Budget statements, which Senator Knowles clearly does not. As I recall it, in putting the price at $23 a barrel for the Budget year the Treasury was making what I think we would say was not even a forecast but a calculated guess at the average price of a barrel of oil over the 12 months period. Of course, that was totally dependent on the events in the Middle East, which at the time of the Budget were newly upon us. So I think it is fair to say that right from the beginning it was expected to be a difficult figure to calculate and one in respect of which, as I have said, a calculated guess was made.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        If potential hostilities in the Middle East were to cease, say, in the next month, it is pretty clear that the price of oil per barrel would come down fairly quickly, and in assessing an average over the 12 months it may be that the figure given in the Budget would turn out to be correct. But right from the beginning it was said that it was a risky exercise to assess such a figure. So the answer is that one has to wait and see. As to the question in so far as it relates to the inflationary impacts of the price of oil, again we will have to wait and see, because that is dependent on what happens in the Middle East.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2504">
      <title>
       ACCORD
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="IF4" page="2504" party="ALP" speaker="Childs  Sen B.K.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="IF4">
          Senator CHILDS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Has the Minister for Industrial Relations seen reports to the effect that the accord between the Australian Council of Trade Unions (ACTU) and the Government is a cause of, rather than a solution to, economic problems? Has he also seen reports suggesting that the accord is now under threat because of the ACTU's current wages campaign? Do these reports have any foundation in fact? Can the Minister advise what effect the accord has had on national economic performance under the Hawke Government? Can he also say whether or not the union movement remains committed to the accord?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="2504" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Yes, I have seen press reports from some writers of that type and I have heard comment-most recently in this chamber last night, as a matter of fact-along the same lines. It should be remembered that the Fraser Government, the one that preceded us, operated from 1981-82 a decentralised wages system which struck the trifecta: it had double digit inflation, double digit unemployment, and double digit wages growth, that is, inflation of 11.5 per cent in its last year, unemployment of 10.1 per cent in its last year, and wages growth of 17 per cent in its last year.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        By contrast, the accord has provided a magnificent new opportunity for Australians. More than 1.6 million new jobs have been created since 1983. The unemployment level during the Fraser years reflected a very low participation rate. The participation rate now, despite some contraction in employment growth, is still near record levels; and that is a figure that should be kept in mind. Disposable household income per head has risen by more than 11 per cent-I think it is 11.1 per cent-during the period of this Government. Under Fraser, average economic growth was 2.1 per cent. Under us it is 4.2 per cent. Industrial disputation has been reduced by 61 per cent under the accord and is now at a near record low. Under Fraser in 1975 to 1983--
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Senator Cook, could you refer to the former Prime Minister as Mr Fraser, or to the Fraser Government.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Under the Fraser Government, from 1975 to 1983, real unit labour costs went up by 1.7 per cent. From 1983 to 1990, real unit labour costs have gone down by 10.5 per cent. What has to be added to that is the extension of superannuation to large sections of the Australian work force, the improvement in Medicare that has enabled health insurance and health treatment to be within the reach of ordinary Australians, the fact that pensions are now at 25.5 per cent of average weekly earnings, the fact that tax cuts have been delivered regularly, and the fact that child-care places are three times higher than they were in 1983.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The Industrial Relations Commission has ultimate responsibility for wage fixing, but the Government is confident that accord mark VI is a positive and responsible package, that it will achieve continuing wage restraint, and that it will also continue the labour market reforms to which I have referred. Since the accord process began, it should be acknowledged, the Australian Council of Trade Unions has delivered wage restraint. Indeed, in accord mark 5, the wages outcome for the year 1989-1990 was 0.5 per cent below the wages Budget estimates target. So not only has it delivered within target, but last year it delivered half a per cent below that level, which is an exercise in restraint that I think has been unprecedented in Australia.
       </para>
       <para>
        I refute the allegations that the accord is not working. It has delivered those huge advantages to the Australian community. If there is a tendency to see the accord as a fixed document and not a flexible one able to be adjusted to the circumstances of the economy, there might be a retrospective view. But it is a dynamic document able to bring change and improvement to the quality of life of ordinary Australians.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2505">
      <title>
       DRAFT COMPANIES AND SECURITIES LEGISLATION
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="XF4" page="2505" party="LP" speaker="Crichton-Browne Sen N.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XF4">
          Senator CRICHTON-BROWNE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister for Justice and Consumer Affairs. I refer him to his outrage at an announcement of proposed amendments to company law in 1984 by the then Ministerial Council for Companies and Securities which, as I recall, led him, as Chairman of the Standing Committee on Legal and Constitutional Affairs, to move for a reference from the Senate to inquire into the whole question of company law and the legislative process. Does the Minister believe it is the responsibility of Mr Tony Hartnell, as Chairman of the National Companies and Securities Commission, or whatever he presently is, to announce his proposed legislation, or is it properly the function of the relevant Minister to announce the legislation, having gone through the due processes of Cabinet? Does the Minister still acknowledge the role of Parliament in rejecting, amending or passing such legislation? What is the status of the proposed legislation that Mr Hartnell has announced? Has the Minister seen the draft legislation?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="2505" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I cannot recall the incident in 1984 with the clarity which is apparent to Senator Crichton-Browne. But I can say in relation to the statement made recently by Mr Hartnell about the exposure of certain draft legislation to do with the duties of directors, that that is part of a process that was undertaken by the Companies and Securities Advisory Committee-I think under Mr Mark Burrows, a leading figure in the business world-at the request of the then Attorney-General, Mr Lionel Bowen.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The idea is that that legislation be exposed for public comment for some three months before the Advisory Committee makes its final recommendation to government as to the best form that such legislation might take. In other words, what is being put forward by Mr Hartnell is a process which allows the greatest possible participation by business interests, shareholders' representatives and the community generally in the formulation of this legislation.
       </para>
       <para>
        As I recall Mr Hartnell's indication, the legislation which is proposed to be exposed for comment is to deal with loans to company directors, transfer of company assets and the disclosure of remuneration pay to executives-all matters of great concern in the community. I understand, though I cannot recall specific recommendations, that Senator Cooney headed a committee which, under his distinguished leadership, did look at certain questions in relation to company directors' duties. No doubt that will also be taken into account by government, as will the coming report of the House of Representatives Standing Committee on Legal and Constitutional Affairs under Mr Lavarch, which is looking into certain aspects of the rights of shareholders.
       </para>
       <para>
        Between those parliamentary reports on the duties of directors on the one hand and the rights of shareholders on the other and this draft Bill being exposed for public comment, I imagine that the Government will be very well placed-I think this is the purport of Senator CrichtonBrowne's question-to take its responsibilities seriously, to come into this national Parliament and to present that legislation where, of course, it will be subject to the full processes of parliamentary debate, including full scrutiny in the Senate. What is more, we will be able to do it after 1 January in a way in which we have not been able to do hitherto-that is, as a national parliament, take full, exclusive responsibility for the legislation governing these very important matters.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="XF4" page="2505" party="LP" speaker="Crichton-Browne Sen N.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XF4">
          Senator CRICHTON-BROWNE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I ask a supplementary question. I am very surprised that the Minister does not remember the grave indignation that he expressed at the time to the Senate that led him to move for a reference from the Senate. However, having said that, do I understand him to be saying that it is not proposed legislation, it is not draft legislation, it is not legislation he has seen and it is not legislation the Government acknowledges-it is simply a collection of ideas of Mr Hartnell and others?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="2505" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not think Senator Crichton-Browne could have been listening very well. What I said was that the Advisory Committee, under Mr Mark Burrows, had been asked to undertake this project by the former Attorney-General, Mr Lionel Bowen. That has been taking place-consideration of the shape of the legislation, the policies that should underlie it and so on-and it will now be exposed for public comment. Over the next three months I believe that there will be good input by Senator Crichton-Browne's friends in the business community, by my friends among shareholders' representatives and by the community generally. As a result of the exposure of the draft Bill, the Committee will be in a position to put its final recommendations to the Government which will then take responsibility for legislation to be introduced into this Parliament.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2507">
      <title>
       MULTIFUNCTION POLIS
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" gov="1" nameid="ZW4" page="2507" party="ALP" speaker="Sherry Sen N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZW4">
          Senator SHERRY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I address my question to the Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce. Has the Minister seen press reports of a British television interview with the South Australian Premier, Mr Bannon? In the light of these reports, can the Minister say whether there is unlikely to be any genuine interest in the multifunction polis (MFP) project from international investors?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2507" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have seen reports of a television interview in which it was suggested that Australia could not afford a project such as the multifunction polis. I must say that on the back of these press reports of the British Broadcasting Corporation interview with Mr Bannon, Senator Coulter has put out a press release yet again, which I propose to deal with in a moment. But let me say that in my view, unlike that of Senator Coulter, the MFP is an important national project, not a parochial city initiative.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Premier Bannon got a hard time from the BBC in that it was constantly put to him that because of the spectacular failures of some of our high-flying, more colourful entrepreneurs, Australia was not a good place in which to invest. The fact of the matter is that the collapse of some of the corporate cowboys here has meant that some hard work has to be done to ensure the good name of this country with international investors and to establish that there are many solid investment opportunities in this country.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is true, of course, that the MFP is an ambitious project. But it will not go ahead, as I have said repeatedly in this place, unless the feasibility study now under way establishes, firstly, that it is in the best economic interests of this country and, secondly, that it has the support and understanding of the Australian people.
       </para>
       <para>
        I must say that Senator Coulter alone in this community is not prepared to wait for that feasibility study of the MFP proposal to be completed before condemning it out of hand. I must say the preliminary study, by the joint steering committee, concluded that there was potential to significantly benefit the long-term economic growth of Australia, and a number of industry sectors were identified in which international investment opportunities could be recognised.
       </para>
       <para>
        I must say there has been considerable international investor interest in the MFP. Several international companies have recently visited Adelaide to discuss the project with the State Government. I have been approached by a number of international companies and they will be concerned to assess proposals and get involved in the MFP at the appropriate time.
       </para>
       <para>
        Senator Coulter-I mention him in passing because he is an honourable senator, a member of this Senate-says in his press release today that the MFP is a publicly funded gravy train for Japanese construction firms. Senator Coulter is never one to let the facts get in the way of a good press release and he seems to make up his press releases as he goes along.
       </para>
       <para>
        First of all, there has not been a decision to build the MFP, let alone select the construction firms. The project, as I said, is truly international, and raising the spectre of a Japanese dominated project, however inaccurate, may help boost the numbers at Senator Coulter's little rallies in Adelaide against the MFP, but it will do nothing to help determine whether the MFP is in Australia's best interests or not.
       </para>
       <para>
        Senator Coulter said that Mr Bannon should spare us the charade of trying to internationalise the MFP. All I can say is: What does he think the Premier is doing in Europe? There are some people in Australia who would reject any development proposal. I suspect Senator Coulter is one of them. I resent, however, the suggestion that it is, as he put it, some Japanese gravy train, because, as I said, although that may be designed to add a few numbers to his little rallies in Adelaide, it will not do anything in terms of a fair assessment of the project.
       </para>
       <para>
        My colleague Senator Walsh always used to describe the Australian Democrats as the `fairies at the bottom of the garden' party. What Senator Coulter is lending to that description is something new-a woodshed at the bottom of the garden, and, according to him, there is something rather nasty in the woodshed. So what we have had in the new version Democrats is a replacement of fairies--
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YW4" speaker="Senator Macdonald">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YW4">
           Senator Macdonald
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Careful, they support you.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Honourable senators opposite should not get excited the moment I mention the word `fairies'. What we have in the Democrats at the moment is a replacement of the `fairies at the bottom of the garden' party with the `demons at the bottom of the garden' party, in a woodshed-which perhaps was made in Japan. I think it is most unfortunate that Senator Coulter indulges in that sort of thing.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        As to Mr Bannon's trip to Europe, his experience in the sort of program which the BBC conducted is not vastly different from the experience to which many other Ministers in this Government and State governments have been subject, and it is largely based, as I said, on the very bad reputation that business in this country has got from the activities of some very unreliable entrepreneurs.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2508">
      <title>
       VIETNAM MEDALS
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="JI4" page="2508" party="LP" speaker="Panizza Sen J.H.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="JI4">
          Senator PANIZZA
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Veterans' Affairs. I refer the Minister to the continued efforts by the Vietnam Logistical Support Veterans' Association of Australia for recognition by awarding of the Vietnam Medal to the personnel of HMAS Sydney and other support ships involved in logistic support. I ask whether the Minister has further considered this matter or intends to further consider it.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="2508" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I believe that Senator Panizza has raised a matter of great concern to several of his constituents and I will certainly ask Mr Humphreys, the Minister for Veterans' Affairs, whether he has given further consideration of the sort that Senator Panizza seeks as far as the awarding of the particular medal is concerned. I will provide an answer to Senator Panizza as soon as possible.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2508">
      <title>
       CONCENTRATION OF WEALTH
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="0X4" page="2508" party="AD" speaker="Spindler Sen S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="0X4">
          Senator SPINDLER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister representing the Treasurer. I preface it by saying that the question is not coming from the fairies at the bottom of the garden but rather from the keepers of the light on the hill. Firstly, is the Minister aware that the recently published study by Dr Andrew Dilnot found that over 55 per cent of Australia's wealth is concentrated in the hands of the richest 10 per cent of Australians? Secondly, is the Minister aware of recent trend figures which show that we now have 32,000 millionaires while the number of people in poverty has increased from 1.6 million at the start of the first Hawke Government to 2.1 million in 1986? Thirdly, will the Minister confirm that the Government is still committed to `the achievement of a more equitable distribution of income, wealth and economic power', as contained in the 1988 platform document of the Australian Labor Party (ALP) at page 51, paragraph B10d? Fourthly and finally, does the Minister agree that ignorance is not bliss--
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="BH4" speaker="Senator Hill">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="BH4">
           Senator Hill
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I raise a point of order, Mr Deputy President. I ask for a ruling as to whether the speech is in fact a question. I was not going to raise the point had it been a short question but, as this is a long question, I ask whether the matter is not already listed on the Notice Paper.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —It is generally accepted that we can be a little flexible and ask questions which are referred to on the Notice Paper. However, the question is a very long one and I ask Senator Spindler to bring it to a speedy conclusion.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="0X4">
          Senator SPINDLER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will do so, Mr Deputy President. Does the Minister agree that ignorance is not bliss, and will the Government support the collection of information on wealth distribution in Australia as a first step towards measures to reduce inequality of wealth?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2508" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —That is a more traditional Democrat question, if I may say so, and it was in four parts. As to the first part, I have not seen the report by Dr Andrew Dilnot. I will certainly see whether I can get access to it.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The second part of the question related to measurement of poverty. I do not want to answer that because there are several measures of poverty. I am not prepared to answer that part of the question without knowing which measure of poverty the honourable member is seeking to use.
       </para>
       <para>
        I was also asked whether the Minister is still committed to a certain section of the platform. I must say that I have not read that section of the platform recently: I have been reading the one on ownership of public enterprises. However, the answer is that of course the ALP is committed to the platform. The question of implementation and the timing of implementation of the platform are matters for government.
       </para>
       <para>
        Regarding the last question as to whether better statistics can be obtained in respect of wealth distribution, I will direct the question to the Treasurer because that falls within the functions of the Australian Bureau of Statistics which is directly within his portfolio. I will give the honourable senator an answer as soon as possible.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2509">
      <title>
       DEATH DUTIES
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="BE4" page="2509" party="LP" speaker="Newman Sen J.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BE4">
          Senator NEWMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to Senator Button as Leader of the Government in the Senate and as Minister representing the Treasurer. I draw the Minister's attention to the public statements made recently by the honourable member for Denison, Mr Kerr, and the honourable member for Lalor and former Minister for Science, Mr Barry Jones, proposing a redistribution of wealth in Australia and the reintroduction of death duties. Do these proposals have the support of the Government? Also, what impact would they have on investment, savings and economic activity?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2509" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have not seen the comments made by Mr Kerr and Mr Jones, but I am sure the Government has nothing before it relating to the reintroduction of death duties. In so far as the question of effects that the reintroduction of death duties would have, I am sure that would have a beneficial effect on redistribution of wealth in Australia; I am fairly confident about that. But there are a number of complex factors which lead a government to consider or otherwise the reintroduction of death duties, and there is nothing planned by the present Government along those lines.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="BE4" page="2509" party="LP" speaker="Newman Sen J.M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BE4">
          Senator NEWMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I ask a supplementary question. I did ask the Minister to advise what impact such death duties and redistribution of wealth would have on investment, savings and economic activity. He did not address that part of the question.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2509" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am unable to answer that part of the question. A whole range of factors would determine that. One cannot look just at death duties in isolation. The whole complex of taxation measures affects investment. This would be part of a package which would affect investment decisions or would not. I cannot say; it is a very hypothetical question.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2509">
      <title>
       MIDDLE EAST
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="IG4" page="2509" party="IND" speaker="Vallentine Sen J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="IG4">
          Senator VALLENTINE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is addressed to the Minister representing the Prime Minister. I ask the Minister to explain why the Prime Minister misled the Australian public about the involvement of west European forces in the military blockade in the Gulf to justify the hasty commitment of Australian warships to the area? Why did Mr Hawke claim that Dutch and Italian military forces were already involved in the blockade before he volunteered Australian warships, as reported in the Australian Broadcasting Corporation's Four Corners program on 3 September? Is it true that at the time the Dutch and Italian governments had not committed warships to the blockade and did not announce naval deployments until 13 August, contrary to the Prime Minister's claim? Further, is it true that the Prime Minister considered the deployment of ground support technicians and a 20-person medical team to the Gulf region to be administrative matters and, therefore, not requiring consultation with the full Caucus and the Leader of the Opposition as promised? Finally, in light of the creeping escalation of our military presence in the Gulf and the upgrading of the rules of engagement, can we expect this to be the pattern over the next few months rather than a full and open consultation before any new deployments or changes are made?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2509" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Whatever Senator Vallentine does, I guess she is not the keeper of the Parliamentary Labor Party Caucus. I think we can manage our own business there.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Opposition senators-Ha, ha!
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —We do not need any assistance from Senator Vallentine. If I can put that another way, to satisfy the Opposition: I do not think Senator Vallentine's view would help us to manage our business in any way. The Prime Minister has not misled the Australian public in respect of the commitment to the Gulf. The decision made by Australia to contribute ships to the multinational force was not, as her question implies, justified by the action of west European forces. It was justified by the actions of the United Nations and by Australia's own national interests.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Nonetheless, at the time Australia announced its commitment, a number of west European countries had committed ships or had indicated that they intended to commit ships to the Gulf region. They included the United Kingdom, Italy and the Netherlands. Senator Vallentine might be interested to know that according to our current information, 12 countries are contributing ships to the force in the Gulf region: The United States, the United Kingdom, France, Belgium, the Netherlands, Australia, Canada, Denmark, Norway, Greece, Spain and Italy. Any suggestion that the United Nations force in the Gulf lacks broad international support is obviously false.
       </para>
       <para>
        In answer to Senator Vallentine's last point: the Prime Minister considers that the establishment of logistic and medical support arrangements for our ships in the Gulf did not change the role of those ships or the nature of our commitment to the Gulf. It therefore did not require the consultation processes which the Prime Minister had established.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="IG4" page="2509" party="IND" speaker="Vallentine Sen J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="IG4">
          Senator VALLENTINE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I ask a supplementary question. I am sorry but the Minister seems to have chosen to ignore the main thrust of the question, which was that on 3 September the Prime Minister stated that the Dutch and the Italians had already made a military commitment to the Gulf region. At the time he made that statement, that was not the case.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Could you ask your question, Senator Vallentine?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="IG4">
          Senator VALLENTINE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am asking for that particular part of the question to be answered. I restate the question: why did the Prime Minister mislead the Australian public about the dates of the involvement of the Dutch and the Italian military forces, which were not committed until 13 August? This was contrary to the Prime Minister's claim.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2509" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Of course, it depends what the word `commitment' means. I am sure that there were understandings that the Prime Minister had that Senator Vallentine would not have had at the time. I am also sure that at that time commitments had been made by a number of countries in terms of what they intended to do. That is the point which the Prime Minister was referring to.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2510">
      <title>
       AUSTRALIAN WHEAT BOARD
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="UW4" page="2510" party="LP" speaker="Crane Sen W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UW4">
          Senator CRANE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister representing the Treasurer to a press statement of 8 August by the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy in which he stated that, if Iraq's debt to the Australian Wheat Board is at risk, wheat growers are already protected by the national interest provisions of the Export Finance and Insurance Corporation (EFIC) insurance cover for wheat sold to Iraq. I ask the Minister: Why has the $490m worth of wheat sold on credit to Iraq under the national interest provisions of EFIC insurance not been accounted for in the Budget, given that national interest insurance claims are paid out of the Budget, not the resources of EFIC?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2510" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will obtain a detailed answer about that. There are one or two technical matters in relation to that question that I would like to give a precise answer to. I will get that answer as soon as possible.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2511">
      <title>
       INDONESIA: HUMAN RIGHTS
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="FE4" page="2511" party="ALP" speaker="Zakharov Sen A.O.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FE4">
          Senator ZAKHAROV
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Is the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade aware that the Indonesian Government has released the prominent political prisoner, Mr Hartono Dharsono? What are the implications of this for human rights and for political developments in Indonesia?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="2511" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is the case that on 16 September the Indonesian Government released from prison Mr Hartono Dharsono, the former Secretary-General of the Association of South East Asian Nations and a retired lieutenant-general. Mr Dharsono had been convicted in 1986 of attempting to undermine the Government and inciting and causing unrest-essentially political offences. He was sentenced to 10 years imprisonment, reduced to seven years on appeal. He was also a prominent member of the opposition group of fifty. Mr Dharsono's release followed a five-month remission granted by President Soeharto on Independence Day, 17 August, and other remissions in previous years. He was greeted by over 1,000 people on his release.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The Australian Government very much welcomes the release of Mr Dharsono. We believe that the release is a reflection of an increased sensitivity by the Indonesian Government towards human rights matters generally, and a growing commitment to greater openness and political pluralism. President Soeharto personally expressed his commitment to such openness during his Independence Day address this year. While there may continue to be issues of human rights concern in Indonesia-and the Australian Government will continue to monitor closely the situation and continue to react as appropriate when those situations arise-I am encouraged by the recent positive signs in Indonesia, including Mr Dharsono's release. I think it is appropriate to publicly recognise and acknowledge these developments on the positive side of the ledger.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2511">
      <title>
       CASCADE BREWERY CO. LTD
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="VJ4" page="2511" party="LP" speaker="Watson Sen J.O.W.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VJ4">
          Senator WATSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister representing the Treasurer. It shows the confusion in the administration of sales tax in Australia. Given the Government's support for conservation and recycling, is the Minister aware that advice from the local sales tax office to the Cascade Brewery Co. Ltd in relation to the recycling of bottles on two separate issues has twice been overruled by bureaucratic intervention from Canberra? Was the central office decision on two separate occasions made to protect the revenue base regardless of law, equity, environment and local employment consequences? Could the Minister give the reasons for this unusual decision?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2511" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am prepared to believe that there may have been bureaucratic intervention from Canberra-it often happens. As to the details of that intervention, I will have to obtain an answer for Senator Watson and I will do so as quickly as possible.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2511">
      <title>
       MULTIFUNCTION POLIS
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" gov="1" nameid="ZF4" page="2511" party="ALP" speaker="Crowley Sen R.A.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZF4">
          Senator CROWLEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce. Further to the questions on the conference on the multi-function polis (MFP), I draw the Minister's attention to his endorsement of the conference and to the fact that not one of the speakers is a woman. While the Minister is not responsible for drawing up the speakers list, can he assure the Senate that his speech will make it clear that women do have a place in Australia's future, in industrial relations and design, telecommunications, environmental management, information services, education and training and the leisure industry as well as contributing to the country's planning and imagination?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2511" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Crowley is quite correct in saying that I had no say in the choice of speakers at that conference. I know some of the people who are speaking. I am sure that had I been asked to choose, I would perhaps have found some better speakers or more interesting speakers. But I was not asked about that. This conference is a non-government initiative. As I say, I had nothing to do with that and cannot interfere with it.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        In so far as the Government involvement in the MFP is concerned, we would welcome at every possible opportunity the involvement of women, particularly were they available in the industries to which Senator Crowley referred.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2512">
      <title>
       CHILD-CARE WORKERS
      </title>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="2512" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have an answer in relation to the question asked earlier by Senator Alston. I must apologise to him. The wording of the index to the brief reads: ACT/NT anomalies decision. That did not give me a sufficient label to enable me to answer Senator Alston's particular query. However, I will give the answer that is in the brief.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The Government accepts the Full Bench decision of 14 September 1990 to accept a negotiated award restructuring for child-care workers in the Australian Capital Territory (ACT) and the Northern Territory. There was an unusual level of support for the new rates and structures from both non-profit and commercial employers.
       </para>
       <para>
        The decision is the result of an extremely detailed and lengthy investigation by the Commission over two years. The Government welcomes the significant benefits likely to flow from the decision. The new structure will give workers better career paths and training opportunities and will reduce wastage rates in the industry.
       </para>
       <para>
        The phased increase in rates over the next 18 months will enable costs to services to be absorbed more easily. Fees for child-care places will rise to some extent but the Government has already announced that it is increasing the fee relief ceiling to $100 from 1 October 1990. These sweeping changes to fee relief will be extended to commercial and employer-provided centres from 1 January 1991. In addition, the Government has promised to index the fee relief ceiling from 1 October next year.
       </para>
       <para>
        These measures will assist low and middle income families to meet any extra costs arising from the decision, except where some services in the ACT are already charging more than the $100 fee relief ceiling. The Government believes that this decision is a positive step towards the introduction of nationally consistent awards for child-care workers which will provide a more stable base for its expansion of places over the next five years.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
    </qwn>
    <debate page="2512" type="Question without Notice">
     <title>
      QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
      <break type="LINE">
       CHILD-CARE WORKERS
      </break>
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="LD4" page="2512" party="LP" speaker="Alston Sen R.K.R.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LD4">
         Senator ALSTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-I wish to pose a question. I am indebted to the Minister for Justice and Consumer Affairs (Senator Tate) for providing that answer but he did undertake to give a full answer to my question. As the answer he has just provided is from a prepared text which does not deal with the question of the flow-on effects and, in particular, because the announcement of those subsidies predates the decision and in many respects will be negated by the effect of the Industrial Relations Commission's judgment, I ask the Minister whether he will undertake to provide a full answer to my question.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="NJ4" speaker="Senator Tate">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator Tate
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Yes.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2512" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      AUSTRALIAN GOVERNMENT PUBLISHING SERVICE
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I wish to advise honourable senators of the anticipated delivery times of the Daily Hansards which are still outstanding as a result of the industrial difficulties last week at the Australian Government Publishing Service. The Senate Hansard for Thursday, 13 September, is now in its final stages of preparation and should be delivered later this afternoon. The Daily Hansard for Friday, 14 September, will go to press tonight and be delivered tomorrow morning. Yesterday's Senate Hansard will be processed immediately the work that I have mentioned is completed. The Hansard report of today's proceedings will be dealt with after that.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        In relation to the Hansard reports of Estimates committees, I advise the Senate that the Hansard report of Estimates Committee A was delivered to honourable senators this morning; the Hansard reports for the remaining Estimates committees which sat last week will be cleared as soon as the Daily Hansards of Senate proceedings have been completed. Quite a deal of that Estimates Committee material is already formatted for printing. When I have further advice on delivery times, I shall advise honourable senators accordingly.
       </para>
       <para>
        Pursuant to my statement on 13 September relating to the industrial dispute at the Australian Government Publishing Service, I now table a proof copy of the Senate Hansard for 17 September 1990.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <petition.grp page="2513">
     <title>
      PETITIONS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10001" speaker="The Clerk">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10001">
          The Clerk
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Petitions have been lodged for presentation as follows:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <petition nameids="RD4" page="2513" presenters="BROWNHILL">
      <title>
       Air Landing Fee: New South Wales
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament:
      </para>
      <para>
       This petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth that the proposed air landing fee for regional and commuter airlines landing at Sydney Mascot Airport during peak times discriminates severely against people in rural Australia and will force many airlines to either revise their schedules, cancel flights or increase passenger fares to cover this additional financial impost of the Federal Labor Government. This will result in less accessibility for country businessmen and travellers alike, will increase the costs of business for rural people and threatens the viability of many smaller airlines who provide valuable services to rural towns. We therefore call on the Federal Government to abolish all plans for the introduction of this discriminatory fee and allow commuter airlines to continue to provide their full range of services to towns throughout New South Wales.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="RD4">
         Senator Brownhill
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 57 petitioners).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="UW4" page="2513" presenters="CRANE">
      <title>
       Telephone Directory: Western Australia
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President and Members of the Senate in Parliament assembled.
      </para>
      <para>
       The petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth that:
      </para>
      <para>
       Since the introduction of three (3) regional West Australian telephone directories there has been a constant demand from users to revert to a consolidated country directory which is convenient to all users.
      </para>
      <para>
       Your petitioners humbly pray that the Senate in Parliament assembled urge the Minister for Communications to direct Telecom to recognise the requirement of rural West Australians and revert to a single consolidated country telephone directory.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="UW4">
         Senator Crane
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 4,950 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="1I4" page="2513" presenters="MCKIERNAN">
      <title>
       United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child
      </title>
      <para>
       To the honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
      </para>
      <para>
       That, because the United Nations' Convention on the Rights of the Child would allow Governments to deprive parents of their rights, we request that the Parliament delay ratification for at least a year, to allow full open public debate and then a binding referendum.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="1I4">
         Senator McKiernan
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 23 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="1I4" page="2513" presenters="MCKIERNAN">
      <title>
       Five-Dollar Note
      </title>
      <para>
       To the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled.
      </para>
      <para>
       The petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth that:
      </para>
      <para>
       There is widespread concern in the Australian community about the proposal by the Reserve Bank of Australia to produce a new plastic $5 note that will feature the Queen, and that the present $5 note featuring Caroline Chisholm will be removed from circulation.
      </para>
      <para>
       Your petitioners humbly pray that the Senate, in Parliament assembled, urge the Reserve Bank to adopt a design for the new note that will promote and identify the unique character of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="1I4">
         Senator McKiernan
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 17 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="O14" page="2514" presenters="POWELL">
      <title>
       Uranium: Mining and Export
      </title>
      <para>
       To the honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
      </para>
      <para>
       That your petitioners request that the Australian Government take steps immediately to stop the mining and export of uranium
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="O14">
         Senator Powell
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 151 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="IG4" page="2514" presenters="VALLENTINE">
      <title>
       Middle East
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable President and Members of the Senate assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully shows:
      </para>
      <para>
       Their Opposition to the despatch of three Australian warships to the Middle East, which is part of an unnecessary militarisation of the region, and which contributed to the likelihood of all-out war. The increasing military buildup in the Middle East does not contribute to a resolution of the conflict. The conflict can only be resolved by regionally based diplomatic means. Whilst we unambiguously oppose the acquisition of territory by force and Iraq's military takeover of Kuwait, we note that current actions against Iraq have not been applied in similar circumstances, such as the annexation of East Timor by Indonesia.
      </para>
      <para>
       Your petitioners therefore pray that:
      </para>
      <para>
       The Australian warships in the Middle East be withdrawn immediately.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator Vallentine
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 19 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="1I4" page="2514" presenters="MCKIERNAN">
      <title>
       Five-Dollar Note
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="1I4" page="2514" party="unknown" speaker="MCKIERNAN">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1I4">
          Senator McKIERNAN
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I present to the Senate the following petition from 84 petitioners which is not in conformity with the Standing Orders:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Here is a petition of people who think that, Caroline Chisholm should not be removed from the five-dollar note.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="0X4" page="2514" presenters="SPINDLER">
      <title>
       Defence Expenditure
      </title>
      <speech electorate="unknown" nameid="0X4" page="2514" party="unknown" speaker="SPINDLER">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="0X4">
          Senator SPINDLER
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I present to the Senate the following petition from 1,469 petitioners which is not in conformity with the Standing Orders:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Currently Australia's military expenditure is $7,658 million a year-$21 million a day.
       </para>
       <para>
        The recent Environmental Land Package allows $320 million to be spent on the environment over the next ten years;
       </para>
       <para>
        - but this is less than the cost of one Anzac frigate ($416 million)
       </para>
       <para>
        - OR less than half the cost of one submarine ($644 million)
       </para>
       <para>
        - The Project Kangaroo '89 military exercise will cost $230 million in three months
       </para>
       <para>
        This amount is two-thirds of the sum given for the environment for ten years!
       </para>
       <para>
        In the meantime we urgently need more money for
       </para>
       <para>
        - housing for the homeless
       </para>
       <para>
        - safer and more efficient public transport
       </para>
       <para>
        - more hospital beds
       </para>
       <para>
        - better health, education, child care, etc.
       </para>
       <para>
        We recognise the need for some spending on defence, but we appeal to the Australian Government to reduce expenditure on armaments and use the money thus saved for the needs of the community and the environment.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </petition>
     <para>
      Petitions received.
     </para>
    </petition.grp>
    <debate page="2514" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      AMERICAN DISCOUNTED WHEAT SALES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="2514">
      <title>
       Notice of Motion
      </title>
      <speech electorate="WA" nameid="JI4" page="2514" party="LP" speaker="Panizza Sen J.H.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="JI4">
          Senator PANIZZA
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate-
       </para>
       <para>
        (a) notes with concern:
       </para>
       <para>
        (i) the record-breaking bonus paid to the United States wheat industry under the Export Enhancement Program for a sale to West African nations as well as a sale to Tunisia, and
       </para>
       <para>
        (ii) that these discounted sales have already caused the Australian Wheat Board to reduce this year's projected return to growers; and
       </para>
       <para>
        (b) calls on the Federal Government immediately to express these concerns to the United States administration with a view to encouraging it to cease such practices and to remind that administration that United States and Australian co-operation should go beyond the Gulf crisis.
       </para>
       <para>
        Petitions received.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2514" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL TERRITORY ELECTORAL SYSTEM
     </title>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="7U4" page="2514" party="AD" speaker="Bell Sen R.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="7U4">
         Senator BELL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) notes with concern the presumption contained in the reported comments of the Minister for Territories (Mr Simmons) who, with reference to the ACT electoral system, was quoted in the Canberra Times of 18 September 1990 as saying that there is no indication that if in fact there were a referendum, the major parties, or indeed the parties in the Senate, would accept the outcome of the referendum; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) takes whatever action is necessary to inform the Minister that the Senate would accept the outcome of such a referendum.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2515" type="Bill">
     <title>
      AIRLINES AGREEMENT (TERMINATION) BILL 1990
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Motion (by Senator Gareth Evans for Senator Robert Ray) agreed to:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the Airlines (Agreement) Termination Bill 1990 be taken to have been reported from the Standing Committee on Transport, Communications and Infrastructure, and that consideration of the Bill in Committee of the Whole be an order of the day for the next day of sitting.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2515" type="Bill">
     <title>
      END OF WAR LIST BILL 1990
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="2515">
      <title>
       First Reading
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
        Motion (by Senator Boswell) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para>
        That the following Bill be introduced: a Bill for an Act to establish an end of war list for Australian service personnel.
       </para>
       <para>
        Motion (by Senator Boswell) agreed to:
       </para>
       <para>
        That the Bill may proceed without formalities and be now read a first time.
       </para>
       <para>
        Bill read a first time.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="2515">
      <title>
       Second Reading
      </title>
      <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="YE4" page="2515" party="NP" speaker="Boswell Sen R.L.D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YE4">
          Senator BOSWELL
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Queensland-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Leader of the National Party of Australia)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (3.12)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That this Bill be now read a second time.
       </para>
       <para>
        I seek leave to have the second reading speech incorporated in Hansard.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leave granted.
       </para>
       <para>
        The speech read as follows-
       </para>
       <para>
        The Senate will recall that my former colleague, Senator McGauran, secured the passage in this place of an End of War List Bill in 1989. This credit for this Bill, as the Senate is well aware, goes entirely to Senator McGauran for his unstinting work on behalf of those who served in the Vietnam war and who have not yet been recognised by the Australian Government.
       </para>
       <para>
        I therefore consider it appropriate that Senator McGauran's original second reading speech, which launched the Bill on its successful passage through this place in 1989, be again placed on record to commend this Bill to the Senate.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Private Member's Bill before the Senate relates to an unfinished chapter in Australian history; that is the Vietnam War.
       </para>
       <para>
        The chapter relates to the failure of the Whitlam Government to establish an End of War List on the return home of the Australian troops from Vietnam.
       </para>
       <para>
        After every war which Australians have served in an End of War List has been drawn-up.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Vietnam War stands as the exception.
       </para>
       <para>
        End of War Lists are established for the purpose of recognising individual acts of valour that were overlooked in the disruption of the war. The list itself consists of a quota of awards ranging, from a `Mention-in-Dispatches' to the highest honour of a Victoria Cross.
       </para>
       <para>
        The purpose of the Bill is to create an End of War List for the Australian Defence Forces personnel who served in Vietnam from 1962 to 1973.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Bill has the full support of the National Executive of the Returned Services League and the Vietnam Veterans Association. The RSL has written to all its branches in Australia requesting its members to sign a petition of support.
       </para>
       <para>
        These petitions are being presented on a daily basis to the Senate.
       </para>
       <para>
        The establishment of an End of War List has much to do with maintaining a certain spirit of Australia, a spirit born out of the Gallipoli campaign. That spirit of pride and appreciation Australians have towards service men and women in times of war.
       </para>
       <para>
        Regardless of the horror and evil of war, Australians have always had an appreciation of, and respect for those who fought and died wearing the Australian uniform. That is what each ANZAC Day parade symbolises.
       </para>
       <para>
        Not to recognise individual acts of valour in the Vietnam War would be to destroy that spirit passed on through time.
       </para>
       <para>
        Unless the decision not to establish an End of War List is reversed, the Vietnam veterans can never be on a par with veterans from past campaigns.
       </para>
       <para>
        Nobody should doubt that because of the decision not to establish an End of War List, that there are now many unsung heroes of the Vietnam war. Two cases of young Australians who died in heroic service have been brought to my attention.
       </para>
       <para>
        Documents released following a Freedom of Information Act request show that the three Defence Departments-the Army, Navy and Air-made two requests for the establishment of an End of War List.
       </para>
       <para>
        The first request was made in 1972 to the Minister for Defence in the McMahon Government, Mr David Fairbairn and was rejected upon the grounds that hostilities were continuing in Vietnam and Australian troops were still in South East Asia.
       </para>
       <para>
        It should be noted that the future establishment of such a list was not ruled out by Mr Fairbairn.
       </para>
       <para>
        The second request was made some nine months later when all of the Australian troops were home.
       </para>
       <para>
        However, the Whitlam Government's Minister for Defence, Mr Lance Barnard, rejected the request on the grounds that it would be seen to be celebrating the war.
       </para>
       <para>
        That decision distinctly lacked an understanding of the Australian people and their history.
       </para>
       <para>
        Nobody at the time of Gallipoli or since could claim the campaign to be an event to celebrate. Indeed, Gallipoli was both a wartime and political disaster. Yet, what we do recognise and remember from that time are the individual acts of valour and those Australians who did not come home.
       </para>
       <para>
        The real hang-over and shame of the lost Vietnam War comes from the fact that Parliament has been unwilling to accept this age-old tradition, for the single reason of fearing the revitalisation of the war debate. We have had to live with that mistake ever since, as we have had to live with defeat in the Vietnam War.
       </para>
       <para>
        I am reminded of one story told to me by a veteran. He said that while his attitude was against Australians being called up to fight, he believed that once in the battle zone, every soldier was duty bound to fight with every ounce of strength for those fellow Australians alongside him. If there was one weak link in the fighting chain, all his mates would be in danger.
       </para>
       <para>
        That was the atmosphere and reality of the war zone in Vietnam regardless of the opinions and demonstrations at home.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is to that spirit which those who served in Vietnam were so true.
       </para>
       <para>
        It was not until the 1987 Coming Home Parade, organised by the Vietnam veterans themselves some 14 years after the soldiers left the battlefields of South East Asia, that the first step towards breaching the gap between the veterans and the Australian society was taken.
       </para>
       <para>
        It was a very moving event for those who watched the thousands of Australian men and women march. The marchers had been given no victory, no glory and not even any pride in having done their duty until that day.
       </para>
       <para>
        One could not help but believe Australia, on that day, had begun to heal the bitter divisions of the war, that the spirit of all that had made the Australian character so unique in the world had returned-that unique spirit of unconquerable determination of Australians against adversity.
       </para>
       <para>
        Certainly, that spirit of mateship was present that day, when stories of bravery and loss were told.
       </para>
       <para>
        If the Coming Home Parade was the first step taken, the second step must be the approval of an End of War List.
       </para>
       <para>
        Many will say that time has passed and it is best to let such a controversial war be forgotten. `Besides', they will ask, `how could any investigation after so long reveal adequately the events of that war'?
       </para>
       <para>
        To that I would reply that, in this Senate just before last Christmas, the War Crimes Amendment Bill was passed. That Bill sought justice some 50 years after World War II. The justice that was sought there was to seek out war criminals. The justice I seek is to seek out war heroes.
       </para>
       <para>
        In my speech on the Bill I said:
       </para>
       <para>
        As we fast approach a new century, the year 2001, we are being asked to look back to a time that for so many was a time in history books, old film footage and, indeed, museums, and I am one such person who was not even born when the atrocities occurred in the Second World War. So it is significant for me to add that my generation has never been asked to go to war. We have been privileged with an era that has not challenged our beliefs to a point where we must take up arms and defend them in war. I rise to speak for that very reason. What my generation owes to past generations is due to the will and suffering of past generations of Australians and Europeans. My generation can say that they live in a free Australia. I believe that the past era should not be forgotten. A time should not be placed on justice, nor should there be a time to forget the dead. That is what every Shrine of Remembrance in this country asks of us-`Lest We Forget' the fallen soldier and civilian.
       </para>
       <para>
        I hold the same belief in seeking the establishment of an End of War List.
       </para>
       <para>
        I will now turn to individual aspects of the Bill.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Bill would establish an End of War List Tribunal.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Tribunal is to consist of 3 members from each of the three arms of the Australian Defence Force: the Navy; Army and Air
       </para>
       <para>
        The three members would be appointed by the Minister for Defence.
       </para>
       <para>
        The function of the Tribunal is to prepare a list of Australian service personnel who served in the Vietnam War, being persons who did not receive awards for valour in respect of the relevant military conflict but who should, in the opinion of the Tribunal, receive awards.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Tribunal is also to recommend to the Minister the level of the awards that the Tribunal believes should be granted.
       </para>
       <para>
        In keeping with the spirit of the original request by the defence force a quota of 30 awards can be recommended, although the Bill empowers the Minister to expand the list beyond the initial total of 30 awards.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Tribunal, in making its recommendations, is not to have regard to whether or not the rigid monthly quota of awards used by the defence forces during war time was filled.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Bill also establishes the principle that such a tribunal would be established for future military conflicts. This aspect of the Bill would ensure that political considerations could never again prevent the creation of End of War Lists.
       </para>
       <para>
        In conclusion, at a time that we are commemorating World War II 50 years since it began and are preparing to commemorate Gallipoli 75 years hence, let now be the time to put aside the arguments for and against the Vietnam war.
       </para>
       <para>
        Let now be the time to turn to the question of finally bringing our troops home.
       </para>
       <para>
        The answer will finally depend upon this Parliament.
       </para>
       <para>
        I seek the support of the Senate.
       </para>
       <para>
        Question resolved in the affirmative.
       </para>
       <para>
        Bill read a second time, and passed through its remaining stages without amendment or debate.
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="YE4" page="2517" party="NP" speaker="Boswell Sen R.L.D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YE4">
          Senator BOSWELL
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Queensland-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Leader of the National Party of Australia)
         </role>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-The reason this End of War List Bill has gone through on such a fast track is that my former colleague Senator McGauran promoted the Bill to service the soldiers, sailors and airmen who returned to Australia from Vietnam without sufficient recognition. I have used Senator McGauran's second reading speech as the speech that will accompany the Bill to the lower House.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2517" type="Committee">
     <title>
      JOINT COMMITTEE ON THE NATIONAL CRIME AUTHORITY
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="2517">
      <title>
       Membership
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I have received a letter from the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button) requesting a change in the membership of the Joint Committee on the National Crime Authority.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>
         Motion (by Senator Gareth Evans)-by leave-agreed to.
        </para>
        <para>
         That Senator Jones be discharged from further attendance on the Joint Committee on the National Crime Authority, and Senator Loosley, having been duly nominated in accordance with the National Crime Authority Act 1984, be appointed a member of the Committee.
        </para>
       </interject>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2517" type="Adjournment">
     <title>
      ADJOURNMENT
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="2517" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="VD4">
         Senator GARETH EVANS
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —To enable Estimates committees to meet, I move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate do now adjourn.
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Before the Senate adjourns, I advise honourable senators that Estimates Committee A will meet in the main committee room, Estimates Committee B will meet in Senate committee room 14, and Estimates Committee C will meet in Senate committee room 16.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Question resolved in the affirmative.
       </para>
       <para>
        Senate adjourned at 3.16 p.m.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2517" type="Documents">
     <title>
      DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The following documents were tabled:
      </para>
      <para>
       Aged or Disabled Persons Homes Act-Charter formulated under section 1ODA, dated 14 September 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Act-Determinations under section 58B-1990
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 116-Post Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 118-Settling In and Settling.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 121-Post Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 122-Post Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 128-Temporary Rental Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 129-Gulf Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       National Health Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Agreement under section 40ABB, dated 14 September 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Charter formulated under section 45F, dated 14 September 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Principles made under subsection 39BA (4), dated 14 September 1990.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
   </chamber.xscript>
   <answers.to.questions page="2518">
    <title>
     ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS
    </title>
    <proctext>
     <para>
      The following answers to questions were circulated:
     </para>
    </proctext>
    <answer.to.qon page="2518">
     <title>
      South Pacific: Maritime Surveillance
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="139">
      (Question No. 139)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="WA" nameid="8G4" page="2518" party="LP" speaker="Durack Sen The Hon P.D.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="8G4">
         Senator Durack
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Defence upon notice, on 14 August 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) What naval and airborne assets do the French possess for maritime surveillance operations in the South Pacific and where are those operations conducted.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) How many airborne surveillance flights over South Pacific EEZ's were conducted by: (a) France; (b) Australia; and (c) New Zealand in 1988 and 1989. (Please give a monthly breakdown if possible.)
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Do the French conduct maritime surveillance operations in the South Pacific for any island states other than those which are French territories; if so, (a) which states; (b) what operations are conducted; and (c) with what level of frequency.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Do commercial remote sensing satellites such as the French SPOT have any potential application for conducting surveillance of the transit of surface ships; if so, what might be the limitations of such use.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Have any of the following countries considered the applications of remote sensing for maritime surveillance in the South Pacific: (a) Australia; (b) New Zealand; and (c) France.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) What forms of defence cooperation has Fiji undertaken with the following countries since May 1987: (a) France; (b) Malaysia; (c) Indonesia; (d) Singapore; (e) United Kingdom; (f) People's Republic of China; (g) Taiwan; (h) Thailand; (i) United States of America (USA).
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) Have any naval vessels of the following countries visited the island states of the South Pacific Forum in 1987, 1988, 1989, and 1990 to date: (a) USA; (b) France; (c) China; (d) Taiwan; (e) Soviet Union (including scientific research vessels); (f) Japan; and (g) any of the ASEAN navies; if so, please provide the names of the vessels, the country of origin, the approximate date of the visit and the country visited.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="WA" nameid="UI4" page="2518" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="UI4">
         Senator Robert Ray
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Most of the information requested by the honourable senator relates to other countries' military forces and activities in the South Pacific. Much of this sort of information is available to the honourable senator through such publications as The Military Balance and Pacific Islands Monthly. I do not consider it my responsibility to provide detailed information, in this way, on other countries activities and bilateral relationships with South Pacific countries, nor is it appropriate for me to do so.
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) See general comment above.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) (a) See general comment above.
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) and (c) Australia conducted 9 surveillance flights in 1988 and 10 in 1989 in the South Pacific. These are coordinated with New Zealand which conducted 13 such flights in each of 1988 and 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) No.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Yes. Such systems (including SPOT) are limited in so far as they do not have the resolution to be able to identify ships.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Australia is not currently considering the use of remote sensing techniques for maritime surveillance in the South Pacific.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) and (7) See general comment above.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2518">
     <title>
      Defence Force Exercises
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="140">
      (Question No. 140)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="WA" nameid="8G4" page="2518" party="LP" speaker="Durack Sen The Hon P.D.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="8G4">
         Senator Durack
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Defence, upon notice, on 14 August 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) Will the Minister bring up to date the information contained in answer to Question Number 1310 (Hansard, House of Representatives, 21 December 1988, Pages 3909-3913) concerning ADF exercises and also provide dates for the commencement and termination of exercises since 21 December 1988.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="WA" nameid="UI4" page="2518" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="UI4">
         Senator Robert Ray
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) The following table provides information on the name, date of commencement and termination, location, purpose and cost of exercises since 21 December 1988. It should be noted that the costs listed are not brought to a common base in dollar terms although the costing method used for each is the same.
      </para>
      <para>
       The table also indicates which exercises were combined with other nation's forces, which nations were involved and which of their units took part.
      </para>
      <para>
       Exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       Location
      </para>
      <para>
       Purpose
      </para>
      <para>
       Cost
      </para>
      <para>
       Com-
      </para>
      <para>
       bined
      </para>
      <para>
       Nations
      </para>
      <para>
       Units
      </para>
      <para>
       $m
      </para>
      <para>
       Airlift Rodeo 89
      </para>
      <para>
       24 May-18 Jun 89
      </para>
      <para>
       USA
      </para>
      <para>
       Tactical air drop competition
      </para>
      <para>
       0.367
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Allied Exposure 89
      </para>
      <para>
       12-31 Oct 89
      </para>
      <para>
       USA
      </para>
      <para>
       Tactical air reconnaissance
      </para>
      <para>
       1.382
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Bell Buoy 89
      </para>
      <para>
       1-12 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Ind/Pac Ocean
      </para>
      <para>
       Naval Control and Protection of Shipping
      </para>
      <para>
       0.439
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US/CA/UK
      </para>
      <para>
       Reserve personnel
      </para>
      <para>
       BISAM 89
      </para>
      <para>
       20-30 Mar 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Brunei
      </para>
      <para>
       Shooting competition
      </para>
      <para>
       0.201
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       Brunei
      </para>
      <para>
       RBAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Black Cat 89-1
      </para>
      <para>
       8-12 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       WA
      </para>
      <para>
       Anti submarine warfare (ASW)
      </para>
      <para>
       0.948
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZN
      </para>
      <para>
       Blue Flyer 89
      </para>
      <para>
       9 Mar-28 Apr 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Puckapunyal
      </para>
      <para>
       Milan concentration
      </para>
      <para>
       0.246
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       BFHK
      </para>
      <para>
       Bullseye 89
      </para>
      <para>
       17-21 Apr 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Richmond
      </para>
      <para>
       Tactical air transport
      </para>
      <para>
       0.045
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       CA/NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       CF/RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Caltrop Force 89-1
      </para>
      <para>
       18-31 Mar 89
      </para>
      <para>
       USA
      </para>
      <para>
       Revise individual skills and train in close tropical environment
      </para>
      <para>
       9.498
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US/UK/CA
      </para>
      <para>
       US/UK/CA forces
      </para>
      <para>
       Chapel Gold 89
      </para>
      <para>
       31 Mar-21 Apr 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Thailand
      </para>
      <para>
       Develop understanding of RTA tactics and interoperability with RTA
      </para>
      <para>
       0.362
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       Thailand
      </para>
      <para>
       RTA
      </para>
      <para>
       Cope Thunder 89-6
      </para>
      <para>
       26 Apr-23 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Philippines
      </para>
      <para>
       Combined air defence training
      </para>
      <para>
       8.439
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USAF
      </para>
      <para>
       El Alamein 89-1
      </para>
      <para>
       24-31 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Army firepower demonstration
      </para>
      <para>
       0.395
      </para>
      <para>
       No
      </para>
      <para>
       EXTENDEX 89-1
      </para>
      <para>
       13-19 Mar 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Guam
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       1.296
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       EXTENDEX 89-3
      </para>
      <para>
       25-30 Jun 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Guam
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       1.009
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       EXTENDEX 89-4
      </para>
      <para>
       16-24 Nov 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Guam
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       1.057
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       EXTENDEX 89-5
      </para>
      <para>
       16-21 Dec 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Guam
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       1.045
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       Far Canopy 89
      </para>
      <para>
       9-30 Jun 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Nowra
      </para>
      <para>
       Airborne exercises
      </para>
      <para>
       0.082
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ army
      </para>
      <para>
       Fincastle Trophy 89
      </para>
      <para>
       15 Oct-6 Nov 89
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW competition
      </para>
      <para>
       1.532
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK/NZ/CA
      </para>
      <para>
       RAF/RN/RNZAF/CF
      </para>
      <para>
       Golden Fleece 89
      </para>
      <para>
       19 Jan-19 Feb 89
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Land exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.966
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ/MAL/SING
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ, MAL &amp;SING forces
      </para>
      <para>
       Haringaroo 19
      </para>
      <para>
       25 Jan-6 Feb 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia
      </para>
      <para>
       Land exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.152
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Haringaroo 20
      </para>
      <para>
       15-25 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia
      </para>
      <para>
       Land exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.314
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Haringaroo 21
      </para>
      <para>
       13-24 Jun 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia
      </para>
      <para>
       Land exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.26
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL Army
      </para>
      <para>
       HICOMMEX 89-90
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       High command communications exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       N/A
      </para>
      <para>
       No
      </para>
      <para>
       High Slope/Oasis
      </para>
      <para>
       12 Jun-13 Jul 89
      </para>
      <para>
       WA exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       Special Air Services (SAS)
      </para>
      <para>
       0.442
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       UK SAS
      </para>
      <para>
       HQIADS ADEX
      </para>
      <para>
       89-2
      </para>
      <para>
       4-7 Apr 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia/Singapore
      </para>
      <para>
       Five Power (FPDA) Air Defence exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       4.635
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL/
      </para>
      <para>
       SING/
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RMAF/RSAF/RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       HQIADS ADEX
      </para>
      <para>
       89-4
      </para>
      <para>
       26-29 Sep 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia/Singapore
      </para>
      <para>
       FPDA ADEX
      </para>
      <para>
       1.510
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL/
      </para>
      <para>
       SING/
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RMAF/RSAF/RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Iron Gauntlet 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Mar 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Enoggera
      </para>
      <para>
       Division Command Post Post exercise (CPX)
      </para>
      <para>
       0.002
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Army
      </para>
      <para>
       JCOMMEX 89-90
      </para>
      <para>
       continuous
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Joint communications exercises
      </para>
      <para>
       N/A
      </para>
      <para>
       No
      </para>
      <para>
       Jupiter/Badge
      </para>
      <para>
       Anvil 89
      </para>
      <para>
       29 Oct-22 Nov 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Tully
      </para>
      <para>
       Special Forces (SF) exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.267
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US SF
      </para>
      <para>
       Kangaroo 89
      </para>
      <para>
       CPX 8-30 Mar,
      </para>
      <para>
       28 Apr-5 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       FTX 1-27 Aug 89
      </para>
      <para>
       North Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Exercise HQADF and 3 Joint HQs, examine ADF command structure
      </para>
      <para>
       TBA
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USAF/USN/USMC
      </para>
      <para>
       Lion Spirit 89
      </para>
      <para>
       16-29 Oct 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia
      </para>
      <para>
       FPDA exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.321
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       FPDA
      </para>
      <para>
       FPDA Armies
      </para>
      <para>
       LOGEX 89
      </para>
      <para>
       9-11 Oct 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Army Logistic Command seminar
      </para>
      <para>
       0.019
      </para>
      <para>
       No
      </para>
      <para>
       Long Look/Sea
      </para>
      <para>
       Surge/Air
      </para>
      <para>
       Wave 89
      </para>
      <para>
       6 Jul-16 Nov 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       Personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       3.746
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       UKDF
      </para>
      <para>
       New Footing 89
      </para>
      <para>
       continuous
      </para>
      <para>
       Canungra
      </para>
      <para>
       RBAF training
      </para>
      <para>
       0.082
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       Brunei
      </para>
      <para>
       RBAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Night Falcon 89
      </para>
      <para>
       28 Apr-30 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       PNG
      </para>
      <para>
       SF training
      </para>
      <para>
       1.626
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       PNG
      </para>
      <para>
       PNGDF
      </para>
      <para>
       North Star 89
      </para>
      <para>
       16 Apr-16 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/UK
      </para>
      <para>
       Personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       1.214
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       RAF/UK Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Pacific Bond 89
      </para>
      <para>
       24 May-20 Jun 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawaii
      </para>
      <para>
       Personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.923
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Pacific Glance 89
      </para>
      <para>
       9 Mar-3 Apr 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Townsville
      </para>
      <para>
       Training of US soldiers
      </para>
      <para>
       0.023
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Pacific
      </para>
      <para>
       Reserve 89-1
      </para>
      <para>
       4-19 Mar 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       USA
      </para>
      <para>
       Army reserve exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.037
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Pacific
      </para>
      <para>
       Reserve 89-2
      </para>
      <para>
       15-30 Jul 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawaii
      </para>
      <para>
       Army reserve exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.347
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army
      </para>
      <para>
       PALEX 89
      </para>
      <para>
       24 May-20 Jun 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawaii
      </para>
      <para>
       Army personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.0662
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Paradise 89
      </para>
      <para>
       17 Sep-11 Oct 89
      </para>
      <para>
       PNG
      </para>
      <para>
       Patrol Boat exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.413
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       PNG
      </para>
      <para>
       PNGDF
      </para>
      <para>
       Penguin 89
      </para>
      <para>
       16-23 Jun 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Brunei
      </para>
      <para>
       Patrol Boat exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.304
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       Brunei
      </para>
      <para>
       RBAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Rapid Move 89
      </para>
      <para>
       8-27 Apr 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia
      </para>
      <para>
       Combined airfield defence
      </para>
      <para>
       0.392
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL
      </para>
      <para>
       RMAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Red Flag 89
      </para>
      <para>
       5-17 Mar 89
      </para>
      <para>
       USA
      </para>
      <para>
       Land exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       6.396
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USAF/NATO forces
      </para>
      <para>
       Reindeer 89
      </para>
      <para>
       7 Apr-6 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       Hong Kong
      </para>
      <para>
       Army personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.780
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       UK LFHK
      </para>
      <para>
       Rendezvous 89
      </para>
      <para>
       11 May-2 Jun 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Canada
      </para>
      <para>
       Land exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.097
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       CA/US/UK
      </para>
      <para>
       CA/US/UK forces
      </para>
      <para>
       Shorthaul 89-1
      </para>
      <para>
       26 Nov-8 Dec 89
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Tactical air lift exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.206
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Silent Pearl 89-1
      </para>
      <para>
       12-26 Feb 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawaii
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       1.826
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       Silent Pearl 89-2
      </para>
      <para>
       19 May-10 Jun 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawaii
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       1.826
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       Silent Pearl 89-4
      </para>
      <para>
       25 Nov-10 Dec 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawaii
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       1.443
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       Silicon Kiwi 89
      </para>
      <para>
       22 Jul-7 Aug 89
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Simulated military exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.0866
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Army, RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Silver Anvil 89
      </para>
      <para>
       1-13 Nov 89
      </para>
      <para>
       WA
      </para>
      <para>
       SAS exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.002
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       UK Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Southern Tiger 89
      </para>
      <para>
       25 Apr-17 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Holsworthy
      </para>
      <para>
       Land exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.555
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Starfish 89
      </para>
      <para>
       3-17 Jul 89
      </para>
      <para>
       South China
      </para>
      <para>
       Sea
      </para>
      <para>
       FPDA maritime and air warfare exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       4.485
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ/MAL/SING UK
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZN, RNZAF, RN, RMN, RSN
      </para>
      <para>
       TAMEX 89-1
      </para>
      <para>
       20-24 Feb 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Sydney/
      </para>
      <para>
       Jervis Bay
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       2.335
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NA
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       TAMEX 89-2
      </para>
      <para>
       11-16 Mar 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Sydney/
      </para>
      <para>
       Jervis Bay
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       2.387
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       TAMEX 89-4
      </para>
      <para>
       28 Nov-4 Dec 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Sydney/
      </para>
      <para>
       Jervis Bay
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       2.225
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasman Canopy 89
      </para>
      <para>
       30 Apr-7 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Parachute seminar
      </para>
      <para>
       0.079
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasman Exchange 89
      </para>
      <para>
       19 Jan-19 Feb 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Personnel exchange; costs within Golden Fleece
      </para>
      <para>
       N/A
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasman Link 89
      </para>
      <para>
       5-9 Jun 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Beecroft Range
      </para>
      <para>
       Fire support exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       3.161
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZN, NZ Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasman Ruler 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Williamtown
      </para>
      <para>
       Air Defence exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.956
      </para>
      <para>
       No
      </para>
      <para>
       Team Spirit 89
      </para>
      <para>
       12-23 Mar 89
      </para>
      <para>
       KOREA
      </para>
      <para>
       Joint field exercise-exchange personnel with US
      </para>
      <para>
       nil
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US/ROK
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army/ROK Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Timor 89
      </para>
      <para>
       1-8 Mar 89
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RMC leadership
      </para>
      <para>
       0.116
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Valiant Usher 89
      </para>
      <para>
       15-23 May 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Shoalwater Bay Area
      </para>
      <para>
       Amphibious exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       1.905
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       Wantok Warrior 89
      </para>
      <para>
       29 May-21 Jun 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/PNG
      </para>
      <para>
       Army personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.982
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       PNG
      </para>
      <para>
       PNGDF
      </para>
      <para>
       Dark Horse 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Darwin
      </para>
      <para>
       LSF TEWT
      </para>
      <para>
       0.058
      </para>
      <para>
       No
      </para>
      <para>
       Willoh 89-2
      </para>
      <para>
       27 Feb-Mar 89
      </para>
      <para>
       Ohakea NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Fighter exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       2.36
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Airlift Rodeo 90
      </para>
      <para>
       2-9 June 90
      </para>
      <para>
       USA
      </para>
      <para>
       Tactical airlift competition
      </para>
      <para>
       0.531
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Aussiam 90
      </para>
      <para>
       22-27 June 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Thailand
      </para>
      <para>
       Maritime exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.736
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       Thailand
      </para>
      <para>
       RTN
      </para>
      <para>
       Battle Heights 90
      </para>
      <para>
       6-20 May 90
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Ground defence and cold weather survival
      </para>
      <para>
       0.443
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Bell-Buoy 90-1
      </para>
      <para>
       11-22 Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Ind/Pac Ocean
      </para>
      <para>
       Naval Control and Protection of Shipping
      </para>
      <para>
       0.48
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US/UK/CAN
      </para>
      <para>
       US/UK/CAN reserve personnel
      </para>
      <para>
       Bullseye 90
      </para>
      <para>
       24-31 May 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Canada
      </para>
      <para>
       Tactical air transport exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.598
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ/CA
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZAF/CF
      </para>
      <para>
       Dark Horse 90
      </para>
      <para>
       26 Feb-3 Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Logistic TEWT (Tactical Exercise Without Troops)
      </para>
      <para>
       0.114
      </para>
      <para>
       No
      </para>
      <para>
       Dungong 90
      </para>
      <para>
       30 Ar-4 May 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Sydney/
      </para>
      <para>
       Jervis Bay
      </para>
      <para>
       Practise minelaying and ordnance disposal
      </para>
      <para>
       0.139
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       EODEX 90
      </para>
      <para>
       14-17 Apr 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Sydney/
      </para>
      <para>
       Jervis Bay
      </para>
      <para>
       Explosive Ordnance disposal and mine countermeasures
      </para>
      <para>
       0.250
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       Expanded Sea 90
      </para>
      <para>
       19-30 Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Worldwide
      </para>
      <para>
       Naval control of shipping CPX
      </para>
      <para>
       0.632
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US/ARG/CA/UK/CHI/VEN/BRA
      </para>
      <para>
       Command Post Officers
      </para>
      <para>
       EXTENDEX 90-1
      </para>
      <para>
       19-21 Feb 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Guam
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       0.760
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       EXTENDEX 90-2
      </para>
      <para>
       22-28 May 90
      </para>
      <para>
       US Pacific bases
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       0.786
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       Haringaroo 22
      </para>
      <para>
       1-14 Feb 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia
      </para>
      <para>
       Land exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.325
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Haringaroo 23
      </para>
      <para>
       10-26 May 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia
      </para>
      <para>
       Land exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.616
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Haringaroo 24
      </para>
      <para>
       10-22 June 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia
      </para>
      <para>
       Land exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.327
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL
      </para>
      <para>
       MAL Army
      </para>
      <para>
       High Slope/Oasis
      </para>
      <para>
       90-1
      </para>
      <para>
       6 Feb-6 Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       WA
      </para>
      <para>
       Unilateral SAS troop level exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.0301
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       UK SAS
      </para>
      <para>
       High Slope/Oasis
      </para>
      <para>
       90-2
      </para>
      <para>
       2-30 June 90
      </para>
      <para>
       WA
      </para>
      <para>
       Unilateral SAS troop level exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.0361
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       UK SAS
      </para>
      <para>
       HQIADS ADEX
      </para>
      <para>
       90-2
      </para>
      <para>
       13-16 Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia/
      </para>
      <para>
       Singapore
      </para>
      <para>
       FPDA Air Defence exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       5.064
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK/SING/MAL/NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       AF elements
      </para>
      <para>
       Iron Gauntlet 90
      </para>
      <para>
       15-16 May 90
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Artillery Exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.240
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Jupiter/Badge
      </para>
      <para>
       Anvil 90
      </para>
      <para>
       14-28 Aug 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Innisfail
      </para>
      <para>
       Special Forces combined exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.004
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US SF
      </para>
      <para>
       Long Look/Sea
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       Personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       3.642
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       RN/RAF/UK Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Surge/Air Wave 90
      </para>
      <para>
       4 Aug-2 Dec 90
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       Mantas 90
      </para>
      <para>
       1-8 Aug 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Vanuatu
      </para>
      <para>
       Maritime surveillance
      </para>
      <para>
       0.154
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       VAN/NZ/PNG/TONGA/SOL IS
      </para>
      <para>
       VAN/NZ/PNG/TONGA/ SOL IS Forces
      </para>
      <para>
       Night Cougar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       1-31 Aug 90
      </para>
      <para>
       USA
      </para>
      <para>
       Special Forces exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.635
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US SF
      </para>
      <para>
       Night Hawk 90
      </para>
      <para>
       20 May-8 Jun 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Brunei
      </para>
      <para>
       Special Forces exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.0866
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       Brunei
      </para>
      <para>
       RBAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Night Panther 90
      </para>
      <para>
       9 Apr-4 May 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Thailand
      </para>
      <para>
       Interoperability with SF
      </para>
      <para>
       0.092
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       Thailand
      </para>
      <para>
       RTA
      </para>
      <para>
       North Star/
      </para>
      <para>
       Southern Cross 90
      </para>
      <para>
       12 Apr-11 May 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       Army personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       1.542
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       UK
      </para>
      <para>
       UK Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Pacific Bond/
      </para>
      <para>
       PALEX 90
      </para>
      <para>
       7 May-6 Jun 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawaii
      </para>
      <para>
       Army personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       1.900
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Pacific Glance 90
      </para>
      <para>
       5-22 Jul 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Brisbane
      </para>
      <para>
       Army personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.014
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Pacific
      </para>
      <para>
       Reserve 90-1
      </para>
      <para>
       11-25 Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       USA
      </para>
      <para>
       Army personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.040
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       Reserve personnel
      </para>
      <para>
       Pacific Reserve
      </para>
      <para>
       21 Jul-5 Aug 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawaii
      </para>
      <para>
       Army reserve personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.566
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       Reserve personnel
      </para>
      <para>
       Penguin 90
      </para>
      <para>
       4-11 Jun 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Brunei
      </para>
      <para>
       Patrol Boat exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.154
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       Brunei
      </para>
      <para>
       RBAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Pitch Black 90
      </para>
      <para>
       16 Jul-3 Aug 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Darwin Area
      </para>
      <para>
       Combined air defence exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       18.111
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US/SING
      </para>
      <para>
       USAF/RSAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Ram 90
      </para>
      <para>
       14-21 Aug 90
      </para>
      <para>
       USA
      </para>
      <para>
       Reconnaissance
      </para>
      <para>
       3.211
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NATO
      </para>
      <para>
       NATO
      </para>
      <para>
       Rimpac 90
      </para>
      <para>
       2 Apr-21 May 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawaii Area
      </para>
      <para>
       Coordinate operation in multi-threat environment
      </para>
      <para>
       44.087
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US/CA/JAP/
      </para>
      <para>
       KOREA
      </para>
      <para>
       US,CA, KOR &amp;JAP force
      </para>
      <para>
       Shorthaul 90-1
      </para>
      <para>
       21-25 May 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Tactical air lift exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.0994
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Silent Pearl 90-2
      </para>
      <para>
       14 Jun-1 Jul 90
      </para>
      <para>
       USA
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW
      </para>
      <para>
       1.826
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
      <para>
       Silicon Kiwi 90
      </para>
      <para>
       16-30 Jul 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Sydney
      </para>
      <para>
       Simulated military exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       0.097
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Army/RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Starfish 90
      </para>
      <para>
       4-18 Jul 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Malaysia/
      </para>
      <para>
       Singapore
      </para>
      <para>
       FPDA maritime exercise
      </para>
      <para>
       6.020
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       FPDA
      </para>
      <para>
       FPDA Naval &amp;Air forces
      </para>
      <para>
       Swift Eagle 90
      </para>
      <para>
       18 Aug-19 Sep 90
      </para>
      <para>
       North
      </para>
      <para>
       Queensland
      </para>
      <para>
       Exercise ODF deployment procedures
      </para>
      <para>
       18.404
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Army-RRF
      </para>
      <para>
       TAMEX 90-1
      </para>
      <para>
       22 Feb-1 Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Maritime aircrew ASW training
      </para>
      <para>
       2.478
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RNSAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasman Canopy 90
      </para>
      <para>
       20-27 Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Parachute training seminar
      </para>
      <para>
       0.134
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasman Exchange 90
      </para>
      <para>
       1-30 Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.741
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Army/RNSAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasman Reserve 90
      </para>
      <para>
       3-18 Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia/
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       Reserve personnel exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       0.524
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Reserve personnel
      </para>
      <para>
       Team Spirit 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Mar 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Korea
      </para>
      <para>
       Joint field exercise-exchange personnel with US
      </para>
      <para>
       0.040
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US/ROK
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army/ROK Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Tropic Prelude 90
      </para>
      <para>
       12-25 Jun 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Enoggera
      </para>
      <para>
       Prepare for Tropic Lightning
      </para>
      <para>
       0.130
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Tropic
      </para>
      <para>
       Lightning 90
      </para>
      <para>
       5-22 Jul 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawaii
      </para>
      <para>
       Improve procedures and test interoperability between AS/US
      </para>
      <para>
       0.654
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       US Army
      </para>
      <para>
       Wallaby 90
      </para>
      <para>
       13 Aug-28 Nov 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Shoalwater
      </para>
      <para>
       Bay Area
      </para>
      <para>
       Armoured Battle Group activity
      </para>
      <para>
       0.350
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       SING
      </para>
      <para>
       SAF
      </para>
      <para>
       Willoh 90-2
      </para>
      <para>
       Jan 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Ohakea
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ Tactical fighter exchange
      </para>
      <para>
       1.396
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       NZ
      </para>
      <para>
       RNZAF
      </para>
      <para>
       EXTENDEX 90-4
      </para>
      <para>
       29 Aug-2 Sep 90
      </para>
      <para>
       Philippines
      </para>
      <para>
       ASW training
      </para>
      <para>
       0.55
      </para>
      <para>
       Yes
      </para>
      <para>
       US
      </para>
      <para>
       USN
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2523">
     <title>
      Royal Commission into Aboriginal Deaths in Custody
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="146">
      (Question No. 146)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="TJ4" page="2523" party="ALP" speaker="Walsh Sen The Hon P.A.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="TJ4">
         Senator Walsh
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Administrative Services, upon notice, on 22 August 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) What has been the total expenditure for the financial years 1987-88, 1988-89 and 1989-90 for the Royal Commission of Inquiry into Aboriginal Deaths in Custody (RCIADIC).
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) For the financial years 1987-88, 1988-89 and 1989-90 what was the expenditure for: (a) commissioners' fees; (b) counsel assisting fees; (c) consultants' fees; (d) staff salaries; (e) establishment and administrative costs; (f) legal aid to the legal representatives of the next of kin; and (g) other categories of costs.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) What have been the contributions to RCIADIC by the states and are there any costings of these contributions by the states to RCIADIC available to the Commonwealth; if so, what is the cost of these contributions.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) How much has been allocated in the program budget for RCIADIC.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) How many deaths in custody have been or are the subject of inquiry or investigation by RCIADIC.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) How many deaths in custody have been or are the subject of inquiry or investigation by the RCIADIC Queensland Commissioner L. F. Wyvill.
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) What has been the total expenditure for the financial years 1987-88, 1988-89 and 1989-90 for the Queensland office of RCIADIC.
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) How much has been allocated in the program budget for the Queensland office of RCIADIC.
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) When was Commissioner L. F. Wyvill appointed as the Queensland Commissioner for RCIADIC.
      </para>
      <para>
       (10) How much has been paid in the financial years 1987-88, 1988-89 and 1989-90 to Commissioner L. F. Wyvill in: (a) fees; (b) travelling allowance; and (c) other allowances and emoluments giving details for: (i) commonwealth car cost, (ii) Cabcharge, (iii) air travel associated with hearings, (iv) air travel other than associated with hearings of RCIADIC, (v) semi-official telephone calls, (vi) spouse travel costs, and (vii) any other categories of costs.
      </para>
      <para>
       (11) How much has been allocated in the program budget for the costs of Commissioner L. F. Wyvill.
      </para>
      <para>
       (12) As at 10 August 1990 how many people were engaged or employed in RCIADIC, giving details of job description, designation and pay levels.
      </para>
      <para>
       (13) As at 10 August 1990 how many people were engaged or employed in the Queensland office of RCIADIC, giving details of job description, designation and pay levels.
      </para>
      <para>
       (14) How many people have left the Queensland office of RCIADIC, giving details of job description, designation and pay levels.
      </para>
      <para>
       (15) As at 10 August 1990 how many people in the Queensland office of RCIADIC were lawyers or held legal qualifications.
      </para>
      <para>
       (16) As at 10 August 1990 how many people in the Queensland office of RCIADIC were non lawyers holding qualifications such as anthropology, sociology, psychology, history and other related disciplines; what are these qualifications and what were their job descriptions or designations.
      </para>
      <para>
       (17) What has been the expenditure for the financial years 1987-88, 1988-89 and 1989-90 of the Aboriginal Issues Unit of the Queensland office of RCIADIC detailing: (a) salary including overtime; (b) travel allowance; and (c) travel costs including: (i) air fares, (ii) air charter, (iii) commonwealth car cost, (iv) Cabcharge, and (v) vehicle hire.
      </para>
      <para>
       (18) How much has been allocated in the program budget for the costs of the Aboriginal Issues Unit of the Queensland office of RCIADIC.
      </para>
      <para>
       (19) How many reports had the Aboriginal Issues Unit of the Queensland office of RCIADIC provided to Commissioner Wyvill to 30 June 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       (20) What has been the expenditure for the financial years 1987-88, 1988-1989 and 1989-90 on consultants engaged by or through the Queensland office of RCIADIC detailing: (a) the number of consultants; (b) the date of the engagement; (c) the topic of the consultancy; and (d) the cost of the consultancy.
      </para>
      <para>
       (21) Were any of these consultants serving prisoners; if so, how many were serving prisoners and how much money was paid to them and for what purpose.
      </para>
      <para>
       (22) How much has been allocated in the program budget for the costs of consultants engaged by or through the Queensland office of RCIADIC.
      </para>
      <para>
       (23) How many word processors are there in the Queensland office of RCIADIC.
      </para>
      <para>
       (24) In respect of each of the individual deaths under inquiry or investigation by Commissioner Wyvill what was: (a) the date of death; (b) the date of the coroner's report; (c) the date of commencement of hearings; (d) the numbers of days of hearings involved; (e) the completion dates of the hearings; (f) the date of presentation of Commissioner Wyvill's report (if any); and (g) the approximate number of words in the main text of each report presented.
      </para>
      <para>
       (25) How many people engaged or employed in the Queensland office of RCIADIC contributed to the actual writing of draft text for the reports of Commissioner Wyvill.
      </para>
      <para>
       (26) How many days was Commissioner Wyvill paid fees for which there were no hearings held.
      </para>
      <para>
       (27) Generally, what was Commissioner Wyvill doing on the days for which he was paid fees but on which no hearings were held.
      </para>
      <para>
       (28) How many days was Counsel Assisting B. C. Hoath paid fees for which there were no hearings held.
      </para>
      <para>
       (29) Generally, what was Counsel Assisting B. C. Hoath doing on the days for which he was paid fees but on which no hearings were held.
      </para>
      <para>
       (30) In relation to the completion of RCIADIC: (a) how many extensions of time have been granted in the past; (b) has RCIADIC asked for an extension of time in which to present its reports; if so, how much longer has been asked for; and (c) will a further extension of time be granted.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="XE4" page="2523" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="XE4">
         Senator Bolkus
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I am advised that the answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) The total expenditure for the financial years 1987-88, 1988-89 and 1989-90 for the Royal Commission into Aboriginal Deaths in Custody was $23,756,800 from Department of Administrative Services appropriations as set out in the following table:
      </para>
      <para>
       Operation
      </para>
      <para>
       of the
      </para>
      <para>
       Commis
      </para>
      <para>
       sion
      </para>
      <para>
       Financial
      </para>
      <para>
       Assistance
      </para>
      <para>
       to the
      </para>
      <para>
       Parties
      </para>
      <para>
       Total
      </para>
      <para>
       $'000
      </para>
      <para>
       $'000
      </para>
      <para>
       $'000
      </para>
      <para>
       1987-88...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,743.3
      </para>
      <para>
       600.2
      </para>
      <para>
       2,343.5
      </para>
      <para>
       1988-89...
      </para>
      <para>
       7,996.2
      </para>
      <para>
       2,252.9
      </para>
      <para>
       10,249.1
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-90...
      </para>
      <para>
       9,460.7
      </para>
      <para>
       1,703.5
      </para>
      <para>
       11,164.2
      </para>
      <para>
       Total...
      </para>
      <para>
       19,200.2
      </para>
      <para>
       4,556.6
      </para>
      <para>
       23,756.8
      </para>
      <para>
       (2)-
      </para>
      <para>
       1987-88
      </para>
      <para>
       1988-89
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-90
      </para>
      <para>
       $'000
      </para>
      <para>
       $'000
      </para>
      <para>
       $'000
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) Commissioners' fees...
      </para>
      <para>
       84.8
      </para>
      <para>
       908.1
      </para>
      <para>
       864.7
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) Counsel Assisting fees...
      </para>
      <para>
       262.1
      </para>
      <para>
       1,959.7
      </para>
      <para>
       1,813.9
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) Consultants' fees...
      </para>
      <para>
       66.7
      </para>
      <para>
       153.0
      </para>
      <para>
       196.3
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) Staff salaries...
      </para>
      <para>
       279.5
      </para>
      <para>
       1,790.6
      </para>
      <para>
       2,650.8
      </para>
      <para>
       (e) Establishment and administrative costs...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,050.2
      </para>
      <para>
       3,184.8
      </para>
      <para>
       3,935.0
      </para>
      <para>
       (f) Legal aid to the legal representatives of the next of kin...
      </para>
      <para>
       415.2
      </para>
      <para>
       1,121.8
      </para>
      <para>
       855.5
      </para>
      <para>
       (g) Other categories of costs-Funds for overview and co-ordination for organisations granted leave to appear...
      </para>
      <para>
       185.0
      </para>
      <para>
       1,131.2
      </para>
      <para>
       848.0
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Under the agreed cost-sharing arrangements the Governments of the States and the Northern Territory have contributed staff and facilities in kind rather than cash and the costings of these contributions are not available. The contributions made by the various governments are as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       New South Wales (since December 1987):
      </para>
      <para>
       Salaries of two law officers and five keyboard/clerical administrative support staff;
      </para>
      <para>
       travel and accommodation costs of those staff within New South Wales;
      </para>
      <para>
       office accommodation costs, and furniture and facilities for those staff;
      </para>
      <para>
       costs of New South Wales Government officers called as witnesses.
      </para>
      <para>
       Victoria:
      </para>
      <para>
       Staff salaries:
      </para>
      <para>
       June 1988-July 1989: a law officer, a field officer and a typist during the Victorian hearings;
      </para>
      <para>
       July 1989-present: a Head of Aboriginal Issues Unit, project officer, field officer and a typist;
      </para>
      <para>
       office accommodation, furniture and facilities for those staff;
      </para>
      <para>
       travel and travel expenses for those staff within Victoria;
      </para>
      <para>
       facilities for hearings;
      </para>
      <para>
       costs of Victorian Government officers called as witnesses.
      </para>
      <para>
       Queensland:
      </para>
      <para>
       Use of magistrates' court in Brisbane;
      </para>
      <para>
       since March 1990 salaries of one full-time staff member and 10 days of one further staff member.
      </para>
      <para>
       Western Australia (since December 1987):
      </para>
      <para>
       Salaries of a law officer, a research officer and a typist;
      </para>
      <para>
       court facilities for hearings;
      </para>
      <para>
       costs of Western Australian Government officers, representing departments, called as witnesses;
      </para>
      <para>
       shared costs of Western Australian Government officers called as witnesses individually.
      </para>
      <para>
       South Australia (since December 1987):
      </para>
      <para>
       Salaries of a law officer, a research officer and secretarial assistance;
      </para>
      <para>
       travel and travel expenses for those staff within South Australia;
      </para>
      <para>
       office accommodation, furniture and facilities for those staff;
      </para>
      <para>
       meeting of some administrative expenses;
      </para>
      <para>
       court facilities for hearings;
      </para>
      <para>
       costs of South Australian Government officers called as witnesses.
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasmania:
      </para>
      <para>
       Contribution to Government of Victoria in respect of the Commission's Victorian staff who worked on the Tasmanian case.
      </para>
      <para>
       Northern Territory (since March 1988):
      </para>
      <para>
       Salaries of a law officer, a research officer and a typist;
      </para>
      <para>
       office accommodation, furniture and facilities for those staff;
      </para>
      <para>
       travel and travel expenses for those staff, in connection with Northern Territory matters;
      </para>
      <para>
       court facilities for hearings;
      </para>
      <para>
       costs of Northern Territory Government officers called as witnesses.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) $7,528,000.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) 125 deaths, 100 of which have been determined to lie within the Commission's jurisdiction.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) 35 deaths, 28 of which have been determined to lie within the Commission's jurisdiction.
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) (a) 1987-88: $263,200; (b) 1988-89: $2,133,900, (c) 1989-90: $1,909,200.
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) $960,000.
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) 6 May 1988.
      </para>
      <para>
       (10)-
      </para>
      <para>
       1987-88
      </para>
      <para>
       $
      </para>
      <para>
       1988-89
      </para>
      <para>
       $
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-90
      </para>
      <para>
       $
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) Fees...
      </para>
      <para>
       53,650
      </para>
      <para>
       540,200
      </para>
      <para>
       468,050
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) Travelling allowance...
      </para>
      <para>
       597
      </para>
      <para>
       17,580
      </para>
      <para>
       16,883
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) Other allowances and emoluments:
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) Common-
      </para>
      <para>
       wealth car cost...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       10,340
      </para>
      <para>
       11,334
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) cabcharge...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       814
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) air travel
      </para>
      <para>
       associated with hearings
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       11,783
      </para>
      <para>
       8,324
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) air travel other than associated with hearings of RCIADIC...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,203
      </para>
      <para>
       4,200
      </para>
      <para>
       5,035
      </para>
      <para>
       (v) semi-official telephone calls...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       (vi) spouse travel costs...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       3,853
      </para>
      <para>
       1,474
      </para>
      <para>
       (vii) any other
      </para>
      <para>
       categories of costs...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       (11) $287,000.
      </para>
      <para>
       (12) 140 of which 108 were paid by the Department of Administrative Services, 10 were paid by the Attorney-General's Department and 22 were provided by State governments.
      </para>
      <para>
       Categories
      </para>
      <para>
       Numbers
      </para>
      <para>
       Job Description
      </para>
      <para>
       Designation
      </para>
      <para>
       Pay Level
      </para>
      <para>
       Commissioners Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       7
      </para>
      <para>
       Associate ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (2)
      </para>
      <para>
       Confidential Clerk to a Commissioner
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-31,150
      </para>
      <para>
       Personal Secretary
      </para>
      <para>
       (5)
      </para>
      <para>
       Personal Secretary to a Commissioner
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-31,150
      </para>
      <para>
       Legal Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       24
      </para>
      <para>
       Counsel
      </para>
      <para>
       (10)*
      </para>
      <para>
       Counsel Assisting to the Commissioner
      </para>
      <para>
       2 @ $1,100/day
      </para>
      <para>
       1 @ $1,000/day
      </para>
      <para>
       1 @ $900/day
      </para>
      <para>
       1 @ $800/day
      </para>
      <para>
       4 @ $750/day
      </para>
      <para>
       1 @ $50,363 pa
      </para>
      <para>
       Senior Solicitor
      </para>
      <para>
       (10)
      </para>
      <para>
       Preparation of cases for hearing before the Commissioner. Instruct Counsel. Provide legal advice to Counsel and Commissioner.
      </para>
      <para>
       Principal Legal Officer (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       $50,363-53,616 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       Junior Solicitor
      </para>
      <para>
       (4)
      </para>
      <para>
       Preparation of cases for hearing before the Commissioner. Instruct Counsel. Provide legal advice to Counsel and Commissioner.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senior Legal Officer
      </para>
      <para>
       $42,013-45,540
      </para>
      <para>
       Investigation Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       7
      </para>
      <para>
       Investigation
      </para>
      <para>
       Officer
      </para>
      <para>
       (4)
      </para>
      <para>
       Assist legal staff in the examination of material relating to the deaths, and the preparation of cases for hearings. Locate witnesses and obtain statements.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO6 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       $34,560-39,700 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       Field Officer
      </para>
      <para>
       (3)
      </para>
      <para>
       Liaison with families of the deceased, Aboriginal people, communities and organisations in relation to the work of the Commission generally and specifically in relation to arrangements for hearings. Locate and interview witnesses and prepare statements for legal staff.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-31,150
      </para>
      <para>
       Research Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       25
      </para>
      <para>
       Senior Research
      </para>
      <para>
       Officer
      </para>
      <para>
       (6)
      </para>
      <para>
       Plan and carry out a program of research. Undertake the more complex research and prepare reports and drafts for consideration by a Commissioner. Supervise and co-ordinate the activities of junior research staff.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO7-ASO8 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       $40,906-49,194 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       Research Officer
      </para>
      <para>
       (11)
      </para>
      <para>
       Responsible for research projects under limited direction. Analyse submissions to the Commission and reports of relevant research undertaken outside the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO6
      </para>
      <para>
       $34,560-39,700
      </para>
      <para>
       Research Assistant
      </para>
      <para>
       (8)
      </para>
      <para>
       Undertake research as directed and draft reports. Monitor relevant research being undertaken outside the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-31,150
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Issues Unit Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       22
      </para>
      <para>
       Head of Units
      </para>
      <para>
       (5)
      </para>
      <para>
       Head the Aboriginal Issues Unit in respect of one of the Commissioners' areas of regional responsibility. Ensure that the Commissioner understands the views of Aboriginal people and Aboriginal communities and organisations about the reasons why so many Aboriginal people are in custody and die in custody, and their views as to how the situation can be changed.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO7-ASO8 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       $40,906-49,194 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       Project Officer
      </para>
      <para>
       (13)
      </para>
      <para>
       Plan and undertake consultations with Aboriginal communities and organisations and prepare reports of those consultations and advice to the Commissioner.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4-ASO6 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-39,700 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       Keyboard/Clerical
      </para>
      <para>
       Support Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       (4)
      </para>
      <para>
       Provide keyboard, clerical and administrative support to the Head of the Unit and the project officers.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO2-ASO3 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       $22,600-27,780 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Sup-
      </para>
      <para>
       port Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       46
      </para>
      <para>
       Secretary
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Responsible for the conduct of the Royal Commission including the management of staff, resources and activities.
      </para>
      <para>
       SES Band 1, Level 2
      </para>
      <para>
       $64,768
      </para>
      <para>
       Assistant
      </para>
      <para>
       Secretary ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Assist the Secretary in the provision of high level administrative and secretariat support to the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO8
      </para>
      <para>
       $43,944-49,194
      </para>
      <para>
       Executive Officer ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (5)
      </para>
      <para>
       EITHER: Provide high level support to the Secretary of the Commission in respect of a wide range of resource management matters including budgeting and estimating, resource allocation, expenditure monitoring, office accommodation, assets control and archival arrangements, OR Responsible to the Secretary for the efficient management and operation of the administrative function in an office of the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO7-ASO8
      </para>
      <para>
       $40,906-49,194
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative
      </para>
      <para>
       Officer ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (6)
      </para>
      <para>
       EITHER:
      </para>
      <para>
       [2] Responsible to the Secretary for the efficient management of a key administrative function such as purchasing, accounts processing or co-ordination of all arrangements for printing and presentation of Commissioners' reports. OR
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4-ASO5
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-33,930
      </para>
      <para>
       [2] Provide support to the Executive Officer in the management and operation of the administrative function and assume responsibility for the function during absences of the Executive Officer at hearings. OR
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO5 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       $32,000-33,930 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       [2] Responsible to the Secretary for the efficient management and operation of the administrative function in an office of the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO5
      </para>
      <para>
       $32,000-33,930
      </para>
      <para>
       Journalist ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Responsible for media and public relations liaison, research media-related issues and prepare reports.
      </para>
      <para>
       Journalist Grade A1
      </para>
      <para>
       $40,075
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative
      </para>
      <para>
       Assistant ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (8)
      </para>
      <para>
       Provide administrative support in a Commission office on one or more of the following:
      </para>
      <para>
       * purchasing, office supplies, furniture and fittings
      </para>
      <para>
       * accounts certification and processing
      </para>
      <para>
       * travel arrangements
      </para>
      <para>
       * registry and information management
      </para>
      <para>
       * personnel.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO2 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       $22,600-24,060 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       Secretarial Staff ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (8)
      </para>
      <para>
       Provide stenographic and secretarial assistance to Counsel Assisting, Senior Solicitors and the Secretary to the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO2 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       $22,600-25,060 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       Keyboard/Clerical
      </para>
      <para>
       Support Staff ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (16)
      </para>
      <para>
       Undertake word processing, typing, photocopying, filing, reception, telephonist, courier and other general clerical support duties.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO1 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       $9,452-22,070 (or State Govt equivalent)
      </para>
      <para>
       Computer Systems Support Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       9
      </para>
      <para>
       Provide support for the Commission's ADP facilities which include a network of Macintosh micro-computers and applications which run on the mainframe computers of the Commonwealth Attorney-General's and Administrative Services Departments.
      </para>
      <para>
       1 x CSO5
      </para>
      <para>
       3 x CSO3
      </para>
      <para>
       3 x CSO2
      </para>
      <para>
       2 x ASO2
      </para>
      <para>
       $47,282-49,194
      </para>
      <para>
       $39,288-42,327
      </para>
      <para>
       $33,623-36,246
      </para>
      <para>
       $22,600-25,060
      </para>
      <para>
       * This figure does not include Counsel appointed for a specific inquiry the hearings of which have been held.
      </para>
      <para>
       (13) 28 of which 23 were paid by the Department of Administrative Services, 4 were paid by the Attorney-General's Department and 1 was provided by the State government.
      </para>
      <para>
       Categories
      </para>
      <para>
       Numbers
      </para>
      <para>
       Job description
      </para>
      <para>
       Designation
      </para>
      <para>
       Pay level
      </para>
      <para>
       Commissioner's Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       1
      </para>
      <para>
       Personal Secretary ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1
      </para>
      <para>
       Personal Secretary to the Commissioner.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-31,150
      </para>
      <para>
       Legal Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       6
      </para>
      <para>
       Counsel ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (3)*
      </para>
      <para>
       Counsel Assisting to the Commissioner
      </para>
      <para>
       -
      </para>
      <para>
       1 @ $800/day
      </para>
      <para>
       1 @ $750/day
      </para>
      <para>
       1 @ $50,363 pa
      </para>
      <para>
       Senior Solicitor ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (3)
      </para>
      <para>
       Preparation of cases for hearing before the Commissioner. Instruct Counsel. Provide legal advice to Counsel and Commissioner.
      </para>
      <para>
       Principal Legal Officer
      </para>
      <para>
       $50,363-53,616
      </para>
      <para>
       Investigation Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       2
      </para>
      <para>
       Investigation
      </para>
      <para>
       Officer ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Assist legal staff in the examination of material relating to the deaths and the preparation of cases for hearings. Locate witnesses and obtain statements.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO6
      </para>
      <para>
       $34,560-39,700
      </para>
      <para>
       Field Officer ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Liaison with families of the deceased, Aboriginal people, communities and organisations in relation to the work of the Commission generally and specifically in relation to arrangements for hearings. Locate and interview witnesses and prepare statements for legal staff.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-31,150
      </para>
      <para>
       Research Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       5
      </para>
      <para>
       Senior Research
      </para>
      <para>
       Officer ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (2)
      </para>
      <para>
       Plan and carry out a program of research. Undertake the more complex research and prepare reports and drafts for consideration by the Commissioner. Supervise and co-ordinate the activities of junior research staff.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO7
      </para>
      <para>
       $40,906-42,327
      </para>
      <para>
       Research Officer ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (3)
      </para>
      <para>
       Responsible for research projects under limited direction. Analyse submissions to the Commission and reports of relevant research undertaken outside the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO6
      </para>
      <para>
       $34,560-39,700
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Issues Unit Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       6
      </para>
      <para>
       Head of Unit ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Head the Aboriginal Issues Unit for Queensland. Ensure that the Commissioner understands the views of Aboriginal people and Aboriginal communities and organisations about the reasons why so many Aboriginal people are in custody and die in custody, and their views as to how the situation can be changed.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO7
      </para>
      <para>
       $40,906-42,327
      </para>
      <para>
       Project Officer ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (4)
      </para>
      <para>
       Plan and undertake consultations with Aboriginal communities and organisations and prepare reports of those consultations and advice to the Commissioner.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO6
      </para>
      <para>
       $34,560-39,700
      </para>
      <para>
       Keyboard/Clerical
      </para>
      <para>
       Support Staff ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Provide keyboard, clerical and administrative support to the Head of the Unit and the project officers.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO2
      </para>
      <para>
       $22,600-25,060
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Support Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       8
      </para>
      <para>
       Executive Officer ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Responsible to the Secretary for the efficient management and operation of the administrative function in the Queensland office of the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO7
      </para>
      <para>
       $40,906-42,327
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative
      </para>
      <para>
       Officer ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Provide support to the Executive Officer in the management and operation of the administrative function and assume responsibility for the function during absences of the Executive Officer at hearings.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO5
      </para>
      <para>
       $32,000-33,930
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative
      </para>
      <para>
       Assistant ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (2)
      </para>
      <para>
       Provide general administrative support.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO2
      </para>
      <para>
       $22,600-25,060
      </para>
      <para>
       Secretarial Staff ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Provide stenographic and secretarial assistance to Counsel Assisting
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO2
      </para>
      <para>
       $22,600-25,060
      </para>
      <para>
       Keyboard/Clerical
      </para>
      <para>
       Support Staff ...
      </para>
      <para>
       (3)
      </para>
      <para>
       Undertake word processing, typing, photocopying, filing, reception, telephonist, courier and other general clerical support duties.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO1
      </para>
      <para>
       $9,452-22,070
      </para>
      <para>
       * This figure does not include Counsel appointed for a specific inquiry the hearings of which have been held.
      </para>
      <para>
       (14) 24
      </para>
      <para>
       Categories
      </para>
      <para>
       Numbers
      </para>
      <para>
       Job Description
      </para>
      <para>
       Designation
      </para>
      <para>
       Pay level
      </para>
      <para>
       Commissioner's staff
      </para>
      <para>
       5
      </para>
      <para>
       (salaries shown at
      </para>
      <para>
       10 August 1990 levels)
      </para>
      <para>
       Associate
      </para>
      <para>
       (2)
      </para>
      <para>
       Confidential Clerk to the Commissioner
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-31,150
      </para>
      <para>
       Personal Secretary
      </para>
      <para>
       (3)
      </para>
      <para>
       Personal Secretary to the Commissioner
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-31,150
      </para>
      <para>
       Legal Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       1
      </para>
      <para>
       Counsel
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Counsel Assisting to the Commissioner
      </para>
      <para>
       -
      </para>
      <para>
       $750/day
      </para>
      <para>
       Investigation Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       3
      </para>
      <para>
       Investigation Officer
      </para>
      <para>
       (2)
      </para>
      <para>
       Assist legal staff in the examination of material relating to the deaths and the preparation of cases for hearings. Locate witnesses and obtain statements.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO6
      </para>
      <para>
       $34,560-39,700
      </para>
      <para>
       Field Officer
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Liaison with families of the deceased, Aboriginal people, communities and organisations in relation to the work of the Commission generally and specifically in relation to arrangements for hearings. Locate and interview witnesses and prepare statements for legal staff.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-31,150
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Issues Unit Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       6
      </para>
      <para>
       Head of unit
      </para>
      <para>
       (2)
      </para>
      <para>
       Head the Aboriginal Issues Unit for Queensland. Ensure that the Commissioner understands the views of Aboriginal communities and organisations about the reasons why so many Aboriginal people are in custody and die in custody, and their views as to how the situation can be changed.
      </para>
      <para>
       1 x ASO7
      </para>
      <para>
       1 x ASO8
      </para>
      <para>
       $40,906-42,327
      </para>
      <para>
       $43,944-49,194
      </para>
      <para>
       Project Officers
      </para>
      <para>
       (4)
      </para>
      <para>
       Plan and undertake consultations with Aboriginal communities and organisations and prepare reports of those consultations and advice to the Commissioner.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO4-ASO6
      </para>
      <para>
       $28,690-39,700
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Support Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       9
      </para>
      <para>
       Executive Officer
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Responsible to the Secretary for the efficient management and operation of the administrative function in the Queensland office of the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO7
      </para>
      <para>
       $40,906-42,327
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Assistant
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Provide general administrative support.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO2
      </para>
      <para>
       $22,600-25,060
      </para>
      <para>
       Secretarial Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Provide stenographic and secretarial assistance to Counsel Assisting.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO2
      </para>
      <para>
       $22,600-25,060
      </para>
      <para>
       Keyboard/Clerical Support Staff
      </para>
      <para>
       (6)
      </para>
      <para>
       Undertake word processing, typing, photocopying, filing, reception, telephonist, courier and other general clerical support duties.
      </para>
      <para>
       ASO1
      </para>
      <para>
       $9,452-22,070
      </para>
      <para>
       (15) Twelve.
      </para>
      <para>
       (16) (i) One. (ii) Bachelors degree, majoring in Anthropology. (iii) Research Officer: Responsible for research projects under limited direction. Analyse submissions to the Commission and reports of relevant research undertaken outside the Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       (17)-
      </para>
      <para>
       1987-88
      </para>
      <para>
       1988-89
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-90
      </para>
      <para>
       $
      </para>
      <para>
       $
      </para>
      <para>
       $
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) Salary including overtime...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       5,175.35
      </para>
      <para>
       99,209.79
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) Travel allowance
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       22,418.00
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) Travel costs:
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) air fares...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       17,454.40
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) air charter...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       2,922.00
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) Common- wealth car cost...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       473.20
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) cabcharge...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       16.70
      </para>
      <para>
       147.60
      </para>
      <para>
       (v) vehicle hire
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       2,515.65
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) Other ...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       2,500.00
      </para>
      <para>
       54,000.00
      </para>
      <para>
       (18) $67,000.
      </para>
      <para>
       (19) No written reports.
      </para>
      <para>
       (20) 1987-88 and 1988-89:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) One.
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) 9 June 1988.
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) Provide advice to Commissioner on Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Communities and provide liaison with Aboriginal/Torres Strait Islander organisations and community groups.
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) $7,355.
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-90:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) Four.
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) (i) 1 July 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) 4 May 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) 18 May 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) 30 May 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) (i) Provision of architectural advice on the design of safe and humane prison cells, with particular regard to the needs of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander prisoners.
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) An analysis of the role and effectiveness of Governments in the delivery of services to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islanders.
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) Survey of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander inmates in prisons in South Eastern Queensland to provide statistical data on cultural, educational, employment and health background on the inmates and their views on the underlying reasons for the deaths of Aboriginals and Torres Strait Islanders in prison and police custody.
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) Prepare an analysis of the Queensland criminal justice system with a view to identifying features which disadvantage Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people and suggest remedies and/or reforms.
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) (i) $2,674.
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) $4,000.
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) $13,512 (part payment).
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) $3,400 (part payment).
      </para>
      <para>
       (21) No. The Queensland Corrective Services Commission made the services of a prisoner available to facilitate the arrangement of meetings and collection of information on Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander inmates in Queensland prisons and it was paid an amount of $2,572.
      </para>
      <para>
       (22) $58,000.
      </para>
      <para>
       (23) Fifteen.
      </para>
      <para>
       (24) -
      </para>
      <para>
       Name
      </para>
      <para>
       Date of
      </para>
      <para>
       Death
      </para>
      <para>
       Coroners
      </para>
      <para>
       Report
      </para>
      <para>
       Hearings
      </para>
      <para>
       Com-
      </para>
      <para>
       menced
      </para>
      <para>
       Hearing
      </para>
      <para>
       Days
      </para>
      <para>
       Hearings
      </para>
      <para>
       Ceased
      </para>
      <para>
       Date of
      </para>
      <para>
       Report
      </para>
      <para>
       No. of
      </para>
      <para>
       Words
      </para>
      <para>
       (a)
      </para>
      <para>
       (b)
      </para>
      <para>
       (c)
      </para>
      <para>
       (d)
      </para>
      <para>
       (e)
      </para>
      <para>
       (f)
      </para>
      <para>
       (g)
      </para>
      <para>
       LISTED-
      </para>
      <para>
       AURUKUN* ...
      </para>
      <para>
       11.4.87
      </para>
      <para>
       8.12.87
      </para>
      <para>
       22.8.88
      </para>
      <para>
       13
      </para>
      <para>
       17.5.89
      </para>
      <para>
       1.6.90
      </para>
      <para>
       13,204
      </para>
      <para>
       BARNEY ...
      </para>
      <para>
       22.2.81
      </para>
      <para>
       28.7.81
      </para>
      <para>
       17.11.89
      </para>
      <para>
       4
      </para>
      <para>
       22.3.90
      </para>
      <para>
       BINKS ...
      </para>
      <para>
       11.3.89
      </para>
      <para>
       Not com-
      </para>
      <para>
       pleted
      </para>
      <para>
       16.8.90
      </para>
      <para>
       5
      </para>
      <para>
       Not com-
      </para>
      <para>
       pleted
      </para>
      <para>
       BOOTH ...
      </para>
      <para>
       15.11.88
      </para>
      <para>
       14.12.88
      </para>
      <para>
       5.4.90
      </para>
      <para>
       4
      </para>
      <para>
       10.4.90
      </para>
      <para>
       DUNROBIN ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2.8.84
      </para>
      <para>
       20.2.85
      </para>
      <para>
       20.2.89
      </para>
      <para>
       8
      </para>
      <para>
       20.3.89
      </para>
      <para>
       9.8.90
      </para>
      <para>
       8,019
      </para>
      <para>
       HYDE ...
      </para>
      <para>
       18.12.86
      </para>
      <para>
       29.5.87
      </para>
      <para>
       17.5.89
      </para>
      <para>
       7
      </para>
      <para>
       15.5.89
      </para>
      <para>
       JOHNSON ...
      </para>
      <para>
       7.6.86
      </para>
      <para>
       19.8.86
      </para>
      <para>
       13.11.89
      </para>
      <para>
       6
      </para>
      <para>
       25.11.89
      </para>
      <para>
       KOOWOOTHA ...
      </para>
      <para>
       14.3.87
      </para>
      <para>
       14.1.88
      </para>
      <para>
       24.4.89
      </para>
      <para>
       7
      </para>
      <para>
       18.5.89
      </para>
      <para>
       KULLA KULLA ...
      </para>
      <para>
       12.8.84
      </para>
      <para>
       2.12.86
      </para>
      <para>
       13.9.88
      </para>
      <para>
       16
      </para>
      <para>
       15.3.90
      </para>
      <para>
       LACEY ...
      </para>
      <para>
       11.6.87
      </para>
      <para>
       24.10.88
      </para>
      <para>
       26.2.90
      </para>
      <para>
       1
      </para>
      <para>
       26.2.90
      </para>
      <para>
       9.8.90
      </para>
      <para>
       6,961
      </para>
      <para>
       ** ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4.12.80
      </para>
      <para>
       17.6.81
      </para>
      <para>
       17.8.90
      </para>
      <para>
       1
      </para>
      <para>
       17.8.90
      </para>
      <para>
       LORRAWAY ...
      </para>
      <para>
       16.5.81
      </para>
      <para>
       12.4.82
      </para>
      <para>
       8.8.90
      </para>
      <para>
       2
      </para>
      <para>
       Not com-
      </para>
      <para>
       pleted
      </para>
      <para>
       MAU ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3.1.81
      </para>
      <para>
       26.11.81
      </para>
      <para>
       21.2.90
      </para>
      <para>
       1
      </para>
      <para>
       21.2.90
      </para>
      <para>
       1.6.90
      </para>
      <para>
       2,234
      </para>
      <para>
       MISI ...
      </para>
      <para>
       14.3.85
      </para>
      <para>
       2.5.85
      </para>
      <para>
       15.11.89
      </para>
      <para>
       6
      </para>
      <para>
       29.3.90
      </para>
      <para>
       1.6.90
      </para>
      <para>
       4,831
      </para>
      <para>
       NOBLE ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4.12.86
      </para>
      <para>
       29.5.87
      </para>
      <para>
       11.4.89
      </para>
      <para>
       14
      </para>
      <para>
       19.5.89
      </para>
      <para>
       O'ROURKE ...
      </para>
      <para>
       11.2.80
      </para>
      <para>
       27.6.80
      </para>
      <para>
       27.9.89
      </para>
      <para>
       5
      </para>
      <para>
       10.4.90
      </para>
      <para>
       9.8.90
      </para>
      <para>
       10,258
      </para>
      <para>
       PILOT ...
      </para>
      <para>
       25.1.87
      </para>
      <para>
       28.9.87
      </para>
      <para>
       22.6.88
      </para>
      <para>
       17
      </para>
      <para>
       14.8.88
      </para>
      <para>
       28.9.90
      </para>
      <para>
       19,499
      </para>
      <para>
       RIVERSLEIGH ...
      </para>
      <para>
       13.3.87
      </para>
      <para>
       2.6.88
      </para>
      <para>
       18.10.88
      </para>
      <para>
       7
      </para>
      <para>
       4.5.89
      </para>
      <para>
       9.11.89
      </para>
      <para>
       12,089
      </para>
      <para>
       RYAN ...
      </para>
      <para>
       30.3.85
      </para>
      <para>
       21.6.85
      </para>
      <para>
       20.11.89
      </para>
      <para>
       6
      </para>
      <para>
       28.11.89
      </para>
      <para>
       SALT ...
      </para>
      <para>
       21.6.87
      </para>
      <para>
       20.12.88
      </para>
      <para>
       20.9.89
      </para>
      <para>
       7
      </para>
      <para>
       7.8.90
      </para>
      <para>
       SHORT ...
      </para>
      <para>
       24.3.89
      </para>
      <para>
       17.8.89
      </para>
      <para>
       21.5.90
      </para>
      <para>
       4
      </para>
      <para>
       29.5.90
      </para>
      <para>
       TIERS ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1.2.89
      </para>
      <para>
       1.11.89
      </para>
      <para>
       9.4.90
      </para>
      <para>
       2
      </para>
      <para>
       10.4.90
      </para>
      <para>
       WALKER ...
      </para>
      <para>
       28.8.84
      </para>
      <para>
       8.5.85
      </para>
      <para>
       1.11.88
      </para>
      <para>
       34
      </para>
      <para>
       5.12.89
      </para>
      <para>
       WEST ...
      </para>
      <para>
       9.7.87
      </para>
      <para>
       16.12.88
      </para>
      <para>
       6.3.89
      </para>
      <para>
       6
      </para>
      <para>
       20.9.89
      </para>
      <para>
       WOUTERS ...
      </para>
      <para>
       15.11.87
      </para>
      <para>
       23.2.88
      </para>
      <para>
       28.8.89
      </para>
      <para>
       4
      </para>
      <para>
       14.8.90
      </para>
      <para>
       WUJAL WUJAL* ...
      </para>
      <para>
       29.3.87
      </para>
      <para>
       8.9.87
      </para>
      <para>
       19.9.88
      </para>
      <para>
       10
      </para>
      <para>
       1.9.89
      </para>
      <para>
       23.3.90
      </para>
      <para>
       12,235
      </para>
      <para>
       YARRIE B ...
      </para>
      <para>
       14.4.86
      </para>
      <para>
       18.2.87
      </para>
      <para>
       12.2.90
      </para>
      <para>
       7
      </para>
      <para>
       26.2.90
      </para>
      <para>
       YARRIE F ...
      </para>
      <para>
       15.12.88
      </para>
      <para>
       15.6.89
      </para>
      <para>
       12.3.90
      </para>
      <para>
       4
      </para>
      <para>
       15.3.90
      </para>
      <para>
       READ OFF-
      </para>
      <para>
       DATE
      </para>
      <para>
       READ
      </para>
      <para>
       OFF-
      </para>
      <para>
       ASHWELL ...
      </para>
      <para>
       8.11.87
      </para>
      <para>
       28.2.90
      </para>
      <para>
       27.9.89
      </para>
      <para>
       BARNES ...
      </para>
      <para>
       12.8.85
      </para>
      <para>
       20.11.85
      </para>
      <para>
       27.9.89
      </para>
      <para>
       DOCTOR ...
      </para>
      <para>
       14.12.82
      </para>
      <para>
       N/A
      </para>
      <para>
       10.6.88
      </para>
      <para>
       GRAEY ...
      </para>
      <para>
       28.11.83
      </para>
      <para>
       N/A
      </para>
      <para>
       10.6.88
      </para>
      <para>
       STANLEY ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2.5.86
      </para>
      <para>
       4.1.87
      </para>
      <para>
       10.6.88
      </para>
      <para>
       TEACE ...
      </para>
      <para>
       27.10.81
      </para>
      <para>
       5.8.82
      </para>
      <para>
       27.9.89
      </para>
      <para>
       YOW YEH ...
      </para>
      <para>
       27.6.75
      </para>
      <para>
       N/A
      </para>
      <para>
       10.6.88
      </para>
      <para>
       * Location of death-name of dead person suppressed in recognition of Aboriginal customary law.
      </para>
      <para>
       ** Name suppressed.
      </para>
      <para>
       (25) Five.
      </para>
      <para>
       (26) 413.
      </para>
      <para>
       (27) Commissioner Wyvill has advised that generally he was accepting instruction for forthcoming case and jurisdictional hearings and making appropriate preparations for their conduct. He was also involved in the writing of case reports and the conduct of investigations pertaining to underlying issues including the social, cultural and legal factors which may have had a bearing on the deaths he is required to investigate. Commissioner Wyvill was also in direct consultation with other Commissioners on a number of occasions and attended a number of meetings of Commissioners. Apart from the Queensland inquiries Commissioner Wyvill also conducted one hearing in Western Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       (28) 502.6.
      </para>
      <para>
       (29) Counsel Assisting B. C. Hoath has advised that generally he was making preparations for the forthcoming hearings which included not only inquiries into deaths in custody that occurred in Queensland but also the nature and extent of the Commission's jurisdiction which was the subject of open challenge by the Queensland Government on a number of occasions. He was consulting with Commissioner Wyvill and taking and acting upon instructions from the Instructing Solicitors and consolidating the findings of cases already held for consideration by the Commissioner and generally preparing himself to assist the Commissioner in the execution of his terms of reference.
      </para>
      <para>
       (30) (a) Two.
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) Yes-3 months.
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) A decision will be announced following consultation which is currently taking place with the Governments of the States and the Northern Territory.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
   </answers.to.questions>
  </hansard>
 </body>
</html>
