<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" "hansard.dtd">
<html>
 <body>
  <hansard chamber="Senate" date="20/09/1990" page="2637" parliament.no="36" period.no="2" proof="No" session.no="1">
   <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
     <day.start date="20/09/1990">
      Thursday, 20 September 1990
     </day.start>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The DEPUTY PRESIDENT (Senator Colston) took the chair at 10 a.m., and read prayers.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </business.start>
    <petition.grp page="2637">
     <title>
      PETITIONS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10001" speaker="The Clerk">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10001">
          The Clerk
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Petitions have been lodged for presentation as follows:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <petition nameids="RD4" page="2637" presenters="BROWNHILL">
      <title>
       Air Landing Fee: New South Wales
      </title>
      <para>
       To the Honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament:
      </para>
      <para>
       This petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth that the proposed air landing fee for regional and commuter airlines landing at Sydney Mascot Airport during peak times discriminates severely against people in rural Australia and will force many airlines to either revise their schedules, cancel flights or increase passenger fares to cover this additional financial impost of the Federal Labor Government. This will result in less accessibility for country businessmen and travellers alike, will increase the costs of business for rural people and threatens the viability of many smaller airlines who provide valuable services to rural towns. We therefore call on the Federal Government to abolish all plans for the introduction of this discriminatory fee and allow commuter airlines to continue to provide their full range of services to towns throughout New South Wales.
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners as in duty bound will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="RD4">
         Senator Brownhill
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 102 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <petition nameids="8G4" page="2637" presenters="DURACK">
      <title>
       Uranium: Mining and Export
      </title>
      <para>
       To the honourable the President and members of the Senate in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of the undersigned citizens of Australia respectfully showeth:
      </para>
      <para>
       That your petitioners request that the Australian Government take steps immediately to stop the mining and export of uranium
      </para>
      <para>
       And your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.
      </para>
      <presenter.block>
       by
       <presenter>
        <name nameid="8G4">
         Senator Durack
        </name>
        <from>
         (from 31 citizens).
        </from>
       </presenter>
      </presenter.block>
     </petition>
     <para>
      Petitions received.
     </para>
    </petition.grp>
    <debate page="2637" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      PRIVATISATION
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="2637">
      <title>
       Notice of Motion
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" nameid="DJ4" page="2637" party="LP" speaker="Short Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate-
       </para>
       <para>
        (a) notes:
       </para>
       <para>
        (i) the decision by Government Senators, including senior Ministers in the Hawke Government, on 19 September 1990 to vote against a motion in the Senate calling for the Senate to endorse the selling of shares in the Commonwealth Bank, Qantas and Australian Airlines,
       </para>
       <para>
        (ii) that Cabinet has recently decided to sell shares in the Commonwealth Bank, Qantas and Australian Airlines, and that this decision has been endorsed by Caucus,
       </para>
       <para>
        (iii) that the proposal to sell shares in Qantas and Australian Airlines is to be put to the Labor Party special conference on Monday, 24 September 1990,
       </para>
       <para>
        (iv) that 5 Labor Senators-Senators Ray, Richardson, Beahan, Loosley and McKiernan-who are delegates to the special conference, voted against the resolution, and
       </para>
       <para>
        (v) that this action of Government Senators was in defiance of the strenuous efforts of the Prime Minister to win support for the policy proposals at the special conference; and
       </para>
       <para>
        (b) calls upon the Prime Minister:
       </para>
       <para>
        (i) to censure all Government Senators for gross disloyalty, and
       </para>
       <para>
        (ii) to either show that he can govern his Party or resign from attempting to govern the country, on the basis that if you can't govern your party you can't govern your country.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2637" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      MINING INDUSTRY
     </title>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="JI4" page="2637" party="LP" speaker="Panizza Sen J.H.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="JI4">
         Senator PANIZZA
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) notes that, despite the slow-down in the Australian economy, the Australian mining industry boosted its output by 14 per cent in the year to 30 June 1990, compared with the previous year; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) recognises the vital importance of that industry to Australia for preventing Australia's foreign debt, already at a record level, blowing out further.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2637" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      OLYMPIC GAMES
     </title>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="EU4" page="2637" party="NP" speaker="O'Chee Sen W.G.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="EU4">
         Senator O'CHEE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) notes with concern comments by a member of the Australian Olympic Committee that Brisbane was too small to be seriously considered as an Olympic Games venue, and that Atlanta has a population of 2.6 million people, similar to the projected population of the Brisbane conurbation in the year 2000;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) calls on the Australian Olympic Committee to explain why, if Brisbane was too small a venue, it was encouraged to spend $5million on its bid for the 1992 games; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) suggests that all interested Australian cities be allowed to bid for selection as a candidate for the Olympic Games in 2000, with no automatic selections.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2638" type="Notice of Motion">
     <title>
      SPACE EXPLORATION
     </title>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="IG4" page="2638" party="IND" speaker="Vallentine Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator VALLENTINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give notice that, on the next day of sitting, I shall move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) notes the proposed launch of the Ulysses space probe from the Kennedy Space Centre in Florida on 5 October 1990;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) notes, too, that this space probe has 24 pounds of plutonium-238 aboard in the form of fuel for generators to provide onboard electricity and warmth for instrumentation;
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) recalls the crash of a number of satellites in past years, including Skylab which came down over Western Australia and a Soviet plutonium-powered satellite which came down over Canada, scattering its deadly load over a wide area;
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) commends the Florida Coalition for Peace and Justice for opposing the Ulysses launch; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (e) urges the Federal Government to call on the Government of the United States of America not to continue with any program that puts nuclear power into space and endangers the whole earth if there is an accident.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2638" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      TABLING OF DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE" nameid="UI4" page="2638" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="UI4">
         Senator ROBERT RAY
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Manager of Government Business in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Papers are tabled in accordance with the list circulated to honourable senators. With the concurrence of the Senate I ask that the list be incorporated in Hansard.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The list read as follows-
      </para>
      <para>
       1. THE GOVERNMENT'S RESPONSE TO THE PHILOSOPHY BEHIND THE PROVISION OF AGED CARE SERVICES IN AUSTRALIA-Paper by the Minister for Aged, Family and Health Services.
      </para>
      <para>
       2. AUSTRALIAN POLICE MINISTERS' COUNCIL-National Common Police Services-Annual Report-1988-89.
      </para>
      <para>
       3. MURRAY-DARLING BASIN COMMISSION-Annual Report-1989 -including the Auditor-General's report-section 14 of the Murray-Darling Basin Act 1983.
      </para>
      <para>
       4. INDUSTRY COMMISSION-Product Liability-Report No. 4-18 July 1990.
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As the Senate will be adjourning early today to enable Estimates committees to meet, there will not be an opportunity to consider the Government documents just tabled. The documents will be listed on the Notice Paper and honourable senators will have the opportunity to consider them during General Business on Thursday, 11 October 1990.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2638" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      UNITED STATES EXPORT ENHANCEMENT PROGRAM
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Motion (by Senator Panizza) agreed to:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the Senate-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) notes with concern:
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) the record-breaking bonus paid to the United States wheat industry under the Export Enhancement Program for a sale to West African nations as well as a sale to Tunisia, and
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) that these discounted sales have already caused the Australian Wheat Board to reduce this year's projected return to growers; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) expresses these concerns to the United States administration with a view to encouraging it to cease such practices and to remind that administration that United States and Australian co-operation should go beyond the Gulf crisis.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2638" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      LEGISLATION
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Motion (by Senator Reid for Senator Hill)-by leave-agreed to:
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) That the following provisions modifying the standing orders operate in conjunction with the orders of the Senate of 5 December 1989 relating to the reference of bills to committees:
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Order 55-Paragraph (1), leave out the reference to Friday;
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Order 57-Leave out the reference to Friday; and
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Order 75-Paragraph (7), leave out the reference to Friday.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) That this order be in substitution for the order of 5 December 1989 relating to sittings of the Senate on Wednesdays, and that the order of 22 August 1990 relating to days of meeting and routine of business for the remainder of the budget sittings be varied to omit the sittings on Fridays.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) That this order come into effect on 9 October 1990.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2639" type="Committee">
     <title>
      STANDING COMMITTEE ON FOREIGN AFFAIRS, DEFENCE AND TRADE
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Motion (by Senator McKiernan for Senator Maguire) agreed to:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the following matter be referred to the Senate Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade for inquiry and report by 30 April 1991:
      </para>
      <para>
       The nature and effectiveness of past Australian participation in UN Peacekeeping Forces and activities, with particular reference to:
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) the costs and benefits to Australia and the lessons that can be drawn from past experience that may be relevant for future Australian participation;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) the current capabilities of Australian civilian and military government apparatus to participate in such activities and any steps needed to enhance that capacity;
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) the possible roles for non-military (for example civil police, Electoral Commission) and non-government organisations (Red Cross, aid organisations, UN Association, etc) in enhancing Australia's ability to participate in UN peacekeeping activities; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) the philosophical underpinning that should provide the basis for any such participation.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <qwn page="2639">
     <title>
      QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
     </title>
     <question.block page="2639">
      <title>
       NATIONAL AUSTRALIA BANK LTD: REMARKS BY TREASURER
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" nameid="8G4" page="2639" party="LP" speaker="Durack Sen The Hon P.D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="8G4">
          Senator DURACK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Leader of the Government in the Senate both in that capacity and as Minister representing the Treasurer. I refer to a statement made by the Treasurer at a press conference on 28 August last when he said:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        No federally supervised bank is in any difficulties whatsoever. The only things in difficulties are ones which have an inadequate supervision.
       </para>
       <para>
        I ask the Minister: Does this mean that no federally supervised bank has been or could be in any difficulties?
       </para>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2639" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I certainly think the statement made as at 28 August was an accurate reflection of the position which the Treasurer enunciated.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2639">
      <title>
       SYDNEY AIRPORT: THIRD RUNWAY
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" gov="1" nameid="4J4" page="2639" party="ALP" speaker="Schacht Sen C.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4J4">
          Senator SCHACHT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support. Is there any rational basis to the claim that the cost of construction of the third runway at Sydney will be 10 times the Government's projection? Also, is there any evidence to support the claim that the construction of the third runway at Sydney will increase, rather than decrease, the noise level associated with the airport's operations?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="2639" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —No, there is not any rational basis for those claims. I did hear yesterday on national television claims being made that, according to the environmental impact statement, the third runway at Sydney Airport would cost $1.7 billion. In accordance with the work that is being done in other studies, the current estimated cost of the third runway at Sydney Airport is $273m. The figure that was used yesterday by the person who made these claims on the Today program was the figure in the environmental impact statement which covered the cost of the third runway, plus the complete cost of the staged development of Badgerys Creek Airport as well. So that claim simply cannot be substantiated.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Regarding the noise level claims that have been made, two key researchers formerly employed by the National Acoustics Laboratories were quoted extensively yesterday as saying that the short term impact of noise from the third runway would be considerably greater than the noise levels estimated by the environmental impact statement. Therefore, people were saying that on that basis the third runway should not proceed. Again that is not correct.
       </para>
       <para>
        The statements made by these two researchers are correct. I agree with them that the short term impact of new noise does have a considerably greater impact on people than the steady state, if you like, impact of noise once the noise has been established for some time. The environmental impact statement recognises that at page 22. The only rational basis on which the EIS and indeed any planning for the third runway could proceed would be on the basis of the long term steady state impacts of noise at Sydney Airport and not on the impact of any new noise generated perhaps in the first six months of its operation.
       </para>
       <para>
        The proposals for the construction of a third runway, whether it proceeds or not, are predicated entirely on the removal of the east-west runway from operations. It is essential that that be done because if the air side capacity at Kingsford-Smith is increased with the construction of a third runway, the land side capacity has to be increased as well to match it. The only available land at Kingsford-Smith Airport that can be used for this purpose is currently occupied by the east-west runway. If a third runway is constructed and the east-west runway is taken out of service, as planned, the number of people seriously affected by noise at Sydney Airport will be cut by half-that is, the residents to the east and west of the airport will suffer no noise impact at all.
       </para>
       <para>
        I point out in conclusion that what appears to be an attractive option which is being pushed-certainly it is canvassed in the EIS-involves transferring all light aircraft from Bankstown to the new light aircraft facility at Badgerys Creek and then transferring commuter traffic from Sydney to Bankstown. Frankly, I am astonished that the opponents of the third runway would push such a proposal. The difficulty with that scenario is that it will not just mean the existing use of the east-west runway will have to be maintained but also the use of it to cope with the additional traffic will have to be increased. Not only does it match the traffic capacity which would be provided by a third runway and a staged development at Badgerys Creek but also it would not just sustain existing noise levels for residents around the airport; it would increase them.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
    </qwn>
    <debate page="2640" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      DISTINGUISHED VISITOR
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Order! I draw the attention of honourable senators to the presence in the President's gallery of Dr Alexander Prlja, Minister for Foreign Affairs in Serbia. On behalf of honourable senators I welcome you to the Senate and trust that your visit to Australia will be informative and enjoyable.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <qwn page="2640">
     <title>
      QUESTIONS WITHOUT NOTICE
     </title>
     <question.block page="2640">
      <title>
       NATIONAL AUSTRALIA BANK LTD: REMARKS BY TREASURER
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="DJ4" page="2640" party="LP" speaker="Short Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I ask the Minister representing the Treasurer which of the following statements by the Treasurer, Mr Keating, yesterday is correct: The National Australia Savings Bank, one, `was insolvent'; two, `was technically insolvent'; or, three, `was heading towards insolvency'? Or were none of those statements correct?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2640" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not know the context in which the respective statements were made. I think that the Opposition would be wise to direct these questions to the Treasurer in the House of Representatives.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="DJ4" page="2640" party="LP" speaker="Short Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="DJ4">
          Senator SHORT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I ask a supplementary question. Is the Minister who represents the Treasurer in this chamber seriously trying to tell the Senate that he cannot give an answer to a question which has been the hottest thing in the national media for the last 12 hours since the Treasurer made such a botched-up, scandalous attempt to denigrate the head of the National Bank yesterday?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2640" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I said in answer to Senator Short's original question, which involved issues such as whether a particular bank was technically insolvent at a particular time--
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="DJ4" speaker="Senator Short">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="DJ4">
           Senator Short
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Or insolvent, or heading towards insolvency.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I understand what the honourable senator said. Confronted with what he described as the hottest issue in the last 12 hours, he has obviously exercised his mind a little this morning and put several options to me in the question. But the fact is that it is not appropriate for me to comment on things taken out of context from the Treasurer's remarks in the House of Representatives. If Senator Short wants me to obtain an answer from the Treasurer on each of these matters for the benefit of the Senate, I will do so.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="DJ4" speaker="Senator Short">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="DJ4">
           Senator Short
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Yes. Thank you.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2641">
      <title>
       AUSTRALIAN CHAMBER OF SHIPPING: OPPOSITION ADDRESS
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="BS4" page="2641" party="ALP" speaker="Loosley Sen S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="BS4">
          Senator LOOSLEY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Is the Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support aware of an address given recently to the Australian Chamber of Shipping by the shadow Minister for shipping and waterfront reform in which the Opposition's shipping industry policies were outlined? Can the Minister inform the Senate of the consequences of implementing such policies?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="2641" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Yes, I was aware of that rather astonishing address by the shadow Minister for shipping and waterfront reform, Mr John Sharp. Nowhere is the weakness and naivety of the Opposition's approach to transport policy generally indicated more than it is in the continuing misinformation and ignorance of the industry that Mr Sharp exhibits. He addressed the Chamber of Shipping and advised it of a very dramatic development in the Opposition's policy on shipping when he said to them that the Opposition would `remove cabotage immediately'.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="JI4" speaker="Senator Panizza">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator Panizza
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Over five years.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will again quote Mr Sharp from his address: `remove cabotage immediately'. They are his words, not mine. No-one in the shipping industry doubts-even people who would like to see cabotage removed immediately-that this would instantly lead to the complete destruction of the domestic Australian shipping industry. What the people who want to see it removed say to me is, `Yes, we agree it would lead to the immediate destruction of a domestic shipping industry in Australia to do this'-that is, to open up our coast, all 12,000 miles of it, to unrestricted competition from sweated labour, flags of convenience and the full disaster-`but there will be a shake-out'.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="JI4" speaker="Senator Panizza">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator Panizza
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Oh, come on! What are you talking about?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Of course, Senator Panizza is one of those who want to see this happen.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="JI4" speaker="Senator Panizza">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="JI4">
           Senator Panizza
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —No, I want to see it over five years-if you want to get the facts straight.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Whether it is over 12 months or five years, the effect will be the same: the complete destruction of an Australian shipping industry. It is interesting to have a look around the world at the policies of maritime nations towards cabotage. There are a very small number of nations in the world that do not have cabotage. Those nations are: Ireland, Belgium, the Netherlands and the United Kingdom. One does not have to be too smart to work out why Ireland does not have cabotage, because of its close proximity to Great Britain and the intensive trade between those two nations. One does not have to be too smart to work out why Belgium does not have cabotage, because it has a coastline two inches long and two ports within close proximity to each other. One does not have to be too smart to work out why the Netherlands does not have cabotage either.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        In fact, the only major maritime nation on earth that does not have cabotage-we had an expert on waterfront reform from that country in Australia just recently-is Great Britain. The interesting thing about that is that the British have recently introduced into their Parliament legislation to return cabotage to the United Kingdom.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="RF4" speaker="Senator Cook">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="RF4">
           Senator Cook
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Now.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Indeed; Maggie has done that. Perhaps that should cross the attention of Mr Sharp. What the Australian shipping industry says, with some strength, because it was extremely alarmed by this Opposition policy, is a very simple and very logical statement, `If the Opposition wants to destroy the Australian shipping industry and if it wants to open up our coast to unrestricted competition and wipe us out overnight, then let us have some reciprocal arrangements'.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The trade unions and shipowners say to me, `We will allow into this country-we will not object-any major maritime nations similar to our own that will allow us to operate in an unrestricted manner on their coast if they are allowed to operate on ours'. That is not an unreasonable proposition, but it seems to have totally escaped Mr Sharp's attention.
       </para>
       <para>
        The other thing that intrigued me about the statement made by Mr Sharp was that he gave a commitment on behalf of the Opposition in his speech to `deregulate manning levels in Australian shipping other than those provided by safety regulations'. I was astonished to hear that we in fact had any regulations determining manning levels or crewing levels on Australian ships other than those to do with safety. I inquired and found that in fact we have not. Mr Sharp has given a public commitment to an expert group-which I can tell the Senate got a great horse laugh from the people he was talking to-that he will implement Opposition policy to take away regulations that do not exist. The only regulations that exist on crewing levels in Australia are to do with safety levels and Mr Sharp has given a commitment, thankfully, at least to retain those.
       </para>
       <para>
        The Opposition's instant policy-the one that it whipped up in an afternoon, along with removing tariffs, selling Telecom Australia, selling the Overseas Telecommunications Commission and selling Aussat Pty Ltd; during a casual afternoon sitting down with a pen and a piece of paper-is a destructive policy in the national interest. There is no reason to believe, in my view-and I hold to this view very strongly on a personal basis-that we should not treat the domestic Australian shipping industry in any other way than we are prepared to treat the other domestic transport industries, road and rail, in this country. I would like the Opposition to consider trying to apply the same kind of approach to road and rail-that is, totally free and unregulated competition from overseas operators on road and rail in Australia. The same thing applies to our coastal shipping industry.
       </para>
       <para>
        I would add, to emphasise how important that industry is to Australia, that today the Bureau of Transport and Communications Economics has released a report which indicates that the Australian domestic shipping industry contributed nearly half a billion dollars towards our balance of payments in 1986-87. This is what the Opposition is determined to destroy. I ask the Opposition to reconsider, in the national interest of Australia, this outrageous policy.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2642">
      <title>
       MIDDLE EAST
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="O14" page="2642" party="AD" speaker="Powell Sen J.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="O14">
          Senator POWELL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I preface my question to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade by noting that in sacking Air Force Chief General Michael Dugan for revealing Pentagon contingency plans for future United States air attacks on Iraq, including Baghdad, the Bush Administration has not denied the accuracy of General Dugan's revelations. I ask, first: Recalling that the Minister provided a detailed justification in international law for unilateral naval action to enforce United Nations sanctions, will the Minister detail the legal justification for a United States first strike on Iraq? Secondly, what is the Government's assessment of the number of civilians who would die if such an attack were to be carried out? Thirdly, given General Dugan's revelations that Baghdad would be a priority Pentagon target and that a high level of civilian deaths would inevitably result, can the Minister confirm that this would violate the Geneva protocols, which the Government has signalled its intention to ratify? Finally, has the Minister conveyed to the Bush Administration the Australian Government's opposition to a first strike by the United States on Iraq, should sanctions fail to liberate Kuwait? If not, why not?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE" nameid="VD4" page="2642" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="VD4">
          Senator GARETH EVANS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —As to the legal basis for military action in response to Iraq's armed attack on and invasion of Kuwait, I have already made it clear on a number of occasions that Australia regards the right of collective self-defence under article 51 of the United Nations charter as a proper basis for both military and economic retaliation. I have also made it clear, though, that it would be very much our preference that any further direct military action-that is to say, as distinct from military action by way of enforcement of the present economic sanctions-be under arrangements specifically the subject of further United Nations resolution. But that is not to say that there would be no proper legal foundation if such action were to be solely based on the right of collective defence.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        As to whether such further direct military action should now be pursued or kept open as an option, the Australian Government's view, as I have made clear on a number of occasions, most recently in a speech last Sunday night, is that military action should not be wholly ruled out at the end of the day should all other means of resolving this crisis fail. But again, this is not an option which we believe should be contemplated in the foreseeable future. That clearly remains the United States' position. Indeed, the fact that it remains the United States' position is one of the reasons why General Dugan got himself into so much trouble for rather implying otherwise, albeit not stating so directly. We are continuing to take the view, and to express this view both publicly and privately, that we would infinitely prefer to see the matter resolved by peaceful means, although of course it would have to be a principled peace, not a peace by way of appeasement. That point has been made over and over again. I do not propose to speculate further as to what such further direct military action might involve and what its consequences might be. I think that such public speculation at such a sensitive time is manifestly inappropriate and, indeed, just as inappropriate for me as it was for General Dugan.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2643">
      <title>
       NATIONAL ROADS AND MOTORISTS ASSOCIATION
      </title>
      <question electorate="NSW" gov="1" nameid="5K4" page="2643" party="ALP" speaker="Faulkner Sen J.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5K4">
          Senator FAULKNER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I ask the Minister representing the Minister for Administrative Services whether his attention has been drawn, first, to the return of electoral expenditure of the National Roads and Motorists Association, which appears to report expenditure on only one newspaper advertisement in the 1990 Federal election; and, secondly, to another advertisement authorised by the NRMA in the Central Western Daily on 23 February 1990, which is related to the Federal election campaign in the electorate of Calare. In view of the fact that the NRMA targeted the electorate of Calare for its election road funding campaign during the 1990 Federal election period, could the Minister request the Australian Electoral Commissioner to investigate whether the 1990 return of electoral expenditure of the NRMA is complete and covers all the political advertisements authorised by the NRMA during the 1990 Federal election campaign?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="2643" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My attention has been drawn to the newspaper advertisements referred to in Senator Faulkner's question. I did note the campaign run by the NRMA in the last election campaign. I have not costed the campaign but, given the type of advertising and the type of coordination that the campaign entered into, it must have cost several hundreds of thousands of dollars. It is also a campaign which ordinary members of the NRMA ought to regard-indeed, if I were an ordinary member of that organisation I would-as going beyond the reasons why they joined it. In fact, this campaign appeared to have a distinct party political purpose: it targeted the Government's marginal seats and it appeared to be coordinated with some elements of the Opposition's campaign. I think that members of the NRMA would be justified in feeling unhappy about the use of their contributions for such a party political purpose. It raises the question of members of those service organisations asking, when their contributions are increased, if their money had not been spent on party political purposes, could the same services have been delivered without the increase in contributions, that is, whether the organisation could have provided the same level of services without the need for increasing its contributions.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Opposition senators interjecting--
       </para>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —There is an interjection about union dues which I will take. Those unions that are affiliated with the Australian Labor Party are affiliated on the basis that they pay an affiliation fee and members join those unions on the basis that they know that that contribution will be made. Members do not join the NRMA on the basis that their contributions will be used for a distinct and discrete political purpose. To take those contributions without warning members that that is how their funds will be used and then use them in that way is to exploit the objectives of the organisation.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        However, in answer to Senator Faulkner's question-I note that he has asked me whether I would refer his questions to the Electoral Commission. I will do so and I will report the matter to him in due course.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2644">
      <title>
       NATIONAL BANK OF AUSTRALIA LTD: REMARKS BY TREASURER
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="NG4" page="2644" party="LP" speaker="Lewis Sen A.W.R">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NG4">
          Senator LEWIS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister representing the Treasurer. Noting the Minister's refusal to defend the Treasurer, I ask: Does he agree that a Treasurer, or indeed any responsible Minister, known to have access to confidential information about banks should be extremely careful about what he says publicly about bank solvency?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2644" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have seen nothing in the press reports as to what the Treasurer said which suggests to me a breach of confidentiality. It is not sufficient to make that unsubstantiated allegation of breach of confidentiality in a question and expect me to respond to it. On the basis of the material which I have seen and on the basis of the material which Senator Lewis has seen, I do not think that allegation stands up. The assumption in Senator Lewis's question is simply this: a Minister has access to confidential information and there is a statement made about institutions which might be affected by that confidential information; ergo the two things go together. I do not think that is a correct assumption.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2644">
      <title>
       NEW ZEALAND ACCORD
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" gov="1" nameid="ZW4" page="2644" party="ALP" speaker="Sherry Sen N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ZW4">
          Senator SHERRY
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Has the Minister for Industrial Relations seen reports that the New Zealand Government has reached an agreement on wages with the New Zealand Council of Trade Unions and the Reserve Bank of New Zealand? If these reports are correct can the Minister advise whether this agreement signifies an important change in the New Zealand wage fixing system? Does this mean that the New Zealand model is now similar in important respects to the Australian accord which has made such a significant contribution to industrial progress since the Hawke Government was first elected in 1983?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="2644" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I have seen those press reports. I have seen reports of an announcement by the Prime Minister of New Zealand, Mr Mike Moore, supported by the President of the New Zealand Federation of Labour, Mr Ken Douglas, on 17 September announcing a historic understanding that has been reached between the Government, the trade unions and the Reserve Bank of New Zealand to strike an agreement to tackle the economic problems facing New Zealand and, importantly, to change the direction of wages policy in that country.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The document is similar to the accord that has served Australia so well over the seven years of the Hawke Government and enabled-as I said in answer to a question yesterday-the household disposable income per capita to rise in the seven years of this Government by 11.1 per cent. Each party to the New Zealand accord, if I may call it that, has entered into commitments that the Government will substantially reduce its Budget deficit for 1991-92, that the New Zealand Council of Trade Unions will exercise its influence to achieve wage settlements of 2 per cent in the present wage round and other increases in wages should be based on future productivity gains, and that the Reserve Bank of New Zealand will not interfere to prevent the positive effects of these actions stabilising and then reducing interest rates in that country.
       </para>
       <para>
        The New Zealand Government has come to recognise, as we did in Australia some years ago, the need for an adjustment strategy which does not throw its economy into recession or, as Mike Moore explained it, into recession, increased unemployment and despair. He has also recognised that this approach is a vast contrast to the divisive and confrontationist approach of conservative governments and, indeed, the conservative National Party Opposition in New Zealand.
       </para>
       <para>
        There are many advantages to the accord. I will not go through them; I talked of them yesterday. But New Zealand seems to have picked up a number of strategies and elements of our accord-that is, a cooperative approach to wage restraint--
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YE4" speaker="Senator Boswell">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YE4">
           Senator Boswell
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President, I raise a point of order. I believe that one of the standing orders refers to relevance. The Minister is a Minister in the Australian Government, not the New Zealand Government. I suggest to you very strongly that, while what New Zealand is doing might be of interest, how the New Zealand Government constructs an agreement with the union movement is certainly not relevant to this chamber. Will you rule the question out of order, please?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="RF4" speaker="Senator Cook">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="RF4">
           Senator Cook
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —On the point of order, Mr Deputy President, methods and policies dealing with wage fixation are related to the portfolio of industrial relations. Therefore, the matter and the answer are relevant.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —The question cannot be ruled out of order, and neither will the answer be. There should be relevance in the Minister's answer. I think the matter at this stage is relevant in that he is using some other country to support his answer. I call Senator Cook.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Thank you, Mr Deputy President. As I was saying, a feature in the New Zealand accord similar to a feature in the Australian accord is that the New Zealanders have adopted a cooperative approach to wage restraint as part of their fight against inflation; they aim for the protection of lower income earners and fairness in economic management; and they have established an ongoing domestic summit to provide macro-economic policy advice, as we have done in Australia with the Economic Planning Advisory Council. I think that if the New Zealand accord enjoys the same success as the Australian accord does, Mike Moore will be returned in the election next month.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2645">
      <title>
       SALE OF PUBLIC ASSETS: PROCEEDS
      </title>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="WW4" page="2645" party="LP" speaker="Kemp Sen R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="WW4">
          Senator KEMP
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister representing the Treasurer to the Treasurer's statement in the other place on 13 September that funds from the sale of public assets will be used to help lower the long term cost of public debt and not to increase capital spending. Can the Minister assure this Parliament that the Government will not be bound by any resolution passed by the Australian Labor Party conference next Monday dealing with privatisation issues that proceeds from the disposal of public assets should be directed to infrastructure?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2645" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Let me explain to Senator Kemp who, having been a student for a long time might be more aware of this than many of his colleagues on the other side of the House, that the Australian Labor Party platform, which determines the basic policy parameters for the Labor Party in government, contains the provision at the beginning that the timing and implementation of policy is a matter for the government of the day.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        In terms of the substance of the honourable senator's question, from a government point of view, if we accept, for example, as I do, that Australia needs to invest a little more money in infrastructure such as ports and transport systems in order that we may be more competitive in export markets, the question of how and when we do that is a matter for the judgment of the government of the day. It is a matter of determining priorities, as governments do, between the desirability of retiring debt and the desirability of some additional investment in infrastructure, for example. That is an issue which the Government will determine at the appropriate time.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="VIC" nameid="WW4" page="2645" party="LP" speaker="Kemp Sen R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="WW4">
          Senator KEMP
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I have a supplementary question. Can I take it from that answer that the Treasurer's statement in the other place that the funds from the disposal of these public assets would not be used to increase capital spending was therefore wrong?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2645" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —No, the honourable senator cannot take that at all.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2646">
      <title>
       GREENHOUSE EMISSIONS
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="TF4" page="2646" party="AD" speaker="Coulter Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="TF4">
          Senator COULTER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Does the Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce accept the report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climatic Change Scientific Committee which says that it is vital that greenhouse gas emissions be reduced by 60 per cent, especially in industrialised countries like Australia? What initiatives has the Minister taken to ensure that Australia's industrial goals conform with this target? Specifically, what scientific research, what entrepreneurial activity and what industrial development or modification has the Minister initiated or supported to reach this target?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2646" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The question which Senator Coulter asked has a number of parts to it. In respect of all the parts of the question, I will take--
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="DJ4" speaker="Senator Short">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="DJ4">
           Senator Short
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You are having a bad day.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not normally deal with interjections, but Senator Short says that I am having a bad day. I am having a very pleasant day. I do not want the honourable senator to be worried about me; just take it easy.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Senator Coulter asks what the Government and particularly my Department have done about greenhouse gas emissions. Last year the Government adopted very strict standards in world terms about chlorofluorocarbons and was a leader in doing that. In terms of greenhouse gas research, we have a number of programs which are being funded by the Government both internationally and here in Australia. In respect of the details of those programs, I will try to get a more specific answer to Senator Coulter's question and provide him with those details as soon as possible.
       </para>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="TF4" page="2646" party="AD" speaker="Coulter Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="TF4">
          Senator COULTER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I have a supplementary question. The levity with which the Minister has dealt with the question indicates that his Department has done very little. So I ask the Minister-and the question was specifically directed to this Minister as the Minister responsible for industry-why he is supporting the continuation of old technologies and effete economic models in his support of the multifunction polis, as just one example, rather than seeking to build technologies and industries in Australia suited to the real world of tomorrow as predicted by the world's leading scientists? If he wants a specific example, why within the much-vaunted Button car plan has he not mandated energy efficiency standards rather than simply dealing with the model in ways which are totally inappropriate?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2646" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am very happy to say that the model for government which is in Senator Coulter's head is going out of fashion everywhere in the world-even, I am told, in Albania. The model which is in Senator Coulter's head is one whereby the views of an elitist group of experts on a particular topic are imposed on society without any reference to the democratic principles which, wearing his other hat, Senator Coulter purports to expound. That is the sort of suggestion which is implicit in Senator Coulter's question.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I am not, as industry Minister-and no Minister in this Government or any alternative government in this country is, thank God-about a police state mentality, chasing rabbits down every burrow in order to perpetrate a particular view of a particular individual. Senator Coulter referred in his question to eminent scientists. I suppose he would have the hide to include himself in that category.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2646">
      <title>
       SYDNEY (KINGSFORD-SMITH) AIRPORT
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="KI4" page="2646" party="LP" speaker="Parer Sen W.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support. I ask the Minister: Is there any substance to the claims made by the New South Wales Australian Labor Party (ALP) Right-led by Senator Richardson and including the Speaker, Mr Leo McLeay, and others-that it will destroy the third runway by destroying the credibility of the environmental impact statement (EIS)? I also ask the question I asked yesterday, which was not responded to: Is there any substance to the claims made by the same group that the third runway will be blocked because the New South Wales Right of the Labor Party will ensure that local fill is not available for the construction of the third runway?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="2646" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —No.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="KI4" page="2646" party="LP" speaker="Parer Sen W.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="KI4">
          Senator PARER
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I ask a supplementary question. I asked the Minister two questions. Is there any substance to the claims by the ALP Right-and publicly reported-that it will destroy the third runway by destroying the credibility of the EIS?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="2646" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —No.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2647">
      <title>
       OIL EXPLORATION: GREAT BARRIER REEF
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="XI4" page="2647" party="ALP" speaker="Reynolds Sen The Hon M.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="XI4">
          Senator REYNOLDS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I direct my question to the Minister representing the Minister for Resources. Is it true that the Bureau of Mineral Resources is still considering areas in the Coral Sea for offshore oil exploration? Is this consistent with the Australian Government's international responsibility to protect the Great Barrier Reef?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="2647" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The current Middle East crisis has emphasised the Western world's dependence on the supply of crude oil and highlights the onus on Australia to efficiently manage our own significant resources of oil. That means providing a taxation regime which favours the development of our reserves with an appropriate return to the community and continuing to open up new oil exploration fields. However, having said that, the Government is also well aware that we need to take into account the environmental sensitivities of an oil exploration program.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        There must be a fair amount of misinformation over the subject of oil exploration in the Coral Sea. But the Prime Minister made the Government's position on this clear back in July. Firstly, he said unequivocally that the Hawke Labor Government would not countenance any drilling that would endanger sensitive marine environments and that he totally ruled out any drilling within the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park.
       </para>
       <para>
        On the subject of oil exploration in areas adjacent to the Great Barrier Reef, such as the Coral Sea, the Prime Minister and the Minister for Resources-the Minister I am representing here in answering this question, Alan Griffiths-have stated that the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority would be asked for a full assessment of the proposal before any such exploration could be contemplated.
       </para>
       <para>
        Any proposals for exploration near the park would trigger the provisions of the Environment Protection (Impact of Proposals) Act. This would mean that the Minister for the Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories would examine the matter to determine whether or not further action is required, or whether a public environment report should be prepared or an environmental impact statement should be prepared.
       </para>
       <para>
        After consultation with the Queensland Government and the companies concerned, Mr Griffiths also announced in July that the Government had decided to terminate the remaining petroleum exploration permits in the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park which have been under suspension since 1971. Mr Griffiths said that he had proposed voluntary surrender of the permits to the companies concerned, but if the companies did not favour voluntary surrender an amendment would be introduced to the Petroleum (Submerged Lands) Act 1967 to terminate the permits. This decision reflects the Government's strong commitment to the protection of the Great Barrier Reef.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2647">
      <title>
       BANK INSOLVENCY
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="UJ4" page="2647" party="LP" speaker="Walters Sen M.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UJ4">
          Senator WALTERS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is to the Minister representing the Treasurer. If a bank which is under the supervision of the Reserve Bank becomes insolvent, does the Minister believe the public should be informed?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2647" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I do not know what Reserve Bank procedures are in respect of those matters. I will find out for Senator Walters and let her know.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="UJ4" page="2647" party="LP" speaker="Walters Sen M.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UJ4">
          Senator WALTERS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I ask a supplementary question. That was not the question I asked the Minister. I repeat my question. If a bank under the supervision of the Reserve Bank becomes insolvent, does the Minister believe the public should be informed?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2647" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I would think that was a matter for the Reserve Bank and I repeat the answer I gave a minute ago.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2648">
      <title>
       TRADE UNIONS
      </title>
      <question electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="2648" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6H4">
          Senator HARRADINE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is to the Minister for Industrial Relations. How many unions would be likely to lose registration rights under the Industrial Relations Act if the definition of `small unions' means an organisation of fewer than 20,000 employees and 10,000 employees respectively? Could the Minister provide us with a list of those organisations? Is he satisfied that the members of those organisations are aware of the dramatic effect that the Government's industrial relations proposals will have on them and on the existence of their organisations?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="2648" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I seek some guidance from you, Mr Deputy President, because this is a matter that is due to come on for debate in the committee stage of the Bill. I am happy to answer the matter, if I am in order in dealing with it.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You may answer it, as long as you do not anticipate debate on the Bill.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I will proceed and I am sure you will stop me if I trespass. The first part of the question was, how many unions would be affected? I cannot answer that because what has happened in the proposal is that there is a subproposal that these matters be determined by the Australian Industrial Relations Commission and that where unions so choose or wish, and can demonstrate reasons to the satisfaction of the Commission, not to comply with the minimum rule of 20,000, the Commission has the power to exempt them from it. I cannot give Senator Harradine a precise answer in terms of numbers.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="6H4" speaker="Senator Harradine">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="6H4">
           Senator Harradine
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Prima facie, on the face of it, how many?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The interjection is, prima facie how many? Therein lies the second difficulty. I can say how many unions there are with fewer than 20,000 members and how many there are with beyond the 20,000 members limit, but in looking to the future one would have to imagine that some of those below the level would amalgamate among themselves, and some of those above the level would amalgamate with those below the level. What the actual outcome would be is a matter of choice for those unions and the partners they seek in the amalgamating process. So what outcome there would be is hard to say.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        In terms of general figures, though, I have a figure of approximately-as I am working on memory I should say these are approximate figures-137 registered unions which would be reduced down to about 46, but that figure is nowhere near a guide and it does depend on the foregoing part of my answer.
       </para>
       <para>
        The second part of the question was, have they all been notified? We have notified all the relevant organisations, but whether all of the unions have been notified is a matter between those peak organisations and their affiliates.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2648">
      <title>
       AUSTRALIA POST: BUSINESS DELIVERY SERVICES DIVISION
      </title>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="FF4" page="2648" party="LP" speaker="Chapman Sen H.G.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to Senator Collins, representing the Minister for Transport and Communications. To what extent is the apparently predatory pricing policy of the business delivery services division of Australia Post, which is causing concern to an already efficient and competitive private sector service, cross-subsidised by other postal services and charges?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="2648" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The commercial activities of Australia Post are encouraged by the Government. Indeed, Australia Post has been as innovative in this area as has, for example, the Australian Broadcasting Corporation (ABC) in recent years.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="O14" speaker="Senator Powell">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="O14">
           Senator Powell
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —To the same extent?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Not to the same extent, because in the services that the ABC and Australia Post are providing there is already quite a bit of competition. The Government is sensitive to concerns that are raised from time to time from private industry in respect of the commercial activities of these public organisations. The attitude that I have taken as Minister and, I am sure, Mr Beazley has also taken as Minister in those portfolio areas that he is responsible for-and Mr Brown is responsible for this particular one-is to deal with those concerns on a case by case basis. So if Senator Chapman does have representations from private industry that raise particular concerns about any of these activities, as often does happen, I would be more than happy to take those concerns on his behalf to Mr Brown.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
      <question electorate="SA" nameid="FF4" page="2648" party="LP" speaker="Chapman Sen H.G.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="FF4">
          Senator CHAPMAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Mr Deputy President, I ask a supplementary question. The specific concern which has been raised by the private sector and to which I directed attention in my question was the extent of cross-subsidisation from other postal services and charges to the business delivery services division. I would direct the Minister's attention to that and seek a response.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NT" gov="1" ministerial="SHIPPING AND AVIATION SUPPORT" nameid="OF4" page="2648" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="OF4">
          Senator COLLINS
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The original question was a general one but, as I said, now that I have got the specifics of Senator Chapman's question, I am happy to take that up with the Minister responsible, Mr Brown.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2649">
      <title>
       PRIVATE SECTOR RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT
      </title>
      <question electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="NE4" page="2649" party="ALP" speaker="Beahan Sen M.E.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NE4">
          Senator BEAHAN
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —My question is directed to the Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce. Is the Minister aware of comments in today's Australian Financial Review that a 22 per cent increase in private sector spending on research and development to a level of $1.738m is insufficient? Can the Minister comment on the accuracy of this claim and on the effectiveness of the Government's measures to encourage private sector research and development?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2649" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I saw the article in the Australian Financial Review, by Peter Roberts I think, and it is a comment on the Australian Bureau of Statistics' business enterprise research and development survey results for the year 1988-89. From the ABS figures Australia appears to have had one of the strongest rates, if not the strongest rate, of increase in business research and development in the whole of the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        The latest data shows that business research and development of $1.738 million in 1988-89 now represents 0.52 per cent of gross domestic product (GDP). This is more than double the business research and development to GDP ratio in 1981-82.
       </para>
       <para>
        I have to interpose by saying Senator Archer will be interested in these statistics, because he receives warm applause from the troglodytes around him when he raises the question of government funding of research and development, and it is suggested by way of interjection in this place that government funding in research and development is the be-all and end-all of a community's efficiency and success in developing products and in applied and pure research. That is not so and that has never been this Government's position.
       </para>
       <para>
        So it is encouraging to see that the ratio of business research and development to GDP has doubled. I must say that while the picture for this new data is encouraging, I believe we still have some way to go.
       </para>
       <para>
        We cannot be certain of the extent to which government research and development measures supporting innovation are responsible for the research and development increases, but it is clear that private sector research and development is continuing to respond positively to a range of government measures put in place to encourage research and development, such as the tax concession, the grants for industrial research and development scheme, the partnership schemes and so on. All these things have undoubtedly been some encouragement to research and development, but I still take the point made by the article in the Australian Financial Review that the improvement in private sector research and development does not mean there is any cause for complacency about levels of research and development in Australia.
       </para>
       <para>
        I make the point that frequently Opposition spokesmen assert that the Government has no role in encouraging the commercialisation of research and development. The Government has traditionally had a role in encouraging the commercialisation of research and development in the rural and mining sectors. It has a similar role in relation to manufacturing in service industries. The Government will continue to encourage research and development efforts to be made where it has the chance of being commercialised, as well as otherwise.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2650">
      <title>
       TAX FILE NUMBER
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="YE4" page="2650" party="NP" speaker="Boswell Sen R.L.D.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="YE4">
          Senator BOSWELL
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister for Social Security to his answer to a question yesterday where he claimed that the way to protect people's privacy was to invade it in secret. I ask the Minister: Under the Government proposals announced in the Budget, the tax file number is to be used by five major agencies: the Australian Taxation Office, the Department of Social Security, the Department of Veterans' Affairs, the Department of Employment, Education and Training, and the Department of Community Services and Health. As well as this, the pharmaceutical benefits scheme is to link two of these departments-the Department of Social Security and the Department of Veterans' Affairs-to the Health Insurance Commission's computer; a match up system of six major government departments. Will the Minister confirm that information that Australians have given to these six departments about their personal affairs will now be used for purposes other than for which they gave it to the Department? Is the Minister aware that this is a breach of a fundamental privacy principle, whether it is done in secret or not? If the Minister is not aware of this, will he ask for a full and public report on this matter from the Privacy Commissioner?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="NSW" gov="1" ministerial="SOCIAL SECURITY" nameid="4E4" page="2650" party="ALP" speaker="Richardson Sen The Hon G.F.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The first point to make is that I did not say what Senator Boswell suggested I said yesterday.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="YE4" speaker="Senator Boswell">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="YE4">
           Senator Boswell
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —That's how it came out. You can forgive me for misunderstanding.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I cannot be responsible for what comes into the farthermost corners of the honourable senator's tortured mind.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="Senator Collins">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —His tortured what?
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Senator Collins should not be rude; that is appalling. That being the case, what I said yesterday was that, if Senator Boswell and other senators go out and inspect the operation, I believe many of his fears can be allayed. There is no attempt on the part of the Government to invade privacy; there is an attempt on the part of the Government to ensure that we do not pay out money to those who are not entitled to it. The efficient management of government requires that.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        There is no way that we can achieve justice for pensioners and beneficiaries if we continue to pay large sums of money to people who are entitled to none of it. The only way we will be able to make that system work is to have some kind of check. In doing that, in having a tax file number and some matching of records, we are making sure that linkage-the honourable senator used the word `link' in his question-is not what it used to mean; we are making sure that the computer terminals of departments are not linked to information that is being matched; we are making sure that public servants cannot tap into that information. By doing that we obviously protect the privacy of the individuals concerned.
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SE4" speaker="Senator Bishop">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SE4">
           Senator Bishop
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —You have no control over it.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I am happy to see that Senator Bishop is taking an interest. Anything we can do to get her off Senator Puplick's back for a while would be helpful.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SE4" speaker="Senator Bishop">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SE4">
           Senator Bishop
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —The matter is of a serious nature.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is a very serious matter. Senator Bishop spent two years of her life knocking Senator Puplick off. It must have been pretty serious to her-and she promised the Liberal Party she would get him up in an election. Let us face it-the honourable senator was not that much of an electoral plus to members of the Liberal Party in New South Wales.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! I remind the Minister of relevance.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Down the drain they went again and those opposite were to blame again. As I was saying, we will make absolutely certain that public servants in those departments will not be able to tap into those records. The only time that anyone will see any part of the records is when the computer shows us a possible incorrect payment. An investigation will then be made, but even then all information is destroyed within three months unless, of course, we discover fraud. When we discover fraud we are bound to take further action. The application of these measures will not take away people's privacy.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Many senators have expressed concern along these lines, and they are serious concerns. Senator Bell gave me a note yesterday saying that, if even one person was to receive information, that would be a breach of privacy. I understand that principle very well; in fact, no-one in my Department will see the information on the vast majority of Australian citizens. Some people will see information only when possible incorrect payments are shown up. I really do not believe that will amount to any breach of privacy.
       </para>
       <para>
        In his question, Senator Boswell mentioned the Privacy Commissioner. The Privacy Commissioner will be writing the guidelines for the application of tax file numbers right across the use of any department. He will be responsible for their implementation. He will be there watching over the shoulders of my Department and other departments to make sure that privacy is not breached.
       </para>
       <para>
        I believe the Parliament at large-I do not think I speak on behalf of the Government-has some faith in the Privacy Commissioner and in the role he will undertake. We are providing him with extra people to make sure that he can undertake this task. Everything that my Department does and other government departments do will be completely open to him. He is the one who will be writing the guidelines, not me. While Senator Boswell may not have great faith in me, and I do not think he does judging by his--
       </para>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="SE4" speaker="Senator Bishop">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="SE4">
           Senator Bishop
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —None of us do.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —If Senator Bishop had faith in me I would know I was doing something wrong.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LI4" speaker="Senator Patterson">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LI4">
           Senator Patterson
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Mr Deputy President, I raise a point of order. This is now about the third time the Minister has directed his comments across the chamber. I ask that he direct his comments through you.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! I call Senator Richardson.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4E4">
          Senator RICHARDSON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Thank you, Mr Deputy President. You will understand that, when one is confronted with such rudeness, it is very difficult to ignore it. I will ensure that all honourable senators have the opportunity to see how it works. All honourable senators will have an opportunity to see what guidelines the Privacy Commissioner comes down with. I am very confident that we will satisfy the privacy concerns not just of Senator Boswell and Opposition senators, but I hope of all Australians.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2651">
      <title>
       MIGRANTS
      </title>
      <question electorate="QLD" nameid="EU4" page="2651" party="NP" speaker="O'Chee Sen W.G.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="EU4">
          Senator O'CHEE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I refer the Minister representing the Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs to comments made recently by the Federated Australian University Staff Association to the effect that employment undertaken by English language intensive course for overseas students (ELICOS) made it doubtful whether the scheme contributed to Australia's export earnings and that the principal motive of many applicants was illegal immigration or higher wages. Will the Minister now acknowledge that the ELICOS scheme is being ripped off by many so-called students to the disadvantage of many legitimate migrants? Will the Government suspend further entry under the scheme until an urgent and full review of ELICOS is conducted?
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </question>
      <answer electorate="WA" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS" nameid="RF4" page="2651" party="ALP" speaker="Cook Sen The Hon P.F.S.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —This is a bit belated, but this is the first time Senator O'Chee has directed a question to me so I should acknowledge his presence in the chamber. I read on his curriculum vitae before he got here that he is a world ranking bobsledder. I thought at the time that there is no better symbol for the National Party than someone going downhill at great speed.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="OF4" speaker="Senator Collins">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="OF4">
           Senator Collins
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —That's a second-hand joke, Cook.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I thought it was original. I am being accused of plagiarism; I thought I was being inventive.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Order! Let us get back to the question.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="LE4" speaker="Senator Michael Baume">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="LE4">
           Senator Michael Baume
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —As the expert on snowing people, get on with it.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="RF4">
          Senator COOK
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Thanks for the blizzard from that corner. The garden gnome speaks again. I do not accept for one minute that the Government is turning a blind eye to the ripping off of any scheme but, since Senator O'Chee has made that allegation and since I cannot find the reference in my briefing folder, I will put it on notice and reply to him in due course.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2652">
      <title>
       CHILD-CARE WORKERS
      </title>
      <answer electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="2652" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="NJ4">
          Senator TATE
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Two days ago Senator Alston asked for further details of the Government's response to a recent decision of the Australian Industrial Relations Commission on child-care awards. The Minister for Aged, Family and Health Services has supplied the following answers to Senator Alston's questions. The first was: Does the Minister concede that the Government will be forced to increase child-care subsidies? The Minister answers that the Government has already provided for significant increases of fee relief subsidies in the 1991 Budget with an indexation expected in October 1991. The Government does not expect any further changes at present.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Senator Alston then asked whether such an increase has been taken into account in the Government's Budget forward estimates for child-care expenditure. The answer is that the Government has fully funded its proposed increases to child-care fee relief subsidies. Thirdly, Senator Alston asked: If not, is the Minister concerned that many working parents, as a result of the Industrial Relations Commission's decision, will no longer be able to afford child-care? The answer is that the question of affordability is central to this Government's child-care policies which is why this Budget has provided for such massive increases to child-care relief which will benefit more than 90,000 ordinary Australian families.
       </para>
       <para>
        Finally, Senator Alston asked: Will many smaller child-care operations be unable to absorb the increased costs and therefore be forced to close down? The Minister replies that the Commission's decision provides for an 18 months phase-in period. The decision on how to deal with increased costs during that time, either through increased fees or other economies, is a matter for individual services. However, there is no doubt that the extension of fee relief to the commercial sector from 1 January 1991 will be of great assistance to that sector.
       </para>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
     <question.block page="2652">
      <title>
       DISTRIBUTION OF WEALTH
      </title>
      <answer electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2652" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —On 18 September 1990 Senator Spindler asked me a question about statistics on wealth distribution in Australia and particularly whether the Government would support the collection of information on wealth distribution as a first step towards measures to reduce inequality of wealth. The Treasurer has advised me that the matter of wealth surveys was canvassed extensively about three years ago. The Government decided then not to proceed with such a survey and it has not changed its mind. There are major technical problems with the measurement of wealth. Overseas experience shows that because of these problems and community sensitivities wealth surveys do not yield reliable data.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <interject chair="0" nameid="0X4" speaker="Senator Spindler">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="0X4">
           Senator Spindler
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I seek leave to move a motion in relation to Senator Button's reply.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>
         Leave not granted.
        </para>
       </interject>
      </answer>
     </question.block>
    </qwn>
    <debate page="2653" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ADVISORY COUNCIL ON AUSTRALIAN ARCHIVES
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="2653">
      <title>
       Membership
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
        Motion (by Senator Button)-by leave-agreed to:
       </para>
       <para>
        That, in accordance with the provisions of the Archives Act 1983, the Senate choose Senator Reid to be a member of the Advisory Council on Australian Archives for a period of three years on and from 20 September 1990.
       </para>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2653" type="Bill">
     <title>
      PRIVACY AMENDMENT BILL 1989 [1990]
     </title>
     <speech electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="2653" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="NJ4">
         Senator TATE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Minister for Justice and Consumer Affairs)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —With the indulgence of the Senate, I table a supplementary explanatory memorandum relating to the Government amendments to be moved to the Privacy Amendment Bill 1989 and advise the chamber that I have already circulated material to Senator Powell and Peter Costello in relation to this matter.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2653" type="Bill">
     <title>
      PATENTS BILL 1990
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="2653">
      <title>
       In Committee
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
        Consideration resumed from 17 September.
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The TEMPORARY CHAIRMAN">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The TEMPORARY CHAIRMAN
          </name>
          <name nameid="XF4">
           (Senator Crichton-Browne)
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —The Committee is considering the Bill and nine amendments moved by Senator Coulter.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </proctext>
      <speech electorate="SA" nameid="TF4" page="2653" party="AD" speaker="Coulter Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="TF4">
          Senator COULTER
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.16)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I wish to round out a few remarks that I made when the Committee last considered the Patents Bill. I stress again that the majority of commercially used patents, in terms of the amount of money which is transacted, based on those patents, is tied strongly to a few very large companies. The use of all patents in a commercial sense rapidly becomes tied to a few very large companies. What we are doing in relation to allowing the patenting of life is very rapidly allowing life itself to become property owned exclusively by a few multinational companies. I am concerned because that fact will come to dominate in a major way the debate over the ethics which should appropriately surround the developments in the area of genetic engineering. I stress that this important debate should not be subverted by ownership of life and those very powerful interests. I point again to the way in which many of those large companies dominate the media. Therefore, they dominate the sources of what passes for information by which many people in the community will come to judge the ethics in this very important area.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I now address my remarks to the amendment which has been accepted by the Government. It has in fact been proposed by the Government but is based on Senator Harradine's earlier suggestions to the Standing Committee on Industry, Science and Technology. It differs significantly from the amendment that I have proposed in that it also includes the disallowance of the patenting of processes. I point out to Senator Button that, despite his earlier remarks in Question Time, I am not seeking to disallow the patenting of the processes but the end products of those processes. There is a very important distinction there. In deference to the general standards in the community, I was accepting the idea of intellectual property in knowledge and the patenting of the processes, but not the end products.
       </para>
       <para>
        While I will be supporting Senator Harradine's suggested amendment, as modified by the Government, I would make that distinction. I would also say that it does not really achieve a great deal because it says that humans shall not be patented. We all know that humans as such are not patentable because, firstly, they are not inventions-we already possibly have too many humans on this planet and heaven help us if we invent more-and, secondly, there are other laws which prevent us from the exclusive ownership of other people. So the first words do not mean a great deal.
       </para>
       <para>
        But where the amendment goes on to say `the biological processes for their generation'-referring specifically to human beings-it begs the very question of which we need some clarification. What are the biological processes for the generation of human beings? I would expect that those words would mean the normal processes for the generation of human beings which would involve a male and a female human being in certain actions which have been the processes of the generation of human beings for perhaps six million years. But we now have very complex and different ways of making creatures which are quasi-human. That is the very point I believe this legislation should develop, but it will not do so unless it is amended in the ways I have suggested.
       </para>
       <para>
        Enormous ethical problems surround this matter of patenting and the ownership of life, of life forms and the elements which go into life forms. It is extremely disappointing that this legislation has adopted no principles whatsoever beyond those which were written into the 1952 Act which this Bill replaces and which in itself predated by a full year the publication of Watson and Crick's model of DNA, the double helix model, on which a great deal of the developments in genetic engineering have been based, and which are accelerating enormously as we develop more sophisticated techniques for the manipulation of genes and for the passage of genes across species barriers. So I can only strongly commend to the Committee the amendments which have been moved in the name of the Australian Democrats.
       </para>
       <para>
        Question put:
       </para>
       <para>
        That the amendments (Senator Coulter's) be agreed to.
       </para>
       <division>
        <division.header>
         <tab leading="NONE" type="NORMAL">
          The Committee divided.
         </tab>
        </division.header>
        <division.data>
         <para>
          (The Temporary Chairman-Senator Crichton-Browne)
         </para>
         <para justification="CENTERJUST">
          <table cellcont="CONTINUED" colsep="1" frame="NONE" orient="PORT" pgwide="1" revchg="0" rowsep="0">
           <tgroup align="LEFT" cols="2" colsep="0">
            <colspec align="LEFT" colname="C1" colwidth="160pt">
             <colspec align="RIGHT" colname="C2" colwidth="50pt">
              <tbody valign="TOP">
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Ayes . . . . . . . . . . .
                </entry>
                <entry align="RIGHT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 9
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Noes . . . . . . . . . . .
                </entry>
                <entry align="RIGHT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 46
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                </entry>
                <entry align="RIGHT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 ——
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Majority . . . . . . . . .
                </entry>
                <entry align="RIGHT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 37
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                </entry>
                <entry align="RIGHT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 ——
                </entry>
               </row>
              </tbody>
             </colspec>
            </colspec>
           </tgroup>
          </table>
         </para>
         <ayes numvotes="9">
          <title>
           AYES
          </title>
          <table cellcont="CONTINUED" colsep="1" frame="NONE" orient="PORT" pgwide="1" revchg="0" rowsep="0">
           <tgroup align="LEFT" cols="2" colsep="0">
            <colspec align="LEFT" colname="C1" colwidth="160pt">
             <colspec align="LEFT" colname="C2" colwidth="160pt">
              <tbody valign="TOP">
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Bell, R. J.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Bourne, V. L.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Coulter, J. R. (Teller)
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Harradine, B.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Kernot, C.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Lees, M. H.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Powell, J. F.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Spindler, S. E.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Vallentine, J.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                </entry>
               </row>
              </tbody>
             </colspec>
            </colspec>
           </tgroup>
          </table>
         </ayes>
         <noes numvotes="46">
          <title>
           NOES
          </title>
          <table cellcont="CONTINUED" colsep="1" frame="NONE" orient="PORT" pgwide="1" revchg="0" rowsep="0">
           <tgroup align="LEFT" cols="2" colsep="0">
            <colspec align="LEFT" colname="C1" colwidth="160pt">
             <colspec align="LEFT" colname="C2" colwidth="160pt">
              <tbody valign="TOP">
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Archer, B. R.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Aulich, T. G.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Baume, Michael
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Beahan, M. E.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Bishop, B. K.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Boswell, R. L. D.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Campbell, I. G.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Chapman, H. G. P.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Childs, B. K.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Coates, J.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Colston, M. A.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Cooney, B. C.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Crane, W.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Crichton-Browne, N. A.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Crowley, R. A.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Devereux, J. R.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Durack, P. D.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Faulkner, J. P.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Foreman, D. J.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Herron, J.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Kemp, C. R.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Knowles, S. C. (Teller)
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Lewis, A. W. R.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Loosley, S.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Macdonald, I. D.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Maguire, G. R.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 McKiernan, J. P.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 McMullan, R. F.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Newman, J. M.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 O'Chee, W. G.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Olsen, J. W.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Panizza, J. H.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Parer, W. R.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Patterson, K. C. L.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Reid, M. E.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Reynolds, M.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Schacht, C. C.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Sherry, N. J.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Short, J. R.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Tate, M. C.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Vanstone, A. E.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Walsh, P. A.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Walters, M. S.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Watson, J. O. W.
                </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C1" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 West, S. M.
                </entry>
                <entry align="LEFT" colname="C2" morerows="0" rotate="0">
                 Zakharov, A. O.
                </entry>
               </row>
              </tbody>
             </colspec>
            </colspec>
           </tgroup>
          </table>
         </noes>
        </division.data>
        <division.result>
         <para>
          Question so resolved in the negative.
         </para>
        </division.result>
       </division>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="2654" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="6H4">
          Senator HARRADINE
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.30)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        1. Clause 18, page 11, line 4, before ``A patentable invention'', insert ``Subject to subsection (2),''.
       </para>
       <para>
        2. Clause 18, page 11, at end of clause, add the following new subclause:
       </para>
       <para>
        ``(2) Human beings, and the biological processes for their generation, are not patentable inventions.''.
       </para>
       <para>
        I need to clarify a point raised by Senator Coulter in addressing an amendment before the vote was taken. Senator Coulter indicated that my amendment could possibly cover normal processes connected with the generation of human beings. Presumably, he meant the act of sexual intercourse. It is presumably nobody's intention to have meters in bedrooms to collect a cent a time. It is an interesting thought. A law professor and writer on biotechnology, George Annas, likens patenting biological processes for the generation of human beings to `patenting a position in sexual intercourse'.
       </para>
       <para>
        Let me give an extreme example of a process which my amendment would prohibit. I refer to the techniques that may well be developed for cloning a human embryo at the four-cell stage. That is an example, albeit an extreme one, of the type of technique or process which my amendment to this Bill would prohibit from being patentable.
       </para>
       <para>
        Amendments agreed to.
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2655" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.33)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        1. Clause 27, page 13, subclause (1), line 29, omit ``(a) or''.
       </para>
       <para>
        2. Clause 43, page 20, at end of clause, add the following new subclause:
       </para>
       <para>
        ``(4) The priority date of a claim of a specification may be different from the priority date of any other claim of the specification.''.
       </para>
       <para>
        3. Clause 69, page 29, subclause (4), line 31, after ``that the Commissioner'', insert ``is satisfied is invalid unless the Commissioner''.
       </para>
       <para>
        4. Clause 142, page 53, paragraph (2)(b), line 22, omit ``45(2)'', substitute ``45(3)''.
       </para>
       <para>
        5. Clause 200, page 71, subclause (2), line 25, omit ``is privileged'', substitute``, and any record or document made for the purposes of such a communication, are privileged''.
       </para>
       <para>
        These amendments, which are proposed by the Government, were discussed during the meeting of the legislation committee and agreed to. Essentially, they are tidying-up amendments in respect of typographical errors and so on in the Bill.
       </para>
       <para>
        Amendments agreed to.
       </para>
       <para>
        Bill, as amended, agreed to.
       </para>
       <para>
        Bill reported with amendments; report adopted.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
     <debate.sub1 page="2655">
      <title>
       Third Reading
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
        Motion (by Senator Button) proposed:
       </para>
       <para>
        That this Bill be now read a third time.
       </para>
      </proctext>
      <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="IE4" page="2655" party="LP" speaker="Archer Sen B.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="IE4">
          Senator ARCHER
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Tasmania)
         </electorate>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.35)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —The Patents Bill 1990 is the first piece of legislation to be considered under this system. I can assure doubters on both sides that the system can, and in this case did, work. It worked because of three things. Firstly, we were fortunate in having a chairman in Senator Childs who ignored some of the trial rules which apparently were laid down. As a result, he made the system work. Secondly, it worked because of the cooperation of the Minister, Senator Button, in ensuring that the officers who were in attendance to give advice were allowed to do so. Thirdly, it worked because of the desire of the committee to make it work. Time was given to negotiate points, to develop amendments and to use the best advice available. No-one has lost any opportunity to participate and there is no doubt that in this case the change has been perfectly satisfactory. I would like to record that and give thanks to the people involved who made it happen.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2655" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce)
         </role>
         <time.stamp>
          (11.36)
         </time.stamp>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Following on what Senator Archer said, I would make the point that some very complex issues were involved in the Patents Bill 1990. Personally, I would like to thank the committee for the way in which it handled the issues. Let me say, however, that in respect of these committees we are, as a Senate, on something of a learning curve. I think it is something of an abuse of the system if issues which have been thrashed out and agreed in the committee again become the subject of further speeches of considerable length in the chamber itself. I think that is something we have to sort out in looking at the operation of the system.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        There is always a tendency to say that if a system does not work after a short trial, because we have become used to our conventional ways, we should abandon it. I hope that that view is not strongly held in the Senate. But it will become a strongly held view if senators do not abide by the spirit of the system, which is designed to ensure that Bills are perhaps more adequately inquired into without posturing before the committee or in the chamber itself. I hope that we can learn from the experience of this committee and others to arrive at a workable system. I thank Senator Archer for his comments.
       </para>
      </speech>
      <speech electorate="SA" nameid="TF4" page="2655" party="AD" speaker="Coulter Sen J.R.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="TF4">
          Senator COULTER
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (South Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I did not intend to speak at this stage of the debate. However, I hope that the remarks by Senator Button a few moments ago were not directed at something I did. I felt that on this occasion the system worked extremely well in that the consideration of amendments which I put to the Standing Committee on Industry, Science and Technology, although rejected by that Committee, allowed me to come back with amendments which were quite substantially different. Although based on the same arguments, they were different in kind and suggested a different mechanism. I was able to put that different mechanism before the Committee of the Whole. It seems to me that in that respect the system worked extremely well and I do not believe that it has delayed the passage of this Bill in any way at all.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Question resolved in the affirmative.
       </para>
       <para>
        Bill read a third time.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2656" type="Committee">
     <title>
      STANDING COMMITTEE ON REGULATIONS AND ORDINANCES
     </title>
     <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="SE4" page="2656" party="LP" speaker="Bishop Sen B.K.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="SE4">
         Senator BISHOP
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales)
        </electorate>
        <time.stamp>
         (11.39)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-I present the Department of Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs Procedures Advice Manual and seek leave to move a motion in relation to these documents.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="SE4">
         Senator BISHOP
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate take note of the documents.
      </para>
      <para>
       Honourable senators will recall that at the end of 1989 the Migration Act was amended extensively. Following these amendments a completely fresh group of migration regulations was made. These regulations were scrutinised by the Standing Committee on Regulations and Ordinances for compliance with its principles of personal liberties and parliamentary proprieties. The Committee has difficulties with some of the aspects of these regulations. However, following advice from the Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (Mr Hand) that an announced major review of the regulations should satisfy the concerns of the Committee, it was decided to defer final consideration until after the review was completed.
      </para>
      <para>
       In the meantime, to assist in its scrutiny, the Regulations and Ordinances Committee asked the Minister for a copy of the Procedures Advice Manual of the Department of Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs. This is the manual of guidelines and procedures used by officers of the Department to administer the Act and the Regulations. The Minister promptly furnished a copy, for which the Committee is grateful.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Committee decided that it would be appropriate to table the manual as an example of the quasi-legislation through which the day-to-day administration of many Acts and Regulations is conducted. These are the documents piled on my desk. In the present case, the manual comprises 195 booklets, some 3,300 pages, as amended by 41 policy control instructions and is 30 centimetres or about one foot high.
      </para>
      <para>
       The manual is a public document available for purchase at the Australian Government Bookshop, although it is priced at about $300, with special folders to keep the booklets costing another $100. Individual booklets may be purchased for $1.50 each. In this case the documents are at least available, even though they are expensive. In some other agencies manuals are unavailable to members of the public, who face procedural difficulties even in obtaining knowledge of their existence.
      </para>
      <para>
       When dealing with members of the public or people overseas wishing to visit or migrate to Australia, it is to the manual that departmental officers refer, at least in the first instance. This quasi-legislation is not subject to tabling or disallowance in Parliament, although it may have an important effect upon the way in which entire classes of individual cases are decided and is, therefore, at least partly legislative in character. For example, the expression `reasonable period' is not defined in respect of a particular provision of the Regulations. The manual advises, however, that for this purpose a reason- able period is normally three years. Other procedures in the manual are less certain. One booklet advises that certain persons are to be contacted by overseas posts of the Department and invited to purchase an application for migration to Australia package.
      </para>
      <para>
       The manual demonstrates an awareness that the entire migration program is based upon powers contained in Acts of Parliament and in regulations and other instruments made under the authority of Acts. The manual urges all officers of the Department to become familiar with the general provisions of the Migration Act and Regulations. The manual wisely advises that its procedures and guidelines do not have the same legal standing as Acts or regulations and should be applied in accordance with the principles of administrative law on the merits of each individual case. In addition, the manual properly points out that government actions must be consistent with the laws enacted by the Federal Parliament to regulate migration. Accordingly, I have tabled this huge manual and seek leave to incorporate in Hansard a table of contents of the manual.
      </para>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The table read as follows -
      </para>
      <para>
       Procedures Advice Manual
      </para>
      <para>
       Table of Contents
      </para>
      <para>
       (The numbers in brackets indicate the number of Booklets dealing with that topic.)
      </para>
      <para>
       1. Technical procedures relating to visas and entry permits
      </para>
      <para>
       The visa system (3)
      </para>
      <para>
       Visa and entry permit exemptions (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       The entry permit system (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Travel documents (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       2. Criteria and procedures for various classes of visas and entry permits
      </para>
      <para>
       Permanent entry visas (19)
      </para>
      <para>
       Refugee and humanitarian visas (12)
      </para>
      <para>
       Student and trainee visas and entry permits (9)
      </para>
      <para>
       Temporary resident visas and entry permits (27)
      </para>
      <para>
       Visitor visas and entry permits (8)
      </para>
      <para>
       Transit visas (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Diplomatic and official visas (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Territorial Asylum (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Conditional visas and entry permits (6)
      </para>
      <para>
       Border visas and entry permits (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Return visas for Australian residents (7)
      </para>
      <para>
       Processing entry permit (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory visitors (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Limitations on further applications (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Permanent entry permits after entry (6)
      </para>
      <para>
       Refugee temporary entry permits (5)
      </para>
      <para>
       Humanitarian responses to people temporarily in Australia (6)
      </para>
      <para>
       Transitional arrangements (7)
      </para>
      <para>
       3. Subjects common to two or more classes of visas/entry permits
      </para>
      <para>
       People with extremist/controversial views (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Bona fides requirement (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Character requirement (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Settlement requirement (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Health requirement (6)
      </para>
      <para>
       Special procedures for particular countries/ nationalities (3)
      </para>
      <para>
       Access to education outside student status (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Marriage and divorce (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       De facto marriage relationships (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Custody of minor children (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Family Unit and dependency (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Balance of family test (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration (Guardianship of Children) Act 1946 (1)
      </para>
      <para>
       Sponsorships (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Assurances of Support (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Assessment of skills and qualifications (3)
      </para>
      <para>
       Occupational classification (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Tripartite negotiated arrangements (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Employer nomination scheme (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Business migration program (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Special skills (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Reporting (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Entry program management (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Fees (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Review by Migration Internal Review Office (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       4. Matters primarily related to compliance functions
      </para>
      <para>
       Introduction to compliance (3)
      </para>
      <para>
       Status of illegal entrant (3)
      </para>
      <para>
       Illegal entrants (8)
      </para>
      <para>
       Custody and apprehension (4)
      </para>
      <para>
       Deportation (13)
      </para>
      <para>
       Offences and prosecutions under the Migration Act (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       Issue of documents to facilitate travel for prohibited entrants and deportees (l)
      </para>
      <para>
       People with outstanding debts to the Commonwealth (2)
      </para>
      <para>
       People excluded from readmission to Australia (l)
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="EU4" page="2657" party="NP" speaker="O'Chee Sen W.G.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="EU4">
         Senator O'CHEE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
        <time.stamp>
         (11.44)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The tabling of the Procedures Advice Manual marks a significant step forward in immigration policy. One of the criticisms of the current legislation and the current delegated legislation, to wit the Migration Regulations, is that it is very unclear. In many respects, the operations of the Department of Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs seem to many applicants unreasonable or very secretive. It is a mark of some concern that when many of my colleagues and I asked the Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (Mr Hand) to provide us with a copy of the manual, that was not so done. I am very pleased that the Minister provided a copy of the manual to the Standing Committee on Regulations and Ordinances and that the Committee was able to obtain the documents here in the Senate. This means that the documents are readily available and are open to public scrutiny.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Given the very imprecise language that appears in many of the Migration Regulations, it is absolutely critical that the documents be available to the public so that people can see how the Department assesses applications. Unless this is the case, we run a very grave risk of individual civil liberties and rights of applicants wishing to come to this country being in some ways limited or contravened by virtue of the operation of the manual. Generally, we need to shorten the legislation regarding immigration. We need to make it much simpler. I am very pleased that a few months ago the Minister gave some sort of undertaking to the Senate to do that. This matter must be pursued as a matter of urgency.
      </para>
      <para>
       I am pleased that this Procedures Advice Manual has been tabled. I look forward to a continuing improvement in the operations of the Department and a continuing openness that we have seen in its dealings with this Committee.
      </para>
      <para>
       Question resolved in the affirmative.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2658" type="Committee">
     <title>
      STANDING COMMITTEE ON PUBLICATIONS
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="2658">
      <title>
       Report
      </title>
      <speech electorate="WA" gov="1" nameid="1I4" page="2658" party="ALP" speaker="McKiernan Sen J.P.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="1I4">
          Senator McKIERNAN
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Western Australia)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present the third report of the Standing Committee on Publications.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Report-by leave-adopted.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2658" type="Adjournment">
     <title>
      ADJOURNMENT
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="2658">
      <title>
       Estimates Committees
      </title>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="2658" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="4F4">
          Senator BUTTON
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria-
         </electorate>
         <role>
          Leader of the Government in the Senate)
         </role>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —To enable Estimates committees to meet, I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate do now adjourn.
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The ACTING DEPUTY PRESIDENT
          </name>
          <name nameid="ZF4">
           (Senator Crowley)
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Before the Senate adjourns I advise honourable senators that Estimates Committee A will meet in Senate committee room 14 and will be televised on channel 2; Estimates Committee C will meet in Senate committee room 13; Estimates Committee D will meet in the main committee room; and Estimates Committee E will meet in Senate committee room 16.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>
         Question resolved in the affirmative.
        </para>
        <para>
         Senate adjourned at 11.47 a.m. till Tuesday, 9 October 1990, at 2 p.m.
        </para>
       </interject>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2658" type="Documents">
     <title>
      DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The following documents were tabled:
      </para>
      <para>
       Christmas Island Act-Christmas Island Lands Ordinance-Notice of guidelines under section 4, dated 11 September 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Civil Aviation Act-Civil Aviation Orders 1990-Parts-
      </para>
      <para>
       105, Amendments, dated 31 July, 2 August, 7 August, 22 August, 28 August, 29 August and 3 September 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       106, Amendments, dated 28 August 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       107, Amendments, dated 28 August 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Housing Authority Act-Statement made under section 10 (3) (a), dated September 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Lands Acquisition Act-Statement describing lands acquired by agreement under subsection 40 (1) of the Act for specified public purposes.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
   </chamber.xscript>
   <answers.to.questions page="2659">
    <title>
     ANSWERS TO QUESTIONS
    </title>
    <proctext>
     <para>
      The following answers to questions were circulated:
     </para>
    </proctext>
    <answer.to.qon page="2659">
     <title>
      Sydney Airport
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="44">
      (Question No. 44)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="NSW" nameid="RD4" page="2659" party="NP" speaker="Brownhill Sen D.G.C.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="RD4">
         Senator Brownhill
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support, upon notice, on 24 May 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) What action has the Civil Aviation Authority (CAA) taken since late 1989 to alleviate congestion and other related difficulties at Kingsford-Smith Airport (KSA).
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Has the Authority carried out any studies of industry requirements at KSA; if so, what are they and at what cost.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Has the CAA employed extra staff to consult with industry; if so, who and at what cost.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) How many staff have left the CAA since June 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) How many people have commenced employment with the CAA since June 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) Has the CAA employed any overseas personnel since June 1989.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="NSW" nameid="OF4" page="2659" party="ALP" speaker="Collins Sen The Hon R.L.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="OF4">
         Senator Collins
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) The Civil Aviation Authority has introduced a range of measures to improve capacity at Sydney (Kingsford-Smith) Airport. In February 1989 a team of CAA officers visited a number of North American airports with similar runway configurations to Sydney to identify any scope for improving the efficiency of the Air Traffic Services (ATS) system at Sydney. The team's report, known as the Bigsworth report, made a number of recommendations to improve Sydney Airport's capacity. The major recommendations have been implemented or are well advanced. These include:
      </para>
      <para>
       * 25 knot cross-wind standards implemented in February 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       - the increase in the cross-wind standard to 25 knots will reduce the frequency of the need to confine operations to a single runway.
      </para>
      <para>
       * Simplified Standard Instrument Departures (SIDS) to be implemented in August 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       - Sydney Airport has 87 SIDS to provide for every outbound track from each runway. These have been simplified which will lead to reduced workload for controllers.
      </para>
      <para>
       * New wake turbulence separation standards to be implemented prior to end of 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       - the new standards are based on distance rather than time which cuts down the separation required for each aircraft, thus reducing delays.
      </para>
      <para>
       * Surface movement radar commissioned in November 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       * Extended simultaneous runway operations (SIMOPS) are under consideration with the staff association and the Industrial Relations Commission
      </para>
      <para>
       - it is proposed to make the standards for SIMOPS more flexible which will increase the opportunities for simultaneous use of both runways and so reduce delays.
      </para>
      <para>
       * Terminal area severe turbulence (TAST) displays currently under operational evaluation.
      </para>
      <para>
       * New wind analysers are expected to be commissioned by end of 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       - the above facilities provide controllers with improved meteorological information on which to base operational decisions.
      </para>
      <para>
       The CAA engaged the Mitre Corporation to undertake a study of how capacity could be improved based on Sydney Airport's existing runway configurations. The Corporation's report makes a number of recommendations, which essentially provide no new findings of substance over and above the work being undertaken in response to the Bigsworth report. It does provide broad confirmation of the work already being undertaken by the CAA. Some matters canvassed in the report raise issues of Government policy, such as changes to the present noise abatement procedures, and so require Government consideration. Industry operators and staff associations have been invited to comment on the report prior to implementation of any of the recommendations.
      </para>
      <para>
       The CAA is upgrading and replacing the existing radar system at the airport. The new radar system is scheduled to be provided towards the end of 1992.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Instrument Landing system (ILS) is being upgraded. The refurbishment of the ILS on 07 runway was completed in September 1989. In March 1990 the outer marker for runway 34 was commissioned. The localiser, glide-path, middle and outer markers for runway 16 have been replaced. The glide-path will be relocated to the other side of the runway when the Federal Airports Corporation completes taxiway works later this year.
      </para>
      <para>
       Training of Air Traffic Service (ATS) staff is being undertaken at full capacity. There are 220 air traffic controllers in training at the Centre for ATS at the Tasmanian Institute of Technology, Launceston, with 60 in training at the CAA's Central Training College in Melbourne. Seventy four of these are expected to graduate within the next year. The CAA is also recruiting experienced controllers from overseas, and about 40 controllers should commence duty in August 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       The CAA, has established a Flow Management Unit which is developing improved arrangements for the management of the flow of air traffic on the major trunk routes. A Flow Management Information System (FMIS) has been implemented to measure and report on delays on the major trunk routes. Discussions are continuing with industry operators on the possible introduction of an industry regulated schedule rationalisation committee. It is proposed that the committee would work towards implementing airline schedules which facilitate an orderly flow of airline traffic, and avoid the present situation where a number of flights are scheduled to depart/arrive at the same time.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Particular studies undertaken by the CAA on industry requirements at Sydney Airport include the Bigsworth report and the Mitre Corporation report. The former report involved travel costs only for the relevant officers of $14,000. The Mitre Corporation report cost $172,153, which included the consultancy charges and associated on-costs for travel and expenses.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) No extra staff have been employed to specifically undertake consultation with the aviation industry. A considerable number of operational and management positions with responsibility for safety standards and aviation services within the CAA routinely consult with the industry. Since the CAA was established special emphasis has been placed on these aspects of the Authority's operations to achieve increased responsiveness to industry and the community.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Since June 1989, 663 staff have left the CAA.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) There have been 938 staff commence employment with the CAA since June 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) The CAA has not employed any overseas personnel through overseas recruitment action since June 1989. Through normal domestic recruitment advertising, overseas personnel may have applied and been employed in the CAA.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2660">
     <title>
      Parliament House: Disposal of Waste
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="53">
      (Question No. 53)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="7U4" page="2660" party="AD" speaker="Bell Sen R.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="7U4">
         Senator Bell
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the President the following question, upon notice, on 25 May 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) What procedures are followed for the disposal of wastes generated in Parliament House, specifically: (a) paper; (b) metal; (c) glass; (d) plastic; (e) organic waste and food scraps?
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) How and where are these waste products separated?
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) What contracts have been let for the disposal or recycling of wastes from Parliament House?
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) (a) are these contracts at present in force?
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) (b) are they at present being actively effected?
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) (c) if not, why not?
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) (d) what types of waste are being disposed of in ways other than according to contract?
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Where is this waste disposal occurring?
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) What quantities of waste are generated by the operation of Parliament House, specifically: (a) paper; (b) metal; (c) glass; (d) plastic; (e) organic waste and food scraps?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="" nameid="10000" page="2636" party="" speaker="The President">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="10000">
         The President
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
       <para>
        (1) The bulk of waste material produced in Parliament House is processed through the central waste system (CWS). The waste material consists mainly of the contents of office waste bins and large amounts of newspapers, reports and other waste paper. The waste is collected by contract cleaning staff and fed into the CWS chutes which are positioned at strategic locations on each floor of the building. Non-recyclable waste (eg. Kitchen waste and building materials) is fed into the garbage compactor at the loading dock and subsequently taken to the tip. The answer to question 2 addresses specific details relating to procedures for the disposal of paper; metal; glass; plastic; organic waste and food scraps.
       </para>
       <para>
        (2) Paper-this is divided and separated into two categories-
       </para>
       <para>
        contaminated non-recyclable paper waste (i.e. Newspapers/paper collected with plastics and food scraps) This is processed through the central waste system, baled and taken to the tip.
       </para>
       <para>
        Uncontaminated recyclable paper waste (i.e. computer paper, reports etc)-processed through the CWS (on a special run) baled and sold to a contractor.
       </para>
       <para>
        Metal-collected separately, placed into a special container at the loading dock and taken away for recycling by a contractor.
       </para>
       <para>
        Glass-collected separately, placed into containers (brown, clear, green glass) at the loading dock and taken away for recycling by a contractor.
       </para>
       <para>
        Plastic-processed with contaminated non-recyclable waste and taken to the tip.
       </para>
       <para>
        Organic waste and food scraps-organic waste is taken to Mugga Lane recycling depot to be turned into compost. Wet food scraps are disposed of down the insinkerators and dry food scraps are deposited in the garbage compactor at the loading dock and taken to the tip.
       </para>
       <para>
        (3) A 2-year contract was awarded to Pacific Waste Management Pty Ltd on 26 August 1988 for a total waste removal and recycling service.
       </para>
       <para>
        (4) (a) Yes
       </para>
       <para>
        (b) Yes
       </para>
       <para>
        (c) Not applicable
       </para>
       <para>
        (d) organic waste
       </para>
       <para>
        (5) Mugga Lane depot
       </para>
       <para>
        (6) (a) 95 tonnes a year
       </para>
       <para>
        (6) (b) 5 tonnes a year
       </para>
       <para>
        (6) (c) 10 tonnes a year
       </para>
       <para>
        (6) (d) not known
       </para>
       <para>
        (6) (e) organic waste-550 cubic meters
       </para>
       <para>
        (6) food scraps-not known
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2661">
     <title>
      Department of Veterans' Affairs: Legal Services
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="105">
      (Question No. 105)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="BE4" page="2661" party="LP" speaker="Newman Sen J.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BE4">
         Senator Newman
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Minister for Veterans' Affairs, upon notice, on 19 July 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) How much does the division of legal services in the department cost to run per year.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) How much does it cost (including superannuation) to employ Attorney-General's staff for use in veterans' matters.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) How many cases per year do these people see.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="NJ4" page="2661" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="NJ4">
         Senator Tate
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Minister for Veterans' Affairs has provided the following answers to the honourable senator's questions:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) There is no Legal Services Division within the Department. Responsibility for AAT and VRB matters lies with the Compensation and Review Branch within the Benefits Program. Responsibility for the Department's legislative program and general legal advisory service lies with the Legal Services Group within the Corporate Services Program. The cost of running these functions has been interpreted as the cost of salaries and administration and as not embracing the cost of counsel and other fees. (See the response to the House of Representatives Question on Notice 2205 of 27 November 1989 for details of counsels' costs).
      </para>
      <para>
       During the 1989/90 financial year $1,719,663 was spent on salaries and $366,198 on administration for the Review Section. $472,844 was spent on salaries and $166,889 for administration for the Legal Services Group.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) The Attorney-General is responding to this question.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) In respect of Department of Veterans' Affairs officers, the Review Section handled 3205 cases in 1989-90. This comprised 1924 on hand at the beginning of the year and 1281 new cases received during the year. Of these, 1231 were finalised, leaving 1974 on hand at the end of the year.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Legal Services Group generally does not have responsibility for individual case files unless litigation arises in respect of the Department, the Repatriation Hospitals or the Repatriation Commission. The majority of staff are involved in the provision of general legal advisory and legislation services to the Department and the Repatriation Commission on a wide range of issues affecting all Programs and areas of the portfolio. This may involve the provision of advice on individual cases but, with the exception of Federal Court matters, is limited to specific aspects of pension or treatment entitlement under the Veterans' Entitlements Act, rather than carriage of a matter in the appeal system. In respect of Federal Court action arising from the determining system, during 1989-90 the Group examined 49 cases referred for possible Federal Court appeal. Forty three appeals were lodged by veterans and the Repatriation Commission. Thirty four cases were resolved and at the end of the year 26 cases remained outstanding.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2661">
     <title>
      Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade: Ministerial Councils
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="111">
      (Question No. 111)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="BE4" page="2661" party="LP" speaker="Newman Sen J.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BE4">
         Senator Newman
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, upon notice, on 11 July 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) How many Ministerial councils or similar forums exist for the meeting of State, Federal and other Ministers.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) What are their names and general objectives.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) How many times per year do(es) the council(s)/forum(s) meet.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) What is the membership (including officials) of each council/forum, and who chairs the meetings.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Is (are) the council(s)/forum(s) served by a secretariat; if so, in each case, what is its composition, who is responsible for financing it, and what does it cost.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) What meetings of the council(s)/forum(s) were held for the last 3 financial years and how many persons attended the meetings, including officials and private ministerial staff.
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) What were the costs of each of these meetings to the Commonwealth including travel, entertainment or dinners/lunches, accommodation, etc.
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) Where were the meetings held and what was the venue.
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) Are the records of the meetings available to the public; if so, where can they be obtained; if not, why not.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="VD4" page="2661" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="VD4">
         Senator Gareth Evans
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       On 22 December 1989 I provided the honourable senator with a reply to an almost identical question. Accordingly, I refer Senator Newman to that reply which, for her convenience, I will repeat.
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) None
      </para>
      <para>
       (2)-(9) Not applicable.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2662">
     <title>
      Department of Finance: Cheques
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="130">
      (Question No. 130)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="QLD" nameid="YH4" page="2662" party="LP" speaker="MacGibbon Sen D.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YH4">
         Senator MacGibbon
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister representing the Minister for Finance, upon notice, on 31 July 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       I refer to a recent bungle in Queensland when a Department of Finance cheque for $31208 which was made payable to Office 2, Collins Place, Duporth Avenue, Maroochydore was delivered in error to Shop 2 of the same address and ask: (a) how many Department of Finance cheques are made payable to addresses rather than to the names of individuals; and (b) why is this done.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="QLD" nameid="4F4" page="2662" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator Button
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The Minister for Finance has provided the following answer to the honourable senator's question:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (a) and (b)
      </para>
      <para>
       The Department of Finance produced approximately 3,312,000 cheques in the year ended 30 June 1990 for payments on behalf of departments.
      </para>
      <para>
       One of the systems used to process the payments is known as the General Payments System (GPAY). The payment in question was one of approximately 771,000 cheques which were produced by the GPAY system in 1989/90.
      </para>
      <para>
       Each user of the GPAY system is provided with a General Payments System Handbook. Chapter 3 of the Handbook advises departments of the format required to enter the payee name followed by up to 3 lines of address. In addition, user departments are advised of input format requirements in Finance's Computer Interface Standards Manual.
      </para>
      <para>
       The data is submitted to the Department of Finance on magnetic tape and is not checked other than to edit that there are at least four characters in the Payee Name field. The accuracy of the data is the responsibility of the department submitting the data, in this case, the Department of Community Services and Health (DCSH) in Brisbane.
      </para>
      <para>
       DCSH has advised the Department of Finance that it has put in place procedures to prevent the recurrence of similar problems.
      </para>
      <para>
       It is not possible to identify how many cheques are made payable to addresses rather than to the names of individuals as the department initiating the payment would have the cheque returned to it for amendment. (The name of the department appears on the cheque butt).
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2662">
     <title>
      Fiji: New Constitution
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="136">
      (Question No. 136)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="LH4" page="2662" party="ALP" speaker="Jones Sen G.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LH4">
         Senator Jones
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, upon notice, on 13 August 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) Has the Australian Government taken steps to recognise the new Fijian Constitution.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Does the new Fijian Constitution address the question of equal rights in line with the United Nations Charter.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Under the new constitution are Indians, Chinese and other races, except for indigenous Fijians, excluded from owning land or from becoming civic leaders or members of parliament.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) In what way does the Fijian Constitution differ from that of South Africa.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Does this Government intend to continue aid payments to Fiji.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="VD4" page="2662" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="VD4">
         Senator Gareth Evans
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's questions is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) Since 19 January 1988, Australian policy has been that the Government will not extend formal recognition, whether de facto or de jure, to new governments taking power in other countries. Instead, Australian authorities will conduct relations with new regimes to the extent and in the manner which may be required by the circumstances of each case. Since January 1988 Australia has recognised the State of Fiji. The recent promulgation of the constitution in Fiji has not affected this. The question of recognition of the new Fiji Constitution does not arise.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) The UN Charter sets out the basic principles and structure of the United Nations Organisation. Its provisions essentially concern relations between States. The Charter does not impose obligations on States in the conduct of their domestic affairs. Article 2.7 expressly provides that the UN may not intervene in matters which are within the domestic jurisdiction of any State. International standards of human rights are set out in two major international covenants: the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, and the International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights. Fiji is not a party to either of these treaties. However, Fiji has ratified the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination (CERD). A comprehensive range of human rights safeguards is contained in Chapter II of the new Fiji Constitution titled ``Protection of Fundamental Rights and Freedoms of the Individual''. These safeguards include detailed provisions for protection from discrimination on the grounds of race. This protection is subject to other provisions of the constitution and, in particular, can be overridden by Chapter III on ``Protection and Enhancement of Fijian and Rotuman Interests'' which gives Parliament and Cabinet certain powers to enact legislation or make directions, in essence to promote the economic, social, educational, cultural, traditional and other interests of the Fijian (and Rotuman) people. This has given rise to some concern that Chapter III in particular may be used in the future in a way which disadvantages the non-Fijian communities in Fiji, particularly, Fiji-Indians. There is also concern at the racial imbalances in the constitution, including the number of seats in parliament reserved for the different communities, and the reservation of certain positions for Fijians only.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Under the new constitution the provisions for ownership of land remain unchanged from the 1970 Constitution. While the majority of land in Fiji (approximately 82%) is owned by the traditional Fijian landholders, other races are not precluded from owning land designated as freehold land. A significant amount of the land owned by Fijians is leased, particularly by Fiji-Indian cane farmers, and administered by the Native Lands Trust Board. Provisions for positive discrimination for Fijians in some areas, particularly economic areas, will make it more difficult for other races to become civic leaders but will not exclude them except, effectively, from the Presidency, and explicitly from the Prime Ministership and the Chairmanship of the Police Services Commission. The new constitution provides for representation in parliament for all races, although with 37 of 70 lower house seats reserved for them, an indigenous Fijian majority is assured. Fiji-Indians have 27 of 70 seats in the House of Representatives reserved for them, while 5 seats are reserved for General Electors (Other Races), including Fiji citizens of Chinese origin, and 1 seat is reserved for Rotumans. In the Senate, there will be 24 chiefs appointed by the President on the advice of the Great Council of Chiefs, one Rotuman and nine Senators from ``other Communities'', also appointed by the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) The constitutions of South Africa and Fiji are quite different. South Africa, unlike any other country in the world, bases its entire social and political system on an institutionalised form of racial discrimination underpinned by its constitution which affects all aspects of the lives of its people, including where they may live and go to school. In South Africa, furthermore, the African majority (some 70% of the population) is constitutionally excluded from any representation in the national parliament. The new constitution in Fiji is racially based and racially biased and has serious flaws, but will at least provide for a return to representative government, with all ethnic groups represented in a single parliament. In addition, the Fiji constitution contains significant safeguards for the fundamental rights and freedoms of Fiji citizens and (unlike its South African counterpart and the laws enacted under it) makes no provision for separate development or institutionalised segregation. The features of the Fiji constitution that have attracted the most criticism are those provisions that actually or potentially favour the indigenous race in terms of parliamentary representation, affirmative action in the economic, social and educational sphere, and the filling of certain positions, as noted above. The shortcomings of the Fiji constitution, although serious, clearly fall well short of those of the South African constitution.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Yes. Australia's aid to Fiji is designed to benefit all communities regardless of ethnic origin and the disbursement of the program is monitored closely. The Defence Cooperation Program with Fiji was suspended following the coups in 1987 and remains suspended.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2663">
     <title>
      Fiji: New Constitution
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="138">
      (Question No. 138)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="LH4" page="2663" party="ALP" speaker="Jones Sen G.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LH4">
         Senator Jones
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, upon notice, on 13 August 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) Does the Government intend taking any action to censure the Fiji Government for its racist constitution.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) In view of this country's attitude towards South Africa, where a racist constitution is in force, will the Government be taking a similar stand against Fiji.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) What amount of aid does Fiji receive from Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Has the Government any intention of cutting aid to Fiji in light of its racist attitude towards the Indians and Chinese.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="QLD" gov="1" nameid="VD4" page="2663" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="VD4">
         Senator Gareth Evans
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's questions is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) The Australian Government has already made known to the Fiji Government its views on the new Fiji constitution, notably in the meeting between the Prime Minister and the Prime Minister of Fiji, Ratu Sir Kamisese Mara, on 2 August, 1990 in Port Vila. The Government has said that the new racially based and racially biased constitution entrenches communal divisions and does not allow fair representation for all groups in Fiji. However, the Government takes the view that, despite its serious flaws, the new constitution at least provides an opportunity for Fiji to return to representative government. In that sense, it provides a firmer basis for government than the interim arrangements in place since the coups. Regrettably, but realistically, there appears to be no likelihood that a significantly better constitution could be agreed upon at this time in Fiji.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) No. There are significant differences between the constitutions of South Africa and Fiji. South Africa, unlike any other country in the world, bases its entire social and political system on an institutionalised form of racial discrimination (apartheid) which affects all aspects of the lives of its people. Africans, who make up almost 70% of the population, have no vote and are not represented in the central parliament. It is for such reasons that successive Australian Governments have maintained an unambiguous opposition to apartheid and participated in international efforts to bring pressure to bear on South Africa for genuine political change. The new constitution in Fiji has serious flaws but these are not as significant or as pervasive as those of the South African constitution and the laws which it underpins.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Australia's regular bilateral aid program for Fiji in 1990/91 is $13.6 million. In addition, Fiji benefits through Australia's contribution to regional organisations and programs, including the South Pacific Forum Secretariat, the Forum Fisheries Agency, the South Pacific Applied Geoscience Commission, the University of the South Pacific and the South Pacific Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) No. Australia's bilateral aid program will continue at normal levels. The program is designed to benefit all communities regardless of ethnic origin and the disbursement of the program is monitored closely. The Defence Cooperation Program with Fiji was suspended following the coups in 1987 and remains suspended.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2664">
     <title>
      Electoral Rolls
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="145">
      (Question No. 145)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="QLD" nameid="KI4" page="2664" party="LP" speaker="Parer Sen W.R.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="KI4">
         Senator Parer
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Administrative Services, upon notice, on 22 August 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) For each electorate, how many people were enrolled after the announcement of the March 1990 election and before the close of the rolls.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) For each electorate, how many people were removed from the rolls after the election as a result of the `Objection Process'.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) What is the program for habitation reviews in each state and what measures are being taken to ensure that the electoral rolls are as accurate as possible in the lead up to the 1990 redistribution.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Were the enrolment projections prepared by the Australian Electoral Commission (AEC) prior to the last redistribution seriously flawed and did this result in a situation where 50 out of the 114 seats on the eastern seaboard failed to achieve the 2 per cent tolerance specified under the Act as the target to be achieved by December 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Given that population projections play such a critical part in the redistribution process, can the Minister give an assurance that the AEC's research paper providing enrolment projections will be released in sufficient time to allow for independent scrutiny and, if necessary, for underlying assumption to be challenged.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="QLD" nameid="XE4" page="2664" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="XE4">
         Senator Bolkus
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) Attached at Appendix A are lists of the numbers of enrolment forms processed from announcement of the General Election on 16 February to close of rolls on 26 February 1990 for each electorate in each State. The enrolment forms processed encompass voters who have enrolled for the first time, or who have re-enrolled, or who have moved into the electoral division, or who have moved within a division and lodged an enrolment form.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) The Australian Electoral Commission will not be in a position to indicate the number of people for each electorate who were removed from the rolls after the election until all post-election objection action is finalised and the subsequent objection tapes are processed. This exercise is currently under way and is expected to be finalised soon. The Commission expects the information requested to be available in October and this will be made available to the honourable senator by way of a supplementary answer.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) The timetable for the electoral roll review for each State is as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       New South Wales
      </para>
      <para>
       Field Work: commence 1 October 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Processing: finalise by May 1991
      </para>
      <para>
       Victoria
      </para>
      <para>
       Field Work: commence 8 October 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Processing: finalise by May 1991
      </para>
      <para>
       Queensland
      </para>
      <para>
       Field work: commence 1 October 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Processing: finalise by March 1991
      </para>
      <para>
       Western Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       A review was completed last year
      </para>
      <para>
       South Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Field Work: commence 8 October 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Processing: finalise by March 1991
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasmania
      </para>
      <para>
       Field Work: commence 15 October 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Processing: finalise by May 1991
      </para>
      <para>
       Northern Territory
      </para>
      <para>
       To be determined.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Capital
      </para>
      <para>
       Territory
      </para>
      <para>
       Field Work: commence 17 September 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Processing: finalise by May 1991
      </para>
      <para>
       In addition to its ongoing roll maintenance work, the Commission is taking the following steps to have the electoral rolls as accurate as possible in the lead up to the 1990 redistributions:
      </para>
      <para>
       results from the electoral roll reviews (or habitation reviews) and post-election objection action will be used to update the Commission's enrolment information on the electoral rolls.
      </para>
      <para>
       A number of reviews and enhancements have been made to the computerised roll maintenance system which have improved the system performance and increased the accuracy of data processing in regard to electoral rolls.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) At the time of the 1984 redistributions, the relevant provision of the Commonwealth Electoral Act 1918, now section 73 (4) (a), specified that each augmented Electoral Commission, in making its final determination of electoral boundaries, should `as far as practicable, endeavour to ensure that, 3 years and 6 months after the making of the determination, the number of electors enrolled in each Electoral Division in the State or Territory will be equal''. There was no reference in the Act at that time to the 2 per cent tolerance mentioned in the honourable senator's question.
      </para>
      <para>
       The timing of the 1984 redistributions was such that in no State or Territory did the 3 years and 6 months period referred to in section 73 (4) (a) of the Act expire in December 1987.
      </para>
      <para>
       The following table sets out the number of Electoral Divisions in each State and the Australian Capital Territory which, 3 years and 6 months after the particular 1984 redistributions at which they were created, had enrolments which differed from the relevant State or Territory average enrolment by up to 2%; by between 2.1% and 5%; by between 5.1% and 10%; and by more than 10%.
      </para>
      <para>
       Number of Divisions differing from average by:
      </para>
      <para>
       0-2%
      </para>
      <para>
       2.1-5%
      </para>
      <para>
       5.1-10%
      </para>
      <para>
       &gt;0%
      </para>
      <para>
       NSW ...
      </para>
      <para>
       26
      </para>
      <para>
       17
      </para>
      <para>
       8
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       VIC ...
      </para>
      <para>
       18
      </para>
      <para>
       12
      </para>
      <para>
       9
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       QLD ...
      </para>
      <para>
       7
      </para>
      <para>
       12
      </para>
      <para>
       4
      </para>
      <para>
       1
      </para>
      <para>
       WA ...
      </para>
      <para>
       8
      </para>
      <para>
       5
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       SA ...
      </para>
      <para>
       7
      </para>
      <para>
       6
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       TAS ...
      </para>
      <para>
       5
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       ACT ...
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       2
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       0
      </para>
      <para>
       TOTAL ...
      </para>
      <para>
       71
      </para>
      <para>
       54
      </para>
      <para>
       21
      </para>
      <para>
       1
      </para>
      <para>
       The table demonstrates that, 3 years and 6 months after the 1984 redistributions at which they were created, 85% of Divisions (excluding the Northern Territory) had enrolments which differed from the relevant State or Territory average enrolment by less than 5%. On this basis the honourable senator's assertion that the projections used at the 1984 redistributions were ``seriously flawed'' is not accepted.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) The Australian Electoral Commission and the Redistribution bodies established under the Commonwealth Electoral Act 1918 are completely independent of the Government in carrying out the redistribution process. What working material they release, and when, will be for these bodies to determine.
      </para>
      <para>
       GENERAL ELECTION 24 MARCH 1990
      </para>
      <para>
       Appendix A
      </para>
      <para>
       Enrolment forms processed from announcement of the General Election (16 February) to close of rolls (26 February)
      </para>
      <para>
       Number of
      </para>
      <para>
       People
      </para>
      <para>
       Enrolled
      </para>
      <para>
       New South Wales
      </para>
      <para>
       Banks ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,741
      </para>
      <para>
       Barton ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,471
      </para>
      <para>
       Bennelong ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,661
      </para>
      <para>
       Berowra ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,337
      </para>
      <para>
       Blaxland ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,422
      </para>
      <para>
       Bradfield ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,993
      </para>
      <para>
       Calare ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,690
      </para>
      <para>
       Charlton ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,937
      </para>
      <para>
       Chifley ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,839
      </para>
      <para>
       Cook ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,957
      </para>
      <para>
       Cowper ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,646
      </para>
      <para>
       Cunningham ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,744
      </para>
      <para>
       Dobell ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,989
      </para>
      <para>
       Dundas ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,356
      </para>
      <para>
       Eden-Monaro ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,096
      </para>
      <para>
       Farrer ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,670
      </para>
      <para>
       Fowler ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,856
      </para>
      <para>
       Gilmore ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,908
      </para>
      <para>
       Grayndler ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,727
      </para>
      <para>
       Greenway ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,385
      </para>
      <para>
       Gwydir ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,886
      </para>
      <para>
       Hughes ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,378
      </para>
      <para>
       Hume ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,123
      </para>
      <para>
       Hunter ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,396
      </para>
      <para>
       Kingsford-Smith ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,670
      </para>
      <para>
       Lindsay ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,561
      </para>
      <para>
       Lowe ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,545
      </para>
      <para>
       Lyne ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,826
      </para>
      <para>
       Macarthur ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,157
      </para>
      <para>
       Mackellar ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,386
      </para>
      <para>
       Macquarie ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,381
      </para>
      <para>
       Mitchell ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,034
      </para>
      <para>
       Newcastle ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,078
      </para>
      <para>
       New England ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,203
      </para>
      <para>
       North Sydney ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,299
      </para>
      <para>
       Page ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,704
      </para>
      <para>
       Parkes ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,621
      </para>
      <para>
       Parramatta ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,519
      </para>
      <para>
       Phillip ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3608
      </para>
      <para>
       Prospect ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,839
      </para>
      <para>
       Reid ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,296
      </para>
      <para>
       Richmond ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,426
      </para>
      <para>
       Riverina-Darling ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,610
      </para>
      <para>
       Robertson ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,832
      </para>
      <para>
       St George ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,960
      </para>
      <para>
       Shortland ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,937
      </para>
      <para>
       Sydney ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,858
      </para>
      <para>
       Throsby ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,279
      </para>
      <para>
       Warringah ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,665
      </para>
      <para>
       Wentworth ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,316
      </para>
      <para>
       Werriwa ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,974
      </para>
      <para>
       State Total ...
      </para>
      <para>
       135,792
      </para>
      <para>
       Victoria
      </para>
      <para>
       Aston ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,719
      </para>
      <para>
       Ballarat ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,161
      </para>
      <para>
       Batman ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,620
      </para>
      <para>
       Bendigo ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,491
      </para>
      <para>
       Bruce ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,130
      </para>
      <para>
       Burke ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,043
      </para>
      <para>
       Calwell ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,712
      </para>
      <para>
       Casey ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,197
      </para>
      <para>
       Chisholm ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,477
      </para>
      <para>
       Corangamite ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,117
      </para>
      <para>
       Corinella ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,066
      </para>
      <para>
       Corio ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,398
      </para>
      <para>
       Deakin ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,664
      </para>
      <para>
       Dunkley ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,729
      </para>
      <para>
       Flinders ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,965
      </para>
      <para>
       Gellibrand ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,285
      </para>
      <para>
       Gippsland ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,930
      </para>
      <para>
       Goldstein ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,985
      </para>
      <para>
       Higgins ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,461
      </para>
      <para>
       Holt ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,565
      </para>
      <para>
       Hotham ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,297
      </para>
      <para>
       Indi ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,966
      </para>
      <para>
       Isaacs ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,313
      </para>
      <para>
       Jagajaga ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,428
      </para>
      <para>
       Kooyong ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,229
      </para>
      <para>
       Lalor ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,353
      </para>
      <para>
       La Trobe ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,060
      </para>
      <para>
       McEwen ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,733
      </para>
      <para>
       McMillan ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,674
      </para>
      <para>
       Mallee ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,436
      </para>
      <para>
       Maribyrnong ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,146
      </para>
      <para>
       Melbourne ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,340
      </para>
      <para>
       Melbourne Ports ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,066
      </para>
      <para>
       Menzies ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,580
      </para>
      <para>
       Murray ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,715
      </para>
      <para>
       Scullin ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,505
      </para>
      <para>
       Wannon ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,648
      </para>
      <para>
       Wills ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,566
      </para>
      <para>
       State Total ...
      </para>
      <para>
       109,770
      </para>
      <para>
       Queensland
      </para>
      <para>
       Bowman ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,434
      </para>
      <para>
       Brisbane ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,584
      </para>
      <para>
       Capricornia ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,391
      </para>
      <para>
       Dawson ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,837
      </para>
      <para>
       Fadden ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,468
      </para>
      <para>
       Fairfax ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,759
      </para>
      <para>
       Fisher ...
      </para>
      <para>
       5,120
      </para>
      <para>
       Forde ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,939
      </para>
      <para>
       Griffith ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,575
      </para>
      <para>
       Groom ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,674
      </para>
      <para>
       Herbert ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,968
      </para>
      <para>
       Hinkler ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,302
      </para>
      <para>
       Kennedy ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,944
      </para>
      <para>
       Leichhardt ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,096
      </para>
      <para>
       Lilley ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,573
      </para>
      <para>
       McPherson ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,954
      </para>
      <para>
       Maranoa ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,519
      </para>
      <para>
       Moncrieff ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,929
      </para>
      <para>
       Moreton ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,736
      </para>
      <para>
       Oxley ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,570
      </para>
      <para>
       Petrie ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,251
      </para>
      <para>
       Rankin ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,174
      </para>
      <para>
       Ryan ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,666
      </para>
      <para>
       Wide Bay ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,779
      </para>
      <para>
       State Total ...
      </para>
      <para>
       83,242
      </para>
      <para>
       Western Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Brand ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,637
      </para>
      <para>
       Canning ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,989
      </para>
      <para>
       Cowan ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,686
      </para>
      <para>
       Curtin ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,231
      </para>
      <para>
       Forrest ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,216
      </para>
      <para>
       Fremantle ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,214
      </para>
      <para>
       Kalgoorlie ...
      </para>
      <para>
       5,704
      </para>
      <para>
       Moore ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,481
      </para>
      <para>
       O'Connor ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,593
      </para>
      <para>
       Pearce ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,111
      </para>
      <para>
       Perth ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,673
      </para>
      <para>
       Stirling ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,013
      </para>
      <para>
       Swan ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,986
      </para>
      <para>
       Tangney ...
      </para>
      <para>
       3,010
      </para>
      <para>
       State Total ...
      </para>
      <para>
       50,544
      </para>
      <para>
       South Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Adelaide ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,070
      </para>
      <para>
       Barker ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,661
      </para>
      <para>
       Bonython ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,843
      </para>
      <para>
       Boothby ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,172
      </para>
      <para>
       Grey ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,386
      </para>
      <para>
       Hawker ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,703
      </para>
      <para>
       Hindmarsh ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,767
      </para>
      <para>
       Kingston ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,940
      </para>
      <para>
       Makin ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,895
      </para>
      <para>
       Mayo ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,228
      </para>
      <para>
       Port Adelaide ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,511
      </para>
      <para>
       Sturt ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,869
      </para>
      <para>
       Wakefield ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,995
      </para>
      <para>
       State Total ...
      </para>
      <para>
       25,040
      </para>
      <para>
       Tasmania
      </para>
      <para>
       Bass ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,851
      </para>
      <para>
       Braddon ...
      </para>
      <para>
       1,759
      </para>
      <para>
       Denison ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,319
      </para>
      <para>
       Franklin ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,192
      </para>
      <para>
       Lyons ...
      </para>
      <para>
       2,011
      </para>
      <para>
       State Total ...
      </para>
      <para>
       10,132
      </para>
      <para>
       Northern Territory
      </para>
      <para>
       Northern Territory ...
      </para>
      <para>
       5,888
      </para>
      <para>
       State Total ...
      </para>
      <para>
       5,888
      </para>
      <para>
       A.C.T.
      </para>
      <para>
       Canberra ...
      </para>
      <para>
       4,910
      </para>
      <para>
       Fraser ...
      </para>
      <para>
       5,160
      </para>
      <para>
       State Total ...
      </para>
      <para>
       10,070
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2667">
     <title>
      Papua New Guinea-Indonesian Border
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="149">
      (Question No. 149)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="WA" nameid="IG4" page="2667" party="IND" speaker="Vallentine Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator Vallentine
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, upon notice, on 23 August 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) Is the Government aware that, according to The Age, dated 17 August 1990, at least five people, including a woman and child, have been killed at the village of Ok Bago on the Papua New Guinea (PNG) side of the border as part of a continuing Indonesian military operation there; if so, has there been any expression of concern from the Australian Government to the Indonesian Government on this matter.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Does Australia intend to publicly lend its support to the protests in Indonesia by PNG Foreign Minister, Michael Somare, as reported by the Australian Federated Press, on 14 August 1990 regarding Indonesian military incursions on PNG territory and infringements of PNG sovereignty.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Did the Australian Ambassador to Indonesia, Mr Philip Flood, discuss these military incursions while on his recent visit to Irian Jaya.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) In view of the report of the current level of military activity on the border, will Australia convey to the PNG Government, in the strongest terms, its concerns that refugees in the Yapsie area be permitted to stay in PNG at least until the situation in Irian Jaya improves and the safe return of the refugees is completely guaranteed.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Is the Government aware of: (a) the whereabouts; and (b) the present condition of the OPM leader Melkianus Salosa who was recently forcibly deported to Indonesia by the PNG Government.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) Has Salosa been granted any access to independent legal or NGO representatives in a position to monitor his rights in his present situation of detention and alleged intense interrogation.
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) Was his forced repatriation legally well-founded and does it comply with PNG's obligations as a signatory to the United Nations Convention on Refugees.
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) Does the Government have any information as to the whereabouts, living conditions, and legal status of the seven Melanesian Irian Jayans who sought asylum in the PNG Consulate, Jayapura on 14 December 1989, and were subsequently handed over to the Indonesian authorities.
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) Has the Government sought assurances from Indonesia that the legal and human rights of these political prisoners will be fully respected.
      </para>
      <para>
       (10) What information does the Government have about Indonesia's intentions regarding the 11 alleged OPM activists recently detained in Irian Jaya.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="WA" nameid="VD4" page="2667" party="ALP" speaker="Evans Sen The Hon G.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="VD4">
         Senator Gareth Evans
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) I am aware of press reports of recent Indonesian incursions into PNG territory. The Australian Government has not commented on these, believing that the management of their joint border is a matter for Indonesia and Papua New Guinea to work out in cooperation with each other.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) The Australian Government was not asked to associate itself with Sir Michael Somare's protest of 14 August calling on Indonesia to respect the territorial integrity of Papua New Guinea. It does not plan to do so .
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) The Australian Ambassador discussed developments along the Indonesian-PNG border with Indonesian officials during his recent visit to Irian Jaya.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) The latest information available to me is that the UNHCR office in Papua New Guinea, with the cooperation of the PNG Government, plans to move refugees from Yapsie to the refugee camp further south at East Awin.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5-6) According to my most recent information, the questioning of Melky Salosa has been completed. I understand that he is being held in Jayapura.
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) I have no information to indicate that the deportation of Salosa was not legally well founded. Salosa did not have refugee status. His extradition was sought by the Indonesian Government for his alleged involvement in an attack on a transmigration camp in Irian Jaya which resulted in the death of a large number of civilians. Salosa was arrested in Papua New Guinea in December last year for the illegal possession of weapons. Before his deportation he was appearing before a PNG court on a charge of illegal entry. I believe that Papua New Guinea's deportation of Salosa did not contravene its obligations as a signatory to the United Nations Convention on Refugees.
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) My latest information about the four Irianese who sought asylum in the PNG consulate in Jayapura in December last year is that all four were brought to trial in June on a count of subversion. I understand that all have received sentences of between twelve and eighteen years imprisonment. Staff from the ICRC have had access to the detainees.
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) The Australian Government through the Australian Embassy in Jakarta has continued to monitor the situation of the four Irianese who sought asylum.
      </para>
      <para>
       (10) I understand that in early August the Indonesian Armed Forces in Jayapura announced the capture of 11 suspected OPM members. They are reportedly being questioned by the security authorities prior to their trial.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
    <answer.to.qon page="2668">
     <title>
      Recycled Paper
     </title>
     <question.number qon.number="181">
      (Question No. 181)
     </question.number>
     <question electorate="TAS" nameid="7U4" page="2668" party="AD" speaker="Bell Sen R.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="7U4">
         Senator Bell
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        asked the Minister for Administrative Services, upon notice, on 11 September 1990:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) Are Government departments using thousands of tonnes of office paper each year and is recycled paper unsuitable for use in most present photocopiers.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Do most existing copiers use a heating process that causes ozone to be released and do they contain a selenium drum which is extremely toxic if overheated or touched.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) Do these machines have a limited life of about three years.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) Is there new technology in existence that allows any grade of recycled paper to be used in photocopiers, that involves no harmful chemicals and does not use a heating process.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Do these copiers have a life of 15 to 20 years.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) Are there contract arrangements currently in place that would preclude a department purchasing these machines: if not, what action will the Minister take to require departments to purchase the machines.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer electorate="TAS" nameid="XE4" page="2668" party="ALP" speaker="Bolkus Sen The Hon N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="XE4">
         Senator Bolkus
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The answer to the honourable senator's question is as follows:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) There is no doubt that government departments use, in total, significant quantities of paper for photocopying and related processes.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government is not in a position to make such a sweeping statement about the suitability of recycled paper for use in current technology photocopiers.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia's two major paper manufacturers, Australian Paper Manufacturers (APM), and Associated Pulp and Paper Mills (APPM), both produce recycled photocopy grade papers. Both recommend their papers as suitable for low to mid volume photocopiers, but not for high speed copiers or in applications where two sided copying is required. The attitude of major photocopying manufacturers varies, and most have indicated that their machines will operate satisfactorily using recycled paper for some or all categories of use, however, performance and warranty depend on the quality of the recycled paper used.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) Most photocopiers use a heating process to fuse toner (the medium used to form the image) onto the paper. This process is not responsible for the production of ozone. Ozone is a gas produced as a result of electrical discharges in air and is primarily associated with the charging and discharging of the photoconductive drum or belt used in photocopiers. The design of the machine generally determines the amount of ozone produced with some photocopiers incorporating ozone scrubbers or filters.
      </para>
      <para>
       It is generally acknowledged that provided care is exercised in relation to the placement of photocopier machines, and if they are regularly serviced, and not seriously overused during any given period, the ozone produced is unlikely to reach the National Occupational Health and Safety Commission threshold limit values for exposure.
      </para>
      <para>
       Photocopiers utilise a photoconductive drum or belt which is electrically charged according to the image on an original to attract toner for transfer to the paper.
      </para>
      <para>
       Many types of material are used as the photoconductive coating on the drum. Selenium, and selenium compounds, amorphous silicone, cadmium sulphide, zinc oxide and organic polymer drums are used in photocopiers.
      </para>
      <para>
       During the normal course of operating a photocopier, there should be no reason to touch the drum, and in fact this may damage it. PSG contract conditions stipulate that the serviceman/technician remove all replaced drums for appropriate disposal. It is highly unlikely that drums will become overheated. Minute amounts of photoconductive coating can be released into the air but the levels produced are unlikely to affect the health of users.
      </para>
      <para>
       Further information about the use of photocopiers and associated health hazards is available from the Worksafe Australia publication `Office Copying Machines'.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) The useful operating life of a photocopying machine is not determined by age but by the number of copies produced. The Purchasing and Sales Group of my Department arranges Common Use Contracts for photocopiers which include provision of support for all equipment for a five year period.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) There is no new technology in photocopiers that my Department is aware of, that involves no harmful chemicals and does not use a heating process.
      </para>
      <para>
       However, I am advised machines known in the industry as copy printers, have recently been released. These machines are new technology ink duplicating machines which incorporate automatic scanning, stencil making and printing facilities. They are simple to operate and look similar to photocopiers. They are not an alternative to the photocopier, but in certain applications they can be provide a direct substitute.
      </para>
      <para>
       Copy printers are costly to operate in situations where less than 30 copies of each original is involved. After this volume per original they become cost competitive. They also tend to be more labour intensive, and are not generally capable of automatic two sided copying.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) Copy printers could conceivably have a life of 15 to 20 years, but as with photocopiers is probably based on chassis copy life. Most machines incorporate sophisticated electronics which it is doubtful could be adequately maintained by the supplier after 15 years.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Purchasing and Sales Group has arranged a Common Use Contract for copy printers and the machines on that contract have an expected life of 10,000,000 copies and are supported by agreements with suppliers for at least five years.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) Departments have the individual freedom to select the office equipment (including photocopiers and copy printers) they need to perform their functions. In selecting such equipment they must have regard to value for money, the availability of funds, the nature of the task concerned, and government policy on the use of recycled and environmentally friendly products.
      </para>
      <para>
       To assist departments and other government agencies in making these purchases, the Purchasing and Sales Group has arranged Common Use Contracts for both photocopiers and copy printers and has specialist technical staff available to advise them on the paper and product most suited to their requirements.
      </para>
      <para>
       In the light of all the information above I am not prepared to issue any directive of the type sought by the honourable member.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </answer.to.qon>
   </answers.to.questions>
  </hansard>
 </body>
</html>
