<!DOCTYPE hansard PUBLIC "-//PARLINFO//DTD HANSARD STORAGE//EN" "hansard.dtd">
<html>
 <body>
  <hansard chamber="Senate" date="08/05/1990" page="1" parliament.no="36" period.no="1" proof="No" session.no="1">
   <chamber.xscript>
    <business.start>
     <day.start date="08/05/1990">
      Tuesday, 8 May 1990
     </day.start>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA
      </para>
      <para>
       PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES
      </para>
      <para>
       SENATE
      </para>
      <para>
       Hansard
      </para>
      <para>
       1990
      </para>
      <para>
       FIRST SESSION OF THE THIRTY-SIXTH PARLIAMENT
      </para>
      <para>
       (FIRST PERIOD)
      </para>
      <para>
       The Senate, on 22 December 1989, adjourned until 2 p.m. on Tuesday, 20 February 1990. By proclamation the Thirty-fifth Parliament was dissolved by His Excellency the Governor-General on 19 February 1990. The Thirty-sixth Parliament was convened for the dispatch of business on 8 May 1990 and the First Session commenced on that day.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </business.start>
    <debate page="1" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      OPENING OF THE PARLIAMENT
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The Senate met at 10.30, pursuant to the proclamation of His Excellency the Governor-General.
      </para>
      <para>
       The PRESIDENT (Senator the Hon. Kerry Sibraa) took the chair.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Clerk read the proclamation.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Deputy appointed by His Excellency the Governor-General for the opening of the Parliament-the Honourable Sir Anthony Frank Mason, AC, KBE, CMG, Chief Justice of the High Court of Australia-having been announced by the Usher of the Black Rod, entered the chamber and took his seat on the dais.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Deputy, through the Clerk, directed the Usher to desire the attendance of the members of the House of Representatives, who being in attendance, the DEPUTY said:
      </para>
      <para>
       Members of the Senate and Members of the House of Representatives: His Excellency the Governor-General, not thinking fit to be present in person at this time, has been pleased to appoint me his Deputy to declare open the Parliament of the Commonwealth, as will more fully appear from the instrument which will now be read by the Clerk of the Senate.
      </para>
      <para>
       The instrument having been read by the Clerk-
      </para>
      <para>
       The DEPUTY said:
      </para>
      <para>
       Members of the Senate and Members of the House of Representatives: I have it in command from His Excellency the Governor-General to let you know that, after certain Members of the Senate, and Members of the House of Representatives, shall have been sworn, the causes of His Excellency calling this Parliament together will be declared by him in person at this place; and, it being necessary that a Speaker of the House of Representatives shall be first chosen, you, Members of the House of Representatives, will retire to the place where you are to sit, and there proceed to the choice of some person to be your Speaker; and later this day you will present the person whom you shall so choose to His Excellency at such time and place as he shall appoint.
      </para>
      <para>
       I will attend in the House of Representatives for the purpose of administering the oath or affirmation of allegiance to honourable Members of that House.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Deputy and members of the House of Representatives having retired-
      </para>
      <para>
       The PRESIDENT again took the chair.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      REPRESENTATION OF WESTERN AUSTRALIA, QUEENSLAND, SOUTH AUSTRALIA AND TASMANIA
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I inform the Senate that on 27 February, 1 March and 17 April 1990 I received letters from Senators Chaney, Stone, Haines, Sanders and Messner resigning their places as senators for their respective States. Pursuant to the provisions of section 21 of the Constitution I notified the Governors of the respective States of the vacancies in the representation of their States caused by the resignation of the senators. I have now received through His Excellency the Governor-General:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        (a) a certificate of the appointment by the Governor of Tasmania, and subsequently a certificate of the choice by the Parliament of Tasmania, of Robert John Bell as a senator to fill the vacancy caused by the resignation of Norman Karl Sanders;
       </para>
       <para>
        (b) a certificate of the choice by the Parliament of South Australia of Meg Heather Lees as a senator to fill the vacancy caused by the resignation of Janine Haines; and
       </para>
       <para>
        (c) a copy of a certificate of the choice by the Parliament of South Australia of John Wayne Olsen as a senator to fill the vacancy caused by the resignation of Anthony John Messner.
       </para>
       <para>
        Certificates and copy of a certificate laid on the table, and read by the Clerk.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      SWEARING-IN OF SENATORS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       The following senators made and subscribed the oath or affirmation of allegiance:
      </para>
      <para>
       Robert John Bell
      </para>
      <para>
       Meg Heather Lees
      </para>
      <para>
       John Wayne Olsen
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      REPRESENTATION OF THE AUSTRALIAN CAPITAL TERRITORY AND NORTHERN TERRITORY
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       The Clerk-I lay on the table the certificates for the election of senators for the Australian Capital Territory and the Northern Territory, as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Capital Territory-
      </para>
      <para>
       Robert Francis McMullan
      </para>
      <para>
       Margaret Elizabeth Reid
      </para>
      <para>
       Northern Territory-
      </para>
      <para>
       Robert Lindsay Collins
      </para>
      <para>
       Grant Ernest John Tambling
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      SWEARING-IN OF SENATORS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       The following Senators made and subscribed the oath or affirmation of alliegiance:
      </para>
      <para>
       Margaret Elizabeth Reid
      </para>
      <para>
       Robert Lindsay Collins
      </para>
      <para>
       Grant Ernest John Tambling
      </para>
      <para>
       Sitting suspended from 10.52 a.m. to 3 p.m.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="2" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      GOVERNOR-GENERAL'S SPEECH
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       His Excellency the Governor-General entered the chamber and, being seated, with the President on his right hand, commanded that a message be sent to the House of Representatives intimating that His Excellency desired the attendance of honourable members in the Senate chamber forthwith, who having come with their Speaker, His Excellency was pleased to deliver the following speech:
      </para>
      <para>
       Honourable Members of the Parliament of Australia:
      </para>
      <para>
       On 24 March, the Australian people gave to the Labor Government an historic and decisive fourth mandate-a mandate to continue the urgent and sweeping task of national reform in the 1990s.
      </para>
      <para>
       In carrying out its mandate, and to implement the commitments it made during the election campaign, the Government will bring before this Parliament an ambitious and far-reaching legislative program.
      </para>
      <para>
       As in the Government's previous terms, these proposals will be designed to work towards two overriding and more complementary goals: the establishment of a stronger, more competitive and environmentally sustainable Australian economy, and the creation of a fairer and more compassionate Australian society.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia has already made good progress towards realising these goals. Futher progress will require a continued and united effort, underpinned by sound economic management; determined micro-economic reform; substantial and targeted measures of social assistance; and implementation of strategies for ecologically sustainable development.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue its disciplined framework of macro-economic policies and with great vigour pursue the ten point plan for micro-economic reform outlined during the election campaign.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will set about ensuring Australia is indeed not just the lucky country but the clever country-with new measures to enhance, dramatically, Australia's scientific research efforts, and to improve the capacity of children of low and middle income Australian families to complete school.
      </para>
      <para>
       And with an unprecedented expansion in the supply and affordability of child care and the creation of better job training prospects for the long-term unemployed, this Government will continue to open opportunities for all Australians, especially Australian women, to enter and re-enter the workforce.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Australian Economy
      </para>
      <para>
       The Australian economy has expanded strongly in recent years, with business investment reaching record levels and employment growing rapidly. However, major challenges remain. In particular, the current account deficit remains at a level which is adding unacceptably to external indebtedness, and inflation needs to be further reduced.
      </para>
      <para>
       The main focus of macro-economic policy must now be on improving Australia's external accounts and reducing inflation.
      </para>
      <para>
       A tight fiscal stance, continued effective incomes policy and firm monetary policy, have removed the excess domestic demand that was evident in 1988-89. Significant improvements in the current account deficit and inflation are expected and policy will be maintained in order to meet these expectations.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government also believes that improving the health of the Australian economy requires the implementation of a continuing agenda of structural reform.
      </para>
      <para>
       The recent strong growth in employment and the surge in business investment, together with the ongoing agenda of industrial and labour market reforms, has already started to enhance the efficiency, flexibility and competitiveness of the Australian economy.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to pursue broad-based structural reform. Reform is planned in trade protection measures; telecommunications and broadcasting; aviation; land transport; the waterfront; and international shipping. The newly established Industry Commission, with its wide charter and robust work program, is to play a key role as a catalyst for change. References to be forwarded to the Commission include railways, energy, statutory marketing arrangements and exports of health and education services. The co-operation of the States and Territories is vital to the success of these initiatives.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Prices Surveillance Authority will continue to play an active role in ensuring that consumers benefit from micro- economic reform.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government recognises that economic restructuring will impose adjustment costs. A feature of the Government's policy strategy is that this cost burden be spread equitably across all sectors of the Australian community.
      </para>
      <para>
       All levels of government in Australia will need to exercise further fiscal restraint to assist with the task of stabilising our external indebtedness. The Commonwealth will be expecting the States and Territories to accept their share of the responsibility to restrain overall public spending and borrowing in the future.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government has already announced its commitment to a major study aimed at simplifying the income tax system for taxpayers and the tax administration by reducing uncertainty and complexity in the law. The study will provide further progress in modernising collection and taxpayer service arrangements.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will reintroduce legislation to give effect to superannuation reforms announced in the August 1989 Budget. It will also examine measures aimed at enhancing the efficiency of superannuation funds and life offices, making them more accountable to their members and clients.
      </para>
      <para>
       In the area of industrial relations, the Government's immediate priority is to ensure that the processes of labour market reform are continued and accelerated. The Government will foster an acceleration of the process of award and trade union rationalisation along industry lines. In particular, it will ensure that there are no legislative impediments to the rationalisation process.
      </para>
      <para>
       As a fundamental goal, the Government seeks the retention of a wage system which is fair, and delivers wage outcomes appropriate to the national interest.
      </para>
      <para>
       Trade and Industry
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will establish a series of Co-operative Research Centres and will provide additional funding for this purpose, rising to $100 million a year after five years.
      </para>
      <para>
       The centres will play a vital role in ensuring that Australia will benefit from the combined strength of the nation's science and technology resources. They will help ensure that Australian research and training will remain at the forefront in those areas of greatest importance to this country or in areas in which Australia has special expertise.
      </para>
      <para>
       Research and development is fundamental to productivity and innovation in Australian enterprises.
      </para>
      <para>
       Research and development has grown substantially since the introduction of Government tax incentives and grants designed to boost our efforts to world standard, and the research and development tax concession will be extended to 1993 at 150 per cent and from 1993 to 1995 at 125 per cent.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will also extend Research and Development Grant Programs to 1995 to ensure that an integrated package of measures is in place. To encourage leading edge research in fields of importance to our future, environmental technologies and services will be made eligible for grant assistance. Also, research programs for the eradication of Mimosa Pigra and for the control of the cane toad will be undertaken.
      </para>
      <para>
       In addition to the revision and extension of the Export Market Development Grants Scheme for a further 5 years from 1 July 1990, a new export development fund will be introduced to support established exporters to enter new markets and launch new products. Smaller companies will be encouraged to form approved trading bodies to achieve the critical mass required to build a sustainable export base. In future, key services also will now be eligible for export grants. Of particular significance is the extension of grants to inbound tourist operators from 1991-92.
      </para>
      <para>
       The greenhouse research program will be extended for a further three years, while forestry research will be upgraded with a new forest research laboratory for CSIRO in Tasmania, and a Tropical Rainforest Centre in North Queensland.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will be aiming, as well, to ensure that Australian industry meets the highest environmental standards through processes such as the guidelines established for the potential development of pulp mills.
      </para>
      <para>
       The current program of phased tariff reductions will be completed in 1992 and the Government already has indicated that further tariff reductions will occur beyond that time. In recognition of the long lead involved in major investment decisions, the Government will be considering post-1992 tariff arrangements at an early stage to ensure a predictable policy framework for industry.
      </para>
      <para>
       At the same time, the Government will continue to seek a fairer and more open international trading system, most notably through its leadership of the Cairns Group in the Uruguay Round. It will continue its efforts to integrate the Australian economy with dynamic regional economies through the active pursuit of bilateral trade opportunities, and the promotion of the Asia-Pacific Economic Co-operation process.
      </para>
      <para>
       Small Business
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government recognises the importance of small business to the Australian economy. The recent House of Representatives Committee Report on Small Business in Australia (the Beddall Report) outlined steps that could be taken to increase the productivity and efficiency of the sector. Progress on some of these steps has already been made and the Government is giving high priority to developing a full response to the Report's recommendations.
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government believes that a national approach to our transport problems is required. With the co-operation of the States and greater involvement by the private sector, the Government will be moving to upgrade substantially the national transport infrastructure and to improve the efficiency of our transport systems.
      </para>
      <para>
       Shipping reforms will progressively put the operating costs and manning levels of Australian flag shipping on a par with those of our major trading partners. Trans-Tasman shipping will be a particular focus. The program for waterfront reform will be actively promoted, and the Government expects that the major enterprise agreements will be concluded this year. Performance indicators are being put in place for both shipping and the waterfront, which will enable an accurate assessment to be made of progress in these industries.
      </para>
      <para>
       Pursuit of a national rail freight initiative, following a feasibility study of the establishment of a national rail freight organisation, will be a priority.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will also maintain its strong commitment to further uniformity in regulation of road use, and improved safety standards for our roads.
      </para>
      <para>
       Deregulation of the domestic aviation industry will take effect in October, and the Government will ensure that new entrants have fair access to major airports. The Trade Practices Commission will take a high profile in ensuring effective competition, with the full support of the Government.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Environmental Impact Statement on the third runway at Sydney Airport will be completed this year and, subject to the outcome, construction is due to commence in early 1991. In the next three months, measures will also be announced to alleviate the current congestion problems at Sydney Airport, and a decision taken on the introduction of a second international freight carrier, and further liberalisation of passenger charter arrangements. The Government will closely examine the merits of merging the Australian and New Zealand aviation markets as part of the Closer Economic Relations process.
      </para>
      <para>
       There is scope for significantly greater competition within the telecommunications sector. The outcome of the review of the existing boundaries between the carriers, and the response to a number of AUSTEL reviews, are due over the next three months. The long term future of AUSSAT will be addressed.
      </para>
      <para>
       In the broadcasting sector the Government's review of the Broadcasting Act will be completed, and a further program of reform announced this year. In the current session the already announced efficiency package of reforms to the Broadcasting Act will be introduced. The regional television equalisation program will continue to be implemented. Other aspects of broadcasting on which decisions will be announced this year include the moratorium on pay TV, the future policy framework for Remote Commercial Television Services, and the second stage of the National Metropolitan Radio Plan.
      </para>
      <para>
       Employment, Training and Social Justice
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government's initiatives in education and training have already done much to provide a firmer base for a more competitive, dynamic and adaptable economy and a fairer society where opportunities are open to all.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will strive for higher national standards at all levels in the education process and a more effective relationship of education and training outcomes with employment opportunities.
      </para>
      <para>
       A central theme of the Government's social justice strategy has been to assist disadvantaged groups into the workforce and reduce welfare dependence through an active approach to social policy that assists such people with education, training and employment needs in a co-ordinated way.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will build on its successful Jobs, Education and Training (JET) and NEWSTART programs. In 1991 it will replace the Unemployment Benefit with an active income support structure. Job Search Allowance will be available for those unemployed for less than 12 months and NEWSTART Allowance for the longer term unemployed. Income support and greater opportunities for training and other employment assistance will be effectively co-ordinated and delivered to those who need them, in conjunction with a stronger job search obligation on the individual.
      </para>
      <para>
       An essential element in addressing disadvantage is to ensure that all young people, regardless of their background, have access to educational opportunities. Building on the dramatic improvement in school retention rates to over sixty percent in Year 12, a special allocation of $30m will be made in 1991 and 1992 to assist in improving facilities and equipment for schools. The Disadvantaged Schools Program-the cornerstone of the Government's commitment to equality of opportunity in education-will be expanded to cover a total of 500,000 children, and enhanced by a new program to improve literacy and learning skills.
      </para>
      <para>
       Low to middle income families will be assisted to keep their children at school through the Education Completion Allowance-two payments of $300 each year will subsume Family Allowance in these cases.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government intends to introduce legislation for a Training Guarantee, as a means of increasing the level and quality of industry training.
      </para>
      <para>
       Massively increased access to child care together with the unprecedented growth in jobs under the Accord and the success of innovative programs such as JET, are all helping ensure that women have a real choice and real opportunities to escape the cycle of disadvantage.
      </para>
      <para>
       Building on this, the Government will be improving further both the supply and affordability of child care. An additional 50,000 community child care places will be provided by 1995-96, including 10,000 new centre based places, 10,000 new family day care places, and 30,000 new outside school hours care places. An estimated additional 28,000 new child care places will be provided also by employers and private centres in response to the Government's decision to extend fee relief to approved private child care centres. The existing fee relief system for users of community-based child care will also be improved to ease the cost of child care for low and middle income families.
      </para>
      <para>
       These measures represent a substantial contribution to a fairer and more prosperous Australia, providing opportunities for all Australians to contribute to, and benefit from, the nation's wealth generating processes.
      </para>
      <para>
       During the Government's fourth term they will be complemented by an increased emphasis on improving services for people in the communities in which they live and work, so as to address the locational disadvantages that too often face families living on the outer fringes of our major cities and in rural communities.
      </para>
      <para>
       Family Resource Centres will be established, marriage counselling and family mediation services will be expanded and public transport improved.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government recognises that education characterised by quality and excellence is of critical importance to the social and economic development of the nation. This fundamental principle will continue to be supported by the Government through new and existing funding programs for schools; through the Government's initiative of a National Negotiation on the Quality of Teaching in Schools; and through its reform program in higher education initiated by the White Paper Policy Statement in 1988. New initiatives, including a charter of institutional autonomy and academic freedom, will be introduced.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Environment
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will give high priority to formulating a sustainable development strategy for major Australian industry sectors. The strategy will be developed through sectoral working groups. State and Territory governments, industry, union and conservation groups will be involved.
      </para>
      <para>
       The activities of the Resource Assessment Commission will assist the Government in the resolution of complex resource use issues.
      </para>
      <para>
       The management of land, soil, water, forest and fish resources will continue to receive close attention.
      </para>
      <para>
       A forest strategy will be developed-with the aim of accommodating both the demands for forest preservation and the need to maintain a thriving and secure timber industry.
      </para>
      <para>
       The work of the National Soil Conservation Program, the Decade of Landcare, the Murray Darling Basin Commission and the National Afforestation Program will all be upgraded. A Land and Water Resources Research and Development Corporation and an Australian Fisheries Management Authority will be established.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to pursue Australia's joint initiative with France for a convention to establish Antarctica as a Nature Reserve and Land of Science. The Government will be intensifying its efforts in the lead-up to the November meeting of the Antarctic Treaty Consultative Parties in Chile.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will maintain a strong stance in favour of a substantial strengthening of the Montreal Protocol on Substances that Deplete the Ozone Layer, to bring it into line with Australia's domestic measures which are among the most stringent in the world.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to give high priority to other major global issues such as climate change and drift-net fishing, and in these matters will pay special attention to the interests of our Pacific Island Neighbours.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will develop a strategy for achieving reductions in greenhouse gas emissions and work for an international convention on climate change to bind all countries to a program of reducing greenhouse gas emissions.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia will participate, too, in the promotion and development of an International Biological Diversity Convention and accelerate efforts in preparing a national strategy on biological diversity resulting in a National Biological Diversity Program.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will be striving to develop national standards for air and water quality and national strategies to implement them. Steps will be taken to establish an Environmental Protection Agency to co-ordinate this work. A national waste minimisation and recycling strategy will also be developed along with the establishment of minimum goals for rates of recycling.
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign Affairs and Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government's foreign policies will continue to be aimed at maintaining a positive security and strategic environment, and advancing Australia's trade and economic interests in a way that complements the internal adjustments being made to the Australian economy.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to approach relations with the countries of the South Pacific within a framework of `constructive commitment', or regional partnership; to consolidate our relationship with our nearest neighbour, Papua New Guinea; and to seek to strengthen and expand Australia's relations with our ASEAN and North Asian neighbours. The Government will also continue its efforts to promote regional stability, particularly through the ongoing Cambodian peace process and the implementation of The Comprehensive Plan of Action for Indo-Chinese refugees.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to work actively towards the promotion of international peace and to promote our alliance relationship with the United States under ANZUS. It will also continue to respond in a positive and constructive way to the momentous changes taking place in Eastern Europe.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will also give priority to the global issues including, in addition to the environment and Antarctica, the forceful and active promotion of human rights and maintaining our record of assistance to developing countries.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government's policies outlined in the 1987 Defence White Paper will continue to guide the development of Australia's defence capabilities and the involvement of Australian industry within the policy context of greater defence self-reliance.
      </para>
      <para>
       The creation of new defence infrastructure in the north and west will continue as a priority with the development of a further bare base, RAAF Scherger near Weipa, and the relocation of elements of the Army to Darwin and Townsville.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government is committed to improve the living and working conditions of service personnel and their families. Enhanced employment and career opportunities for women will also be provided and improved family and community support initiatives pursued.
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration and Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government's commitment to multiculturalism-to the principles of equality of treatment and opportunity for all Australians-will continue over the next three years. The reform and review initiatives arising out of the National Agenda for a Multicultural Australia will be developed and pursued.
      </para>
      <para>
       The National Policy on Languages will be renewed. Improved processes for the recognition of overseas qualifications will be a priority.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to ensure that its immigration policy remains relevant to Australia's needs. To assist in the evaluation of our immigration programs during the 1990s the Government has created an independent Bureau of Immigration Research which will examine the impact of immigration on our population growth and economic development. A national bureau will be established to provide more effective interpreter and translator services throughout Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       Law and Justice
      </para>
      <para>
       A high priority of this Government is the enhancement of Australia's ability to combat crime successfully-in particular, the prevention and detection of money laundering and international drug trafficking-through the continuing program of establishing extradition and mutual assistance treaties, and through effective co-operation among law enforcement agencies both within and outside Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government remains committed to a national system of companies and securities regulation, and it will continue to promote sound commercial practices, particularly in the area of corporate mergers, takeovers and monopolies, while strengthening prohibitions on such activities as insider trader.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government is conducting a comprehensive review of Commonwealth Criminal Law to structure Commonwealth Criminal Laws on a more systematic and principled basis. The initial work of the present review is being undertaken by a committee led by former Chief Justice of the High Court, Sir Harry Gibbs.
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government is committed to playing an educative and leadership role in bringing about a deeper understanding on the part of non-Aboriginal Australians of the culture, past dispossession and continuing disadvantage suffered by Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government also remains committed to a genuine reconciliation with Australia's indigenous people. In particular, it will be seeking wide community support and bipartisan political endorsement of an instrument of reconciliation, variously referred to as a Treaty or Compact, between Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Australians and the wider Australian community.
      </para>
      <para>
       The form and content of such a document will not and cannot be finalised until extensive consultation is initiated with Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people and other Australians. This process of consultation will be enhanced following the recent establishment of the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commission.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to assist Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people to achieve broad equality with other Australians. To promote this goal, emphasis will continue to be placed on addressing land, health, education, housing and infrastructure needs and the further development of the Aboriginal Employment Development Policy.
      </para>
      <para>
       Women
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government has a strong commitment to equality of opportunity for the women of Australia-a commitment to give women a real say, a choice and a fair go in all aspects of life as set out in the National Agenda for Women.
      </para>
      <para>
       To ensure women have a real choice, the Government, as I have outlined, places a high priority on access to affordable, quality child care.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government has ratified International Labour Organisation Convention No 156 ``Workers With Family Responsibilities''. To support the Convention the Government will establish a Work and Family Unit to improve attitudes and practices in the workplace and will run a community education program to educate workers, unions and employers on their respective rights and responsibilities.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will also support extensive reforms of school curricula in Australia aimed at ensuring equal relevance for girls and boys.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government will continue to expand, improve and target services in recognition of women's special health needs. It will establish a National Program for the Early Detection of Breast Cancer in co-operation with States and Territories and Anti-Cancer Councils.
      </para>
      <para>
       A high level Commonwealth-State Committee on Violence Against Women with funding of $1.35 million over three years will continue the work of the National Domestic Violence Education Program in changing community attitudes and will take on a policy development, education, research and co-ordination role.
      </para>
      <para>
       Machinery of Government
      </para>
      <para>
       The major machinery of government reforms the Government put in place in 1987 have shown significant benefits and no major adjustment has proven necessary. Several refinements have, however, been made including the appointment of a Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Northern Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       Honourable Members of the Parliament of Australia:
      </para>
      <para>
       The Government believes the initiatives of economic reform, social justice and protection of the environment I have outlined are essential to its programs to enable the Australian nation to meet the challenges of the 1990s.
      </para>
      <para>
       As representatives of the Australian people you have the honour and privilege, in considering and debating these initiatives as they are brought into the Parliament, to ensure that the best interests of all Australians are advanced.
      </para>
      <para>
       I wish you well in carrying out this ambitious but achievable agenda.
      </para>
      <para>
       His Excellency the Governor-General and members of the House of Representatives retired-
      </para>
      <para>
       Sitting suspended from 3.48 to 5 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       The PRESIDENT took the chair at 5= p.m., and read prayers.
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <debate.sub1 page="9">
      <title>
       Address-in-Reply
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —I inform the Senate that I have received a copy of the opening speech which His Excellency the Governor-General was pleased to deliver to both Houses of the Parliament.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
        <para>
         Ordered that consideration of the Governor-General's opening speech be an order of the day for the next day of sitting.
        </para>
       </interject>
      </proctext>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="10" type="Ministerial Arrangements">
     <title>
      MINISTERIAL ARRANGEMENTS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="10" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-Mr President, I have the honour to inform the Senate that following the election held on 24 March 1990, the Governor-General commissioned the Prime Minister, Mr Hawke, to form a Government. The Ministry was appointed on 4 April. I seek leave to incorporate in Hansard two documents giving details of the Ministry.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The documents read as follows-
      </para>
      <para>
       COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENT
      </para>
      <para>
       Fourth Hawke Ministry
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Ministerial Office
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister
      </para>
      <para>
       Representation
      </para>
      <para>
       in other Chamber
      </para>
      <para>
       Department
      </para>
      <para>
       administered
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       * Prime Minister
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon R J L Hawke, AC, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Button
      </para>
      <para>
       Prime Minister and Cabinet
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliamentary Secretary to the Prime Minister
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Ross Free, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       * Treasurer and Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Commonwealth-State Relations
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon P J Keating, MP Deputy Prime Minister
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Button
      </para>
      <para>
       Treasury
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasurer
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator the Hon Bob McMullan
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator the Hon John Button, Leader of the Government in the Senate
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Crean
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry, Technology and Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Science and Technology, Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Science and Minister Assisting the Treasurer
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Simon Crean, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Button
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry, Technology and Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Small Business and Customs
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon David Beddall, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Button
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry, Technology and Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator the Hon Gareth Evans, QC, Deputy Leader of the Government in the Senate
      </para>
      <para>
       Dr Blewett
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign Affairs and Trade
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Trade Negotiations, Minister Assisting the Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce, and Minister Assisting the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Neal Blewett, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Evans
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign Affairs and Trade
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Finance
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Ralph Willis, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Button
      </para>
      <para>
       Finance
      </para>
      <para>
       * Attorney-General
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Michael Duffy, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Tate
      </para>
      <para>
       Attorney-General's
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Justice and Consumer Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator the Hon Michael Tate
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Duffy
      </para>
      <para>
       Attorney-General's
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Employment, Education and Training
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon J S Dawkins, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Bolkus
      </para>
      <para>
       Employment, Education and Training
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Higher Education and Employment Services
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Peter Baldwin, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Bolkus
      </para>
      <para>
       Employment, Education and Training
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Aboriginal Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Robert Tickner, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Collins
      </para>
      <para>
       Employment, Education and Training
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Kim C Beazley, MP, Vice President of the Executive Council and Leader of the House
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Collins
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support and Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Northern Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator the Hon Bob Collins
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Beazley
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Land Transport
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Bob Brown, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Collins
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Warren Snowdon, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Primary Industries and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon John Kerin, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Cook
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Resources
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Alan Griffiths, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Cook
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Community Services and Health and Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Social Justice
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Brian Howe, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Tate
      </para>
      <para>
       Community Services and Health and Veterans' Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Aged, Family and Health Services
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Peter Staples, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Tate
      </para>
      <para>
       Community Services and Health
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Veterans' Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Ben Humphreys, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Tate
      </para>
      <para>
       Veterans' Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Social Security
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator the Hon Graham Richardson
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Howe
      </para>
      <para>
       Social Security
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Security
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Con Sciacca, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator the Hon Robert Ray, Manager of Government Business in the Senate
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Bilney
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Defence Science and Personnel
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Gordon Bilney, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Ray
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs and Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Multicultural Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Gerard L Hand, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Bolkus
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Local Government and Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for the Status of Women
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Wendy Fatin, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Bolkus
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for the Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon Ros Kelly, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Richardson
      </para>
      <para>
       The Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for the Arts, Tourism and Territories
      </para>
      <para>
       The Hon David Simmons, MP
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Richardson
      </para>
      <para>
       The Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Industrial Relations and Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Public Service Matters
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator the Hon Peter Cook
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Willis
      </para>
      <para>
       Industrial Relations
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister for Administrative Services
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator the Hon Nick Bolkus
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Beddall
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Services
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       * Minister in the Cabinet
      </para>
      <para>
       RESPONSIBILITIES OF NON-PORTFOLIO
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTERS
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTER FOR INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE-(Senator the Hon. John Button)
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Science and Technology-(The Hon. Simon Crean, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       The CSIRO, the Australian Institute of Marine Science, the Australian Nuclear and Science Technology Organisation, the Commission for the Future, the National Standards Commission and the Snowy Mountains Engineering Corporation.
      </para>
      <para>
       Housing and construction activities.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Crean is also Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Science and Minister Assisting the Treasurer.
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Small Business and Customs-(The Hon. David Beddall, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       The small business function in the Industry, Technology and Commerce portfolio and, in conjunction with the respective Ministers, small business matters in other portfolios.
      </para>
      <para>
       Issues involving the management of, and day-to-day decisions required in relation to, the Customs Service (in consultation with Senator Button as appropriate).
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTER FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND TRADE-(Senator the Hon. Gareth Evans, QC)
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Trade Negotiations-(The Hon. Neal Blewett, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Bilateral and multilateral trade policy and negotiations, including relevant ministerial meetings and diplomatic contacts.
      </para>
      <para>
       Co-ordination and conduct of Australia's position in the Uruguay Round of multilateral trade negotiations-and more generally the promotion of a more equitable international trading environment.
      </para>
      <para>
       The agreement on Closer Economic Relations with New Zealand.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australia's relations with UNCTAD.
      </para>
      <para>
       Operations of trade-related councils involving the Australian business community.
      </para>
      <para>
       Dr Blewett also assists the Minister for Industry, Technology and Commerce and the Minister for Primary Industries and Energy in relation to major commodity negotiations and export promotion.
      </para>
      <para>
       ATTORNEY-GENERAL-(The Hon. Michael Duffy, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Justice and Consumer Affairs-(Senator the Hon. Michael Tate)
      </para>
      <para>
       Bankruptcy matters.
      </para>
      <para>
       Consumer affairs matters (including statutory responsibilities under the Trade Practices Act) and representation of the Government on appropriate Commonwealth-State ministerial committees.
      </para>
      <para>
       Criminology, including youth and crime.
      </para>
      <para>
       Legal aid and financial assistance, including carriage of negotiations with the States on new legal aid agreements.
      </para>
      <para>
       Remissions of fines.
      </para>
      <para>
       Federal prisoners.
      </para>
      <para>
       Marriage celebrants, marriage guidance, counselling and mediation services.
      </para>
      <para>
       Police and police liaison, including membership of appropriate Commonwealth-State committees.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Protective Services Co-ordination Centre.
      </para>
      <para>
       Territories matters coming within the Attorney-General's portfolio (other than the ACT Supreme Court, ACT Magistrates Court and corporate affairs involving the ACT).
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTER FOR EMPLOYMENT, EDUCATION AND TRAINING-(The Hon. J. S. Dawkins, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Higher Education and Employment Services-(The Hon. Peter Baldwin, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Higher education programs, including targeted research and development.
      </para>
      <para>
       Special employment, education and income support programs:
      </para>
      <para>
       Employment and Training Assistance for Disadvantaged Clients: the Integrated Program (JOBTRAIN, JOBSTART, Job Search Training); NEWSTART, JET; and restructured arrangements for assistance to the unemployed (administrative/delivery aspects).
      </para>
      <para>
       Community-based Strategies: SkillShare; New Enterprise Incentive Scheme; Rural Education and Training.
      </para>
      <para>
       Education Income Support (administrative/delivery aspects): AUSTUDY; ABSTUDY; Assistance for Isolated Children.
      </para>
      <para>
       Labour market operations:
      </para>
      <para>
       Client Services (administrative/delivery aspects): Job Placement Services; Job Seeker Specialist Services; Youth Services; Industry Services; and Information Services.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mobility Assistance.
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry Labour Adjustment Assistance (including OLMA).
      </para>
      <para>
       Corporate services and portfolio advising in relation to Youth Programs and Services.
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Aboriginal Affairs-(The Hon. Robert Tickner, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Commonwealth Aboriginal affairs responsibilities, including the operations of the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Commission (ATSIC); and programs under the responsibility of ATSIC.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Aboriginal Education Policy and those aspects of the Aboriginal Employment Development Policy administered by DEET.
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTER FOR TRANSPORT AND COMMUNICATIONS-(The Hon. Kim C. Beazley, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Land Transport-(The Hon. Bob Brown, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Land transport (including road programs and the implementation of rail reform at the Federal level and oversight of AN) and road safety matters.
      </para>
      <para>
       Representation of the Commonwealth on the Australian Transport Advisory Council.
      </para>
      <para>
       Policy and administrative issues associated with Australia Post.
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support-(Senator the Hon. Bob Collins, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Shipping (including oversight of ANL), the waterfront, and maritime operations (pending the establishment of AMSA).
      </para>
      <para>
       Aviation infrastructure (including implementation of the Government's decisions on the Kingsford-Smith Airport third runway and management of congestion at the Airport) and airport safety; and oversight of the FAC and CAA.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Collins is also Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Northern Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTER FOR PRIMARY INDUSTRIES AND ENERGY-(The Hon. John Kerin, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Resources-(The Hon. Alan Griffiths, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum and energy matters, including the Asia Pacific Economic Co-operation-Regional Energy Co-operation Project, the High Level Energy Group, the Pipeline Authority, the Snowy Mountains Authority and (with Mr Kerin) the Bureau of Mineral Resources.
      </para>
      <para>
       Forestry.
      </para>
      <para>
       Food quality issues and the Australian Quarantine and Inspection Service.
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTER FOR COMMUNITY SERVICES AND HEALTH-(The Hon. Brian Howe, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Aged, Family and Health Services-(The Hon. Peter Staples, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Aged care (including aged residential care, the Home and Community Care Program and broader issues in relation to the aged).
      </para>
      <para>
       Services for the homeless and others in crisis (the Supported Accommodation Assistance Program and the Burdekin initiatives for homeless youth).
      </para>
      <para>
       The Children's Services Program and policy development in the area of family services.
      </para>
      <para>
       The Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme.
      </para>
      <para>
       Issues relating to drugs of dependence, including the National Campaign Against Drug Abuse.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulation in the interests of public health of pharmaceuticals and medical devices (through the Therapeutic Goods Administration), food quality, chemicals safety, radiation health and air and water quality.
      </para>
      <para>
       Broader environmental health issues.
      </para>
      <para>
       Services for the hearing impaired (principally children and aged pensioners) through the National Acoustics Laboratory.
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Veterans' Affairs-(The Hon. Ben Humphreys, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Administration and policy development in relation to services for veterans.
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTER FOR DEFENCE-(Senator the Hon. Robert Ray)
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Defence Science and Personnel-
      </para>
      <para>
       (The Hon. Gordon Bilney, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       The Defence Science and Technology Organisation, including development of policies and programs for the marketing of the DSTO product.
      </para>
      <para>
       Oversight and administration of service personnel policies relating to members and ex-members of the Australian Defence Force and their families.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Defence Force assistance to the civil community, of a non-emergency nature.
      </para>
      <para>
       Community matters arising from, and in connection with, Australian Defence Force operational training activities.
      </para>
      <para>
       Acquisition and disposal of defence properties; planning, design, construction and budgetary aspects of defence facilities; Public Works Committee matters; environmental and heritage aspects of defence facilities; repairs and maintenance of defence facilities; leasing of buildings and properties for defence purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       Logistic support for the Australian Defence Force.
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTER FOR IMMIGRATION, LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND ETHNIC AFFAIRS-(The Honourable Gerard L. Hand, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for Local Government-(The Honourable Wendy Fatin, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Local government and regional development.
      </para>
      <para>
       Ms Fatin also assists the Prime Minister in relation to the status of women.
      </para>
      <para>
       MINISTER FOR THE ARTS, SPORT, THE ENVIRONMENT, TOURISM AND TERRITORIES-(The Honourable Ros Kelly, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Minister for the Arts, Tourism and Territories-(The Honourable David Simmons, MP)
      </para>
      <para>
       Territories (excluding the Antarctic territories), including continuing involvement in relations between the ACT and Commonwealth Governments.
      </para>
      <para>
       Tourism matters, including the tourist industry.
      </para>
      <para>
       The arts and cultural affairs.
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —The first document is a list of Ministers and the offices they hold. It shows those Ministers who constitute the Cabinet and provides details of representation arrangements in each chamber. It also shows the four Parliamentary Secretaries appointed by the Prime Minister to assist their respective portfolio Ministers. The Parliamentary Secretaries have also been appointed Executive Councillors. In accordance with the normal conventions concerning ministerial responsibility, the Parliamentary Secretaries will not be able to answer questions during Question Time. The other document shows the responsibilities of the non-portfolio Ministers.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       While I am on my feet, I should also take the opportunity to announce to the Senate the Government leadership and whips in the Senate. I am Leader of the Government in the Senate, the Deputy Leader of the Government is Senator Gareth Evans, the Manager of Government Business is Senator Robert Ray, the Government Whip is Senator Gerry Jones, and the Deputy Government Whips are Senator J. McKiernan and Senator D. Foreman.
      </para>
      <para>
       I also take this opportunity to congratulate Senator Robert Hill on his election as Leader of the Opposition in the Senate. Whatever reasons finally motivated Senator Chaney to depart from this place, one reason he gave me is that he found seven years dealing with me rather boring, and that comment was reciprocated. I am sure it will be refreshing, at least for a week or two, to have Senator Hill here.
      </para>
      <para>
       I congratulate Senator Durack on his election as Deputy Leader. I also congratulate Senator Boswell on his election as Leader of the National Party in the Senate. It is almost a case of leadership without `followership' but, nonetheless, I congratulate him as well as Senator Tambling as Deputy Leader. I also congratulate Senator Macklin-how shall I put it?-who, for the time being, is Leader of the Australian Democrats.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="13" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      LEADERSHIP OF THE LIBERAL PARTY
     </title>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="13" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BH4">
         Senator HILL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-Mr President, for the record, as Senator Button has referred to the matter, I inform the Senate that the Parliamentary Liberal Party has elected me its leader in this place and Senator Peter Durack my Deputy. The Opposition Whip will continue to be Senator Margaret Reid and Senator Susan Knowles will continue as the Deputy Opposition Whip.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Senator Button has made mention of Senator Chaney, and I think that it is appropriate that I take this opportunity to congratulate Senator Chaney on his contribution to the Senate, and certainly we on this side of the chamber wish him well in the other place. I seek leave to incorporate in Hansard a list showing the shadow Ministry representation and parliamentary secretaries for the Opposition in both chambers.
      </para>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The document read as follows-
      </para>
      <para>
       SHADOW MINISTRY REPRESENTATION
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Portfolio
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister
      </para>
      <para>
       Representation
      </para>
      <para>
       in other Chamber
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       * Leader of the Opposition
      </para>
      <para>
       Dr Hewson
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Hill
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliamentary Secretary to the Leader
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Rocher
      </para>
      <para>
       * Leader of the National Party and Shadow Minister for Energy and Resources
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Fischer
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Parer
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliamentary Secretary to the Leader of the National Party
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Brownhill
      </para>
      <para>
       * Deputy Leader of the Opposition, Shadow Treasurer and Chairman of the Economics and Business Group
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Reith
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Short
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliamentary Secretary to the Deputy Leader
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Watson
      </para>
      <para>
       * Deputy Leader of the National Party and Shadow Minister for Primary Industry
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Lloyd
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Tambling
      </para>
      <para>
       * Leader of the Opposition in the Senate and Shadow Minister for Foreign Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Hill
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Ruddock
      </para>
      <para>
       * Deputy Leader of the Opposition in the Senate and Shadow Minister for Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Durack
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Downer
      </para>
      <para>
       * Shadow Minister without Portfolio and Manager of Opposition Business in the House
      </para>
      <para>
       Hon. Wal Fife
      </para>
      <para>
       * Shadow Attorney-General, Shadow Minister for Justice and Chairman of the Public Administration Group
      </para>
      <para>
       Hon. Andrew Peacock
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Hill
      </para>
      <para>
       * Shadow Minister for Industrial Relations, Employment and Training, Shadow Minister assisting the Leader on the Public Service and Chairman of the Manpower and Labour Market Reform Group
      </para>
      <para>
       Hon. John Howard
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Durack
      </para>
      <para>
       * Shadow Minister for the Environment
      </para>
      <para>
       Hon. Fred Chaney
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Puplick
      </para>
      <para>
       * Shadow Minister for Shipping and Waterfront Reform and Deputy Manager of Opposition Business in the House
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Sharp
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Parer
      </para>
      <para>
       * Shadow Minister for Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       Hon. Neil Brown
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Alston
      </para>
      <para>
       * Shadow Minister without Portfolio assisting the Leader on Policy Co- ordination and Development and Chairman of the Social Policy and Health Group
      </para>
      <para>
       Hon. Jim Carlton
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliamentary Secretary to the Chairman of the Social Policy and Health Group
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Patterson
      </para>
      <para>
       * Shadow Minister for Arts, Heritage and Sport and Manager of Opposition Business in the Senate
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Puplick
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Jull
      </para>
      <para>
       * Shadow Minister for Industry and Commerce and Chairman of the Industry and Structural Reform Group
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr McLachlan
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Durack
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliamentary Secretary to the Chairman of the Industry and Structural Reform Group
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr McArthur
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Tourism and Aviation
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Jull
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Newman
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs and Shadow Minister assisting the Leader on Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Ruddock
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Puplick
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Privatisation
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Smith
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Short
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Community Services and Aged Care
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Braithwaite
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Alston
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Social Security, Child Care and Retirement Incomes and Shadow Minister assisting the Leader on Social Policy
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Alston
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Braithwaite
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Veterans' Affairs, Shadow Minister for Defence Personnel and Shadow Minister assisting the Leader on the Status of Women
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Newman
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Fischer
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Science and Technology
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr McGauran
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Newman
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Finance and Shadow Minister assisting the Leader on Commonwealth/State Relations
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Short
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Reith
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Trade and Trade Negotiations
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Downer
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Hill
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Health
      </para>
      <para>
       Dr Woods
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Puplick
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Administrative Services, Local Government and the ACT
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Parer
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Hawker
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Land Transport
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Hawker
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Parer
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Regional Development, External Territories and Northern Australia
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Tambling
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Braithwaite
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Aboriginal Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Dr Wooldridge
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Puplick
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Small Business, Housing and Customs
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Prosser
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Newman
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Education and Shadow Minister assisting the Leader on Science
      </para>
      <para>
       Dr Kemp
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Alston
      </para>
      <para>
       Shadow Minister for Corporate Law Reform and Consumer Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr Costello
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Hill
      </para>
      <para>
       Secretary to the Shadow Cabinet and Co-ordinator of Election Strategy
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator M Baume
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       * indicates member of Shadow Cabinet.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="16" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      LEADERSHIP OF THE NATIONAL PARTY OF AUSTRALIA
     </title>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="YE4" page="16" party="NP" speaker="Boswell Sen R.L.D.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YE4">
         Senator BOSWELL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the National Party of Australia)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-I wish to advise the Senate that I have been elected leader of the National Party of Australia in the Senate. The Deputy Leader is Senator Tambling, and Senator Sheil will be the Whip.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="16" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      LEADERSHIP OF THE AUSTRALIAN DEMOCRATS
     </title>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="2I4" page="16" party="AD" speaker="Macklin Sen M.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2I4">
         Senator MACKLIN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-Mr President, the failure of Janine Haines to win a seat in the House of Representatives at the last election and hence continue in the Parliament as Leader of the Australian Democrats is something we regret very much. I was appointed Leader of the Australian Democrats until 30 June, that is, the length of this Senate, and Senator Jenkins was appointed as deputy. Senator Paul McLean will continue as our Democrat Whip. I also inform the Senate that, according to the rules of our Party, the leader and deputy leader of the Parliamentary Party are elected by secret postal ballot of members. The ballot, hopefully, will be determined later this month. I also wish to incorporate in Hansard lists of the allocations made until 30 June amongst myself and my colleagues with regard to various portfolio responsibilities.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The document read as follows-
      </para>
      <para>
       PORTFOLIO ALLOCATIONS TO THE 30TH OF JUNE
      </para>
      <para>
       MICHAEL MACKLIN
      </para>
      <para>
       Leader
      </para>
      <para>
       - Prime Minister &amp;Cabinet
      </para>
      <para>
       - Treasury
      </para>
      <para>
       - Finance
      </para>
      <para>
       - Employment, Education &amp;Training
      </para>
      <para>
       - Attorney-General
      </para>
      <para>
       - Justice
      </para>
      <para>
       ROBERT BELL
      </para>
      <para>
       - Energy &amp;Resources
      </para>
      <para>
       - Transport &amp;
      </para>
      <para>
       - Aviation Support
      </para>
      <para>
       - the Environment
      </para>
      <para>
       JOHN COULTER
      </para>
      <para>
       - Industry, Technology &amp;Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       - Science &amp;Customs
      </para>
      <para>
       - Aboriginal Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       - Community Services &amp;Health
      </para>
      <para>
       - Housing &amp;Aged Care
      </para>
      <para>
       JEAN JENKINS
      </para>
      <para>
       - Immigration &amp;Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       - Foreign Affairs &amp;Trade
      </para>
      <para>
       MEG LEES
      </para>
      <para>
       - Arts, Sport, Tourism &amp;Territories
      </para>
      <para>
       - Status of Women
      </para>
      <para>
       PAUL McLEAN
      </para>
      <para>
       - Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       - Veterans' Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       - Industrial Relations
      </para>
      <para>
       - Small Business
      </para>
      <para>
       JANET POWELL
      </para>
      <para>
       - Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       - Primary Industry
      </para>
      <para>
       - Social Security
      </para>
      <para>
       - Administrative Services
      </para>
      <para>
       - Local Government
      </para>
      <para>
       - Consumer Affairs
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="16" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      NOTICES OF MOTION
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I understand that a number of senators wish to give notices of motion. With the concurrence of the Senate and in accordance with past practice, to expedite the proceedings I propose to allow the leaders of the Government, the Opposition and the Australian Democrats and the Independent senators to give notices of motion of their own and on behalf of other senators in accordance with the lists that have been circulated in the chamber. I will then have the notices of motion put on the Notice Paper in the order in which I would have called honourable senators if notices had been given in accordance with the Standing Orders.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="16" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following notices of motion on behalf of the Manager of Government Business in the Senate (Senator Robert Ray):
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       No. 1-That standing order 3 (4) be suspended to enable the Senate to consider business other than that of a formal character before the Address-in-Reply to the Governor-General's opening speech has been adopted.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-That, notwithstanding anything contained in the standing orders, on Thursdays at 12.45 p.m. till 2 p.m. matters of public interest may be discussed by Senators without any question before the Chair, provided that a Senator shall not speak for more than 15 minutes, and if a division is called for, the division shall be taken at a later hour of the day, not being earlier than 2 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-That, notwithstanding anything contained in the standing orders, on Wednesday, 9 May 1990, the President, shall put the question for the adjournment of the Senate at 6 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-That, in accordance with standing order 25 (3), departments are allocated to the legislative and general purpose standing committees as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Committee on Community Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Community Services and Health
      </para>
      <para>
       Veterans' Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Social Security
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Committee on Employment, Education and Training
      </para>
      <para>
       Employment, Education and Training
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Committee on Environment, Recreation and the Arts
      </para>
      <para>
       Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Committee on Finance and Public Administration
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliament
      </para>
      <para>
       Finance
      </para>
      <para>
       Prime Minister and Cabinet
      </para>
      <para>
       Treasury
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Devence and Trade
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign Affairs and Trade
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Committee on Industry, Science and Technology
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry, Technology and  Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       Industrial Relations
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Committee on Legal and Constitutional Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Attorney-General
      </para>
      <para>
       Standing Committee on Transport, Communications and Infrastructure
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Services
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-That Estimates Committees consider proposed expenditure in relation to departments as follows:
      </para>
      <para>
       Estimates Committee A
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliament
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry, Technology and Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       Prime Minister and Cabinet
      </para>
      <para>
       Treasury
      </para>
      <para>
       Finance
      </para>
      <para>
       Estimates Committee B
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign Affairs and Trade
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence
      </para>
      <para>
       Estimates Committee C
      </para>
      <para>
       Social Security
      </para>
      <para>
       Arts, Sport, the Environment, Tourism and Territories
      </para>
      <para>
       Veterans' Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Estimates Committee D
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Services
      </para>
      <para>
       Employment, Education and Training
      </para>
      <para>
       Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Estimates Committee E
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport and Communications
      </para>
      <para>
       Attorney-General
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Affairs
      </para>
      <para>
       Community Services and Health
      </para>
      <para>
       Estimates Committee F
      </para>
      <para>
       Industrial Relations
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-That, notwithstanding anything contained in the standing orders-
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) The Senate meet from Monday, 28 May 1990 to Friday, 1 June 1990, inclusive.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) The hours of meeting and routine of business be as for Week 1 except for Monday, 28 May, and Tuesday, 19 May, when-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) the hours of meeting shall be:
      </para>
      <para>
       10 a.m.-12.45 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       2 p.m.-6.30 p.m.
      </para>
      <para>
       8 p.m.-10.30 p.m., and
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) the routine of business shall be:
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) Petitions
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) Notices of motion
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) Formal motions-Discovery of formal business
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) Postponement and re-arrangement of business
      </para>
      <para>
       (v) Government Business
      </para>
      <para>
       (vi) At 2 p.m., questions
      </para>
      <para>
       (vii) Any proposal to debate a matter of public importance or of urgency
      </para>
      <para>
       (viii) Consideration of government documents
      </para>
      <para>
       (ix) Further consideration of Government Business.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 7-That consideration of the 3rd and 4th reports of the Procedure Committee for the 63rd session be an order of the day under Business of the Senate for the next day of sitting.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 8-
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent the succeeding provision of this resolution having effect.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) That the following bills be restored to the Notice Paper and that consideration of each of the bills be resumed at the stage reached in the last session of Parliament:
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian National Maritime Museum Amendment Bill 1989 Privacy Amendment Bill 1989
      </para>
      <para>
       Senate (Quorum) Bill 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 9-
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) That the committee known as the Select Committee on Animal Welfare, constituted by resolutions of the Senate on 16 and 17 November 1983, be re-constituted under the same terms and with the same functions and powers.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) That the committee have power to consider and use for its purposes the minutes of evidence and records of the Select Committee on Animal Welfare appointed in the previous Parliaments.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) That the committee present its final reports on or before 29 June 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) That the foregoing provisions of this resolution, so far as they are inconsistent with the standing orders, have effect notwithstanding anything contained in the standing orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 10-
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) That the committee known as the Select Committee on Agricultural and Veterinary Chemicals in Australia, constituted by resolution of the Senate on 1 November 1988, be re-constituted under the same terms and with the same functions and powers.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) That the committee have power to consider and use for its purposes the minutes of evidence and records of the Select Committee on Agricultural and Veterinary Chemicals in Australia appointed in the previous Parliament.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) That the committee present its final report on or before 29 June 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) That the foregoing provisions of this resolution, so far as they are inconsistent with the standing orders, have effect notwithstanding anything contained in the standing orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       On behalf of the Minister for Shipping and Aviation Support (Senator Collins), I give the following notices of motion:
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 1-That the following Bill be introduced: A Bill for an Act to amend the Federal Airports Corporation Act 1986, and for related purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-That the following Bill be introduced: A Bill for an Act to amend the Civil Aviation Act 1988, and for related purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       I give the following notice of motion:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the following Bill be introduced: A Bill for an Act to amend the Export Market Development Grants Act 1974-Export Market Development Grants Amendment Bill 1990.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="2I4" page="18" party="AD" speaker="Macklin Sen M.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2I4">
         Senator MACKLIN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following notice of motion:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       (1) That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent the succeeding provision of this resolution having effect.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) That the following bills be restored to the Notice Paper and that consideration of each of the bills be resumed at the stage reached in the last session of Parliament:
      </para>
      <para>
       Constitution Alteration (Fixed Term Parliaments) Bill 1987
      </para>
      <para>
       Constitution Alteration (Parliament) Bill 1987
      </para>
      <para>
       Constitution Alteration (Appropriations for the Ordinary Annual Services of the Government) Bill 1987
      </para>
      <para>
       Constitution Alteration (Electors' Initiative) Bill 1989
      </para>
      <para>
       Legislative Initiative Bill 1989
      </para>
      <para>
       Geneva Conventions Amendment Bill 1989
      </para>
      <para>
       National Identification System (Reference to the People) Bill 1987
      </para>
      <para>
       Income Tax Assessment (Savings Accounts Interest) Amendment Bill 1989 (No. 2)
      </para>
      <para>
       Income Tax Assessment (Housing Loan Interest) Amendment Bill 1989 (No. 2)
      </para>
      <para>
       Federal Court (Grouped Proceedings) Bill 1989
      </para>
      <para>
       Nuclear Non-Proliferation (Exports) Bill 1988
      </para>
      <para>
       Acts Interpretation (Ministerial Undertakings) Amendment Bill 1989
      </para>
      <para>
       Ozone Depleting Substances Regulation Bill 1988 (No. 2)-Industry, Technology and Commerce
      </para>
      <para>
       National Health (Pharmaceutical Benefits Determinations) Amendment Bill 1989
      </para>
      <para>
       Sales Tax (Exemptions and Classifications) Amendment Bill (No. 3) 1989
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum Retail Marketing Sites Amendment (Divorcement of Ownership) Bill 1987
      </para>
      <para>
       Koongarra Project Area Repeal Bill 1988
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Amendment Bill 1988
      </para>
      <para>
       Delegated Legislation Review Bill 1988
      </para>
      <para>
       Industrial Relations (Right to Strike) Amendment Bill 1989.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="18" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following notices of motion:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       No. 1-That the Senate-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) notes that persons under 21 years constituted 22.2 per cent of the Australian Public Service staff in 1966, falling to 12.2 per cent in 1974, 5.6 per cent in 1985, 3.8 per cent in 1987, and falling further to an all time low of 2.2 per cent as at 31 December 1989; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) calls on the Federal Government to take positive action to remedy the apparent structural bias in appointment procedures, which at present discriminate against youth.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-That the Senate notes with concern that over the past 2 decades families have been subjected to increasing pressures from indirect taxation, as well as from direct taxation, and that moves to downgrade the spouse rebate and family allowances are a further example of this iniquitous trend of placing an inordinate taxation burden on families, particularly one-income families.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-
      </para>
      <para>
       (1) (a) That a Standing Committee of the Senate, be known as the Standing Committee on Treaties, be appointed to consider all treaties laid before the Senate, and any other treaties to which the Committee may have access, and to report in respect of each such treaty:
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) whether Australian should undertake to be bound by that treaty if that treaty is not already binding upon Australia, and
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) the effect which Australia's being bound by that treaty has or would have upon the legislative powers and responsibilities of the Australian States; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) that, for the purposes of this resolution:
      </para>
      <para>
       `treaty' means any agreement or proposed agreement in writing between 2 or more countries which imposes or would impose rights and obligations upon those countries and which is or is intended to be binding upon those countries; and
      </para>
      <para>
       `undertake to be bound' in relation to a treaty refers to any action which would have the effect of making that treaty binding upon Australia, including the signing of documents, the ratification of that treaty or adherence or accession to that treaty.
      </para>
      <para>
       (2) (a) That the Committee consist of 8 Senators, 4 nominated by the Leader of the Government in the Senate, 2 nominated by the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, one nominated by the Leader of the Australian Democrats, and one Independent Senator;
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) that, of the Senators appointed to the Committee pursuant to subparagraph (2) (a), there shall be at least one Senator for each State; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) that, if nominations made under subparagraph (2) (a) are such that appointments to the Committee in accordance with those nominations would not comply with subparagraph (2) (b), the President shall notify the Senate accordingly and ask for fresh nominations, and if those fresh nominations are such that appointments to the Committee in accordance with them would not comply with subparagraph (2) (b), the President shall notify the Senate accordingly and the Senate shall determine the appointments to the Committee in accordance with this paragraph so far as is practicable.
      </para>
      <para>
       (3) That the Committee may proceed to the despatch of business notwithstanding that all members have not been duly appointed and notwithstanding any vacancy.
      </para>
      <para>
       (4) That the quorum of the Committee be 4.
      </para>
      <para>
       (5) That the Committee have power to appoint sub-committees consisting of 3 or more of its members, and to refer to any such sub-committee any of the matters which the Committee is empowered to consider, and that the quorum of a sub-committee be 2 Senators.
      </para>
      <para>
       (6) That the Committee elect a member nominated by the Leader of the Government in the Senate as Chairman.
      </para>
      <para>
       (7) That the Chairman may, from time to time, appoint a member of the Committee to be Deputy-Chairman and the member so appointed act as Chairman of the Committee at any time when there is no Chairman or the Chairman is not present at a meeting of the Committee.
      </para>
      <para>
       (8) That, in the event of an equality of voting, the Chairman, the Deputy-Chairman when acting as Chairman, have a casting vote.
      </para>
      <para>
       (9) That a Senator, though not a member of the Committee, may participate in its public sessions and question witnesses, unless the Committee orders otherwise, but shall not vote.
      </para>
      <para>
       (10) That the Committee or any sub-committee have power to send for persons to move from place to place, and to meet and transact business in public or private session and notwithstanding any prorogation of the Parliament or dissolution of the House of Representatives.
      </para>
      <para>
       (11) That the Committee be empowered to print from day to day such papers and evidence as may be ordered by it, and that a daily Hansard be published of such proceedings of the Committee as take place in public.
      </para>
      <para>
       (12) That the Committee be provided with all necessary staff, facilities and resources and be empowered to appoint counsel to advise the Committee and other persons with specialist knowledge for the purposes of the Committee, with the approval of the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       (13) That the Committee have leave to report from time to time its proceedings and the evidence taken and such recommendations as it may deem fit and make regular reports on its deliberations.
      </para>
      <para>
       (14) That the foregoing provisions of this Resolution, so far as they are inconsistent with the Standing Orders, have effect notwithstanding anything contained in the Standing Orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-That the Senate-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) notes that:
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) the Executive-Director of the United Nations Fund Population (UNFPA), Dr Nafis Sadik, recommended to a meeting of the Governing Council of the United Nations Development Program which commenced in New York on 5 June 1989 that an amount of US$57 million (A$76 million) be allocated by UNFPA for assistance to the Government of the People's Republic of China (PRC) for a population control program co-ordinated by the Department of International Relations/Ministry of Foreign Economic Relations of the PRC,
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) this action has been condemned by the US Government as a further example of UNFPA's support for population control programs involving the violation of human rights including coercive abortions and involuntary sterilisations,
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) in August 1985 the US Congress enacted legislation which prohibits US contributions to any organisation which supports or participates in the management of a program of coercive abortion or involuntary sterilisation,
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) in September 1985 USAID issued an official declaration that UNFPA participates in the management of a program of coercive abortion and involuntary sterilisation in the PRC,
      </para>
      <para>
       (v) the US withdrew all support for UNFPA, has regularly monitored its activities and has refused to resume support because there are `no significant changes either in the nature of the China population program or in UNFPA's assistance to China which would warrant resuming support for UNFPA',
      </para>
      <para>
       (vi) in December 1988, in response to assurances sought by members of the AIDAB sub-committee of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade, that UNFPA had not funded programs, which involved coercive practices, Dr Sadik advised that `a review conducted by USAID had found that UNFPA had not been involved in coercion'. Dr Sadik failed to advise that this March 1985 USAID review was careful to note that it had not included audits of UNFPA accounts or site visits of UNFPA field activities, and failed to advise the Committee that by September 1985 USAID itself had rejected the statement in that review relied upon by Dr Sadik; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) calls on the Australian Government to immediately cease allocating aid money to UNFPA which, despite its lip service to high-sounding principles, continues to be involved with the population control program of the Government of the PRC which is responsible for gross and continuing violations of human rights and repeatedly holds the PRC's population control program up as a model for developing countries to emulate.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-That the Senate, noting that-
      </para>
      <para>
       (a) the Governor of Victoria (Dr Davis McCaughey) deliberately chose as the subject for the 23rd Tracy Maud Memorial Lecture the title ``Medical Ethics: Who decides what and how?'' which in his speech he describes as ``one of public controversy'';
      </para>
      <para>
       (b) when referring to the question of human embyro experimentation, the Governor in his speech said: ``Even if legislation of a restrictive kind were to receive a majority vote, say in the Senate, or were to reflect public opinion as expressed in a public opinion poll, it would still be questionable whether it would be good democracy to impose it'';
      </para>
      <para>
       (c) Dr Davis McCaughey, in conjunction with another member of the National Health and Medical Research Council's Medical Research Ethics Committee (Dr Robert Jansen, now a director of an IVF clinic in New South Wales) drew up the pro-experimentation guidelines in 1982 which have given rise to so much public concern; and
      </para>
      <para>
       (d) these guidelines were subjected to the scrutiny of the Senate Select Committee on the Human Embyro Experimentation Bill 1985 which found that the marker event contained in the guidelines before which experimentation on human embyros could take place lacked inherent ethical validity and that the concept contained in those guidelines that the human embyro could be regarded as property, should be rejected,
      </para>
      <para>
       declares that:
      </para>
      <para>
       (i) the statement by the appointed Governor of Victoria, His Excellency Dr Davis McCaughey, which questions whether it would be good for democracy in effect for executive governments to enforce laws passed by elected Parliaments restricting experiments on human embyros strikes at the heart of our system of Parliamentary democracy and raises fundamental questions as to the role of Her Majesty's representatives in Australia,
      </para>
      <para>
       (ii) the question of experiments on human embyros is a major matter of public importance which cannot be confined to and determined by selected scientists and ethics committees,
      </para>
      <para>
       (iii) insofar as the Governor's statement seeks to undermine an Act of the Victorian Parliament which restricts experiments on human embyros, that is a question for the people of Victoria to determine, and
      </para>
      <para>
       (iv) insofar as the Governor's statement relates to Federal legislation to restrict experiments on human em- byros, as indeed has been recom-mended by a Senate Select Committee and the Family Law Council whose reports are now under consideration by the Federal Government, the statement of the Governor of Victoria might understandably be interpreted to be a reflection upon and an attempt to unduly influence the democratic processes of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-That the Senate take note of the Ministerial Statement of 18 December 1987 on the Select Committee on Human Embyro Experimentation Bill 1985-``Human Embyro Experimentation in Australia'' and the Family Law Council Report, tabled in the Senate on 8 October 1986.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="21" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following contingent notices of motion:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       No. 1-To move (contingent on the Senate on any day concluding its consideration of any item of business and prior to the Senate proceeding to the consideration of another item of business)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent a Minister moving a motion to provide for the consideration of any matter.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-To move (contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under standing order 75)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent a Minister moving an amendment to the motion.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="21" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BH4">
         Senator HILL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following contingent notices of motion:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       No. 1-To move (contingent on the Senate on any day concluding its consideration of any item of business and prior to the Senate proceeding to the consideration of another item of business)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate (Senator Hill) moving a motion relating to the conduct of the business of the Senate or to provide for the consideration of any other matter.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-To move (contingent on the Senate proceeding to the consideration of government documents)-That so much of the standing order relating to the consideration of government documents be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate (Senator Hill) moving a motion relating to the order in which the documents are called on by the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-To move (contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under standing order 75)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate (Senator Hill) moving an amendment to the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-To move (contingent on a Minister moving a motion that a bill be considered an urgent bill)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent debate taking place on the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-To move (contingent on a Minister moving a motion to specify time to be allotted to the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent the motion being debated without limitation of time and each Senator speaking for the time allotted by standing orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-To move (contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill, has expired)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent further consideration of the bill, or the stage of the bill, without limitation of time or for a specified time.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 7-To move (contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill, has expired)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent the questions being put in respect of any amendments circulated by the Opposition, the Australian Democrats or Independent Senators, and that such questions be put accordingly.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 8-To move (contingent on the President proceeding to the placing of business on any day)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate (Senator Hill) moving a motion relating to the order of business on the Notice Paper.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 9-To move (contingent on any Senator being refused leave to make a statement to the Senate)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent the Senator making that statement.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="2I4" page="22" party="AD" speaker="Macklin Sen M.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2I4">
         Senator MACKLIN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following contingent notices of motion:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       No. 1-To move (contingent on the Senate on any day concluding its consideration of any item of business and prior to the Senate proceeding to the consideration of another item of business)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Australian Democrats (Senator Macklin) moving a motion relating to the conduct of the business of the Senate or to provide for the consideration of any other matter.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-To move (contingent on the Senate proceeding to the consideration of government documents)-That so much of the standing order relating to the consideration of government documents be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Australian Democrats (Senator Macklin) moving a motion relating to the order in which the documents are called on by the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-To move (contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under standing order 75)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Australian Democrats (Senator Macklin) moving an amendment to the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-To move (contingent on a Minister moving a motion that a bill be considered an urgent bill)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent debate taking place on the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-To move (contingent on a Minister moving a motion to specify time to be allotted to the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent the motion being debated without limitation of time and each Senator speaking for the time allotted by standing orders.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-To move (contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill, has expired)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent further consideration of the bill, or the stage of the bill, without limitation of time or for a specified time.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 7-To move (contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill, has expired)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent the questions being put in respect of any amendments circulated by the Australian Democrats, the Opposition or Independent Senators, and that such question be put accordingly.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 8-To move (contingent on the President proceeding to the placing of business on any day)-that so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent the Leader of the Australian Democrats (Senator Macklin) moving a motion relating to the order of business on the Notice Paper.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="22" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following contingent notices of motion.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       No. 1-To move (contingent on the Senate on any day concluding its consideration of any item of business and prior to the Senate proceeding to the consideration of another item of business)-That so much of standing orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Harradine moving a motion relating to the conduct of the business of the Senate or to provide for the consideration of any other matter.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-To move (contingent on the Senate proceeding to the consideration of Government Documents)-That so much of standing orders relating to the consideration of Government documents be suspended as would prevent Senator Harradine moving a motion relating to the order in which the documents are called on by the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-To move (contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under standing order 75)-That so much of standing orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Harradine moving an amendment to the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-To move (contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill, has expired)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent further consideration of the bill, or the stage of the bill, without limitation of time or for a specified time.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-To move (contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill, has expired)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent the questions being put in respect of any amendments circulated by Senator Harradine, or any other Independent Senator, the Australian Democrats, or the Opposition, and that such questions be put accordingly.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-To move (contingent on the President proceeding to the placing of business on any day)-That so much of standing orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Harradine moving a motion relating to the order of business on the Notice Paper.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="3K4" page="23" party="IND" speaker="Dunn Sen I.P.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="3K4">
         Senator DUNN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following contingent notices of motion:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       No. 1-To move (contingent on the Senate on any day concluding its consideration of any item of business and prior to the Senate proceeding to the consideration of another item of business)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Dunn moving a motion relating to the conduct of the business of the Senate or to provide for the consideration of any other matter.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-To move (contingent on the Senate proceeding to the consideration of government documents)-That so much of the standing order relating to the consideration of government documents be suspended as would prevent Senator Dunn moving a motion relating to an order in which the documents are called on by the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-To move (contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under standing order 75)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Dunn moving an amendment to the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-To move (contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill, has expired)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent further consideration of the bill, or the stage of the bill, without limitation of time or for a specified time.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-To move (contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill, has expired)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent the questions being put in respect of any amendments circulated by Senator Dunn, or any other Independent Senator, the Australian Democrats, or the Opposition, and that such questions be put accordingly.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-To move (contingent on the President proceeding to the placing of business on any day)-That so much of standing orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Dunn moving a motion relating to the order of business on the Notice Paper.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="IG4" page="23" party="IND" speaker="Vallentine Sen J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="IG4">
         Senator VALLENTINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I give the following contingent notices of motion:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       No. 1-To move (contingent on the Senate on any day concluding its consideration of any item of business and prior to the Senate proceeding to the consideration of another item of business)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Vallentine moving a motion relating to the conduct of the business of the Senate or to provide for the consideration of any other matter.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-To move (contingent on the President proceeding to the placing of business on any day)-That so much of standing orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Vallentine moving a motion relating to the order of business on the Notice Paper.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-To move (contingent on the Senate preceeding to the consideration of government documents)-That so much of the standing order relating to the consideration of government documents be suspended as would prevent Senator Vallentine moving a motion relating to an order in which the documents are called on by the President.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-To move (contingent on the moving of a motion to debate a matter of urgency under standing order 75)-That so much of the standing orders be suspended as would prevent Senator Vallentine moving an amendment to the motion.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-To move (contingent on the Chair declaring that the time allotted for the consideration of a bill, or any stage of a bill, has expired)-That so much of standing order 142 be suspended as would prevent further consideration of the bill, or the stage of the bill, without limitation of time or for a specified time.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="23" type="Committee">
     <title>
      SELECT COMMITTEE ON CERTAIN ASPECTS OF THE AIRLINE PILOTS' DISPUTE
     </title>
     <debate.sub1 page="23">
      <title>
       Final Report
      </title>
      <proctext>
       <para>
       </para>
       <para>
       </para>
       <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
        <talk.start>
         <talker>
          <name nameid="10000">
           The PRESIDENT
          </name>
         </talker>
         <para in-line="1">
          —Pursuant to the resolution of the Senate on 17 October 1989, I lay on the table the final report of the Select Committee on Certain Aspects of the Airline Pilots' Dispute together with the transcript of evidence presented to me on 27 February 1990. In accordance with the terms of the resolution, I have authorised the printing and circulation of the report.
         </para>
        </talk.start>
       </interject>
      </proctext>
      <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" nameid="SF4" page="23" party="ALP" speaker="Cooney Sen B.C.">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="SF4">
          Senator COONEY
         </name>
         <electorate>
          (Victoria)
         </electorate>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —by leave-I move:
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        That the Senate take note of the document.
       </para>
       <para>
        I seek leave to continue my remarks later.
       </para>
       <para>
        Leave granted; debate adjourned.
       </para>
      </speech>
     </debate.sub1>
    </debate>
    <debate page="24" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ELECTRONIC VOTING
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Pursuant to the order of the Senate of 22 December 1989 I present a paper on electronic voting.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Motion (by Senator Macklin)-by leave-agreed to:
       </para>
       <para>
        That consideration of the document be an order of the day under Business of the Senate for the next day of sitting.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="24" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      REVISED STANDING ORDERS: SUPPLEMENTARY EXPLANATORY MEMORANDUM
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present a supplementary explanatory memorandum relating to the revised Standing Orders adopted by the Senate on 21 November 1989.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="24" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      BUSINESS OF THE SENATE
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I table the publication Business of the Senate for the period 1 January to 31 December 1989.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        Ordered that the publication be printed.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="24" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      QUESTIONS ON NOTICE: SUMMARY
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I table a summary of questions on notice for the period 14 September 1987 to 7 May 1990.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="24" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      PRESIDENT'S REPORT ON ANNUAL REPORTS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —I present the first President's Report on Annual Reports. This report is in accordance with paragraph (1) of the resolution of the Senate of 14 December 1989. I believe this report will be of considerable benefit to honourable senators in monitoring the large number of reports tabled in the Senate and determining whether those reports are tabled in accordance with the relevant statutory requirements. I commend the report to the Senate.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
       <para>
        I also present a list allocating the reports to the standing committees which has been provided to me by the Chair of the Standing Committee on Finance and Public Administration pursuant to paragraph (2) of the resolution of the Senate of 14 December 1989.
       </para>
       <para>
        Ordered that the document be printed.
       </para>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="24" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      ASSENT TO LAWS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       Messages from His Excellency the Governor-General were reported, informing the Senate that His Excellency had, in the name of Her Majesty, assented to the following laws:
      </para>
      <para>
       19 December 1989-Message-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 157-
      </para>
      <para>
       Sales Tax (Exemptions and Classifications) (Computer Programs) Amendment Act 1989 (Act No. 166 of 1989)
      </para>
      <para>
       Taxation Laws Amendment Act (No. 4) 1989 (Act No. 167 of 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       21 December 1989-Message-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 160-
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Legislation (Anti-Dumping) Act 1989 (Act No. 174 of 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       24 December 1989-Message-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 161-
      </para>
      <para>
       National Health Amendment Act 1989 (Act No. 175 of 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 162-
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Tariff Amendment Act (No. 4) 1989 (Act No. 176 of 1989)
      </para>
      <para>
       Excise Tariff Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989 (Act No. 177 of 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       28 December 1989-Message-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 163-
      </para>
      <para>
       Overseas Students Charge Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989 (Act No. 178 of 1989)
      </para>
      <para>
       University of Canberra Act 1989 (Act No. 179 of 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 164-
      </para>
      <para>
       Migration Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989 (Act No. 180 of 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 165-
      </para>
      <para>
       Smoking and Tobacco Products Advertisements (Prohibition) Act 1989 (Act No. 181 of 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 166-
      </para>
      <para>
       Family Law Amendment Act 1989 (Act No. 182 of 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       29 December 1989-Message-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 167-
      </para>
      <para>
       Foreign Corporations (Application of Laws) Act 1989 (Act No. 183 of 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       17 January 1990-Message-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 168-
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Education (Supplementary Assistance) Act 1989 (Act No. 1 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Land Rights (Northern Territory) Amendment Act 1989 (Act No. 2 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Community Services and Health Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989 (Act No. 3 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Crimes Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989 (Act No. 4 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs and Excise Legislation Amendment Act (No. 4) 1989 (Act No. 5 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Hazardous Waste (Regulation of Exports and Imports) Act 1989 (Act No. 6 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Housing Assistance Act 1989 (Act No. 7 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Industrial Chemicals (Nofitication and Assessment) Act 1989 (Act No. 8 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry Commission Act 1989 (Act No. 9 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry, Technology and Commerce Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989 (Act No. 10 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Law and Justice Legislation Amendment Act 1989 (Act No. 11 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Overseas Students Charge Amendment Act 1989 (Act No. 12 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Overseas Students Charge Collection Amendment Act 1989 (Act No. 13 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Overseas Students (Instalment Payments) Charge Act 1989 (Act No. 14 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989 (Act No. 15 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy Legislation Amendment Act (No. 3) 1989 (Act No. 16 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy Research and Development Act 1989 (Act No. 17 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Sales Tax (Exemptions and Classifications) Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989 (Act No. 18 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Sales Tax Laws (Computer Programs) Amendment Act 1989 (Act No. 19 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Taxation Laws Amendment Act (No. 5) 1989 (Act No. 20 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Therapeutic Goods Act 1989 (Act No. 21 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Therapeutic Goods (Charges) Act 1989 (Act No. 22 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       Transport and Communications Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989 (Act No. 23 of 1990)
      </para>
      <para>
       23 January 1990-Message-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 169-
      </para>
      <para>
       Electoral and Referendum Amendment Act 1989 (Act No. 24 of 1990).
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="25" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      SITTINGS OF THE SENATE
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       Motion by (Senator Robert Ray) proposed:
      </para>
      <para>
       That the order of the Senate of 5 December 1989 relating to the sitting of the Senate on Wednesdays, and modifying the operation of standing orders, be taken not to have come into effect, and come into effect on the first day of sitting in August 1990.
      </para>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="TI4" page="25" party="LP" speaker="Puplick Sen C.J.G.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="TI4">
         Senator PUPLICK
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales)
        </electorate>
        <time.stamp>
         (5.13)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I simply wish to indicate on behalf of the Opposition that we will support the motion to defer until August the new procedures which were adopted in December. We do so in the expectation that this chamber will sit for a four-week period and the hope that in fact there will not be a fifth week. Our decision in the party room that we would cooperate with the Government by not moving to have the Wednesdays not set aside for committees, and not have the process of the automatic referral of Bills to committees through the selection committee process, was made on the basis of the advice received that this chamber would sit for a four-week period. I say in my capacity as Manager of Opposition Business in the Senate that if in fact it turns out at the end of the four-week period that this chamber is to sit for a fifth week or subsequent weeks, we will regard ourselves as having been, in effect, inadvertently or deliberately misled as a result of having taken the Government on trust as to the four-week sitting period.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Our understanding of the argument for not introducing the Wednesday arrangements and not introducing the selection of Bills procedures during this period is essentially that the four-week period would be too short for all those procedures to be put into effect, and would cause some problem with the Government's legislative requirement for passage of Bills by a certain date. It was put to us that, with the House of Representatives sitting for only seven days in the first seven months of the new decade and with all of the considerable problems that the Government and the nation face, it was proper that the Senate should sit for a longer period. We have taken at face value the distributed list indicating a four-week sitting period.
      </para>
      <para>
       On that basis we have come to the conclusion that in fact it would not be unreasonable to suspend until August the orders made in December in relation to the Wednesday committee day and the automatic consideration of the reference of Bills to committees. All I can say is that we hope that the Senate will be able to proceed in good order to complete within that four-week period the program which has been notified to us and that a fifth week or subsequent weeks will not be necessary. If we had been notified that a fifth or subsequent week was contemplated, then in fact we would not have been so ready in our assent to the suspension of the December arrangements both in relation to Wednesdays and in relation to consideration of the automatic reference of Bills to committees.
      </para>
      <para>
       It is on the basis of a four-week sitting that we support Senator Ray's motion, and we hope that orderly processes can be followed during this period. If they are not, we may have cause to view with jaundiced eyes this whole exercise of postponing these arrangements until August. I trust that that will not happen.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="DEFENCE" nameid="UI4" page="26" party="ALP" speaker="Ray Sen The Hon R.F.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="UI4">
         Senator ROBERT RAY
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Manager of Government Business in the Senate)
        </role>
        <time.stamp>
         (5.17)
        </time.stamp>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —in reply-I am really forced to point out to Senator Puplick that he has totally misunderstood the motion. All it does is suspend the Wednesday committee sittings and nothing else. That is the effect of the motion. The selection of Bills committee will still come into existence, as will all the other changes agreed to last December. The only modification being made now is to do away with the Wednesday committees for this period of sittings.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="UJ4" speaker="Senator Walters">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UJ4">
          Senator Walters
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —He has not misunderstood a bit.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="UI4">
         Senator ROBERT RAY
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —If Senator Walters had listened she would have heard Senator Puplick say that we are not proceeding with the selection of Bills committee. We are. We are also proceeding with the rest of the changes. The only change we are not proceeding with at this stage is the one for Wednesday committee sittings.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       On the second matter raised by Senator Puplick: no guarantee has been given to anyone, certainly not by me, that we will sit for only four weeks. However, it is my fervent hope that we will sit for only four weeks. I have said that the list of Bills circulated this afternoon will not be added to. If anything is added to it, something of equal substance will have to come off. It is as simple as that. The two Bills that have been added most recently can proceed only at Thursday lunchtime, and that really depends on the integrity of the Minister saying that agreement has been reached on them and that there is no controversy about them. Otherwise they will get thrown off.
      </para>
      <para>
       I do not think there is a desire by anyone to sit for five weeks. I know Senator Puplick did not say that there was any desire to sit that long. There is no plan to sit for five weeks, but there is a tight program and it will need the cooperation of everyone in the chamber to get through the program. No one can blame me if the sitting goes into the fifth week simply because we spend three weeks debating the Estimates in the Committee of the Whole. That is something beyond my control. At the moment we intend to sit four weeks, and the only effect of this motion is to suspend Wednesday as the committee day. The rest of what we agreed to on 5 December is still in operation.
      </para>
      <para>
       Question resolved in the affirmative.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="26" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      DEATH OF THE HON. SIR REGINALD WRIGHT
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is with regret that I inform the Senate of the death, on 10 March 1990, of former Senator the Hon. Sir Reginald Charles Wright, Senator for the State of Tasmania from 1950 to 1978.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="26" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-I move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate expresses its deep regret at the death, on Saturday 10 March 1990, of the Hon. Sir Reginald Charles Wright, senator for Tasmania from 1950 to 1978 and a Minister of the Crown from 1968 to 1972, places on record its appreciation of his long and meritorious public service and tenders its profound sympathy to his widow and members of his family in their bereavement.
      </para>
      <para>
       Reg Wright was a senator for 28 years. He was born on 10 July 1905 at Central Castra, Tasmania, educated at Devonport State High School and the University of Tasmania. He was admitted to the Bar in 1928 and lectured in law at the University of Tasmania for 15 years. He enlisted in the 2nd Australian Imperial Force in 1941, was appointed a lieutenant in the 6th Australian Field Regiment and was promoted to captain in 1943.
      </para>
      <para>
       Prior to entering Federal Parliament Reg Wright was the Deputy Leader of the Liberal Party in the Tasmanian House of Assembly from 1946 to 1949 and was the inaugural State president of the Liberal Party in Tasmania. He was elected to the Federal Parliament as a senator for Tasmania in 1950 and served in that position until his retirement in 1978. He was appointed Minister for Works and had that portfolio from 1968 to 1972. Reg Wright was a member of numerous parliamentary Senate committees and delegations. I seek leave to have that portion of my speech which sets out those committees incorporated in Hansard.
      </para>
      <para>
       Leave granted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The speech read as follows-
      </para>
      <para>
       He served on various parliamentary committees including the Senate Standing Committee on Standing Orders from 1956 to 1962 and from 1965 to 1971 and the Senate Legislative and General Purpose Committee on Constitutional and Legal Affairs from 1973 to 1975 and the Standing Committee on Regulations and Ordinances where he served for a total of 17 years between 1956 and 1978. He was a leader of the parliamentary delegation to East Asia in 1969 as well as serving on other delegations.
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, Reg Wright was a very distinguished contributor to Australia and he was knighted for his services to the public in 1978. He was a man I think of very firm principles and was one of the great characters of the Senate. I do not think many senators in here remember Reg Wright but a few of us remember Reg Wright as a contributor to Senate debates. Those who did not have the opportunity of hearing him really missed something, in my view. Senator Peter Baume nods, and he is absolutely right. But he was on the same side as him; I was on the other side.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       He was always a formidable opponent and not just because he was a great thespian, a great orator.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="ME4" speaker="Senator Peter Baume">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="ME4">
          Senator Peter Baume
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —He was a peripatetic speaker. He went backwards and forwards.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —He was also a great wit. He used to move around the chamber and he was a very stocky and solid man. I interjected at some stage saying he resembled a bollard such that ships are tied to, and in his speech Reg Wright said, `Not only does this man insult my intelligence; tonight he has insulted my trunk'. I have never forgotten that. He really was a very formidable, great debater and a great wit.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       I say this: in those days I was an Opposition senator, of course; he was one of the greats of the Senate and it was a pleasure to be here with him even when being mercilessly done over by him. So I would like to pay that personal tribute to him and also to say that since he left the Senate I have always enjoyed his company albeit briefly when he has visited Canberra.
      </para>
      <para>
       Reg Wright, of course, was also well known for his habit of singing around Parliament House. When he retired he was presented with a book entitled the `Reg Wright Records Office Choir Book'. There are many other aspects of his character which other senators may well wish to touch on. I very much regret his passing although it was a long and distinguished life and career. On behalf of the Government I extend to his family our most sincere sympathy in their bereavement.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="27" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BH4">
         Senator HILL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —On behalf of the Opposition I support the motion moved by the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button) and extend our condolences to the family of the late Sir Reginald Wright. I will not repeat the statistics of the late Sir Reginald Wright's record, which have just been stated by the Leader of the Government, but one will have to recognise that 29 years of service to the Parliament-firstly to the Parliament of Tasmania and then to this Senate-is an incredible record of service. Looking through the achievements of Sir Reginald and what has been written about him, I must say that although I commenced my term in this place a few years after he retired, he clearly was one of the great characters of the Senate and, fairly I think, can be talked of in legendary terms with regard to this place.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       I found it interesting to read his maiden speech. In it he talked about his commitment to the Constitution, his commitment to federalism and to this Senate, and the very strong belief that he had in the Senate as a States House. I think it might be said that by the time of his retirement he may not have achieved all he wished in further developing this place as a States House, but what he did as an alternative was to play a considerable part in helping contribute to the development of the committee system within this place. So he looked in addition for other ways in which the Senate could continue to play a worthwhile and productive role within Australian politics.
      </para>
      <para>
       It was interesting also to read, in his final speech in this place, his comments again on the importance of this place and how he felt that it had developed during his long period of service. As I said, I came into the Senate after Sir Reginald left but it was interesting to note what Senator Withers said upon his retirement in 1978, Senator Withers being a person who is not unduly generous in his praise of others. He said:
      </para>
      <para>
       I have always admired Senator Wright as a robust man, forthright in his views and determined in his convictions. There are few, if any, who can equal his capacity to fight strongly for those things in which he believes. I have also respected him for his fairness and honesty.
      </para>
      <para>
       I think that that is a form of tribute which all of us would like to be paid upon completing service in parliamentary life. I guess Sir Reginald Wright will be remembered by many because I think he holds the record for the number of times he crossed the floor in this place. I gather it was in excess of 150 times. Those of us who have done it once or twice know it is not necessarily an easy thing to do. But what was important about it was that he refuted the tag of rebel as applying to himself. Rather he saw it as the proper recognition of the independent role that senators should play in this place and it reflected his concern about the fact that party politics was reducing that independence.
      </para>
      <para>
       I think that independent spirit is something which we should recognise and admire. I noted that in 1969 when he was speaking of this place-and it reflects what Senator Button said a few moments ago-he said:
      </para>
      <para>
       My purpose is to make Parliament a living, vital forum.
      </para>
      <para>
       I do not think there was any doubt that he contributed to making the Senate in the Parliament simply that. On behalf of the Opposition I extend to his widow and to his family our sincere sympathy in their bereavement.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="2I4" page="28" party="AD" speaker="Macklin Sen M.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2I4">
         Senator MACKLIN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —On behalf of myself and my colleagues I would like to associate us with this motion moved by Senator Button upon the death of Sir Reginald Wright. He left rather long before I came here. My previous Leader, in fact, when she was here in 1977 filling out a part of a Senate term, in one of the few votes in which she was able to take part in the six months that she was here, was able to associate herself with Senator Wright and one other in a lonely stand on an issue.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       In terms of detail I defer to my colleague, Senator Bell, who has not spoken in this place but wishes to speak on this condolence motion. I ask that in doing so it not be taken as his traditional first speech.
      </para>
      <para>
       In terms of detail, I would defer to my colleague Senator Bell, who has not yet spoken in this place but would wish to speak on this condolence motion. I would ask that his doing so not be taken as his traditional first speech. I understand that this precedent has been established.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="WA" nameid="8G4" page="28" party="LP" speaker="Durack Sen The Hon P.D.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="8G4">
         Senator DURACK
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Western Australia)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        -I also rise to associate myself with the condolence motion moved by the Leader of the Government on the death of Sir Reginald Wright, extending my own sympathy to his widow and members of his family on their very great loss. The record of Reg Wright as a senator has been well covered by the three previous speakers and I do not want to go over that ground again. Perhaps I should start by indicating my own first personal experience of Reg Wright. It was not when I came into the Senate; it was a few years before I did so. Reg was then still a backbencher in the Senate, where he had been for 17 or 18 years. I was asked to look after him for a couple of days after the law conference that he came to Perth to attend. I took him down to a small town in the south-west of Western Australia where I had a case in the local magistrate's court. Not only did he tell me how to win that case-which, incidentally, I lost-but he gave me a remarkable insight into his view of the Senate from the magnificent experience of all those years that he had spent here, in the process of which he had crossed the floor on many occasions. So I got a different view of the then Menzies Government front bench of the Senate from that which I probably should have had.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       On this trip we spent the evening with Reg Withers, who was then living in Bunbury, and I saw another aspect of Reg Wright. It was a great opportunity, as he was encouraged by Reg Withers, to learn something about Reg's wit and pleasure in life. The thing that I would like to emphasise most about Reg Wright was his great commitment to various causes and his strong belief in those that he adopted. He was, of course, a founder of the Liberal Party of Australia and, as has been mentioned, he was its inaugural President in Tasmania. Despite the many times that he voted against a Liberal Government, he never wavered in his deep commitment to the philosophy of liberalism, in which he so passionately believed and which he expounded with such eloquence, not only in this chamber but also in other places. He was undoubtedly a great parliamentarian, with a special devotion to the Senate and its particular role under our constitution.
      </para>
      <para>
       In the years that he was on the back bench in the Senate he continued to practise law with a great deal of success. I am sure that if he had not adopted a career in politics, he would have proved to be one of Australia's most distinguished advocates. As it was, he had a flourishing practice in the High Court. He got his opportunity when John Gorton-who had know his worth in the Senate and I suppose had felt it more keenly than many other members of the Menzies Government-became Prime Minister, for he made him Minister for Works in the years from 1968 until 1972. When I came into the Senate Reg Wright was on the front bench and there was never a stronger believer in teamwork and the need for everybody to get behind the ministry, the front bench and the party line, whatever it might be. Reg showed the same fervour that he demonstrated when expounding his views on many subjects from the back bench when insisting on the rights at all times of the front bench of which he was then a member.
      </para>
      <para>
       I think the best example of Reg's contribution to the work of this place that I can think of is the fact that when he left it we saw the need to establish a committee to do the work he had done. He was, of course, a great reader of Bills. I think he probably did read every Bill that came into this place. Admittedly for most of his career here there were many fewer Bills and less complicated Bills than we now are faced with, nevertheless he was a great reader of Bills. He went through them, of course, to see particularly how they affected the liberty of the individual. He was, I see, a member of the Regulations and Ordinances Committee for 17 years and he no doubt found in that committee a great challenge concerning his particular interests.
      </para>
      <para>
       But it was his work on Bills and his attention to the details of Bills which was the most impressive aspect of his work as I saw it in this place. As I said, when he left the Senate a number of senators who were aware of this felt that we needed to have a committee to scrutinise Bills for the same reasons that Senator Reg Wright had scrutinised them. He was a notable character, a great mind, a great parliamentarian, and he was, of course, a great Tasmanian. Another one of his great passions was representing the people of his State and there will not be many others the like of him to sit in this place again.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" gov="1" ministerial="JUSTICE AND CONSUMER AFFAIRS" nameid="NJ4" page="30" party="ALP" speaker="Tate Sen The Hon M.C.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="NJ4">
         Senator TATE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Minister for Justice and Consumer Affairs)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, I wish to associate myself with the motion of condolence moved by Senator Button. I do so because I knew Sir Reginald Wright for some 30 years in Tasmania. I believe that I first met him back in 1963 when I was a law student and visited his home in Newtown, in Mortimer Street, with Phillip Wright, who was a fellow student of mine and a son of Reg Wright. I did so with some trepidation because I can tell you Reg Wright was a very gruff and intimidating figure as he stomped around that house and, as a young law student, being confronted with such an eminent reputation in law filled me with awe.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       I last met Sir Reginald at the centenary celebrations of the University of Tasmania down in Hobart and I believe there, even though perhaps I did not view him with trepidation, I certainly still felt that I was moving into a presence which filled me with respect. There was something about the man which I think conveyed the sense that he was somebody extraordinary and yet certainly in his later, more mellow years there was a gentleness and a happiness about his personality which was, as I say, at variance with that early impression of being so gruff and intimidating.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mr President, Reg Wright was born in Central Castra on the north-west coast of Tasmania, and in his later years in retirement he returned from Hobart to the very same farmhouse where he was brought up as a child. I think in the symbolism of his birth and death in Central Castra we have an indication of his very strong link with Tasmanian soil. He felt he was first and last, and had proved to be first and last, a son of the Tasmanian soil, particularly that lovely red soil of the north-west coast of Tasmania. I am sure that he intended, in a way, that when he died it should be in that farmhouse which he so lovingly restored in his retirement.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Durack has spoken of Sir Reginald's considerable skills as an advocate. As a student I used to visit the courts in Tasmania, including the Supreme Court, where Sir Reginald would be defending an accused person in a trial before a judge at that level. Equally, however, during the next week he may have argued a section 92 case before the High Court when it used to visit Tasmania more regularly. In both instances one was aware that here was a great mastery of the law wedded to a great theatrical presence. He no doubt brought the sense of theatre which he displayed in his skills as an advocate in the courts to this chamber. Unfortunately, I never saw him speak in the chamber, but I believe that that sense of theatre, which was one of his great attributes, was used in devastating fashion and to great effect both before judges at all levels and in this chamber. No doubt it was similarly used in party rooms.
      </para>
      <para>
       He was always prepared to stand up for the values in which he believed and he would never retreat from them. That was certainly a characteristic of his. Some would call it stubborness; others would say that it was a firm adherence to principles and values which he treasured. To his widow, his children, his grandchildren and his great-grandchildren, I express my sympathy on the loss of a revered patriarch.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="VJ4" page="30" party="LP" speaker="Watson Sen J.O.W.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="VJ4">
         Senator WATSON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I rise in support of the condolence motion for the Hon. Sir Reginald Wright. Since I succeeded Sir Reginald in the Senate in 1978, I rise with special purpose to pay tribute to this remarkable man and fine parliamentarian. Sir Reginald's career in the Senate lasted for 29 years and was often turbulent and forthright, but he never once went against his true liberal principles and never forgot that his primary role here was as a senator for Tasmania.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Reg Wright was educated at Devonport High School and the University of Tasmania. At the university, he took degrees in both the arts and law. He was admitted to the Tasmanian Bar in 1928 and then lectured in law, while practising, for 15 years. From 1941 to 1944 Reg Wright was a captain in the field of artillery, 2nd AIF and then, in 1946, he was elected as member for Franklin in the Tasmanian House of Assembly. A mark of his colleagues' regard was that he was immediately elected Deputy Leader of the Opposition to the late Neil Campbell and was President of the Tasmanian Division of the Liberal Party. In 1949 he resigned from State Parliament to successfully contest the Senate election.
      </para>
      <para>
       Reg Wright was a founding member of the Liberal Party in 1945. He devoted the whole of his parliamentary career to attacking encroachments of the Executive on the parliamentary arena. This attitude engendered several notable and public disagreements with Sir Robert Menzies, Harold Holt and Malcolm Fraser. He voted against his Party about 160 times. However, these comments that he made in 1978 show his attitude to the party system in general and the Liberal Party in particular:
      </para>
      <para>
       No man can achieve anything in politics just as an individual. In order to gather support, you've got to be associated with others in a common cause.
      </para>
      <para>
       Sir Reginald Wright was created a Knight Bachelor in the Queen's Birthday Honours List in 1978 for his distinguished public and parliamentary service-a recognition that was acclaimed throughout Tasmania. At his testimonial dinner in July 1978 more than 800 members of the Party paid tribute to his State and Federal career of service. After leaving politics, Reg Wright moved to his Central Castra farm, next door to the farm on which he was born. His name was occasionally to be found in the coastal reports of magistrates' cases-always, of course, on the defence side. His brother, Sir Douglas Wright, also brought up in Central Castra, achieved international renown as a physician and Chancellor at Melbourne University.
      </para>
      <para>
       When I stood at the 1977 Senate election, Senator Wright took me around many parts of Tasmania and introduced me to various groups. He was always greeted with affection, even in staunch Labor areas, simply because all Tasmanians knew that Senator Wright stood up very strongly for his beliefs. I think that it is a mark of the greatness of the Liberal Party that a parliamentarian can cross the floor on matters of conscience and hold no fears of losing preselection or even of being expelled. Reg Wright frequently joined former Senator Ian Wood from Queensland in disputing the party line. Both had notable victories in the Menzies years when they fiercely rejected an increase in the sales tax on cars and succeeded in changing some Cabinet decisions.
      </para>
      <para>
       John Gorton had experienced Reg Wright's formidable skills as a debater when he was Leader of the Government in the Senate and decided that Reg Wright would be an asset to the Ministry. Reg was appointed Minister for Works and Minister-in-charge of Tourist Activities in 1968 and served until 1972. It was a belated recognition of his first class intellect and analytical skills.
      </para>
      <para>
       Reg Wright never wrote a speech for delivery in the Senate. His speeches were always of an impromptu nature and delivered with rolling cadences and the beautifully crafted sentences of a barrister.
      </para>
      <para>
       Reg Wright was a true politician-a man who served his constituents, his beliefs and his ideals faithfully. At this time I would like to convey my condolences to his wife, Lady Wright, his children and their families. He is a man who will be greatly missed by all.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="UJ4" page="31" party="LP" speaker="Walters Sen M.S.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="UJ4">
         Senator WALTERS
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I rise to join my colleagues in expressing my deep sorrow at the sudden death in March of Sir Reginald Wright. Reg was considered by his colleagues as the ultimate politician of the highest ideals and principles. His greatest love was his home State of Tasmania and that was one of the reasons he made the Senate his political career. It was during that period of his life that I knew Reg so well. I firmly believe that he was one of the greatest Tasmanians ever to represent that State in this Parliament.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       He loved the Senate and the Australian Constitution. Indeed, in 1977 he led just a handful of Liberal Party senators-I think there was one from Western Australia, one from South Australia, three from Queensland and the five Tasmanian senators-in opposing the constitutional referendum for simultaneous elections. This was done without any finances at all. It was against the might of the two major parties, the Liberal Party and the Australian Labor Party which were supporting the referendum proposal, that we fought and won that referendum. I will never forget Reg on that night as we gathered at his home waiting for the last figures to come in from Western Australia. When the figures finally came through his joy knew no bounds and he kept repeating, `We have won, my girl. We have saved the Senate and the Constitution'. He believed that and I believe it.
      </para>
      <para>
       Reg Wright, right from his very first year, pointed out his complete independence. He said that the Senate should be a House of review, answerable only to the Parliament, that there should not be Ministers in the Senate, and yet he regretted very strongly-and I think he thought it was his greatest mistake-his short sojourn on the front bench.
      </para>
      <para>
       We are told that he crossed the floor 150 times, each time on issues that he believed were terribly important. My father was Leader of the House during Reg's early days, and I remember his commenting that if there was ever any living proof that the Tasmanian tiger was still alive and well it was because Reg Wright proved such a problem. He used to say, `It will never be extinct while Reg is alive'.
      </para>
      <para>
       My office was next to his for the last three years of his term in the Senate, and I can assure honourable senators that there was never a dull moment. As everybody had indicated, he was fiercely Tasmanian, and he kept the rest of his Tasmanian colleagues well aware of their responsibilities in that regard.
      </para>
      <para>
       He was the most generous man I have known, helping the disadvantaged in every way possible, not only financially but also with his great knowledge. I join with my colleagues in sending my deep condolences to Lady Wright and his family.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="TI4" page="32" party="LP" speaker="Puplick Sen C.J.G.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="TI4">
         Senator PUPLICK
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        -Mr President, it is perhaps unusual for a Senator from New South Wales, one who has been here only since Sir Reginald Wright left the chamber, to associate himself with this condolence motion, but the first job that I had when I left university was as an officer on the staff of the then Minister for Social Services and Aboriginal Affairs, as he was then called, William Charles Wentworth. The first job that I was given in that capacity was to be sent up to the Senate to be told that each day prior to Question Time I had to brief the Ministers representing my Minister. The portfolios that Mr Wentworth held were respectively represented in the chamber by Dame Annabelle Rankin and by Senator Wright. It was my responsibility each sitting day to front Senator Wright in his office and to brief him on matters that were likely to arise at Question Time, either spontaneously or with some degree of anticipation.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       On the first occasion that I had the temerity to go to his office with my sheaf of papers and the instructions from my Minister, I recall finding a Rumpolian character sitting behind his desk. He then proceeded to put me through the sort of experience which I suspect that unsuspecting witnesses in the Hobart Magistrate's Court may have got used to from time to time. I recall simply retreating into saying to him, when he asked me why, as he would put it, `mollions and mollians' of dollars were to be spent on particular social welfare programs, that I could not really say but it was Government policy. I was told that despite the fact that he was Minister for Works, it was not a policy that he particularly approved of, but nevertheless he would do his best to give an answer to the extent that he thought that he was able to give an answer on Government policy without unduly compromising his own conscience on the matter.
      </para>
      <para>
       For the period that he was Minister for Works this was my daily task, and one which initially I looked forward to with great fear and trepidation, but eventually came to considerably enjoy, as I enjoyed my responsibility in briefing Dame Annabelle Rankin, who also represented us at that stage, and whom one could always rely upon to be far more gentle. Indeed, if the buttons on one's coat were not exactly fixed properly, they were fixed while she was listening to one's dissertation of the day.
      </para>
      <para>
       The second great experience I had of Sir Reginald was that I was invited as part of the ministerial staff on the inaugural trip of the Indian Pacific train, leaving Central Station in Sydney and travelling to Perth. On the first night, finding the bar car largely unoccupied, but nevertheless occupied by Senator Wright and a piano, I was told by Senator Wright that one of the great qualities of senators was their capacity to sing, which he proceeded to prove with some degree of expertise, and all I can say is that I do not actually remember the next two days of the trip.
      </para>
      <para>
       The third point that I want to make is that Senator Wright achieved one of those things that a lot of us dream about with some degree of envy: He took Richard Carleton and the Australian Broadcasting Corporation for a large sum of money for having approached with cavalier disregard the truth of particular matters in a way in which a lot of us are used to seeing journalists operate, in the ABC in particular. Sir Reginald Wright was not one to allow an opportunity to pass to put the record straight, and to do it properly.
      </para>
      <para>
       The final point that I make is that Senator Durack has rightly referred to the establishment of the Scrutiny of Bills Committee. It was perhaps the greatest of tributes to Sir Reginald Wright-and I say it with the greatest of affection for colleagues on this side who might have been members of the then Ministry-that the Scrutiny of Bills Committee was in fact established only because a large number of Liberal and National Party senators crossed the floor in the teeth of the opposition of the then Executive of the day to have that Committee established. Just as Sir Reginald as Minister for Works may have then or at a later stage had some view about the value of Party discipline, so have I always been interested to hear members of the Executive of the day, who opposed the establishment of the Senate Standing Committee for the Scrutiny of Bills and forced their colleagues to cross the floor, now saying what a wonderful institution it is and how it has improved the operations of the Senate.
      </para>
      <para>
       So I do in fact remember Sir Reginald quite well in a number of different capacities. I do agree with comments which have been made by honourable senators that he was in fact a unique character in the best sense of that term and I join with my colleagues in this place in extending my sympathy to the members of his family.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="IE4" page="33" party="LP" speaker="Archer Sen B.R.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="IE4">
         Senator ARCHER
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I, too, last saw Sir Reginald Wright on 12 February at the University of Tasmania centenary, where he was, as usual, enjoying himself and preparing to go away on a fortnight's holiday. I first met him in about 1950 and I had various associations with him, both in our roles hovering around the courts and at political associations.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       A lot of people in Australia probably have not heard of Central Castra, but I can inform honourable senators that it became a most outstanding place as a result of the Wright family. It was quite a big family and every single member of that family was outstanding in his or her own area and on his or her own merits. The whole of the north-western coast became involved with various members of that family. It really was an outstanding group. It did not matter where Sir Reginald was or how long he had been there; he would always come back to talking about Central Castra on the north-western coast.
      </para>
      <para>
       I do not think I have ever seen anybody who had a greater loyalty to his friends, family, State and ideals than Reg Wright. If you were not amongst his friends, very often you got short shrift. And he seldom relented. But he was one of the greatest speakers I have ever heard. He had a great voice, he was a great parliamentarian. I would say that, since I have been in this place, I have heard four really brilliant speeches. Two of them were by Reg Wright, and I think that is a pretty good average.
      </para>
      <para>
       He loved a good fight. He did not really mind who was involved or what it was about-if there was a good fight, he would be there. He was feared in the courts and outside. One has only to remember some of the committee work he was involved in and some of the debates that went on here. Those who remember him debating things like the tree pull scheme, the shipping question and the wharves, or his setting up the inquiry into the Mount Lyell mine, which of course he won, will remember that he proved that the points of view he was putting were correct. He read Bills from cover to cover. Not many people can really read a Bill and work it out, or spend the time and the effort he did. He was terribly thorough, and he was like this with his court work also.
      </para>
      <para>
       I had been here I suppose only about a month when one day I bumped into him in the passage. I made some comment. He said, `My boy, never impugn the motives of your colleagues'. I thought that was a silly thing for that man to say, but I am still here, and I still remember it every day. I doubt that I can give any better advice to any senator in this chamber or any member in the other chamber, or to the people who will come over the next many years. If I could be so bold, I would say I would offer the same advice myself now. He was never an easy colleague, but he was certainly a brilliant one. He was highly motivated by his own strong personal convictions, and I certainly remember the way that he looked after us when I started here at the end of 1975. Both Senator Walters and I knew at the time that never would a day go by when he would not offer some advice or ask us how we were going.
      </para>
      <para>
       An outstanding quality of Reg Wright was that-as somebody else has said-no matter where he was, his presence was always there. It was just impossible to have Reg Wright at a function, in a court, at a party or conference, or in the chamber without knowing and feeling he was there. Whether he was speaking, singing or sharing some of his stories and experiences, Reg was always at the centre of things.
      </para>
      <para>
       Right up to the time of his death he was still running his farm and still involved in legal work. One of the records that Reg claimed was that he had children at the Friends School in Hobart longer than any other parent had ever had. It was one of those records that one could readily associate with our old senator friend.
      </para>
      <para>
       I certainly would like to extend my sympathy to Lady Wright and the family of Reg Wright. Having attended the funeral, I can say it was a huge funeral, but it was not a sad one in any way because all the people there had various things to remember him by. They all had happy memories. The afternoon tea that was put on after the funeral was a very happy affair for all the people that congregated there.
      </para>
      <para>
       Please be assured there will never be another Reg Wright. There will never be another one like him in this place, and I doubt whether there will ever be another one like him in any of the parliaments of Australia. The passing of Sir Reginald is the end of an era. Australia benefited greatly from his participation in both politics and the law and will be the worse off for his passing.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="5F4" page="34" party="LP" speaker="Calvert Sen P.H.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="5F4">
         Senator CALVERT
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I too wish to associate myself with the motion of condolence moved by Senator Button. Might I say, as a fourth generation Tasmanian, I am very well aware of the contribution that Sir Reginald Wright made, not just to the Senate but to the legal profession and to Tasmania. My association with Sir Reginald was of a social nature. I had the pleasure of attending the Friends School, to which Senator Archer alluded, with some of the late Sir Reginald's sons. It is interesting to note that his son Christopher is following in his father's footsteps and is currently a judge of the Supreme Court of Tasmania, having previously been the Solicitor-General for that State. His other son, Philip, is a magistrate in Tasmania.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       My association with Sir Reginald began when I visited his seaside cottage at Opossum Bay. Work load permitting, he used to spend many happy hours there. In particular, on Saturday nights he would put in an hour or two at the local RSL club. That is where I first met Sir Reginald and, like many others, I looked forward to meeting him and hearing his anecdotes about Parliament and the characters he met. Of course, he was obviously one of the greatest characters one would want to listen to and speak with.
      </para>
      <para>
       I always remember him saying that he probably crossed the floor more times than he had crossed Bass Strait. Some friends of mine in Tasmania affectionately called him Tasmania's version of Rumpole of the Bailey. I agree with Senator Tate that, in later life in retirement, Sir Reginald's greatest love was his farm-Wally's Farm, as he affectionately called it. Anybody who visited Reg at Wally's Farm could not help being impressed by his love of the land and his love of nature-his cattle, his ducks and his garden.
      </para>
      <para>
       I also remember very well when the Tall Ships left the Derwent River in January 1988. Sir Reginald was staying at his seaside cottage. He armed himself with a small rucksack, filled with the appropriate refreshments, and a stick, walked from Opossum Bay to Fort Direction, which is about 6 miles away, so he could view the ships going out and then returned. I did not think that that was a bad effort for a person of 84 years. It is typical of the determination that Sir Reginald had. The tributes that have been paid to him today testify not only to his dogged determination but also to what a great man he was.
      </para>
      <para>
       Might I conclude by saying that I too pass on my sincere condolences to Lady Wright and the members of the the family. Like Senator Archer, I did attend the funeral. Probably one of the best speeches I have ever heard was made by the Hon. Michael Hodgman, QC, in a eulogy which I believe summed up the life and times of Sir Reginald Wright in a very fine manner.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="ME4" page="35" party="LP" speaker="Baume Sen The Hon P.E.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="ME4">
         Senator PETER BAUME
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —It is proper that we record the passing of great senators and even at this hour and on this day we should not avoid saying the things about a senator such as Sir Reginald Wright that we wish to say. It is good that his political opponent, Senator Tate, has said the generous things that he has said and it is proper that senators from other States should join our Tasmanian colleagues in fleshing out this story of Reginald Wright. He died in the same week as his brother, Sir Douglas Wright, who was the Chancellor of Melbourne University and was known affectionately throughout Australia as `Pansy' Wright. For those who do not know, Mr President, Pansy is short for chimpanzee.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The Chancellor of Melbourne University was, as was the honourable senator, a very formidable character. He was a teacher in my profession. He taught physiology. If you were ever unfortunate enough to attend a tutorial conducted by Sir Douglas Wright, you would know that he had a voice not unlike Reg's. He would say, `Tell me, boy, what you know about swallowing'. Anything you ever had known about swallowing you forgot immediately. It was in fact a family tragedy that both these great Australians died so close to each other.
      </para>
      <para>
       Honourable senators who were not here may not have really understood how Reg Wright dominated the chamber. Senator Button said in his contribution that Senator Wright moved around a little. He did not move around a little. He would start in one place and move to another; he would then move out to the next bay and anyone listening on the radio would wonder why the sound was rising and falling. He was the most mobile orator this chamber has ever seen-a peripatetic senator. He moved within about a six or eight-foot radius when he spoke, but at all times he commanded the chamber. People come into the chamber to hear him speak-the ultimate test of a senator. Those who heard John Wheeldon in his last days in this place would know--
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Archer interjecting-
      </para>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="ME4">
         Senator PETER BAUME
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —That is one of Senator Archer's speeches. When Senator Wheeldon spoke the chamber filled. Reg Wright was also one of those people who could bring people into the chamber. I remember an Irish politician telling me in Strasbourg once that he had observed of politicians that very few would come into parliament to listen to another person speak. But we would come in to listen to Reg Wright.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       There was something else about Reg to which I think Senator Watson has referred. We have our new Standing Orders. I am going to be the first to quote from them. What is now standing order 187 was standing order 406 in our previous volume. It is a very simple standing order. It says:
      </para>
      <para>
       No Senator shall read his speech.
      </para>
      <para>
       Equally, of course, no senator shall read her speech. I commend that standing order to certain senators. Senator Vallentine, for example, might care to read it.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senator Wright did not read his speeches and to see him speak was an experience. He would come in, staggering under the weight of law books and Senate documents on all kinds of references. He would spread these reference books out, having asked the colleague seated beside him to move, and then conduct his speech from them as if he were conducting a law case, in a manner that was impeccable. The speeches were beautifully crafted, beautifully documented with the various records he had brought in and beautifully rounded. He was a master of the Senate. He was also, Mr President, an institutional senator.
      </para>
      <para>
       We have in this chamber good party senators and we have a few people who are institutional senators. Their commitment is to the institution of Parliament and they devote themselves to advancing the institution of Parliament. For those who were not here with Reg Wright I point out that he was a master institutional senator. Not that he could not do other things.
      </para>
      <para>
       In my early days here we used to have tribal wars every so often. I remember that when the Chowilla Dam was being built we had South Australians conducting tribal wars late into the night, and when the tree pull scheme was on, we had Tasmanians conducting tribal wars, and Reg Wright would do his bit. If the tribal wars are less these days, well, that is partly because senators like Wright have gone. He left in 1978 and with his leaving, I suppose, there was a principle that was demonstrated, and it applies also to the other great long-serving senators I have known. Senator Justin O'Byrne was here for 33 years.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="UJ4" speaker="Senator Walters">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="UJ4">
          Senator Walters
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —And Senator Cavanagh.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="ME4">
         Senator PETER BAUME
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I do not know how long Senator Cavanagh was here, but Senator Ian Wood was here for well over 20 years. They dominated the chamber. They had an institutional memory going back forever, and when they left it was, next day, as if they had never been because what carries on is the institution. Any senator who is here-any one of us who is here-is here for a moment only. What we can do is contribute to the institution and to the Senate. Reg Wright did that. For that reason alone his passing should be honoured and should be remembered, and it is right that we are passing this motion today.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="BJ4" page="36" party="NP" speaker="Sheil Sen G.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BJ4">
         Senator SHEIL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I rise to associate the National Party of Australia with this motion of condolence about Senator Sir Reginald Wright. I happen to be one of the fortunate ones who shared some time in this chamber with him. I am thrilled to hear the glowing tributes that are being paid to him now, and I can almost see the smile on his cherubic face, if he could hear the things that are being said here. As one who realises that time in this place can be as but a moment, I appreciate Senator Peter Baume's last comments too. They add to the glowing tribute to Reg Wright.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       He was a dominant figure, he was peripatetic, and I can remember him with his coat open, sticking out his corporation, wandering around the aisles, waving his hand, and with his stentorian voice putting forth the most impeccable arguments that swayed the Senate.
      </para>
      <para>
       Just on that subject, I remember the time when Mr Jim Odgers retired as Clerk of the Senate. We had a function for him. He was speaking of great moments in the Senate. One of the great moments he remembered was a time when Reg Wright stood up against the Government and the Opposition, and he argued. He argued such a forceful and well presented case, that eventually the Government and the Opposition turned around and agreed with Reg Wright. Jim Odgers thought, `Well, now there is the Senate operating in a proper way at last'. However, it went back to a normal practice after that. But he was much appreciated by Jim Odgers.
      </para>
      <para>
       My first association with Reg as a committee member was when Mr Whitlam was Prime Minister. We had a deluge of revolutionary-type legislation coming through and there was an Opposition Attorney-General's committee. I had to go on that. I suppose I was the nearest thing to a lawyer that the National Party had, and I was on it with a whole lot of other lawyers. I remember Reg Wright himself, and Reg Withers. Also there was Ivor Greenwood, Alan Missen, all those people.
      </para>
      <para>
       The anti-discrimination Bill was coming in and they were talking about getting rid of discrimination in clubs. The argument wafted backwards and forwards and it was way above my head. After about an hour and a half, they suddenly said, `Oh, Glen, you haven't said anything about discrimination in clubs. What do you think about this?'. I said, `Well, I think the whole idea of having a club is to discriminate'. That logic seemed to be lost on most of them and they thought I had missed the point. But Reg Wright considered I had a certain rustic charm and took up the cudgels with me. I enjoyed his time. I loved the way he could use words and wrap his tongue around meretricious and millions. He made a contribution to this place that we should be proud of forever.
      </para>
      <para>
       I was aware that he really read every Bill. I sincerely believe he did. His office was awash with papers. He came in and made speeches exactly as Senator Peter Baume said, and he presented them with distinction. That is all one can say. So on behalf of the National Party I express my condolences to his widow and his family. I am sure that everyone who knew him, and this Senate in particular, is the richer for having had an association with Sir Reginald Wright.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="7U4" page="37" party="AD" speaker="Bell Sen R.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="7U4">
         Senator BELL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —On this occasion I ask for the Senate's tolerance and understanding. Though I have yet to make my first speech, I would like to make a brief contribution to and to be associated with this motion of condolence. I knew Sir Reginald Wright as most Tasmanians knew him-as a Tasmanian first and politician second. We Tasmanians sent him over here to represent us, and that he did with a passion. He was our representative, our champion, in the way that you send champions forth to do all sorts of duties. At his funeral I heard him referred to most accurately as a statesman-a State's man. He entered this place in the year that I was born. Throughout my early years his influence was such that I thought all senators were like Sir Reginald Wright, or Senator Wright as he was then. I have lived to learn that that is not so, and I wonder how Senator Button and his colleagues might cope with several clones of Reggie Wright. I think that Senator Archer's assurance that there will never be another was probably a most welcome assurance.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       In this States House Reggie Wright championed my State in his own peculiar way, and I say `peculiar' on good advice. I use the word to reflect Sir Reginald's individuality. He was an individual who loved words. He gloried in his individual, particular and effective use of words. He prepared words. He savoured words. And when he presented them for our edification they were almost like a meal. They were something to chew on and to enjoy-something to sustain you for the rest of the day. The walls of the old Senate chamber echo innumerable anecdotes about Sir Reginald and I shall not attempt to add to that store for we have already heard enough to sustain us for some days.
      </para>
      <para>
       My island State has Reggie Wright stories embedded within its fabric. He is part of our folklore and the particular individual world perspective that we Tasmanians enjoy. Those of us who heard him speak-which was a unique experience-will for ever treasure his skills in spreading words and images across our memories. I still carry my personal memory of Sir Reginald insisting that it was always important to consider the effect of legislation on Tasmania. I will not lose that memory and I hope it will give me guidance in the future. I join with the previous speakers in offering my condolences to his relatives.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="BE4" page="38" party="LP" speaker="Newman Sen J.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BE4">
         Senator NEWMAN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —As the Senate can clearly understand now, we Tasmanians were very proud of our Senator Reg Wright. Already this evening we have heard a great deal of his qualities. I do not think it appropriate to repeat what has already been said. I did not know Senator Wright very well personally. However, he was a colleague of my husband's during the Fraser Ministry years and my husband and I both attended his funeral service. As has already been said, it was a very happy funeral. I have never previously been to a funeral where people laughed so consistently throughout the service. For those of us who were present, it was a very good reminder of how a life lived to the full can be a matter for celebration at the end.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       I simply want to join with my colleagues in sending my sympathy and that of my husband to Lady Wright and to his family. He was a patriarch at the end and I hope that his genes will be long and strong in Tasmania political life. He was an orator of whom we were very proud, as we were of course of that other orator, Dame Enid Lyons. Certainly we who follow in the Liberal tradition in Tasmania have a lot to live up to. I would like to think that we will continue to strive for some of the qualities of courage, independence and intelligence for which we remember Sir Reginald.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="38" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, I would like to associate myself with the motion moved by the Leader of Government in the Senate (Senator Button) and seconded by the Leader of the Opposition (Senator Hill). As Senator Bell said, not every senator is like Senator Wright-and I might add that this Senate is not the same place now as it was when Senator Wright was here. Soon after his retirement, he said:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       If you only knew the spirit of apathy in the Senate 20 years ago and see the spirit today, why, the contrast is enormous.
      </para>
      <para>
       I would suggest that if one knew the spirit in the Senate 12 years ago, and then saw the spirit today, one would also say, `Why, the contrast is enormous'. I think it is very important for us, whilst supporting this condolence motion, to reflect on where this institution is going. I was here for only two or three years before Senator Wright retired-he retired in 1978-but I recall seeing him in the old chamber. I think he sat in the middle row, sort of a centre half-back position, and, as Senator Peter Baume said, whilst he was making a speech he was often out in the centre of the aisle or over here, as Senator Baume said, picking up a legal treatise and quoting from it. It is true, as Senator Baume said, that people came into the chamber to hear his contributions to a debate. I think probably the only one who did not come into the chamber was the person sitting sharing the bench with him, because he could not get into his seat. I do not recall who that was.
      </para>
      <interject chair="0" nameid="5F4" speaker="Senator Calvert">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="5F4">
          Senator Calvert
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —Neville Bonner.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Neville was there very, very often. He did not often miss a debate. But that was when debates were debates and there would be communication across the chamber. There is not that communication now, and that is a sad reflection on this chamber. It has changed. Of course, as Senator Bell said, not every one of us senators is like Senator Wright was. He was a truly independently minded person. He said of the Senate that it should be the check on unbridled power-the unbridled power, of course, of the Executive. Why was it that he took such a leading role, as Senator Walters quite rightly said, in that 1977 referendum campaign? Because had that proposal been adopted, in his view-and it was my view, as it was of a handful of others who opposed that proposition-it would reduce the power of the Senate as a check on the unbridled power of executive government and particularly of the Prime Minister of the day.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Mr President, in view of the time I should like simply to associate myself with this condolence motion and convey my sympathy to the widow and family of the late Sir Reginald Wright.
      </para>
      <para>
       Question resolved in the affirmative, honourable senators standing in their places.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="39" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      DEATH OF THE HON. ROBERT CUMMIN KATTER
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is with deep regret that I inform the Senate of the death on 18 March 1990 of the Hon. Robert Cummin Katter, a former member of the House of Representatives for the division of Kennedy from 1966 until his retirement earlier this year.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
     <speech electorate="VIC" gov="1" ministerial="INDUSTRY, TECHNOLOGY AND COMMERCE" nameid="4F4" page="39" party="ALP" speaker="Button Sen The Hon J.N.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="4F4">
         Senator BUTTON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Victoria-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Government in the Senate)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —by leave-I move:
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       That the Senate expresses its deep regret at the death, on Sunday, 18 March 1990, of Robert Cummin Katter, member of the House of Representatives for the seat of Kennedy from 1966 until his retirement earlier this year, places on record its appreciation of his long and meritorious public service and tenders its profound sympathy to his family in their bereavement.
      </para>
      <para>
       Bob Katter was born on 5 September 1918 at Brisbane, Queensland. He grew up in Cloncurry, where his family ran the general store. He attended school in Charters Towers where he was an athletics and football champion and active in local theatre and public speaking. He studied law at the University of Queensland and served as an infantry captain in World War II.
      </para>
      <para>
       Before entering Federal Parliament, Bob Katter was a councillor for the Cloncurry Shire from 1946 to 1967, including two periods as Chairman. He served as a member of the executive of the Queensland Local Government Association and was Chairman of that Association's Canberra Committee on Local Government. He was one of the Federal Parliament's longest serving National Party members. He was Minister for the Army in the McMahon Government in 1972. He served on various Commonwealth delegations and parliamentary committees, including the House of Representatives Standing Committee on Road Safety, on which he served as Chairman from 1976 to 1983; the Joint Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade; and the Joint Select Committee on the Family Law Act from 1978 to 1980.
      </para>
      <para>
       Throughout his long public life Mr Katter represented the people of north Queensland with dedication and energy. I must say that I did not know Bob Katter well, but on at least two occasions I visited Mount Isa-I think as a Minister on each occasion. Bob Katter, as the member for that area, with the proprietorial air which National Party members for big electorates tend to have, extended considerable hospitality to me, although I suppose I was there to try to get rid of him. On each of those occasions when I was in his electorate I appreciated his kindness and hospitality to me.
      </para>
      <para>
       There are, of course, many occasions when we express sorrow at the passing of former members. On this occasion the sadness is keen, in part because he was so recently a colleague in the House of Representatives. The memories are fresh and we think of him with respect. On behalf of the Government I extend to Mr Katter's family our sincere sympathy on their bereavement.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="SA" nameid="BH4" page="39" party="LP" speaker="Hill Sen R.M.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BH4">
         Senator HILL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (South Australia-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Opposition)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —On behalf of the Opposition I join the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button) in support of the motion and in expressing our sympathy to the family of the late Bob Katter. I will not reiterate the details of his career as they have just been outlined by the Leader of the Government, but I will repeat his record in public life-that is, 20 years as a councillor for the Cloncurry Shire and 24 years as a National Party member of this Parliament. That, in anyone's language, is an enormous contribution in public service and one for which we should all be grateful.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       He pursued many interests in this place, some of which should be particularly remembered. Firstly, I refer to his representation of the interests of northerners. This always seemed to be his first priority. He was a co-founder of the Longreach Stockman's Hall of Fame. After the change of government in 1972 he was coalition spokesman for northern development and the Northern Territory. Secondly, he served on many committees and was particularly interested in foreign affairs and defence. You will remember, Mr President, his contribution to a document headed Threats to Australia's Security which became known as the Katter report, which was put down in 1981 by the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence. It was recommended by one reviewer as `required reading for anyone who seeks a well-informed, clearly written and bipartisan document'-and I will come back to that committee contribution in a moment.
      </para>
      <para>
       Thirdly, I think he will be remembered for his service over 11 years on the House of Representatives Select Committee on Road Safety. He was deeply concerned about the road toll and argued strenuously for the introduction of random breath testing on a national basis.
      </para>
      <para>
       In this strange business of politics, there are some with whom one comes into contact rarely and some whom one meets often. I actually had a lot of contact with Bob Katter over the nine years that I have been in this place through our mutual interest in foreign affairs and defence and our mutual involvement on the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence. I will remember certain aspects of his contribution. I will always remember his enthusiasm. He had great pride in Australia. He was always an optimist and, I think felt that there were too many pessimists within our community.
      </para>
      <para>
       His pride extended particularly to his view of the Australian armed forces. When we travelled together visiting military establishments and when he saw military personnel in this place, he was constantly putting to them how important he regarded their work and their commitment. Also, I will always remember his attitude to foreign visitors, which was a lesson to us all. The Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence receives many foreign visitors. Bob Katter was always present, and was not only courteous but also genuinely warm in welcoming these visitors to our shores, and in that way- which may not be known to many senators-was, in my view, a great ambassador for Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       On behalf of the Opposition, I extend to his widow and children our sincere sympathy in their bereavement.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="YE4" page="40" party="NP" speaker="Boswell Sen R.L.D.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YE4">
         Senator BOSWELL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the National Party of Australia)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I support the motion moved by the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button). Bob Katter was well known to many of us both in the Senate and in the House of Representatives. As Senator Button has said, he was a person who would go out and welcome people into his electorate. I well recall him on one occasion turning up to welcome the Prime Minister (Mr Hawke) to his electorate at Mount Isa. When visiting Mount Isa during the last campaign, the Prime Minister offered to go and see Bob Katter in hospital.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Bob Katter was born in 1918 in Brisbane and grew up in north Queensland. He was the proprietor of the local drapery business, menswear store and picture theatre. He won the seat of Kennedy in 1966 and held it until six days before the election. Kennedy had been an Australian Labor Party electorate held by the Riordan family for two generations. Bob Katter won that seat because he had the ability to mix with the mighty and the humble and would give each the same time and consideration. He was just as much at home with the leader of the grazing community or the captain of the mining industry as he was with the ringers, fencers, fettlers, kangaroo shooters and the Aboriginals. In fact, he had a special affinity with the Aboriginal people and was extremely kind and generous to them.
      </para>
      <para>
       Before television came to the bush, one of the main sources of entertainment in country Queensland was a night at the pictures, and it was customary at that time for Aboriginal people to sit on the hard benches either in the back or front of the theatre and the Europeans to sit in the canvas chairs. Bob Katter would not tolerate that segregation. In fact, he removed the hard chairs so that everyone was forced to share the canvas seats.
      </para>
      <para>
       Those attributes were passed on to his son, young Bob. Bob junior played with the Cloncurry Tigers, which was an all-black team. The reason he played with the all-blacks is that he did not like racism or segregation. Bob Katter champ- ioned the causes of north Queensland and his beloved seat of Kennedy. In his maiden speech he called for the development of the north. He saw the tremendous job potential, the job opportunities and the wealth creation that were in north Queensland-the timber industry, cattle industry, mining, wool growing-and he continually fought for people in the bush to have the same facilities as were taken for granted in the cities. In his maiden speech he called for television for remote areas, and he lived to see three television stations servicing north Queensland, including his electorate. He successfully pushed for decent communication, and at present very few people in western Queensland do not have a telephone or some decent form of communication. That is a tribute to him. I can remember probably less than 12 months ago being at a meeting with him in the town of Blackall, where he continued to fight for people to get off party lines and to have some form of communication comparable to that of the cities. Bob always said that he thought everyone was entitled to know who won the last on Saturday.
      </para>
      <para>
       Bob Katter worked hard for a decent road system in north Queensland. When he was elected to the House of Representatives in 1966 it was a seven-hour drive between Cloncurry and Mount Isa, a distance of some 200 kilometres. It is now a comfortable one-hour journey because he achieved decent roads for the north. Bob was an achiever for his massive electorate of Kennedy, an electorate that is three times the size of Victoria. Both he and his wife, Joy, moved around the electorate, calling on the major centres but never neglecting little towns like Dajarra, five or six houses. He kept in communication with his electorate. He was also a great supporter of the underprivileged.
      </para>
      <para>
       Bob had a great many years in local Government, as Senator Button has said, as a councillor, deputy chairman and chairman of Cloncurry Shire Council. He was a man before his time in a lot of ways. As chairman of the Cloncurry Shire Council he was responsible for the installation of fridges and evaporative air conditioners by making bulk purchases and amortising them against the cost of the rates, because he knew that many of the people there could never afford those amenities that are so necessary in the heat and the dryness of western Queensland.
      </para>
      <para>
       While he was its chairman the local shire council provided small one-room cottages for retired station workers who were living in absolutely appalling conditions in Cloncurry and were unable to afford any accommodation. He was well respected and admired in the local government community right throughout Queensland and was a member of the Queensland Local Government Association and an executive of the western Queensland local government association. He continued that interest right up until his demise. I can recall going out and meeting Senator Reid and a number of other senators on a local government committee when he was taking them around and showing them north Queensland only a couple of years ago. He served in the Army between 1936 and 1942, rising to the rank of captain. I can recall him naming one of the Army helicopters after the Kalkadoons, who were the local Aboriginal people in Cloncurry. Mr Bob Katter was a legend in Kennedy and a legend in north Queensland. There are many Katter stories told about Bob right throughout the north.
      </para>
      <para>
       I believe that the people in Mount Isa said it all on the day of the funeral. Many thousands of people lined the streets from the church to the cemetery to pay their respects to their member of 24 years. He had won a great deal and done much for north Queensland. Bob lived by the maxim, `Work hard, play hard and pray hard'. He is survived by his wife Joy, four sons-Bob, Norman, Carl, Richard-and two daughters-Geraldine and Bernadette. On behalf of the National Party of Australia, I extend our sympathy to them.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="YH4" page="41" party="LP" speaker="MacGibbon Sen D.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="YH4">
         Senator MacGIBBON
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I would like to add a brief personal tribute to the late Bob Katter. This afternoon the Senate is revering the passing of two really great characters of the Australian Parliament in Reg Wright and Bob Katter. They were very different people, although of somewhat similar build physically. Bob Katter was one of those really great Queensland personalities. He was known throughout the length and breadth of the State. It was my pleasure to meet him in 1977 when I was campaigning for the Senate, and he exhibited that generosity to me to which Senator Button referred. I think that in all the time I have been in the Senate Bob and I constantly shared membership on one committee or another.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Reference has been made to Bob Katter's great interest in defence. About six years ago I succeeded him as Deputy Chairman of the Joint Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence but, as Senator Hill has said, Bob's interest in that committee was undimmed. Bob Katter was a man of very great generosity and very great enthusiasm-enthusiasm for life in all its many facets. He was also a man of great love for his family and for the community-not any one part of it and not with any narrow vision, but for the whole country, the whole of Australia. He was a very proud Australian. In my experience around Queensland he had absolutely no enemies at all, and that is a claim that very few of us in politics can make. Bob was genuinely liked and admired by all the people who knew him. I think that great admiration for Bob was shown by the community at his funeral service in Mount Isa where, sadly, since it was only a few days before the election, a large number of his colleagues who would otherwise have been there from this Parliament were not able to attend. But from all over Queensland, and particularly from Mount Isa and the Kennedy region, they turned up in their legions to pay their last respects. It was a privilege to know Bob, and his passing is a great loss for his family, for his friends and for Australia.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="2I4" page="42" party="AD" speaker="Macklin Sen M.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="2I4">
         Senator MACKLIN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         Leader of the Australian Democrats)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I would like to associate the Australian Democrats with the condolence motion moved by Senator Button. I think that Senator Hill put it very well when he said that one of the characteristics that Bob Katter exhibited to overseas guests was courtesy. It was an extraordinary strong type of courtesy that he exhibited; always very robust but never abrasive. It was, to me at least, an experience to see how he handled those two sides. Unfortunately, not many of us manage to get them right.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       I think that Bob Katter was one of the first House of Representatives people I met when I came to the Senate 10 years ago. Unfortunately, honourable senators have very little contact with honourable members of the House of Representatives, but one tends to meet one's colleagues on plane trips more than anywhere else. On many occasions going back to Queensland we drew corresponding seats. We talked about a lot of things, but I think the thing I remember most about him was his great love of his family. They were, despite his intensive public life, something that he cherished greatly. He had, of course, as all honourable senators know, a young family as well as his older children. He was always proud to talk about their school achievements. We spent a lot of time swapping stories about what our children were doing at various stages in school.
      </para>
      <para>
       That love of children, of course, extended to his work on the Parliamentary United Nations Children's Fund committee as a member of the executive; it was not in fact simply limited to his own children. Bob Katter had a genuine human compassion for the plight of children around the world. Indeed, as I have found out over the years it is impossible to move anywhere in his electorate or to talk with any council in north-west Queensland without hearing Bob Katter stories, a lot of which are not able to be repeated here. One cannot go anywhere without hearing one of those stories, and they added up in number.
      </para>
      <para>
       During the last election campaign, I was in the Kennedy area. People knew that Bob Katter was then sick and, later, that he had died. A lot of them talked about him and about their memories of him. The comments were all of the type that Senator MacGibbon has referred to. I never ever met anyone anywhere who had anything bad to say about him. That is, as Senator MacGibbon has said, not something that is universal in this profession. Bob Katter was well loved throughout the entire area and will be sadly missed. It is indeed disappointing that he could not have had a long retirement after his extraordinarily vigorous and lengthy public life.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="ND4" page="43" party="NP" speaker="Bjelke-Petersen Sen F.I.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="ND4">
         Senator BJELKE-PETERSEN
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queens-
        </electorate>
        <role>
         land)
        </role>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I wish to join with the Leader of the Government in the Senate (Senator Button), the Leader of the Opposition (Senator Hill), the National Party of Australia (Senator Boswell) and other honourable senators in paying tribute to the late Hon. Bob Katter, who for almost 25 years was a member of the Federal Parliament and who served the people of Kennedy, his electorate in north-west Queensland based on Mount Isa, faithfully and well.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The late Bob Katter, as has been mentioned here by quite a number of speakers, was Minister for the Army in the McMahon Government for a short period and he was a loyal and hardworking member of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence. I believe that that was really one of the very important matters in his life as a member of parliament. He was certainly very involved in it and he regularly attended meetings. I suppose that came from the fact that he was a member of the Australian Army himself from 1936 until 1942, when he rose to the rank of captain.
      </para>
      <para>
       I was interested in what our Leader of the Opposition said about Bob Katter's appreciation of the defence forces. That would have come, of course, as I said, from his having been in the Army. At his funeral I thought to myself how pleased Bob would have been to have known that an Army colonel and major were there representing the Governor-General and the Queensland Governor.
      </para>
      <para>
       Prior to becoming a member of parliament, Bob had been very active in local government, having served two terms as the chairman of the Cloncurry shire and through executive positions with the Queensland local government associations.
      </para>
      <para>
       I have been in and out of Mount Isa over many years, firstly as the wife of the Premier of Queensland and then latterly as a senator. The hospitality of the Katter home was extended to me on many occasions. Actually, I have often said that the best feed of barramundi that I have ever had was given to me by Joy Katter in the Katter home at Mount Isa. It was lovely fresh barramundi from the Gulf of Carpentaria and beautifully cooked by Joy.
      </para>
      <para>
       I often met Bob on the plane, especially if I had seat 1A. Bob's seat was always 1B. No-one ever got seat 1B if Bob Katter was travelling on the plane.
      </para>
      <para>
       At one time Bob represented part of South Burnett, my home district, when it was in his vast electorate of Kennedy which took in almost one-third of the State of Queensland. When I say that Queensland fits Victoria into it seven times you know just how great an area Bob had to look after. He travelled that whole area so often that it is a wonder that his children knew him, particularly the younger ones, because he was away from home so often. But that was his job and he put 100 per cent effort into it.
      </para>
      <para>
       It is no wonder that Mount Isa paid a tremendous tribute to him on the day of his funeral. People came not only from Mount Isa, but also, as Senator MacGibbon said, from far afield to pay a tribute to Bob Katter. The church was full to overflowing and the crowds lined the streets all the way to the cemetery. The tribute that his son, Bob junior, the member for Flinders, paid to his father that day brought tears to many people's eyes; members of the Katter family took part in the service.
      </para>
      <para>
       The late Bob Katter was an executive member of our pro-life group in the Parliament and also an attending member of our parliamentary christian fellowship. His christian faith meant a lot to him. As a Queensland senator and as a friend I want to pay this tribute to him and extend to Joy and the children at home, Carl, Richard and Bernadette, and indeed to other members of the family, young Bob, Geraldine and Norman, my sincere sympathy and pray that God will be their comfort in their loss of a devoted husband and father.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="QLD" nameid="BJ4" page="44" party="NP" speaker="Sheil Sen G.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="BJ4">
         Senator SHEIL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Queensland)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Bob Katter was known as Alligator Katter long before we ever got Crocodile Dundee and he was a very colourful denizen of the north. He drove around that gigantic electorate of Kennedy incessantly and visited every nook and cranny in it. If he did not know everybody in Kennedy, then everybody in Kennedy knew Bob. He was the consumate politician, as has been attested here. I do not want to go over all the tributes again, but I appreciate all the things that he did.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       As was said by Senator Macklin, everybody in the north of Queensland had a story about Bob Katter, he was so well known. He did not tell any of them, but I think that a couple are worth recalling. On one occasion he was driving along one of these long outback roads when he saw a plume of dust approaching from the other direction; it was another car. As he slowed down to pass he saw the other driver had the window down. The lady who was driving put her head out to say something to him as she went past. He put his window down and his head out and she said, `Pig'. He just had time to stick his head out the window to say, `Bitch'. He went on in the dust and hit the pig!
      </para>
      <para>
       I remember another story. After a meeting way out west a little group was having a cup of tea. All of a sudden a minibus full of Japanese spending a few days in the outback arrived. When they got out of the bus they were all chattering away and talking and laughing. Bob sent one of the chaps over to the interpreter to ask what they were all talking about. He came back laughing his head off. He said `You won't believe this. They've been on that bus on that road there for two hours and they haven't passed another car. They wanted to know if it is a one-way street'. I do not think any of them realised the vast distances we had to cover in those times.
      </para>
      <para>
       But Bob Katter enjoyed parliamentary life. The highlight for him was when he was Minister for the Army. I think he felt he made a solid contribution there; I am sure he did. He enjoyed his time as a parliamentary representative at the United Nations which was another highlight of his career. The foundation of the Stockman's Hall of Fame gave him enormous satisfaction. The Hall of Fame is a highlight of the trip from the Great Barrier Reef to Ayers Rock in the middle of Australia. I also mention his contribution to local government which is a subject he dearly loved to deal with and spent endless time on. He also made an enormous contribution to road safety in Australia.
      </para>
      <para>
       As has been said, he has had two families. His first wife died after a long and distressing illness. He then married Joy and they had another family, a lovely family whom he doted on. Just before he died I ran into him one day when he was going into the hospital. He knew the jig was up. He said `Oh, I just want to hang on a little. I want the grandchildren to be able to remember me'. He was a family man right to his heart.
      </para>
      <para>
       As a matter of fact I think he would have liked to establish a dynasty in Kennedy if his son, young Bob, could have got the preselection. But, as he said, it seemed as though he had run into a great big fat bladder of lard. I do not know what that was but he had a colourful way of expressing everything. So that was one disappointment for him. But I have appreciated his career no end and I express my sympathy to Joy and the family and add what support I can to this motion of condolence.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NT" nameid="6E4" page="44" party="NP" speaker="Tambling Sen G.E.J.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6E4">
         Senator TAMBLING
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Northern Territory)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —It is a great tribute to Bob Katter that so many honourable senators can speak of him with such great personal memory and identification. For a person to contribute to public life from the levels of local government to the General Assembly of the United Nations and then also incorporate in his term so many areas and fields of community endeavour is a very great plus and positive attribute. He was man who made a marvellous contribution.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Bob Katter stood for election 10 times to this Federal Parliament and was successful on every occasion. Like many other members and senators I shared a great deal of interest in the area of northern Australia with the late Bob Katter. I shared a common electorate boundary both in the House of Representatives and in the Senate as a senator for the Northern Territory. I know that I am speaking for my party colleagues, Sam Calder, Bernie Kilgariff and Paul Everingham who also had a great deal to do with Bob in his parliamentary career in this particular place.
      </para>
      <para>
       My memories of Bob Katter go back to the period shortly after my election to the Northern Territory Legislative Assembly in late 1974. That was the period of the Whitlam administration and Bob Katter at that time was the Opposition spokesman for northern development and the Northern Territory. I have two very vivid memories of Bob in that particular period. One relates to the early moves and initiations for self-government for the Northern Territory. We certainly enjoyed the major support of Bob Katter in progressing the Northern Territory's case for further transfers of power and for what finally eventuated in self-government in 1978. He must have been so proud to have been a party to that.
      </para>
      <para>
       A month or so after I was elected, Cyclone Tracy hit Darwin. One of the first parliamentarians to visit Darwin on that occasion was Bob Katter. He was in there, I think, on the first or the second day and had a very personal and meaningful involvement in the negotiations that were so necessary with Dr Cairns and so many other people in the very early days.
      </para>
      <para>
       I know that there are thousands of my constituents in the Northern Territory who share in the great loss of Bob's passing. As other honourable senators have mentioned, these of course include thousands of Aboriginal territorians who also knew him so well through his operation in Mount Isa. I would like to express the condolences of my party, the Northern Territory Country Liberal Party. We remember the special endeavours that Bob made on behalf of the Northern Territory and I express sympathy to Joy and the family.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="RD4" page="45" party="NP" speaker="Brownhill Sen D.G.C.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="RD4">
         Senator BROWNHILL
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I rise to associate myself with the condolence motion moved by Senator Button for the Hon. Robert Katter. Ten times elected as the member for Kennedy and once to heaven, which is surely where he is now because he would be one of the people first elected to that area.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       If ever there was a member of this Parliament who could be called `Hail Fellow, Well Met', Bob Katter was that member. He was a tireless worker for his electorate and for the people of the Australian traditional outback. He played a formidable part in the establishment of the Australian Stockmen's Hall of Fame. This man, a traditionalist for the outback, will be missed by this Parliament. We are all the poorer for his passing. I share with the family the loss they feel at this stage and extend the sympathy of all the National Party people in New South Wales to Joy and the family.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="NSW" nameid="LE4" page="45" party="LP" speaker="Baume Sen M.E.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="LE4">
         Senator MICHAEL BAUME
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (New South Wales)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —I, too, would like to join briefly in this set of tributes to Bob Katter, who I first met when I became a member of the House of Representatives halfway through his 24 years of service in that chamber. I have an immense professional and personal regard for Bob Katter-a professional regard because of the incredible example he gave to all members of Parliament, particularly in the matter of caring for his constituents. He faced 10 elections in 21 years during his 24 years of service-one almost every two years. He had three-quarters of a million square kilometres to look after. That is the size of the Kennedy electorate. The burden that imposed on him personally and physically was enormous. Yet, as other speakers have said, he was probably one of Australia's best known members of parliament so far as his constituents were concerned. Any one of us who went to his electorate was greeted, as has been said, with incredible hospitality. His achievements, culminating in his period as a Minister of the Crown, speak for themselves, but his holding for 24 years of what was traditionally a Labor seat, which on his death was regained by Labor, is a further indication of the outstanding personal contribution he made on behalf of his constituents.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       The two people we have mourned so far today-Sir Reginald Wright and Bob Katter-both served their country in the Parliament and in the defence forces. Between them they served this Parliament for more than 50 years. They contributed immensely to our nation and we are certainly the poorer for their passing.
      </para>
     </speech>
     <speech electorate="TAS" nameid="6H4" page="46" party="IND" speaker="Harradine Sen B.">
      <talk.start>
       <talker>
        <name nameid="6H4">
         Senator HARRADINE
        </name>
        <electorate>
         (Tasmania)
        </electorate>
       </talker>
       <para in-line="1">
        —Mr President, Bob Katter, as has been detailed before the Senate, gave distinguished public service over a very long time. Also, he was a family man. He often spoke of his family. He had a great feel and compassion for the battlers, the under-privileged and the voiceless, including unborn human beings, expressing their rights. He was a great raconteur. Time does not permit me to tell the great story he told me the last time I met him. He was a great man and a great mate of mine. I felt his death very deeply and personally, and I would like Joy to know that prayers were offered for him as far south as Hobart. I would like to extend to her and to all of his family my deepest sympathy.
       </para>
      </talk.start>
      <para>
       Question resolved in the affirmative, honourable senators standing in their places.
      </para>
     </speech>
    </debate>
    <debate page="46" type="Miscellaneous">
     <title>
      DEATHS OF THE RIGHT HON. SIR EDWARD ALOYSIUS McTIERNAN AND HENRY NORMAN CHARLES BANDIDT
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <interject chair="1" nameid="10000" speaker="The PRESIDENT">
       <talk.start>
        <talker>
         <name nameid="10000">
          The PRESIDENT
         </name>
        </talker>
        <para in-line="1">
         —It is with deep regret that I inform the Senate of the death of the Right Hon. Sir Edward Aloysius McTiernan on 9 January 1990, a former member of the House of Representatives between 1929 and 1930 and a former Justice of the High Court of Australia from 1930 to 1976, and of Henry Norman Charles Bandidt, on 6 January 1990, a former member of the House of Representatives from 1958 to 1961.
        </para>
       </talk.start>
      </interject>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="46" type="Adjournment">
     <title>
      ADJOURNMENT
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
       Motion (by Senator Button) agreed to:
      </para>
      <para>
       That, as a mark of respect to the memory of the deceased, the Senate do now adjourn.
      </para>
      <para>
       Senate adjourned at 7.05 p.m.
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
    <debate page="46" type="Documents">
     <title>
      DOCUMENTS
     </title>
     <proctext>
      <para>
       The following documents were tabled:
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Heritage Protection Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 420.
      </para>
      <para>
       Acts Interpretation Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Correspondence and Statements relating to extensions of specified periods for presentation of the A.C.T. Transport Trust, A.C.T. Housing Trust and A.C.T. Forestry Trust Account Annual Reports for 1989-90.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statement relating to failure to furnish within the specified period the Christmas Island Services Corporation 1988-89 Annual Report and Financial Statements.
      </para>
      <para>
       Acoustic Laboratories Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 374.
      </para>
      <para>
       A.C.T. Self-Government (Consequential Provisions) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 Nos 391-398.
      </para>
      <para>
       Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 373.
      </para>
      <para>
       Aged or Disabled Persons Homes Act-Guidelines made under section-
      </para>
      <para>
       9b, dated 19 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       10f, dated 16 February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Air Navigation Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 400.
      </para>
      <para>
       Audit Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 377.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Capital Territory Supreme Court Act-Rules of Court-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 2.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Federal Police Act-Regulations-
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1989-Nos 361 and 363 (in substitution of Documents previously tabled on 21 December 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990-Nos 23, 45 and 87.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Meat and Live-stock Corporation Act-Orders-1989-Nos-
      </para>
      <para>
       L8/89-Export of sheep to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.
      </para>
      <para>
       MQ 32/89-High quality beef to EEC-1990 Quota Administration Scheme.
      </para>
      <para>
       MQ 33/89-Sheepmeat and/or goatmeat to EEC-1990 Quota Administration Scheme.
      </para>
      <para>
       MQ 34/89-Buffalo meat to EEC-1990 Quota Administration Scheme.
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian National Railways Commission Act-By-laws 1989-
      </para>
      <para>
       Boards of Appeal Amendment No. 1
      </para>
      <para>
       General Amendments Nos 4 and 8.
      </para>
      <para>
       Bankruptcy Act-Rules-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 376.
      </para>
      <para>
       Bounty (Photographic Film) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 415.
      </para>
      <para>
       Cash Transaction Reports Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 36.
      </para>
      <para>
       Child Support (Registration and Collection) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 90.
      </para>
      <para>
       Civil Aviation Act-Civil Aviation Orders-
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-Parts-
      </para>
      <para>
       105, Amendments, dated 6 December, 15 December and 19 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       1990-Parts-
      </para>
      <para>
       20, Amendments, Nos 119 and 120, dated 4 April 1990 and No. 121, dated 9 April 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       29, Amendments, No. 28, dated 15 February 1990 and No. 29, dated 16 February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       40, Amendments, No. 114, dated 6 February 1990, No. 115, dated 16 February 1990 and No. 116, dated 4 April 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       95, Amendments, No. 53, dated 25 January 1990, Nos 52 and 54, dated 6 February 1990 and No. 55, dated 18 April 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       101, Amendment, No. 85, dated 6 February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       105, Amendments, dated 9 January (3), 16 January (2), 18 January, 29 January, 31 January, 5 February, 8 February (2), 12 February (3), 13 February, 16 February (5), 19 February, 26 February (2), 27 February, 5 March, 13 March (3), 22 March (3), 30 March, 3 April and 4 April 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       106, Amendments, dated 16 January, 2 February, 13 February and 13 March 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       107, Amendments, dated 16 January and 13 March 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Commonwealth Electoral Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 33.
      </para>
      <para>
       Companies Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 370.
      </para>
      <para>
       Consular Fees Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 44.
      </para>
      <para>
       Copyright Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 4, 5 and 76.
      </para>
      <para>
       Crimes Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 32.
      </para>
      <para>
       Criminology Research Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 85.
      </para>
      <para>
       Currency Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 60.
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Notice 1990 No. 1-Declared rate in respect to the diesel fuel rebate, dated 2 February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1989 Nos 379, 380, 388, 409 and 417.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 6, 8, 39 and 40.
      </para>
      <para>
       Dairy Produce Levy (No. 1) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 50.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Determinations under section 58b-
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 172-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Austria and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 192-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Tanzania and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 193-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Luxembourg and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 194-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Kenya and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 196-Rates of Travelling Allowance-New Zealand and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 197-Camping Allowance-Indonesia.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 199-China.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 202-Extra Tuition Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 204-Salary of Permanent Force Members and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 205-Vehicle Allowance and Isolated Establishment Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 206-Post Allowance-Papua New Guinea.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 207-Uniform Maintenance Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 208-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Algeria and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 209-Revised rates of allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 210-Reunion Travel.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 211-Financial Benefits for Members of the Australian Defence Force Declared Redundant.
      </para>
      <para>
       1990-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 1-Rates of Travelling Allowance-USSR and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-Disturbance Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-Expense of Office Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Portugal and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Tunisia and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Pakistan and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 7-Temporary Rental Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 8-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Greece and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 9-Revised rates of allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 10-Pet Relocation Expenses Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 11-Temporary Rental Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 12-Dwelling Purchase or Sale Expenses Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 13-Revised rates of allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 14-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Jordan and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 15-Household maintenance and assistance allowance and Household maintenance and assistance-certain localities.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 16-Rates of Travelling Allowance-United Kingdom and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 17-Approving authority and Reimbursement for excess expenses.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 18-Expense of Office Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 19-Rates of Travelling Allowance-USA, Statford and St Louis and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 20-Revised rates of allowance-Pay period commencing 7 December 1989 and Revised rates of allowance-Pay period commencing 21 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 21-Rates of Travelling Allowance-China and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 22-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Italy and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 23-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Finland and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 24-Post allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 25-Revised rates of allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 26-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Korea and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 27-Temporary Rental Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 28-Antarctic Parity Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 29-Rates of Travelling Allowance-New Caledonia and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 30-Member provided with official motor vehicle.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 31-Reimbursement of education costs-at locality of posting and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 32-Education assistance-United Kingdom.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 33-Excess Commuting Costs Allowance-USA.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 34-Temporary Rental Allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 35-Attendance Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 36-Revised rates of allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 37-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Norway and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 38-Rates of Travelling Allowance-United Kingdom and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 39-District Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 40-Flight Duties Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 41-Woomera Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 42-Rates of Travelling Allowance-India-Elsewhere and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 43-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Belgium and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 44-Rates of Travelling Allowance-French Polynesia and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 45-Jerusalem-Post Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 46-Isolated Establishment Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 47-Post allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 48-Revised rates of allowance-Turkey and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 49-Revised rates of allowance and others
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 50-Other Conditions-United Kingdom and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 51-Additional Recreation Leave for Service in a Remote Locality.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 52-Expense of Office Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 53-Revised rates of allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 54-Member provided with official motor vehicle and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 55-Household maintenance and assistance-USA.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 56-Travelling Allowance and In Port Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 57-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Poland and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 58-Education Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 59-Revised rates of allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 60-Revised rates of allowance and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 61-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Iraq and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 62-Rates of Travelling Allowance-Malta and others.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 65-Rent and utilities contribution for officers on long term posting overseas.
      </para>
      <para>
       58H-
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 16-Flying Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 17-Clearance Diving Allowance.
      </para>
      <para>
       1990-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 1-Review of Salary of Senior Officers.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-Salary of Permanent Force Members.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 42.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Act, Naval Defence Act and Air Force Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 10 and 11.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Force Retirement and Death Benefits Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 12.
      </para>
      <para>
       Defence Housing Authority Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Statement under section 10 relating to the development of land at Holsworthy, dated 29 November 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       Letter relating to failure to furnish within the specified period the Statement relating to the development of land at Holsworthy.
      </para>
      <para>
       Designs Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 29.
      </para>
      <para>
       Environment Protection (Impact of Proposals) Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 31.
      </para>
      <para>
       Excise Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Instrument of approval by the Comptroller-General, dated 5 February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Notice 1990 No. 1-Declared rate in respect to the diesel fuel rebate, dated 2 February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1989 No. 408.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990 No. 7.
      </para>
      <para>
       Explosives Act-Order by the Minister under Regulation 67 of the Explosives Regulations, dated 15 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       Export Control Act-Export Control (Orders) Regulations-Orders 1990-No. 1-Export Control (Quality Assured Foods).
      </para>
      <para>
       Export Inspection (Establishment Registration Charges) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 405.
      </para>
      <para>
       Export Inspection Charges Collection Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 406.
      </para>
      <para>
       Extradition Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 372.
      </para>
      <para>
       Family Law Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 37 and 67.
      </para>
      <para>
       Rules of Court-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 20 and 74.
      </para>
      <para>
       Federal Court of Australia Act-Rules of Court-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 72.
      </para>
      <para>
       Fisheries Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Fisheries Notices-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 187A-Great Australian Bight Trawl Fishery-Prohibition on trawling, dated 15 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. NIF1-Norfolk Island Fishery-Prohibition on the taking of fish, dated 9 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. ORF5-Orange Roughy Fishery-Prohibition on taking Orange Roughy off St Helens Point, Tas., dated 15 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       Plan of Management-No. GAB 1-Great Australian Bight Trawl Fishery Preliminary Management Plan, dated 15 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 78 and 79.
      </para>
      <para>
       Fisheries Levy Act-Regulations-
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1989 No. 410.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 49 and 80-82.
      </para>
      <para>
       Fringe Benefits Tax Assessment Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 68.
      </para>
      <para>
       Futures Industry Act-Regulations-
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1989 No. 371.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990 No. 41.
      </para>
      <para>
       Goat Fibre Levy Collection Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 386.
      </para>
      <para>
       Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Act-Regulations-
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1989 Nos 367 and 368.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 9 and 35.
      </para>
      <para>
       Health Insurance Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulation-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 25, 83 and 84.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statements (2) of particulars of Ministerial Determinations made under subsection 106aa, dated 23 January 1990 and 14 February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Higher Education Funding Act-Determinations 1990-Nos-
      </para>
      <para>
       T1-Grants for Expenditure for Operating Purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       T2-Grants for Expenditure for Limited Operating Purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       T3-Grants for Expenditure for Operating Purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       T4-Grants for Expenditure for Limited Operating Purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       T5-Declaration of Higher Education Institutions.
      </para>
      <para>
       T8-Grants for Expenditure for Operating Purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       T9-Grants for Expenditure for Limited Operating Purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 407.
      </para>
      <para>
       Income Tax Assessment Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 19.
      </para>
      <para>
       International Organizations (Privileges and Immunities) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 26.
      </para>
      <para>
       Lands Acquisition Act-Statements (2) describing lands acquired by agreement under subsection 40 (3) of the Act for specified public purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
       Live-stock Export Charge Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 47.
      </para>
      <para>
       Live-stock Slaughter Levy Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 46 and 51.
      </para>
      <para>
       Meat Chicken Levy Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 52.
      </para>
      <para>
       Merit Protection (Australian Government Employees) Act-Regulation-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 411.
      </para>
      <para>
       Migration Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Notices under section-
      </para>
      <para>
       32 (1), dated 11 January 1990 (2).
      </para>
      <para>
       32 (2), dated 6 March 1990 (2).
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1989 Nos 412-414 and 416.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 1, 34, 69 and 75.
      </para>
      <para>
       Mutual Assistance in Criminal Matters Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 22.
      </para>
      <para>
       National Crime Authority Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 38.
      </para>
      <para>
       National Health Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Declarations 1990-Pharmaceutical Benefits (3) made under subsections-
      </para>
      <para>
       85 (2)-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. PB1, dated 15 February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. PB2, dated 16 March 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       85 (2aa)-No. PB3, dated 16 March 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Determinations-
      </para>
      <para>
       BPT1/1989-under Section 4d for the purposes of paragraph (db), dated 20 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       BPT2/1989-under Section 4d for the purposes of paragraph (dc), dated 20 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       BPT3/1989-under subsection 4 (1), for the purposes of paragraph 4b (b), dated 20 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       BPT4/1989-under subsection 4 (1), for the purposes of paragraph 4b (a), dated 20 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       BT1/1990-under subsection 4 (1) for the purposes of paragraph (dd), dated 6 March 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-90/33-under subsection 47 (2), dated 22 March 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Notice for the purposes of subsection 47 (1), dated 15 February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 24 and 86.
      </para>
      <para>
       Navigation Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Navigation (Orders) Regulations-Marine Orders-
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-No. 6-Part 2 (Fees).
      </para>
      <para>
       1990-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 1-Part 93 (Pollution Prevention-Noxious Liquid Substances).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-Part 13 (Ship Stability and Subdivision).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-Part 20 (Ship Machinery).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-Part 29 (Emergency Procedures and Safety of Navigation).
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1989 Nos 381-383.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990 No. 14.
      </para>
      <para>
       Ozone Protection Act-Notice under subsection 40 (7), dated 19 December 1989.
      </para>
      <para>
       Patents Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 390.
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 54.
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) (Exploration Permit Fees) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 55.
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) (Pipeline Licence Fees) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 57.
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) (Production Licence Fees) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 56.
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) (Registration Fees) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 58.
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) (Retention Lease Fees) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 59.
      </para>
      <para>
       Plant Variety Rights Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 15.
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy Research and Development Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 16 and 61-66.
      </para>
      <para>
       Protection of the Sea (Prevention of Pollution from Ships) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 13.
      </para>
      <para>
       Public Service Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Determinations-
      </para>
      <para>
       1989-Nos 152, 153, 166, 168-180.
      </para>
      <para>
       1990-Nos 1-31, 33-45 and 47.
      </para>
      <para>
       Parliamentary Presiding Officers' Determinations-
      </para>
      <para>
       1989 No. 5.
      </para>
      <para>
       1990 Nos 1 and 5-7
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 399.
      </para>
      <para>
       Radiocommunications Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 70 and 71.
      </para>
      <para>
       Remuneration Tribunal Act-Determinations-
      </para>
      <para>
       1989
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 23-Remuneration and Allowances for holders of Public Offices.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 24-Remuneration and Allowances for holders of Public Offices.
      </para>
      <para>
       1990-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 1-Remuneration and Allowances for holders of Public Offices.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2- Holders of Public Offices-Remuneration and Allowances.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-Remuneration and Allowances for holders of Public Offices.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-Remuneration and Allowances for holders of Public Offices.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-Remuneration and Allowances for holders of Public Offices.
      </para>
      <para>
       Rural Industries Research Act-Regulations-
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990 No. 387.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 48 and 77.
      </para>
      <para>
       Seaman's War Pensions and Allowances Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 389.
      </para>
      <para>
       Seat of Government (Administration) Act-Ordinances 1989-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 60-Magistrates Court (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 61-Juries (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 62-Classification of Publications (Amendment).
      </para>
      <para>
       Securities Industry Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 369.
      </para>
      <para>
       Shipping Registration Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 384.
      </para>
      <para>
       Ships (Capital Grants) Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Guidelines under section 18, dated 20 February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulation-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 385.
      </para>
      <para>
       States Grants (Schools Assistance) Act-Determination of amount under Section 17, dated 8 January 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Stevedoring Industry Levy Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 401.
      </para>
      <para>
       Student Assistance Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 Nos 402-404.
      </para>
      <para>
       Superannuation Act-
      </para>
      <para>
       Determinations under section 153ac-1990-
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 1-ANL Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 2-AUSSAT Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 3-Australian Airlines Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 4-Qantas Airways Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 5-National Terminals (Australia) Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 6-Snowy Mountains Engineering Corporation Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 7-ANL Cargo Operations Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 8-Asia Pacific Distribution Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 9-Australia Asia Airlines Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 10-Australian National Container Management Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 11-Australian National Shipping Agencies Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 12-Australian Regional Airlines (Qld) Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 13-Australian Resorts Pty Ltd
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 14-Bedarra Island Resort
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 15-Brampton Island Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 16-Cape York Wilderness Lodge Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 17-Creative Tours Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 18-Great Barrier Reef Hotel Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 19-Hideaway Island Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 20-Lizard Island Lodge Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 21-Parkview (Keppell) Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 22-Qantas Distribution Services Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 23-Qantas Flight Catering Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 24-Qantas Information Technology Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 25-Qantas Jetabout Holidays Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 26-Qantas Superannuation Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 27-QH Tours Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 28-Telecommunications Power Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 29-Trans-United Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 30-Viva! Holidays Limited.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 31-Australian Industry Development Corporation Act 1970.
      </para>
      <para>
       No. 32-Australian Defence Industries Pty Ltd.
      </para>
      <para>
       Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 73.
      </para>
      <para>
       Superannuation Benefit (Interim Arrangement) Act-Regulations
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1989 No. 378.
      </para>
      <para>
       Statutory Rules 1990 No. 43.
      </para>
      <para>
       Supported Accommodation Assistance Act-Agreement between the Commonwealth of Australia and New South Wales, dated 13= February 1990.
      </para>
      <para>
       Telecommunications Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 418.
      </para>
      <para>
       Television Licence Fees Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 3.
      </para>
      <para>
       Therapeutic Goods Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 88.
      </para>
      <para>
       Therapeutic Goods (Charges) Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 89.
      </para>
      <para>
       Tobacco Charges Act (No. 1)-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 21.
      </para>
      <para>
       Trade Marks Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 No. 30.
      </para>
      <para>
       Trade Practices Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 375.
      </para>
      <para>
       War Precautions Act Repeal Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1989 No. 419.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wheat Marketing Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 27 and 28.
      </para>
      <para>
       Wool Marketing Act-Regulations-Statutory Rules 1990 Nos 17, 18 and 53.
      </para>
      <para>
       GOVERNOR-GENERAL'S PROCLAMATIONS-COMMENCEMENT OF PROVISIONS OF ACTS: Proclamations by His Excellency the Governor-General were tabled, notifying that His Excellency had proclaimed the following provisions of Acts to come into operation on the dates specified:
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Communication Act 1989-5 March 1990 (Gazette No. S 48, 23 February 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Aboriginal Land Rights (Northern Territory) Act 1976-Amendment made pursuant to the provisions of the Aboriginal Land Rights (Northern Territory) Amendment Act 1987-subsections 50 (2d) and 50 (2e)-1 March 1990 (Gazette No. S 51, 28 February 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Australian Federal Police Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989-Part 2 (other than sections 11 and 38), Part 4, Part 5 other than section 71) and Part 6-1 January 1990 (Gazette No. S 397, 21 December 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Banking Legislation Amendment Act 1989-28 December 1989 (Gazette No. S 383, 15 December 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Child Support (Assessment) Act 1989-1 October 1989 (Gazette No. S 314, 28 September 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Commonwealth Electoral Act 1918-amendments made to subsections 29 (2) and 100 (1), section 128, subsection 169 (2), section 277 and subsections 294 (2) and 334 (4) pursuant to Schedule 3 of the Electoral and Referendum Amendment Act 1989-9 February 1990 (Gazette No. S 30, 9 February 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Community Services and Health Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1988-sections 19 to 26 (inclusive) and sections 28 to 34 (inclusive)-24 January 1990 (Gazette No. S 13, 24 January 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Community Services and Health Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989-sections 33, 34 and 36-1 April 1990 (Gazette No. S 83, 30 March 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Copyright Amendment Act 1989-sections 3, 5, 7, 12, 13, 21, 22 and 28 of that Act, and items 1, 4, 10, 12, 14, 19, 25, and 26 in the Schedule to that Act-1 October 1989 (Gazette No. S 316, 29 September 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Courts and Tribunals Administration Amendment Act 1989-Parts 2, 3, 4, 5, 7 and 8-1 January 1990 (Gazette No. S 398, 21 December 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Customs Tariff (Anti-Dumping) Amendment Act 1989-the provisions of that Act (other than sections 1 and 2)-21 December 1989 (Gazette No. S 395, 21 December 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Electoral and Referendum Amendment Act 1989-
      </para>
      <para>
       paragraphs 4 (a), (c) and (e);
      </para>
      <para>
       sections 38, 44 to 48 (inclusive) and 54;
      </para>
      <para>
       paragraph 55 (c);
      </para>
      <para>
       sections 57, 58, 61, 65, 73, 74 and 76;
      </para>
      <para>
       paragraphs 80 (e), 81 (e) to (n) (inclusive) and 85 (a), (d), (e) and (f);
      </para>
      <para>
       sections 86 to 109 (inclusive), 111, 112, 113, 115, 116, 119 and 120;
      </para>
      <para>
       Export Inspection (Establishment Registration Charges) Amendment Act 1987-15 February 1990 (Gazette No. S 32, 13 February 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Grain Legumes Levy Legislation Amendment Act 1989-1 January 1990 (Gazette No. S 387, 19 December 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Horticultural Legislation Amendment Act 1989-sections 4 and 9, paragraph 10 (c), section 11, to the extent that it inserts a new section 7a in the Horticultural Export Charge Collection Act 1987, sections 12 to 18 (inclusive), section 21, paragraph 22 (c), section 23, to the extent that it inserts a new section 7a in the Horticultural Levy Collection Act 1987, sections 24 to 30 (inclusive) and section 32-1 October 1989 (Gazette No. S 313, 28 September 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Industry Commission Act 1990-9 March 1990 (Gazette No. S 44, 21 February 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Law and Justice Legislation Amendment Act 1988-section 20-21 December 1989 (Gazette No. S 384, 15 December 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Minerals (Submerged Lands) Act 1981-1 February 1990 (Gazette No. S 387, 19 December 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Patents Amendment Act 1989-15 December 1989 (Gazette No. S 384, 15 December 1989).
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) Act 1967-Amendments made pursuant to the provisions of the Primary Industries and Energy Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989-1 March 1990 (Gazette No. S 52, 26 February 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) (Exploration Permit Fees) Act 1967-Amendments made pursuant to the provisions of the Primary Industries and Energy Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989-1 March 1990 (Gazette No. S 52, 26 February 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) (Pipeline Licence Fees) Act 1967-Amendments made pursuant to the provisions of the Primary Industries and Energy Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989-1 March 1990 (Gazette No. S 52, 26 February 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) (Production Licence Fees) Act 1967-Amendments made pursuant to the provisions of the Primary Industries and Energy Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989-1 March 1990 (Gazette No. S 52, 26 February 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Petroleum (Submerged Lands) (Retention Lease Fees) Act 1985-Amendments made pursuant to the provisions of the Primary Industries and Energy Legislation Amendment Act (No. 2) 1989-1 March 1990 (Gazette No. S 52, 26 February 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Primary Industries and Energy Legislation Amendment Act (No. 3) 1989-Part 2 (other than sections 21, 23 and 26)-1 February 1990 (Gazette No. S 16, 25 January 1990).
      </para>
      <para>
       Public Service and Statutory Authorities Amendment Act 1980-section 20 and subsection 45 (2)-1 March 1990 (Gazette No. S 50, 23 February 1990).
      </para>
     </proctext>
    </debate>
   </chamber.xscript>
  </hansard>
 </body>
</html>
